<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T03:24:28Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8691876" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8691876</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-31</datestamp>
        <setSpec>ghsp</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Glob Health Sci Pract</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Glob Health Sci Pract</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">ghsp</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ghsp</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Global Health: Science and Practice</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2169-575X</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Global Health: Science and Practice</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8691876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8691876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34933978</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34933978</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GHSP-D-20-00349</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Participation in a Community-Based Women's Health Education Program and At-Risk Child Development in Rural Kenya: Developmental Screening Questionnaire Results Analysis</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Maternal Health Education Program and Child Development in Rural Kenya</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McHenry</surname>
                    <given-names>Megan S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Maldonado</surname>
                    <given-names>Lauren Y.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>Ziyi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Anusu</surname>
                    <given-names>Gertrude</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kaluhi</surname>
                    <given-names>Evelyn</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Christoffersen-Deb</surname>
                    <given-names>Astrid</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>d</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Songok</surname>
                    <given-names>Julia J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>f</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ruhl</surname>
                    <given-names>Laura J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>f</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label><institution>Academic Model Providing Access to Healthcare (AMPATH)</institution>, <addr-line>Eldoret, Kenya</addr-line>.</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label><institution>Indiana University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Indianapolis, IN, USA</addr-line>.</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label><institution>Massachusetts General Hospital, Departments of Medicine and Pediatrics</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA, USA</addr-line>.</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label><institution>University of British Columbia, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</institution>, <addr-line>Vancouver, Canada</addr-line>.</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label><institution>University of Toronto, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</institution>, <addr-line>Toronto, Canada</addr-line>.</aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>f</label><institution>Moi University College of Health Sciences, Department of Child Health and Paediatrics</institution>, <addr-line>Eldoret, Kenya</addr-line>.</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="other" id="FN1">
                  <label>*</label>
                  <p>Co-principal investigators on this study and share equal authorship on this article.</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Megan McHenry (<email>msuhl@iu.edu</email>).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <day>31</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>31</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>9</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>818</fpage>
              <lpage>831</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© McHenry et al.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly cited. To view a copy of the license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. When linking to this article, please use the following permanent link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349">https://doi.org/10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349</ext-link></license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="GH-GHSP210101.pdf"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="precis">
                <p>A community-based intervention focused on women's health education may help protect against early childhood developmental delays in resource-limited settings.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <sec>
                  <title>Key Findings</title>
                  <p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Infants in Chamas had a lower likelihood of at-risk development compared to those in the control group. Older infant age at time of screening and having natural or uncovered walls was also associated with lower odds of at-risk development.</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Our findings offer evidence to support that by addressing health literacy, providing community in a supportive environment, and offering a means to combat social determinants of child developmental delays, the Chamas for Change intervention may help protect children from developmental delays in this resource-limited setting in Kenya.</p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Key Implications</title>
                  <p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                      <list-item>
                        <p>When looking to revise current strategies to help protect children from developmental delay in this setting, policy makers should consider interventions that leverage existing resources to ensure their sustainability.</p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>Over 43% of children living in low- and middle-income countries are at risk for developmental delays; however, access to protective interventions in these settings is limited. We evaluated the effect of maternal participation in Chamas for Change (Chamas)—a community-based women's health education program during pregnancy and postpartum—and risk of developmental delay among their children in rural Kenya.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>We analyzed developmental screening questionnaire (DSQ) data from a cluster randomized controlled trial in Trans Nzoia County, Kenya (ClinicalTrials.gov, NCT03187873). Intervention clusters (Chamas) participated in community health volunteer-led, group-based health lessons twice a month during pregnancy and postpartum; controls had monthly home visits (standard of care). We screened all children born during the trial who were alive at 1-year follow-up. We labeled children with any positive item on the DSQ as “at-risk development.” We analyzed data using descriptive statistics and multilevel regression models (α=.05); analyses were intention-to-treat using individual-level data.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>Between November 2017 and March 2018, we enrolled 1,920 pregnant women to participate in the parent trial. At 1-year follow-up, we screened 1,273 (689 intervention, 584 control) children born during the trial with the DSQ. Intervention mothers had lower education levels and higher poverty likelihood scores than controls (<italic>P</italic>&lt;.001 and <italic>P</italic>=.007, respectively). The overall rate of at-risk development was 3.5%. Children in Chamas clusters demonstrated significantly lower rates of at-risk development than controls (2.5% vs. 4.8%, <italic>P</italic>=.025). Adjusted analyses revealed lower odds for at-risk development in the intervention arm (OR=0.50; 95% confidence interval=0.27, 0.94).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p>Maternal participation in a community-based women's health education program was associated with lower rates of at-risk development compared to the standard of care. Overall, rates of at-risk development were lower than expected for this population, warranting further investigation. Chamas may help protect children from developmental delay in rural Kenya and other resource-limited settings.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Early childhood development (ECD) lays the foundation upon which every individual's cognitive, social, and emotional abilities are built. As such, investing in ECD not only benefits individuals but also boosts shared prosperity and helps eliminate extreme poverty.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> However, recent data suggest that more than 43% of children under age 5 years living in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) are at risk for developmental delays.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Among children at risk, more than 60% reside in sub-Saharan Africa.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> This inequity perpetuates intergenerational cycles of poverty, particularly in rural communities where children are often denied equal access to resources and opportunities that nurture ECD.</p>
              <p>The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that 45% of children under age 5 years in Kenya are at risk for developmental delays (56% rural, 25% urban), translating to an estimated 138% loss in annual adult wages.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Multifaceted challenges have limited the success of recent efforts (e.g., government policies, school-based programming) to bolster ECD. These challenges include inadequate financial investment in early education, poor access to health services that protect against known risk factors (e.g., malnutrition, recurrent and/or chronic infections), and limited awareness of the deleterious role of chronic stress (e.g., harsh punishment) on development.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Moreover, few policies focused on ECD target the first 1,000 days of life—a critical period during which the brain undergoes rapid change and establishes a framework for lifelong learning.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Inadequate antenatal care,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> malnutrition,<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and maternal depression,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> during this period can also have long-standing negative consequences.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Effective interventions that protect against developmental delays within rural, resource-limited settings are urgently needed to address these disparities.</p>
              <p>In 2012, the Academic Model Providing Access to Healthcare partnership and Republic of Kenya Ministry of Health established the Chamas for Change (Chamas) program to help improve maternal, newborn, and child health (MNCH) in rural western Kenya.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Chamas is a longitudinal program that supports women during pregnancy and for the first 1,000 days of the infants' lives with community-driven, group-based health education. Importantly, this intervention integrates known strategies to improve outcomes for women and infants, including ECD, while leveraging existing resources in rural Kenyan communities. A pilot study evaluating the first year of this program demonstrated significant associations between participation and the likelihood of practicing positive MNCH behaviors, including attending adequate antenatal care and exclusively breastfeeding.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>A pilot study evaluating the first year of Chamas demonstrated significant associations between participation and the likelihood of practicing positive MNCH behaviors, including attending adequate antenatal care and exclusively breastfeeding.</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>To test our hypothesis that maternal participation in Chamas improved MNCH outcomes, including ECD, we conducted a cluster-randomized controlled trial in Trans Nzoia County, Kenya. In this article, we report results from developmental screening questionnaires (DSQ) completed on children born during the trial at 1-year follow-up.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>METHODS</title>
              <sec id="s2.1">
                <title>Study Design and Setting</title>
                <p>We analyzed DSQ data from a 2-arm cluster randomized controlled trial in 74 communities across 4 subcounties (Cherangany, Saboti, Kwanza, and Kiminini) in Trans Nzoia County, Kenya. We chose a cluster-randomized design to minimize contamination due to intervention exposure between neighboring villages. We defined clusters as community health units—geographically defined health service delivery areas for populations of 5,000 people overseen by community health volunteers (CHVs).<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> We randomized community health units 1:1 (non-stratified, non-matched) using a simple random allocation sequence to participate in Chamas (intervention) or receive recommended monthly home visits from CHVs (standard of care) for 1 year. Data collectors, analysts, and investigators were masked to cluster allocation throughout the study; however, trial arms were identifiable to participants and CHVs by design.</p>
                <p>We selected Trans Nzoia due to its geographic and socioeconomic diversity, as well as the presence of longstanding collaborations between the Government of Kenya, Ministry of Health, and Academic Model Providing Access to Healthcare. Trans Nzoia has nearly 1 million residents who largely subside on agricultural businesses and raising livestock. Moreover, health indicators for mothers and infants are consistently poorer than national estimates, reflecting a need for increased attention to MNCH policy and programming.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref></p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2.2">
                <title>Procedures</title>
                <p>Pregnant women presenting to the local health facility for their first antenatal care visit by 32 weeks' gestation were eligible to participate in the parent trial. Participants were allocated to each arm by their randomized community of residence. At approximately 1-year follow-up (i.e., 12 months of Chamas participation, initiating prenatally), we screened all children born during the trial with the DSQ, with no additional exclusion criteria. Data collectors traveled to participant homes to collect in-person data using electronic tablet-based, structured questionnaires. We synced data at the end of each collection day to a central, encrypted server. Research assistants made 3 attempts to contact participants over a 2-week period before declaring them lost to follow-up.</p>
                <p>Intervention details are described in our protocol (ClinicalTrials.gov NCT03187873)<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> and previous publications. A detailed summary of the intervention is noted within <ext-link xlink:href="http://ghspjournal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349/-/DCSupplemental" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">Supplement 1</ext-link>. Briefly, Chamas clusters convened twice per month for 12 months for group-based health lessons led by CHVs. Each group typically included 15–20 women, their infants, 2 CHV facilitators, and 2 postmenopausal mentor mothers. Health lessons during the first year of the program promoted positive MNCH behaviors during pregnancy (e.g., attending adequate antenatal care) and infancy (e.g., exclusively breastfeeding and immunizing infants). Women were also introduced to topics contributing to risk factors and social determinants associated with developmental delays such as infant growth monitoring and nutrition,<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> disease prevention,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> childhood harsh punishment,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> and parental stress.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> These and other developmentally focused lessons are largely addressed during the second and third years of the curriculum. After each lesson, women were also invited to participate in an optional microfinance program called Group Integrated Savings for Health and Empowerment (GISHE). Participation in GISHE was completely optional so as not to deter women without financial means to contribute to group savings from joining Chamas. Women who chose to participate were encouraged to use savings and loans generated by GISHE to enroll in health insurance, pay for school fees and educational materials, and/or start small businesses.</p>
                <p>Control clusters had monthly CHV home visits during the antenatal and postpartum period as recommended by the current standard of care.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> During monthly visits, CHVs aimed to collect basic health information, recognize antenatal and early postpartum danger signs, aid in infant growth monitoring, and refer individuals requiring services to health facilities. Further, CHVs were expected to encourage women to adopt the same positive health behaviors emphasized in Chamas, namely: attending antenatal care, delivering in health facilities, exclusively breastfeeding, adopting modern methods of contraception, fully immunizing infants, and ensuring adequate infant nutrition.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2.3">
                <title>Study Outcomes</title>
                <p>Our primary outcome of interest was the rate of “at-risk development” across study arms. We defined “at-risk development” as any child who screened positive in 1 or more functional domains on the DSQ. We selected the DSQ as it has been validated for use among children less than aged 2 years in an LMIC.<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Of note, this tool is a screening questionnaire and not a diagnostic neurodevelopmental assessment. This validated questionnaire asks parents to report responses to 8 dichotomous “yes/no” questions in each of the following functional domains, which are specific to age (in months): gross motor, fine motor, vision, hearing, cognition, socialization, behavior, and speech. A list of the DSQ testing items can be viewed within <ext-link xlink:href="http://ghspjournal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349/-/DCSupplemental" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">Supplement 2</ext-link>. We considered any “yes” response a positive screen. Data collectors used age-appropriate DSQs for each infant by imposing an electronic checkpoint in RedCap (coded by birthdate). Lastly, if participants carried a multiple gestation pregnancy, we conducted independent questionnaires for each child.</p>
                <boxed-text position="float">
                  <p>Our primary outcome of interest was the rate of “at-risk development” across study arms.</p>
                </boxed-text>
                <p>To assess modifying effects of covariates, we collected baseline sociodemographic and reproductive health data for all participants. We used the validated Kenya 2015 Poverty Probability Index (PPI) tool to calculate individual poverty likelihood scores using the National Poverty Line Look-Up Table.<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> This tool comprises 10 questions that assess sociodemographic factors such as county of residence, household education level, housing materials, and recent household purchases. Answers are coded using a numeric scoring system and summarized in a composite PPI score, which can be converted to a percentage value for poverty probability. We additionally collected end-line data on participant attitudes toward harsh punishment, infant birth weight, and age of first mixed-feeding as these variables have demonstrated significant associations with developmental delay outcomes in previous studies.<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> We used a single item from the validated ISPCAN child abuse screening tool, parent version, to assess harsh punishment.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Responses were collected using a 5-point Likert scale, ranging from “strongly disagree” to “strongly agree.”</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2.4">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>The sample size calculation was based on the study's primary outcome, which was facility-based births.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> This calculation used methods described by Rutterford et al. for a proposed mixed-effects regression analysis<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> using derived baseline estimates.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> We assumed a mean cluster size of 20 individuals, with 77 clusters (equally allocated between arms) and intracluster correlation coefficient of 0.44 (based on pilot data<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>), and 20% attrition. With these assumptions, a total of 1,280 individuals would be needed to detect a 4.7% difference on the risk difference scale with 80% power at a (2-tailed) significance level of .05. A total of 1,273 (66.3%) of participants completed the study at 12-month follow-up with DSQ data: we included 689 individuals from 37 clusters in the intervention (69.2%) and 584 individuals from 37 clusters in the control (63.2%) arms for analysis.</p>
                <p>We assessed individual-level outcomes on all participants with complete DSQ data at 12-months follow-up. We used an intention-to-treat approach by evaluating all intervention participants, regardless of Chamas attendance. We summarized participant characteristics in a tabular form. We calculated frequencies and percentages for categorical variables, as well as means and standard deviations for continuous variables. We compared proportions using chi-squared tests and means using independent t-tests.</p>
                <p>We compared proportions of at-risk development among children within each study arm using chi-square tests. We used simple descriptive statistics to determine DSQ testing items and domains for which children most commonly screened positive. We reviewed available sociodemographic as well as endline variables and identified potential confounders using clinical judgment and evidence from the literature. We performed a univariate analysis with each identified variable and included those demonstrating statistical significance (<italic>P</italic>&lt;.05) or clinical meaning in our adjusted multivariate logistic regression model. We reported overall tests for each variable as well as estimated odds ratios with their 95% confidence intervals (CI). For households with twin children, we included DSQ data from the twin screened first in our regression model to limit bias introduced from duplicating covariate data from the same household and mother.</p>
                <p>We decided a priori to restrict analyses solely to participants with both complete DSQ data and complete PPI data. We disaggregated items within the PPI to appropriately adjust for specific confounding variables known to impact child development (e.g., primary caregiver education level, head of household education level, housing materials).<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> We conducted all statistical analyses in SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC) statistical software and with α set to .05.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2.5">
                <title>Ethical Considerations</title>
                <p>We prospectively registered the parent trial with ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT03187873). Our study received ethics approval from the Institutional Research Ethics Committee at Moi Teaching and Referral Hospital and Moi University (IREC/2018/269) and the Office of Research Administration at Indiana University (1905296355). We obtained written informed consent from participants before data collection.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2.6">
                <title>Role of the Funding Source</title>
                <p>The funders had no role in the research design, collection, analysis, or interpretation of data, writing this report, or the decision to submit this manuscript for publication. The corresponding author had full access to all data in the study as well as final responsibility for the decision to submit this manuscript for publication.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Between November 27, 2017, and March 8, 2018, we enrolled 1,920 pregnant women from 74 communities to participate in the parent trial. At 1-year follow-up, we screened 1,273 (689 intervention, 584 control) of their children with the DSQ (<xref rid="f01" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>). Among those without DSQ data, 36 children in the intervention arm and 42 children in the control arm died before follow-up. Lastly, all 12 twin pairs in our study cohort had concurrent DSQ screening results between the twins.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="f01">
                <label>FIGURE</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Cluster-Randomized Controlled Trial Profile and Study Inclusion Criteria of Maternal Participation in a Community-Based Women's Health Education Program in Rural Kenya</p>
                  <p>Abbreviations: CUs, community health units; DSQ, developmental screening questionnaire; Chamas, Chamas for Change Program.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="GH-GHSP210101F001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p><xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes sociodemographic data for our study population (N=1,273). Among included households, the mean child age was 10.9 months (standard deviation [SD]: 2.3) and maternal age was 26.8 years (SD: 6.4). The majority of mothers were married (83.8%, n=1,067) and unemployed (63.0%, n=802). Overall, arms were fairly balanced; however, controls had more household members educated beyond primary school (41.1% vs. 37.6%; <italic>P</italic>&lt;.001) and a lower poverty likelihood (29.0% vs. 32.0%; <italic>P</italic>=.007) compared to intervention participants. Participants lost to follow-up were similar in number across study groups and attrition was not significantly associated with sociodemographic characteristics.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="tab1">
                <label>TABLE 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Characteristics of Women Included in a Cluster-Randomized Study on the Effect of Maternal Participation in a Women's Health Education Intervention on Early Childhood Development, Tranz Nzoia County, Kenya</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="bottom">
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (N=1,273) N (%)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention (n=689) n (%)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (n=584) n (%)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P Value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child's age, months, mean (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (2.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (2.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (2.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mother's age, years, mean (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 (6.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0 (6.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7 (6.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.341</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorized mother's age, years</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    &lt;18</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (3.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (4.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2.8)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    18–24</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">462 (36.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (35.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (38.1)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    25–32</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">487 (38.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259 (38.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (39.2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    &gt;32</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256 (20.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (20.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (19.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.266</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Single/divorced/separation/widowed</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (16.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (17.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (15.2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Married</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1067 (83.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572 (83.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">495 (84.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.401</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employment status</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Unemployed</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">802 (63.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">437 (63.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (62.5)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Temporary work</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (5.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (6.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (5.7)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Self-employed/permanently employed</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (31.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (30.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (31.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.885</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest educational level of household head*</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Pre-primary/none/other</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (14.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (12.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (16.1)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Primary</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592 (46.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342 (49.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (42.8)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Secondary/post-primary/ vocational</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (30.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218 (31.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (29.6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    College or higher</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (8.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (5.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (11.5)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest educational level of any member<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Pre-primary/none/other</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (8.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (6.5)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (10.1)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Primary</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">485 (38.5)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268 (39.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217 (37.2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Secondary/post-primary/vocational</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468 (37.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272 (40.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (33.6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    College or higher</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (16.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (13.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (19.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Household food access (during last 7 days)<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Bread</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">834 (65.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439 (64.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (67.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.209</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Meat/fish</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">924 (72.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">488 (71.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436 (74.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.173</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Bananas</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">782 (62.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (59.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 (64.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.057</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Household items<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Towels</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">761 (59.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398 (58.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 (62.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.134</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Thermos flask</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">899 (71.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492 (72.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (69.8)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.362</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing: wall material<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Natural walls</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">994 (78.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">561 (81.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433 (74.1)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Finished walls</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (20.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (18.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (23.6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Uncovered wall</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (1.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (2.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing: floor material<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Natural floor</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">933 (73.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">523 (76.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4110 (70.3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Other</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335 (26.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (23.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (29.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.015</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% poverty likelihood<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.3" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup> (at national poverty line<sup><xref rid="ngtab1.2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup>, mean (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.20)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.21)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.007</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">        Missing data (n)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
                      <td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="ngtab1.1">
                    <p>Abbreviation: SD, standard deviation.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="ngtab1.2">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Indicates variables included within the poverty probability index.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="ngtab1.3">
                    <label>b</label>
                    <p>The % poverty likelihood was derived based on the participants who had non-missing values on variables with <sup>a</sup> in the table. We excluded 6 intervention and 6 control second-born twins among live dyads assessed.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The overall rate of at-risk development among our study cohort was 3.5% (n=45). When divided into study groups, we observed a significantly lower rate of at-risk development in the intervention arm (2.5% vs. 4.8%, <italic>P</italic>=.025). We noted variable rates of at-risk development across child age (in months) at the time of screening (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The only significantly different rate between study arms, however, occurred at 8 months of age (10% (4/40) control vs. 0% (0/46) intervention, <italic>P</italic>=.043). The highest proportion of positively screened items pertained to the speech (33.7%, 30/89); gross motor (18.0%, 16/89); and cognition (11.2%, 10/89) domains. All remaining domains—fine motor, vision, hearing, socialization, and behavior—individually comprised no more than 4.5%–10.1% of remaining positive screening items.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="tab2">
                <label>TABLE 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Rates of Child At-Risk Development, by Age and Study Group, in a Cluster-Randomized Study on the Effect of Maternal Participation in a Women's Health Education Intervention on Early Childhood Development, Tranz Nzoia County, Kenya</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="bottom">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child Age (Months) (N=1,273)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P Value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (N=5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/3 (66.7%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.400</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (N=5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (N=8)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3 (33.3%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.375</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (N=6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3 (33.3%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3 (33.3%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (N=9)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (N=6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2 (100.0%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4 (75.0%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (N=55)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/29 (6.9%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/26 (11.5%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.659</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (N=86)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/46</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/40 (10.0%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.043</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (N=132)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/59 (3.4%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/73 (5.5%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.691</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (N=169)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/78</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/91 (4.4%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.125</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (N=243)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/114 (0.9%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/129 (0.8%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (N=236)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/114 (2.6%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/122 (2.5%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (N=169)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/120 (1.7%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/49 (4.1%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.580</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (N=102)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/73 (1.4%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/29 (0)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (N=42)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/36 (8.3%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>TOTAL</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/689 (2.5%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/584 (4.8%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>We observed a significantly lower rate of at-risk development in the intervention arm (2.5%) compared to the control arm (4.8%).</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>We recorded outcomes on maternal attitudes toward harsh punishment, age of first mixed-feeding, and infant birthweight to adjust for their modifying effects on at-risk development. Mothers in the intervention arm more commonly agreed or strongly agreed with the use of physical punishment to discipline their children (80.6% vs. 71.1%; <italic>P</italic>&lt;.001). Mean infant birthweight differed slightly between study arms, however, both were clinically normal (3.5 kg control vs. 3.4 kg intervention, <italic>P</italic>=.036). Lastly, mothers in the intervention arm more commonly delayed mixed feedings after 3 months of age compared to controls (80.1% vs. 75.4%; n=1260; <italic>P</italic>=.049).</p>
              <p>Multivariate logistic regression models demonstrated randomized study group (<italic>P</italic>=.03), housing wall material (<italic>P</italic>=.018), and child's age (in months) at screening (<italic>P</italic>&lt;.001) were significantly associated with likelihood of at-risk development (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Specifically, infants in Chamas had lower odds of at-risk development compared to controls (OR=0.50; 95% CI=0.27, 0.94) (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Participants with natural or uncovered walls demonstrated lower odds of at-risk development than those with finished walls (OR=0.27; 95% CI=0.09, 0.80). Older infant age (in months) at the time of screening was also associated with a protective effect (OR=0.82; 95% CI=0.73, 0.92).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="tab3">
                <label>TABLE 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Factors Associated With Child At-Risk Development in a Cluster-Randomized Study on the Effect of Maternal Participation in a Women's Health Education Intervention on Early Childhood Development, Tranz Nzoia County, Kenya</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="bottom">
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degrees of Freedom</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald Chi-square Test Statistic</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P Value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study randomization (intervention vs. control)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.030</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorized mother's age in years</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.807</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.739</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employment status</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.105</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest educational level of household head</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.186</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing-wall material</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.018</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing-floor material</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.053</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of mixed feeding</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.162</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attitudes towards harsh punishment</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.437</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child's birth weight in kilograms</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.060</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child's age in months</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.52</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="tab4">
                <label>TABLE 4.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Factors Associated With Child At-Risk Development in a Cluster-Randomized Study on the Effect of Maternal Participation in a Women's Health Education Intervention on Early Childhood Development, Tranz Nzoia County, Kenya</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead valign="bottom">
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="top">
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study randomization</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27, 0.94 <sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-------</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorized mother's age (in years)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    &lt;18</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14, 5.84</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    18–24</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57, 3.53</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    25–32</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60, 3.62</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    &gt;32 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">------</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Single/divorced/separated/widowed</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36, 2.05</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Married (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employment status</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Unemployed</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93, 5.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Temporary work</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97, 11.26</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Self-employed/permanently employed (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">----</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest educational level of household head</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Pre-primary/none</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39, 6.11</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Primary</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47, 5.46</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Secondary</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18, 2.41</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    College or higher (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-------</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing- wall material</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Natural/uncovered walls</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09, 0.80<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Finished walls (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-------</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing- floor material</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Natural floor</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97, 9.26</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Other (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-------</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of mixed feeding</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    &gt;3 months</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33, 1.20</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    ≤ 3 months (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-------</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Attitudes towards harsh punishment (response to “To properly raise a child, one must use harsh punishment”)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Strongly agree/ agree</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40, 81.53</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Disagree/strongly disagree</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.42</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36, 82.04</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Neither agree or disagree (reference)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-----</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child's birth weight (in kilograms)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40, 1.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child's age in months (in months)<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73, 0.92<sup><xref rid="ngtab4.2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="ngtab4.1">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Excluded 168 subjects due to missing values for primary outcome or covariate data, with 1,105 children remaining for analysis.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="ngtab4.2">
                    <label>b</label>
                    <p>Statistically significant with α set at .05.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="ngtab4.3">
                    <label>c</label>
                    <p>At the time of developmental screening questionnaire evaluation.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>In 2015, the inclusion of ECD in the United Nation's Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) was a landmark in the history of global policy surrounding this issue. Protecting, supporting, and promoting ECD is essential to accomplishing the first SDG, “to ensure that all human beings can fulfill their potential in dignity and equality.”<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> Despite invigorated efforts and national commitments to support ECD, however, programs globally remain challenged by multi-factorial obstacles including inadequate and uncertain funding, inefficient resource allocation, and persistent health disparities.<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Moreover, recent investments in sub-Saharan Africa have largely focused on bolstering early education for children aged 4–5 years; while important, these strategies miss a critical window to intervene during the first 1,000 days of life.<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> In this context, we rigorously evaluated the effect of a community-based women's health education program on at-risk development among children in rural Kenya. Our intention-to-treat analysis using a large sample from a geographically diverse catchment demonstrated a significant protective association between Chamas participation and at-risk development. Specifically, infants in Chamas demonstrated half the odds of at-risk development compared to those whose mothers received Ministry of Health recommended home visits.</p>
              <p>The Chamas model embraces a multipronged approach to enhancing MNCH outcomes, including ECD. By providing women with opportunities to gain health literacy in a peer supportive environment, Chamas empowers women with both knowledge and community to improve outcomes for themselves and their infants during a critical developmental period. Further, among a subset of women that also engaged in microfinance activities through GISHE, this approach may have also helped mitigate important social determinants of health (e.g., inadequate funds to pay for health services). Though the latter is not a focus of this report (and will be explored in future publications), we speculate all 3 components of the model significantly contribute to its success. Our findings offer evidence to support that by addressing health, providing community, and offering a means to combat social determinants, this intervention may help protect children from developmental delays in this resource-limited setting.</p>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>Chamas empowers women with both knowledge and community to improve outcomes for themselves and their infants during a critical developmental period.</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>It is important to note that at the point of DSQ testing, Chamas participants received limited education related to child development-focused topics, and instead, prioritized topics related to basic infant care, including proper nutrition, breastfeeding, watching for worrisome signs in the first 2 weeks of life, and the importance of setting routines, with 1 session on infant development. Interpreted in context, these findings underscore that when other factors known to impact child development are addressed, such as antenatal care attendance, facility-based delivery, exclusive breastfeeding, and adequate nutrition, rates of developmental delay may simultaneously decrease.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> This hypothesis is supported by literature from other LMICs that highlight a synergistic relationship between reinforcing positive MNCH behaviors and mitigating developmental delay risk.<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> However, recent studies measured the effectiveness of 1 or 2 focused interventions on improving ECD outcomes and most have had mixed results. A recent trial that evaluated a water, sanitation, and hygiene intervention combined with nutritional counseling and supplementation in Zimbabwe demonstrated differential ECD improvement based on HIV status, with HIV-exposed children experiencing greater benefit than those uninfected.<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> A home-based program in Pakistan that combined nutritional services and responsive caregiving training also demonstrated improvement in ECD outcomes.<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> Very little data exist, however, on programs utilizing multiple concurrent strategies like in Chamas. As such, our findings build upon a growing body of evidence that supports MNCH strategies for mitigating developmental delay risk while also underscoring the importance of addressing its social determinants.</p>
              <p>The rate of at-risk development was lower among infants in our cohort compared to population-based modeling estimates. Less than 4% of infants in our cohort demonstrated at-risk development, which is significantly lower than an estimated 45% in Kenya and 43% across LMICs.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Of note, the national and international estimates of at-risk development are modeled using population data for extreme poverty and stunting as proxies for at-risk development, rather than individual-level evaluations, which generally yield greater precision. Even with more informed modeling, using data from health surveys, cohort studies, and hospital databases, the estimates of identified developmental disability in young Kenyan children is 10%,<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> which is still higher than this trial's estimate. Due to the varying definitions of at-risk development or developmental disability and the data used for modeling, it is difficult to compare those values with individual-level screening with the DSQ. When our findings are compared to other studies using the DSQ, rates of at-risk development within this study are comparable, albeit, still slightly lower than expected. These studies determined rates of at-risk development of 4.8%–7.3% in children under age 2 years using the DSQ.<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> Within the DSQ validation trial in Bangladesh, 17% of children tested were identified as at-risk for developmental delays.<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Because the DSQ was administered among a myriad of other questions, the risk for response bias and interpretability of questions across different cultural contexts may complicate these results. Additional investigations, such as formative work and cognitive interviews to ensure face validity of questions, testing alongside clinical examinations, or more detailed developmental assessments, are needed to evaluate the DSQ's adequacy in identifying infants with at-risk development in this setting.</p>
              <p>Our study found that the majority of mothers in both the intervention and control groups agreed with using physical punishment to discipline their children, although this was more common among those in the intervention group. Corporal punishment as a discipline method is associated with worse child behavioral and developmental outcomes; however, most evidence is focused on outcomes of children older than those within our cohort (i.e., aged older than 5 years).<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> Positive parenting training is integrated within the Chamas curriculum after 2 years of program enrollment, thus study participants had minimal exposure at the time of assessment. Mothers would have relied on their prior knowledge and experiences to guide their views on physical punishment, which is very common in Kenya,<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> and the higher rates of physical punishment use among the intervention group was likely incidental. The long-term impact of childhood physical punishment and parental exposure to positive parenting on ECD should be explored within this cohort in future studies.</p>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>The majority of mothers in both the intervention and control groups agreed with using physical punishment to discipline their children, which is associated with worse child behavioral and developmental outcomes.</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>Aligned with current evidence, this study found that delayed introduction of mixed feeding was protective against at-risk development. Exclusive breastfeeding in the first 3–6 months of life has been associated with improved cognitive outcomes early in life; however, that benefit may not be maintained as children become school-aged.<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> While the mechanism for this effect is unclear and likely multifactorial,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref> delayed mixed feeding improves nutritional status.<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> Malnutrition is a critical risk factor for worsened developmental outcomes.<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Although our analyses were limited by the absence of objective nutritional markers, we predict this adjustment would have minimally impacted our primary outcome. Children within the control group had a lower probability of poverty and, by proxy, would have been more likely to access nutritious foods. Future studies involving this cohort will work toward obtaining anthropometric measurements on study participants.</p>
              <p>Moreover, our findings demonstrated that as the age of the child increased, the rates of at-risk development decreased. One potential explanation for this finding is related to the left-shifted or skewed distribution of age within this study cohort toward the upper end of the age range, allowing for a more reliable interpretation of the data through the model at older ages. Another potential explanation for this age-related difference is the enhanced reliability of testing in older children. The American Academy of Pediatrics recommends beginning developmental screening at 9 months, as many skills emerge by and differentiate at this age, resulting in a more reliable evaluation of developmental status.<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> While less reliable, screening for at-risk development within younger aged children can be helpful to allow for those identified as having delays to be referred to appropriate therapies during the first 1,000 days of life, when they are most likely to gain the most benefit from the services.<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Longitudinal assessment of this cohort should be explored to understand the stability of developmental status over time.</p>
              <p>An unexpected finding of our analysis was the decreased odds of at-risk development associated with uncovered or natural walls compared to finished walls. Finished walls are typically correlated with higher socioeconomic status, which has demonstrated association with improved developmental outcomes.<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> There is evidence to suggest the quality of a child's home environment, such as the housing quality, residential mobility, and availability of learning materials, may impact ECD.<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref> However, few studies have looked at specific housing materials,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and none have specified an association between wall material and ECD.<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Attempting to quantify poverty status in LMICs poses significant challenges and limitations. However, tools that incorporate multiple variables to differentiate individuals on economic statuses, such as the PPI, can be helpful. While it is unclear at this time why a finding associated with higher socioeconomic status is linked with increased odds of at-risk development, we hypothesize that more complex mediators may come into play when a family has finished walls. For example, families with finished walls within their home may have 2 income-earning parents, requiring childcare for the infants. In settings like Kenya, there are limited options for high-quality, stimulating childcare, a variable for which no data were collected for this study. Another potential mediating factor may be potential exposure to lead paint, which is still used in parts of Kenya<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> and is known to be associated with worse developmental outcomes.<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref> However, these ideas are speculative in nature and should be further explored. More delineated knowledge about household factors and their implications on child development is needed.</p>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>An unexpected finding of our analysis was the decreased odds of at-risk development associated with uncovered or natural walls compared to finished walls.</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>Our study also has notable strengths. First, by using a cluster-randomized design, we strengthen the reliability as well as contextual relevance of our results for future implementation in a community-based setting. Second, we successfully recruited and collected data on a large cohort of participants across 4 diverse sub-counties in Trans Nzoia, strengthening the generalizability of our findings. Third, by conducting an intention-to-treat analysis, our findings suggest any degree of exposure to the Chamas intervention may yield protective benefits against developmental delay. This analysis approach helps simulate a real-world context where perfect program attendance is unexpected. Fourth, this cohort was sufficiently large to generate significant results in our outcome of interest. These results help strengthen our understanding of developmental delay and potentially associated risk factors in a resource-limited setting. Lastly, we used a validated questionnaire to assess ECD, which also expands upon limited data to support the utility of this screening tool in other LMICs.</p>
              <sec id="s4.1">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>Our study has several limitations. We experienced moderate loss to follow-up rates, highlighting challenges in retention and data collection. Women living within rural areas of Kenya tend to be more difficult to trace for follow-up due to limited details regarding the location of their residence (i.e., no street addresses) and lack of cell phone access or cellular network coverage. Individuals who are self-employed as casual laborers must frequently move for employment opportunities. We believe these are the major reasons for lost-to-follow-up within our cohort, but more formal analysis may be required. Another limitation to this study is that the DSQ requires mothers to subjectively affirm responses to a set of observed behaviors, which risks introduction of both response and recall biases. Screening mechanisms that triangulate data from both subjectively recorded data and observed behaviors would improve the reliability of these outcomes; however, it is worth noting that these evaluations are often cost-prohibitive, particularly in resource-limited settings. Lastly, some variables that may influence child development, such as anthropometrics and nutritional status, were not included within our follow-up evaluations due to limited trial resources. We hope future studies of this intervention will include these data to strengthen our analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>POLICY IMPLICATIONS AND CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>A significant advantage of the Chamas model is that it leverages existing resources (e.g., CHVs) and emphasizes collaborative investment from key stakeholders to ensure the program iteratively responds to the community's needs. While other group-based caregiver interventions have demonstrated positive results for ECD, many of these strategies introduce resource-related challenges that may compromise long-term quality and sustainability in these settings.<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref> A cost-effectiveness analysis of the Chamas model was performed and found to be US$46 per beneficiary, with both mother and infants included as beneficiaries, and would decrease to US$33 per beneficiary if continued within the same region over time (full analysis detailed in <ext-link xlink:href="http://ghspjournal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349/-/DCSupplemental" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">Supplement 3</ext-link>). Further, this analysis of DSQ data from a cluster randomized controlled trial demonstrated Chamas' potential to improve ECD outcomes. Our findings suggest this community-based intervention focused on health education for pregnant and postpartum women may support ECD as compared to the standard of care. As such, policy makers should consider the Chamas model when looking to revise current strategies to help protect children from developmental delay in this setting.</p>
              <boxed-text position="float">
                <p>A significant advantage of the Chamas model is that it leverages existing resources and emphasizes collaborative investment from key stakeholders to ensure the program iteratively responds to the community's needs.</p>
              </boxed-text>
              <p>In summary, maternal participation in a community-based women's health education program was associated with lower rates of at-risk development among their children compared to the standard of care. Overall, rates of at-risk development were lower than expected for this population, warranting further investigation. Chamas may help protect children from developmental delay in rural Kenya and other resource-limited settings. Future studies are needed to clarify this association and to improve our model so that we may continue to support women and children across Kenya and in other resource-limited settings.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
                <caption>
                  <title>20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-2.pdf</title>
                </caption>
                <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-2.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="PMC_2" content-type="local-data">
                <caption>
                  <title>20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-1.pdf</title>
                </caption>
                <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-1.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="PMC_3" content-type="local-data">
                <caption>
                  <title>20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-3.pdf</title>
                </caption>
                <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="20-00349-McHenry-Supplement-3.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>We thank our study participants, community health volunteers, research assistants, and staff without whom this work would not be possible. We additionally thank the sub-county and county Ministry of Health representatives in Trans Nzoia County, Kenya, for their support and collaboration. The Chamas for Change parent trial was made possible through the generous support of the Saving Lives at Birth partners: the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), the Norwegian Agency for Development Cooperation (Norad), the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Grand Challenges Canada, the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), and the Korea International Cooperation Agency (KOICA). It was prepared by the Chamas for Change team and does not necessarily reflect the views of the Saving Lives at Birth partners or the institutions with which the authors are affiliated.</p>
            </ack>
            <ack>
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This study was made possible through the generous support of the Saving Lives at Birth partners: the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), the Norwegian Agency for Development Cooperation (Norad), the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Grand Challenges Canada, the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), and the Korea International Cooperation Agency (KOICA) (Grant No. 0755-03). This manuscript is the work of the authors listed above and does not necessarily reflect the views of the Saving Lives at Birth partners. Megan McHenry's salary was supported by a career development award funded through the National Institutes of Mental Health (K23MH116808.)</p>
            </ack>
            <ack>
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>LJR, ACD, JJS conceptualized and sought funding for this study. LYM developed the protocols and data collection instruments, with oversight from LJR. MSM helped select an appropriate screening tool to conduct developmental assessments for the parent trial, with feedback provided by LYM and LJR. GA and EK oversaw data collection activities and data management processes. All authors contributed to developing our statistical analysis plan. MSM and LYM completed the first draft of this manuscript. ZY completed all statistical analyses with significant input from MSM and LYM. All authors contributed substantially to revising this article critically for important intellectual content. All authors contributed to the final manuscript and approved submission for publication.</p>
            </ack>
            <ack>
              <title>Data sharing</title>
              <p>The deidentified data set and a data dictionary will be made available with publication of the trial after obtaining relevant Institutional Research Ethics Committee approval of a proposal and signed data access agreement. Inquiries can be made to co-author, Dr. Lauren Y. Maldonado (<email>lymaldonado@mgh.harvard.edu</email>).</p>
            </ack>
            <ack>
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p>None declared.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grantham-McGregor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cueto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glewwe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Strupp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>International Child Development Steering Group</collab>. <article-title>Developmental potential in the first 5 years for children in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>369</volume>(<issue>9555</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60032-4</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 17208643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17208643</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Early Childhood Development Overview</collab>. <article-title>World Bank</article-title>. <comment>Updated October 25, 2021</comment>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/earlychildhooddevelopment" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/earlychildhooddevelopment</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>LCH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early childhood development coming of age: science through the life course</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10064</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31389-7</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27717614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Nurturing Care: a framework for helping children survive and thrive to transform health and human potential</article-title>. <source>Country profiles</source> (<year>2020</year>). <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://nurturing-care.org/resources/country-profiles/" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://nurturing-care.org/resources/country-profiles/</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Nurturing Care for Early Childhood Development</collab>. <source>Early Childhood Development: Kenya Country Profile</source>. <publisher-name>UNICEF, Countdown to 2030 Women's Children's and Adolescent's Health</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://nurturing-care.org/profiles/Kenya" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://nurturing-care.org/profiles/Kenya</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwoma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Owino</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngutu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okeng'o</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelima</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Expanding the Basics: Mapping the Gaps Between Expert, Decision-Maker and Public Understandings of Early Childhood Development in Kenya</source>. <publisher-name>A FrameWorks Research Report. UNICEF, Center on the Developing Child at Harvard University, Africa Early Childhood Network</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frameworksinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/KenyaECDMTG-FINAL.pdf" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://www.frameworksinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/KenyaECDMTG-FINAL.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>LCH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early childhood development coming of age: science through the life course</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10064</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31389-7</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27717614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Five-minute Apgar score as a marker for developmental vulnerability at 5 years of age</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>F114</fpage>–<lpage>F120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2015-308458</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 26187935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26187935</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleves</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cradock</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>KJS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive and behavioral outcomes of school-aged children who were born preterm: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>288</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.288.6.728</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 12169077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169077</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive and motor outcomes in children born low birth weight: a systematic review and meta-analysis of studies from South Asia</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-019-1408-8</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 30696415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30696415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernard-Bonnin</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>Canadian Paediatric Society, Mental Health and Developmental Disabilities Committee</collab>. <article-title>Maternal depression and child development</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Child Health</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pch/9.8.575</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 19680490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachs</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantham-McGregor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inequality in early childhood: risk and protective factors for early child development</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>378</volume>(<issue>9799</issue>):<fpage>1325</fpage>–<lpage>1338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60555-2</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 21944375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944375</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Chamas for Change improves mother-baby health</article-title>. <source>AMPATH</source>. <month>April</month><day>20</day>, <year>2018</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://ampath.squarespace.com/news-blog-feed/2018/4/20/chamas-for-change-improves-mother-baby-health" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://ampath.squarespace.com/news-blog-feed/2018/4/20/chamas-for-change-improves-mother-baby-health</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Songok</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Promoting positive maternal, newborn, and child health behaviors through a group-based health education and microfinance program: a prospective matched cohort study in western Kenya</article-title>. <source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>288</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-020-02978-w</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 32398156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32398156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christoffersen-Deb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Elung'at</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Atieno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Songok</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chamas for Change: an integrated community-based strategy of peer support in pregnancy and infancy in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Lancet Glob Health</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>S22</issue>):<fpage>S22</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(15)70141-5</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Republic of Kenya Ministry of Health (MOH)</collab>. <source>Taking the Kenya Essential Package for Health to the Community: A Strategy for the Delivery of Level One Services (Community Health Strategy)</source>. <publisher-name>MOH</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.communityledtotalsanitation.org/sites/communityledtotalsanitation.org/files/community_strategy.pdf" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://www.communityledtotalsanitation.org/sites/communityledtotalsanitation.org/files/community_strategy.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Kenya National Bureau of Statistics. Republic of Kenya Ministry of Health. Kenya National AIDS Control Council. Kenya National Council for Population and Development. Kenya Medical Research Institute</collab>. <source>Kenya Demographic and Health Survey 2014</source>. <publisher-name>ICF International</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr308/fr308.pdf" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr308/fr308.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Chama Cha MamaToto: a pilot study of peer support groups in Kenya</article-title>. <comment>NCT03188250. ClinicalTrials.gov</comment>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03188250" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03188250</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grantham-McGregor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of studies on the effect of iron deficiency on cognitive development in children</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>2</issue>)(<issue>2S-2</issue>):<fpage>649S</fpage>–<lpage>668S</lpage>, <comment>discussion 666S–668S</comment>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/131.2.649S</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 11160596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsimis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Infections and brain development</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/OGX.0000000000000236</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 26490164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26490164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kvestad</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hysing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diarrhea, stimulation and growth predict neurodevelopment in young North Indian children</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e0121743</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121743</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 25826376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25826376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuartas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey-Guerra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beatriz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salhi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early childhood exposure to non-violent discipline and physical and psychological aggression in low- and middle-income countries: national, regional, and global prevalence estimates</article-title>. <source>Child Abuse Negl</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2019.03.021</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 30939376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30939376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachs</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeks Gardner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Child development: risk factors for adverse outcomes in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>369</volume>(<issue>9556</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60076-2</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 17223478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223478</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachs</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantham-McGregor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inequality in early childhood: risk and protective factors for early child development</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>378</volume>(<issue>9799</issue>):<fpage>1325</fpage>–<lpage>1338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60555-2</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 21944375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944375</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Republic of Kenya. Ministry of Health (MOH). Division of Community Health Services</collab>. <source>Community Health Volunteers (CHVs): Basic Modules Handbook</source>. <publisher-name>MOH</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="http://guidelines.health.go.ke:8000/media/CHV_handbook_PDF-F.pdf" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">http://guidelines.health.go.ke:8000/media/CHV_handbook_PDF-F.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muslima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilpi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of a home-based neurodevelopmental screening tool for under 2-year-old children in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2214.2012.01393.x</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 22676392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676392</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Kenya Poverty Probability Index. Innovations for Poverty Action</article-title>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.povertyindex.org/country/kenya" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://www.povertyindex.org/country/kenya</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Proulx</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nurturing care: promoting early childhood development</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10064</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31390-3</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27717615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks-Gunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Provisions of learning experiences in the home and early childhood school readiness are clearly linked</article-title>. <source>New Dir Child Adolesc Dev</source>. <year>2001</year>;(<issue>92</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cd.11</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 11468863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11468863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Runyan</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zolotor</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The development and piloting of the ISPCAN Child Abuse Screening Tool-Parent version (ICAST-P)</article-title>. <source>Child Abuse Negl</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>826</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2009.09.006</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 19854511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854511</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutterford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Copas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for sample size determination in cluster randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1051</fpage>–<lpage>1067</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyv113</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 26174515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174515</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathways between paternal and maternal education, caregivers' support for learning, and early child development in 44 low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>Early Child Res Q</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecresq.2017.07.001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnick</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Housing quality and access to material and learning resources within the home environment in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Child Dev</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8624.2011.01674.x</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 22277008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22277008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs</collab>. <source>Transforming Our World: The 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development</source>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://sdgs.un.org/2030agenda" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://sdgs.un.org/2030agenda</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Daelmans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Investing in the foundation of sustainable development: pathways to scale up for early childhood development</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10064</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31698-1</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27717610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Shonkoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>From Neurons to Neighborhoods: The Science of Early Childhood Development</source>. <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>. <?supplied-pmid 25077268?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization</collab>. <source>Accountability in Education: Meeting Our Commitments</source>. <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>. <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed October 25, 2021</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://en.unesco.org/gem-report/report/2017/accountability-education" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://en.unesco.org/gem-report/report/2017/accountability-education</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Strategies to avoid the loss of developmental potential in more than 200 million children in the developing world</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>369</volume>(<issue>9557</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60112-3</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 17240290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17240290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaivada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffey</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Promoting early child development with interventions in health and nutrition: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e20164308</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2016-4308</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 28771408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28771408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladstone</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandawasvika</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Independent and combined effects of improved water, sanitation, and hygiene (WASH) and improved complementary feeding on early neurodevelopment among children born to HIV-negative mothers in rural Zimbabwe: substudy of a cluster-randomized trial</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e1002766</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002766</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 30897095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30897095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntozini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of improved complementary feeding and improved water, sanitation and hygiene on early child development among HIV-exposed children: substudy of a cluster randomised trial in rural Zimbabwe</article-title>. <source>BMJ Glob Health</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e001718</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2019-001718</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 32133164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32133164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousafzai</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Obradović</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of responsive stimulation and nutrition interventions on children's development and growth at age 4 years in a disadvantaged population in Pakistan: a longitudinal follow-up of a cluster-randomised factorial effectiveness trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Glob Health</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e548</fpage>–<lpage>e558</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(16)30100-0</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27342433?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27342433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousafzai</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of integrated responsive stimulation and nutrition interventions in the lady health worker programme in Pakistan on child development, growth, and health outcomes: a cluster-randomised factorial effectiveness trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>384</volume>(<issue>9950</issue>):<fpage>1282</fpage>–<lpage>1293</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60455-4</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 24947106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24947106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olusanya</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wertlieb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>Global Research on Developmental Disabilities Collaborators</collab>. <article-title>Developmental disabilities among children younger than 5 years in 195 countries and territories, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016</article-title>. <source>Lancet Glob Health</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e1100</fpage>–<lpage>e1121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30309-7</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 30172774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30172774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilpi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Displaced Rohingya children at high risk for mental health problems: findings from refugee camps within Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12623</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 30335204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30335204</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>ASH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Status of neurodevelopmental impairments among children using rapid neurodevelopmental assessment attending a tertiary care hospital</article-title>. <source>Int J Contemp Ped</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>6</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18203/2349-3291.ijcp20194701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldfogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks-Gunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Corporal punishment and child behavioral and cognitive outcomes through 5 years-of-age: evidence from a contemporary urban birth cohort study</article-title>. <source>Infant Child Dev</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/icd.758</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 24839402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24839402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aucoin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodin</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Corporal punishment and child adjustment</article-title>. <source>J Appl Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appdev.2006.08.001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B49">
                <label>49.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldfogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks-Gunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spanking and child development across the first decade of life</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1118</fpage>–<lpage>e1125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-1227</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 24144718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24144718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B50">
                <label>50.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lansford</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Alampay</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Hassan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Corporal punishment of children in nine countries as a function of child gender and parent gender</article-title>. <source>Int J Pediatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2010</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/672780</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 20976255?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976255</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B51">
                <label>51.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jedrychowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of exclusive breastfeeding on the development of children's cognitive function in the Krakow prospective birth cohort study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00431-011-1507-5</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 21660433?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21660433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B52">
                <label>52.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Breastfeeding, cognitive and noncognitive development in early childhood: a population study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e20161848</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2016-1848</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 28348200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B53">
                <label>53.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horta</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Loret de Mola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Victora</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Breastfeeding and intelligence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>467</issue>)(<issue>S467</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apa.13139</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 26211556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26211556</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B54">
                <label>54.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The science of breastfeeding and brain development</article-title>. <source>Breastfeed Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/bfm.2017.0122</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 28836820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28836820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B55">
                <label>55.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuchenbecker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinbott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exclusive breastfeeding and its effect on growth of Malawian infants: results from a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Int Child Health</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/2046905514Y.0000000134</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 25005815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25005815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B56">
                <label>56.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Council on Children With Disabilities; Section on Developmental Behavioral Pediatrics; Bright Futures Steering Committee; Medical Home Initiatives for Children With Special Needs Project Advisory Committee</collab>. <article-title>Identifying infants and young children with developmental disorders in the medical home: an algorithm for developmental surveillance and screening</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2006-1231</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 16818591?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818591</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B57">
                <label>57.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassells</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>MacAllister</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The physical environment and child development: an international review</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207594.2013.804190</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 23808797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23808797</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B58">
                <label>58.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Housing: an under-explored influence on children's well-being and becoming</article-title>. <source>Child Indic Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12187-018-9550-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B59">
                <label>59.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogilo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Onditi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of levels of heavy metals in paints from interior walls and indoor dust from residential houses in Nairobi City County, Kenya</article-title>. <source>Chem Sci Int J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/CSJI/2017/37392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B60">
                <label>60.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santa Maria</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lead (Pb) neurotoxicology and cognition</article-title>. <source>Appl Neuropsychol Child</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21622965.2018.1428803</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 29494781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29494781</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B61">
                <label>61.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Caregiver-mediated intervention for low-resourced preschoolers with autism: an RCT</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e72</fpage>–<lpage>e79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-3229</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 24958585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24958585</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B62">
                <label>62.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Does engaging in a group-based intervention increase parental self-efficacy in parents of preschool children? A systematic review of the current literature</article-title>. <source>J Child Fam Stud</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3173</fpage>–<lpage>3191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10826-016-0464-z</pub-id>. <?supplied-pmid 27795657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27795657</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes>
              <p>
                <bold>Peer Reviewed</bold>
              </p>
              <p><bold>First published online:</bold> December 3, 2021.</p>
              <p><bold>Cite this article as:</bold> McHenry MS, Maldonado LY, Yang Z, et al. Participation in a community-based women's health education program and at-risk child development in rural Kenya: developmental screening questionnaire results analysis. <italic>Glob Health Sci Pract</italic>. 2021;9(4):818-831. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:show="new">https://doi.org/10.9745/GHSP-D-20-00349</ext-link></p>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
