<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T07:36:54Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2833262" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2833262</identifier>
        <datestamp>2011-03-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>brjcancer</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="other" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Cancer</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br J Cancer</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>British Journal of Cancer</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0007-0920</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1532-1827</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2833262</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2833262</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2833262</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20197772</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">6605581</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6605581</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20197772</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Short Communication</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Adenovirus DNA in Guthrie cards from children who develop acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL)</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running">Adenovirus DNA in Guthrie cards of children with ALL</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Honkaniemi</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
                    <sup>9</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Talekar</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
                    <sup>9</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bogdanovic</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Forestier</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>von Doblen</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Engvall</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ornelles</surname>
                    <given-names>D A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gooding</surname>
                    <given-names>L R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Clinical Science, Intervention and Technology, Astrid Lindgren Children's Hospital, Karolinska University Hospital-Huddinge, CLINTEC, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm S-141 86, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Emory University School of Medicine</institution>, Atlanta, GA, <country>USA</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Karolinska University Hospital</institution>, Stockholm, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Microbiology, Tumour and Cell Biology, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Clinical Science, Paediatrics, Umeå University Hospital</institution>, Umeå, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Division of Metabolic Diseases, Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Wake Forest University School of Medicine</institution>, Winston-Salem, NC, <country>USA</country></aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>britt.gustafsson@ki.se</email></corresp>
                <fn id="note1" fn-type="equal">
                  <label>9</label>
                  <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>02</day>
                <month>03</month>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>02</day>
                <month>03</month>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>102</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>796</fpage>
              <lpage>798</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>06</day>
                  <month>01</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>01</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2010 Cancer Research UK</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Cancer Research UK</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material.If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>In search of a proposed viral aetiology of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL), the common species C adenoviruses were analysed in Guthrie cards.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>Guthrie cards from 243 children who later developed ALL and from 486 matched controls were collected and analysed by nested polymerase chain reaction for the presence of adenovirus DNA.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>Adenovirus DNA was reliably detected from only two subjects, both of whom developed ALL.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>Adenovirus DNA is detected in Guthrie card samples at too low a frequency to reveal an association between adenovirus and the development of leukaemia.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>aetiology</kwd>
                <kwd>childhood leukaemia</kwd>
                <kwd>adenovirus</kwd>
                <kwd>prenatal infection</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL) is the most common malignancy in childhood, with an annual incidence of three to four cases per 100 000 children in developed countries. Although the aetiology in over 95% of ALL is unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Doll, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Margolin, 1997</xref>), it is widely believed that an infectious agent may have an effect in the development of this haematological malignancy. We recently reported that adenovirus DNA was detected in 13 of 51 Guthrie cards from ALL patients, but in only 6 of 47 healthy controls (<italic>P</italic>=0.0122, Fisher's exact test), indicating that adenovirus may be such a causative agent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Gustafsson <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>). However, a subsequent study of twice as many paediatric ALL patients in California failed to find adenovirus DNA in the corresponding neonatal blood spots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Vasconcelos <italic>et al</italic>, 2008</xref>). This study sought to further examine the possibility of an association between prenatal adenovirus infection and ALL using a larger number of archived Swedish samples from children who later developed ALL and controls without the disease.</p>
            <sec>
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <p>The patient population included 243 Swedish children who were diagnosed with ALL between 1992 and 2006. The mean age was 5.4 years and the median was 4.3 years (range 67 days to 15 years). Patients were randomly selected from the Nordic Society of Paediatric Haematology and Oncology register. Ten of these 243 children were included in our previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Gustafsson <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>) and two of them were positive for adenovirus DNA in that study. More than half (58%) of the subjects were male and 217 (89%) of the leukaemias were of B-cell lineage. As controls, Guthrie cards from 486 children with no known history of leukaemia were picked two Guthrie cards apart from the patient Guthrie card in the Guthrie card archive, thereby matching for birthplace and birthdate.</p>
              <p>The blood from infants that was collected on Guthrie cards at 3–5 days of age was processed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Barbi <italic>et al</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Priftakis <italic>et al</italic>, 2003</xref>), except that a total of four punches were harvested from each card compared with three punches in the previous study. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee at Karolinska Institutet and by the Institutional Review Board of Emory University.</p>
              <p>The material recovered from four 3-mm punches from a Guthrie card represented approximately 12 <italic>μ</italic>l of blood containing about 180 000 leukocytes and 120 000 lymphocytes in a final volume of 60–80 <italic>μ</italic>l. Samples were first tested for the presence of DNA by real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for the human albumin gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Laurendeau <italic>et al</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Desire <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>), using 5 <italic>μ</italic>l of material from each sample. The sensitivity of the method was 10 copies per reaction. Positive samples were coded and sent to Atlanta, where they were screened for the presence of species C adenovirus DNA by nested PCR (nPCR-2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>) using primers P11–P14, which were designed to amplify a conserved region of the species C adenovirus hexon gene corresponding to nucleotides 18 838–19 205 of Ad2 (GenBank accession no. BK000407). Samples having one or more positive reactions with nPCR-2 were then re-tested in duplicate with nPCR-2 and with another nested PCR assay (nPCR-1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>) using primers P7–P10 derived from the Ad2 hexon sequence, to amplify nucleotides 20 721–21 572. Both adenovirus-specific PCR assays routinely detect fewer than five copies of the viral genome. Products of nPCR-1 from samples testing positive by both reactions were sequenced at Eurofins MWG Operon (Huntsville, AL, USA) to confirm the adenovirus serotype. The sequences were aligned by Lasergene software (DNAStar, Inc., Madison, WI, USA) and compared with the sequences from species C adenoviruses in GenBank.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>DNA was successfully extracted from the Guthrie cards of 243 patients and from 484 of 486 controls. Two of the control samples were negative for the albumin gene by real-time PCR and were therefore excluded. All samples were analysed in duplicate reactions for the presence of species C adenovirus DNA using hexon-specific nPCR-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>). Only nine of the 727 samples yielded a positive result in at least one PCR reaction. These nine samples were re-tested using both nPCR-2 and nPCR-1, which detected a different region of the hexon gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>). Two of the nine samples were confirmed to contain adenoviral DNA by their yielding at least one positive result in each pair of reactions performed with both hexon-specific PCR assays. The other seven samples failed to yield a positive reaction with either PCR assay and were considered negative. Both positive samples were derived from ALL donor Guthrie cards. Both positive samples were confirmed to contain Ad2 DNA by sequencing the product of nPCR-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">2009</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The reasons for the discrepancy between this investigation and our previous preliminary study are unclear. Quantitative analysis for a single-copy cellular gene indicated that the DNA present in Guthrie card extractions in this study was significantly more concentrated than that used in the preliminary report (data not shown). Controls analysed in the previous study eliminated the likelihood of PCR procedural contamination. Nonetheless, levels of adenovirus DNA measured by quantitative real-time PCR showed very low levels of viral DNA in the positive samples. We are unable to exclude the possibility of random environmental contamination in the previous study, although no negative controls were found to contain adenoviral DNA.</p>
              <p>The low fraction of Guthrie cards positive for adenoviral DNA is in sharp contrast with studies on amniotic fluid. Of 1187 unique amniocentesis samples analysed in four separate studies of sonographically normal pregnancies, more than 1 in 20 (5.4%) contained adenoviral DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Van den Veyver <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Wenstrom <italic>et al</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baschat <italic>et al</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Reddy <italic>et al</italic>, 2005</xref>). Remarkably, subsequent studies have detected no increased morbidity in infants following prenatal infection with adenovirus, as determined by PCR of amniocentesis samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Miller <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>), suggesting that prenatal infection, similar to postnatal infection, with species C adenoviruses is largely asymptomatic. Given a prenatal infection rate of 5%, our Guthrie card analysis seriously underestimates the frequency of fetal adenovirus infections, which is consistent with the biology of this pathogen. These results lead us to conclude that adenovirus DNA is not readily detected in the archived neonatal blood spots, irrespective of whether the subject subsequently develops leukaemia. Although the findings reported here fail to support our previously reported preliminary results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Gustafsson <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>), these findings agree with those reported subsequently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Vasconcelos <italic>et al</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p>
              <p>Adenovirus is not commonly found in peripheral blood, except during a fulminant infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Flomenberg <italic>et al</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Perlman <italic>et al</italic>, 2007</xref>). By contrast, a large majority of lymphocyte samples isolated from the adenoids or tonsils of normal children undergoing tonsillectomy or adenoidectomy contain adenovirus DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">2009</xref>). Thus, after acute infection, adenovirus DNA may be restricted to mucosal lymphoid compartments in the infected neonate, as well as in the latently infected child, which may explain our inability to detect this virus in a high fraction of Guthrie cards containing peripheral blood.</p>
              <p>Although these findings show no association between the development of leukaemia and adenovirus DNA in neonatal blood, this pathogen remains an intriguing candidate for a role in the aetiology of leukaemia. Species C adenovirus oncoproteins that disable the cellular DNA repair machinery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Weitzman and Ornelles, 2005</xref>) also have the power to transform cells by a ‘hit and run’ mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Nevels <italic>et al</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Endter and Dobner, 2004</xref>), making species C adenovirus a candidate for promoting the initial genetic lesion leading to leukaemia. Adenovirus may also have a role in the second hit postulated in the delayed infection model of leukaemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Greaves, 2006</xref>). The fraction of children undergoing tonsillectomies with adenovirus DNA in their mucosal lymphocytes peaks between 2 to 5 years (see Figure 1 of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Garnett <italic>et al</italic>, 2009</xref>), which coincides with the peak presentation of childhood ALL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Greaves, 2006</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>We thank Marianne Alverstrand and Peter Castenbäck for their invaluable technical assistance. This work was supported by the Mary Béve Foundation for Paediatric Cancer Research, The Swedish Children Cancer Foundation, The Samariten Foundation, The Fernström foundation, a Government Public Health Grant (ALF), and by US PHS Grant CA127621.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Barbi M, Binda S, Primache V, Luraschi C, Corbetta C (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Diagnosis of congenital cytomegalovirus infection by detection of viral DNA in dried blood spots</article-title>. <source>Clin Diagn Virol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–32<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15566887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baschat AA, Towbin J, Bowles NE, Harman CR, Weiner CP (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of viral DNA in amniotic fluid of low-risk pregnancies in the second trimester</article-title>. <source>J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–384<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12962262</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Desire N, Dehee A, Schneider V, Jacomet C, Goujon C, Girard PM, Rozenbaum W, Nicolas JC (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Quantification of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 proviral load by a TaqMan real-time PCR assay</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1303</fpage>–1310<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Doll R (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The epidemiology of childhood leukemia</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc Ser</source>
<volume>Series A 152</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–351</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Endter C, Dobner T (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cell transformation by human adenoviruses</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source>
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–214<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14674602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Flomenberg P, Gutierrez E, Piaskowski V, Casper JT (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Detection of adenovirus DNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cells by polymerase chain reaction assay</article-title>. <source>J Med Virol</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–188<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9139081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garnett CT, Erdman D, Xu W, Gooding LR (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Prevalence and quantitation of species C adenovirus DNA in human mucosal lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>10608</fpage>–10616<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garnett CT, Talekar G, Mahr JA, Huang W, Zhang Y, Ornelles DA, Gooding LR (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Latent species C adenoviruses in human tonsil tissues</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>2417</fpage>–2428<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19109384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Greaves M (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Infection, immune responses and the aetiology of childhood leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–203</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gustafsson B, Huang W, Bogdanovic G, Gauffin F, Nordgren A, Talekar G, Ornelles DA, Gooding LR (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Adenovirus DNA is detected at increased frequency in Guthrie cards from children who develop acute lymphoblastic leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>
<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>992</fpage>–994<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17876329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Laurendeau I, Bahuau M, Vodovar N, Larramendy C, Olivi M, Bieche I, Vidaud M, Vidaud D (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>TaqMan PCR-based gene dosage assay for predictive testing in individuals from a cancer family with INK4 locus haploinsufficiency</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>982</fpage>–986<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Margolin J (<year>1997</year>) <source>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</source>. Lippincott-Raven: New York</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Miller JL, Harman C, Weiner C, Baschat AA (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Perinatal outcomes after second trimester detection of amniotic fluid viral genome in asymptomatic patients</article-title>. <source>J Perinatal Med</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–143</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nevels M, Tauber B, Spruss T, Wolf H, Dobner T (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>‘Hit-and-run’ transformation by adenovirus oncogenes</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>3089</fpage>–3094<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perlman J, Gibson C, Pounds SB, Gu Z, Bankowski MJ, Hayden RT (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Quantitative real-time PCR detection of adenovirus in clinical blood specimens: a comparison of plasma, whole blood and peripheral blood mononuclear cells</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–300<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17959413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Priftakis P, Dalianis T, Carstensen J, Samuelsson U, Lewensohn-Fuchs I, Bogdanovic G, Winiarski J, Gustafsson B (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Human polyomavirus DNA is not detected in Guthrie cards (dried blood spots) from children who developed acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Med Pediatr Oncol</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–223<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12555248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reddy UM, Baschat AA, Zlatnik MG, Towbin JA, Harman CR, Weiner CP (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Detection of viral deoxyribonucleic acid in amniotic fluid: association with fetal malformation and pregnancy abnormalities</article-title>. <source>Fetal Diagn Ther</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–207<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15824499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Van den Veyver IB, Ni J, Bowles N, Carpenter Jr RJ, Weiner CP, Yankowitz J, Moise Jr KJ, Henderson J, Towbin JA (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Detection of intrauterine viral infection using the polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Metab</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–95<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9562961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vasconcelos GM, Kang M, Pombo-de-Oliveira MS, Schiffman JD, Lorey F, Buffler P, Wiemels JL (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Adenovirus detection in Guthrie cards from paediatric leukaemia cases and controls</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>1668</fpage>–1672<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19002185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weitzman MD, Ornelles DA (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Inactivating intracellular antiviral responses during adenovirus infection</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>7686</fpage>–7696<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wenstrom KD, Andrews WW, Bowles NE, Towbin JA, Hauth JC, Goldenberg RL (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Intrauterine viral infection at the time of second trimester genetic amniocentesis</article-title>. <source>Obstetr Gynecol</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>–424</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
