<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T05:40:18Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3994928" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3994928</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-05-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>diacare</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diacare</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dcare</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3994928</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3994928</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3994928</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24595633</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2358</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc13-2358</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Cardiovascular and Metabolic Risk</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Increased Skeletal Muscle Capillarization After Aerobic Exercise Training and Weight Loss Improves Insulin Sensitivity in Adults With IGT</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Prior</surname>
                    <given-names>Steven J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Blumenthal</surname>
                    <given-names>Jacob B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Katzel</surname>
                    <given-names>Leslie I.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Goldberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrew P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ryan</surname>
                    <given-names>Alice S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Division of Gerontology and Geriatric Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Baltimore Veterans Affairs Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center and Research and Development Service, Baltimore, MD</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Steven J. Prior, <email>sprior@grecc.umaryland.edu</email>.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>37</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>1469</fpage>
              <lpage>1475</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2014 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="creative-commons">
                  <license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="1469.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>OBJECTIVE</title>
                  <p>Transcapillary transport of insulin is one determinant of glucose uptake by skeletal muscle; thus, a reduction in capillary density (CD) may worsen insulin sensitivity. Skeletal muscle CD is lower in older adults with impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) compared with those with normal glucose tolerance and may be modifiable through aerobic exercise training and weight loss (AEX+WL). We tested the hypothesis that 6-month AEX+WL would increase CD to improve insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance in older adults with IGT.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title>
                  <p>Sixteen sedentary, overweight-obese (BMI 27–35 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), older (63 ± 2 years) men and women with IGT underwent hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps to measure insulin sensitivity, oral glucose tolerance tests, exercise and body composition testing, and vastus lateralis muscle biopsies to determine CD before and after 6-month AEX+WL.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTS</title>
                  <p>Insulin sensitivity (M) and 120-min postprandial glucose (G<sub>120</sub>) correlated with CD at baseline (<italic>r</italic> = 0.58 and <italic>r</italic> = −0.60, respectively, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). AEX+WL increased maximal oxygen consumption (VO<sub>2max</sub>) 18% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02) and reduced weight and fat mass 8% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.02). CD increased 15% (264 ± 11 vs. 304 ± 14 capillaries/mm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01), M increased 21% (42.4 ± 4.0 vs. 51.4 ± 4.3 µmol/kg FFM/min, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and G<sub>120</sub> decreased 16% (9.35 ± 0.5 vs. 7.85 ± 0.5 mmol/L, <italic>P</italic> = 0.008) after AEX+WL. Regression analyses showed that the AEX+WL-induced increase in CD independently predicted the increase in M (<italic>r</italic> = 0.74, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) as well as the decrease in G<sub>120</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = −0.55, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
                  <p>Six-month AEX+WL increases skeletal muscle CD in older adults with IGT. This represents one mechanism by which AEX+WL improves insulin sensitivity in older adults with IGT.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="7"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>More than 26% of older Americans have impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), increasing their risk for developing type 2 diabetes. A sedentary lifestyle may further increase this risk through changes in skeletal muscle morphology and insulin signaling that worsen insulin resistance. We (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) and others (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) report low skeletal muscle capillarization in sedentary, insulin-resistant subjects that is inversely associated with the degree of glucose tolerance (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and directly associated with insulin sensitivity (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) in cross-sectional studies.</p>
              <p>As the major interface between the circulation and skeletal muscle, the microvasculature affects a number of physiological processes, including insulin resistance. Transcapillary transport of insulin is an important determinant of glucose uptake in skeletal muscle (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) and is a rate-limiting step for insulin action (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The reduced capillary surface area in IGT and type 2 diabetes is associated with lower glucose uptake during insulin infusion (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>); therefore, low skeletal muscle capillarization, along with defects in insulin signaling, can contribute to insulin resistance in IGT and type 2 diabetes by decreasing the available surface area for diffusion of insulin and glucose (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p>
              <p>Lifestyle interventions including aerobic exercise and weight loss (AEX+WL) are a cornerstone of the treatment of insulin resistance and can prevent progression from IGT to type 2 diabetes in older people (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). AEX training increases skeletal muscle capillarization in healthy adults (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), but less is known about its effects on skeletal muscle capillarization in insulin-resistant subjects. One study showed that AEX training increases skeletal muscle capillarization in subjects with IGT (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and such an increase in capillarization after AEX+WL may represent a mechanism for enhancing insulin and glucose delivery to skeletal muscle to improve insulin sensitivity. We hypothesized that a 6-month AEX+WL program would increase skeletal muscle capillarization in older adults with IGT, and that the increase in capillarization would translate to improvements in insulin sensitivity and glucose tolerance. To test this hypothesis, we examined skeletal muscle capillarization, glucose tolerance, and insulin sensitivity during hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps before and after 6 months of AEX+WL in overweight-obese, older adults with IGT.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2">
              <title>Research Design and Methods</title>
              <sec id="s3">
                <title>Subjects</title>
                <p>Men and postmenopausal women 50–80 years of age, who were nonsmokers and had no previous diagnosis of diabetes or cardiovascular disease, were recruited from the Baltimore, MD, regional area to participate in studies examining metabolic responses to AEX+WL. Data from eight men and eight women (mean age 63 ± 2 years) with IGT and skeletal muscle samples for assessment of capillarization are reported herein; subject characteristics and certain metabolic data from a larger sample of the subjects were previously reported (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Subjects were all weight stable (&lt;2.0 kg weight change in past year), sedentary (&lt;20 min of aerobic exercise two times per week), and screened by medical history questionnaire, physical examination, and fasting blood profile. Subjects were screened for IGT by oral glucose tolerance tests (OGTTs) according to American Diabetes Association criteria (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). All subjects were nonsmokers and showed no evidence of cancer; liver, renal, or hematological disease; or other medical disorders. The women in the study had not menstruated for at least 1 year. Subjects taking medications for hypertension or dyslipidemia were included if medically stable and if medications were not known to affect glucose metabolism. The research protocols were approved by the institutional review board at the University of Maryland School of Medicine. All subjects provided written informed consent.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4">
                <title>AEX+WL Intervention</title>
                <p>Prior to metabolic testing, subjects received 6–8 weeks of instruction on the Therapeutic Lifestyle Changes diet (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) in order to minimize potential confounding by changes in dietary composition during the intervention. Subjects followed the dietary guidelines and were weight stable for at least 2 weeks prior to baseline testing. After baseline testing, subjects were instructed to maintain the diet, and all subjects attended weekly weight loss classes for 6 months led by a registered dietitian. Individuals were counseled to restrict their caloric intake by 300–500 kcal/day to achieve &gt;5% weight loss during the intervention. Compliance was monitored by 7-day food records using the American Diabetes Association exchange list system. In addition, all subjects underwent 6 months of supervised AEX training on treadmills at the Baltimore Veterans Affairs Medical Center Geriatric Research, Education, and Clinical Center exercise facility. Exercise intensity was prescribed by target heart rate range calculated using the Karvonen formula (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>); heart rates were monitored during exercise with chest-strap heart rate monitors (Polar Electro Inc., Lake Success, NY). AEX training began at a volume of three sessions per week of 20 min at 50% of heart rate reserve, and gradually increased to three sessions per week of 45 min at ∼85% of heart rate reserve, a level maintained for &gt;4 months. Each exercise session included 5-min warm-up and cool-down phases. Compliance with the AEX+WL sessions was &gt;85%.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s5">
                <title>Body Composition</title>
                <p>Fat mass, fat-free mass, and percent body fat were measured with dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (Prodigy; LUNAR Radiation Corp., Madison, WI). Intra-abdominal (IAF) and subcutaneous abdominal (SAF) fat areas were determined by a computed tomography scan at L<sub>4</sub>-L<sub>5</sub> region using a Siemens Somatom Sensation 64 Scanner (Fairfield, CT) and Medical Image Processing, Analysis and Visualization software (MIPAV v.7.0.0; NIH, Bethesda, MD).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Maximal Oxygen Consumption</title>
                <p>Maximal oxygen consumption (VO<sub>2max</sub>) was measured by indirect calorimetry during a graded treadmill exercise test on a motorized treadmill. Subjects walked at a constant velocity throughout the protocol; grade was initially set to 0% and increased every 2 min thereafter to maximal effort. VO<sub>2max</sub> was defined as the highest oxygen consumption value obtained for a full 30-s increment. Attainment of VO<sub>2max</sub> was verified by standard physiological criteria (respiratory exchange ratio &gt;1.10 or a plateau in VO<sub>2</sub> with an increase in workload).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s7">
                <title>OGTT</title>
                <p>Subjects underwent 2-h OGTTs after a 12-h overnight fast. A catheter was placed in an antecubital vein and blood samples were drawn before and 30, 60, 90, and 120 min after the ingestion of a 75-g glucose solution. Blood samples were centrifuged and plasma was separated and stored at –80°C until analysis. Plasma glucose levels were analyzed with a glucose analyzer (2300 STAT Plus; YSI, Yellow Springs, OH). Plasma insulin levels were determined by radioimmunoassay (Millipore, St. Charles, MO). Glucose (G<sub>AUC</sub>) and insulin (I<sub>AUC</sub>) areas under the curve during the OGTT were calculated using the trapezoidal method. The homeostatic model assessment for insulin resistance was calculated as described by Matthews et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s8">
                <title>Hyperinsulinemic-Euglycemic Clamp</title>
                <p>Insulin-stimulated glucose uptake (M) was measured as an index of insulin sensitivity. Subjects were provided with all meals for the 2 days preceding the clamp to control nutrient intake. After a 12-h overnight fast, subjects underwent the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic glucose clamp (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) as performed in our laboratory (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Insulin was infused at a rate of 555 pmol/m<sup>2</sup>/min, and M is reported in micromoles of glucose infused per kilogram of fat-free mass per minute (µmol/kg FFM/min). Clamp data were not available for one subject after AEX+WL due to a technical problem. Plasma glucose levels were analyzed at 5-min intervals using the glucose oxidase method (Beckman Instruments, Fullerton, CA). Plasma insulin levels were determined by radioimmunoassay (Millipore, St. Charles, MO). Mean insulin and glucose levels during the clamp were 1,131 ± 32 pmol/L and 5.1 ± 0.1 mmol/L, respectively, and did not differ before and after AEX+WL (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.4).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s9">
                <title>Muscle Biopsies</title>
                <p>Percutaneous needle biopsies were obtained from the vastus lateralis, ∼12–13 cm above the patella on the anterolateral aspect of the right thigh using a Bergstrom needle (Stille, Solna, Sweden) as previously described (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Muscle samples were rapidly embedded in optimal cutting temperature-tragacanth gum mixture, frozen, and stored at −80°C for histochemical analyses.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s10">
                <title>Capillary Density</title>
                <p>Muscle was sectioned to a thickness of 14 μm on a cryostat and capillaries were identified using a modified double-stain technique (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In brief, muscle sections were fixed in acetone and washed with 1% BSA. Sections were then incubated with primary antibodies (Ulex europaeus agglutinin I for endothelial cells and mouse anticollagen IV for muscle fiber perimeters) and secondary antibodies (rabbit anti-Ulex europaeus, goat anti-rabbit, and goat anti-mouse). Sections were then reacted with avidin-biotinylated alkaline phosphatase (ABC/AP; Dako, Carpinteria, CA) and the New Fuchsin Substrate System (Dako, Carpinteria, CA). Immunostained muscle sections were viewed under a light microscope and digital images were obtained (Eclipse Ti; Nikon Instruments Inc., Melville, NY). Quantification of capillarization was performed on at least 50 fibers for each sample (mean = 69 ± 4 fibers/sample); sampling a larger number of fibers does not improve the estimation of capillarization in human muscle (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Images were analyzed using NIS Elements software (Nikon Instruments Inc.). The following four indices of capillarization were measured: <italic>1</italic>) capillary contacts (the number of capillaries in contact with each muscle fiber), <italic>2</italic>) individual capillary-to-fiber ratio (the number of whole capillary equivalents in contact with each muscle fiber), <italic>3</italic>) capillary density (CD; the number of capillaries per mm<sup>2</sup> of muscle cross-sectional area), and <italic>4</italic>) capillary-to-fiber perimeter exchange index (the number of capillaries per mm of muscle fiber perimeter).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s11">
                <title>Skeletal Muscle Fiber Type</title>
                <p>For each vastus lateralis sample, a serial section was obtained and fiber type was determined using a myosin ATPase technique. After an initial 5-min incubation in an acid solution (0.4% sodium acetate, 0.6% sodium barbital, and 0.04 N hydrochloric acid), the samples were incubated for 45 min in an ATP reaction solution (0.6% glycine, 0.6% calcium chloride, 0.4% sodium chloride, 0.3% sodium hydroxide, and 0.17% ATP). This was followed by a 3-min incubation in 1% calcium chloride, a 3-min incubation in 2% cobalt chloride, and a 1-min incubation in 0.2% ammonium sulfide. Stained sections viewed under a light microscope and digital images were obtained (Eclipse Ti).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s12">
                <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
                <p>The primary study outcomes were skeletal muscle capillarization, M, fasting plasma glucose, plasma glucose response to an OGTT, and VO<sub>2max</sub>. Secondary variables included fasting plasma insulin, plasma insulin response to an OGTT, and body composition. Data are presented as means ± SEM. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS v12.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY). Repeated-measures ANOVA was used to test for differences in outcome variables after AEX+WL, with sex used as a covariate in all analyses. Regression analyses were used to test for associations between capillarization variables and other primary and secondary variables; multivariable regression accounting for age, sex, and/or baseline levels of primary outcome variables was conducted where indicated. A type I error rate of α = 0.05 was selected, and two-tailed probabilities are reported for all analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s13">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s14">
                <title>Subject Characteristics and Responses to AEX+WL</title>
                <p>Subject characteristics, body composition, and cardiorespiratory fitness levels before and after 6-month AEX+WL are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. In response to the AEX+WL intervention, subjects reduced their body weight and fat mass by 8% and their BMI by 7% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 for all). The subjects did not have a statistically significant reduction in IAF, but did reduce SAF by 9% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.007). The subjects significantly increased VO<sub>2max</sub> (L/min) by 18% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Subject characteristics and responses to 6-month AEX+WL</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1469tbl1"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>AEX+WL significantly increased skeletal muscle capillarization (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), with a 15% increase in CD (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01), a 14% increase in capillary-to-fiber perimeter exchange index (<italic>P</italic> = 0.004), and a greater number of capillaries in contact with each skeletal muscle fiber (capillary contacts and capillary-to-fiber ratio, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The proportion of type I or II muscle fibers did not change after AEX+WL (65 ± 4 vs. 67 ± 5% type I fibers, <italic>P</italic> = 0.75) nor did skeletal muscle fiber area and perimeter (≤2% difference, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.68). These results indicate that the increase in CD was due to an increase in the number of capillaries, not a reduction in muscle fiber size.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Skeletal muscle capillarization, glucose tolerance, and insulin sensitivity before and after 6-month AEX+WL</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1469tbl2"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Data from glucose tolerance tests and hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. Fasting plasma glucose and insulin concentrations were numerically lower after AEX+WL, but the differences were not statistically significant. AEX+WL reduced 120-min postprandial glucose concentrations (G<sub>120</sub>) by 16% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.008), reduced 120-min postprandial insulin concentrations by 31% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04), and reduced G<sub>AUC</sub> by 10% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03). I<sub>AUC</sub> was numerically lower after AEX+WL (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08). Likewise, AEX+WL increased M (µmol/kg FFM/min) by 21% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s15">
                <title>Relationships Between Metabolic Variables and Skeletal Muscle Capillarization</title>
                <p>At baseline, M (µmol/kg FFM/min) directly correlated with CD (<italic>r</italic> = 0.62, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01) and tended to inversely correlate with IAF (<italic>r</italic> = −0.49, <italic>P</italic> = 0.07) in bivariate analyses. M was not associated with the proportion of type I or II muscle fibers (<italic>r</italic> =│0.0–0.27│, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.33 for all). Baseline G<sub>120</sub> correlated only with CD (<italic>r</italic> = −0.68, <italic>P</italic> = 0.004). In multivariable regression analyses accounting for age, sex, and body weight in the model, baseline CD was the only variable independently associated with M (partial <italic>r</italic> = 0.58, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>) and G<sub>120</sub> (partial <italic>r</italic> = −0.60, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>). Inclusion of IAF as an independent variable slightly reduced the overall <italic>r</italic> values in the regression models but did not affect the independent relationships (partial <italic>r</italic> values) between CD and M or G<sub>120</sub> in the models.</p>
                <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Scatterplots depicting the relationships between skeletal muscle CD and insulin sensitivity (M) (<italic>A</italic>) and 120-min postprandial glucose (G<sub>120</sub>) (<italic>B</italic>) at baseline in overweight-obese, older adults with IGT. Bivariate correlation coefficients are shown in the figures; partial correlation coefficients from regression models are <italic>r</italic> = 0.58 and <italic>r</italic> = −0.60, respectively. <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1469fig1"/>
                </fig>
                <p>After AEX+WL, the change in M (µmol/kg FFM/min) directly correlated with the change in CD (<italic>r</italic> = 0.53, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) but not with the changes in VO<sub>2max</sub>, body weight, body fat, IAF, or SAF (<italic>r</italic> = −0.19 to 0.29, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.33) in bivariate analyses. Likewise, the change in G<sub>120</sub> inversely correlated with the change in CD (<italic>r</italic> = −0.51, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04). In multivariable regression analyses accounting for age, sex, and the change in body weight, the AEX+WL-induced increase in CD independently correlated with the increase in M (partial <italic>r</italic> = 0.74, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>) and the decrease in G<sub>120</sub> (partial <italic>r</italic> = −0.55, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Scatterplots depicting the relationships between the AEX+WL-induced change in skeletal muscle CD and insulin sensitivity (M) (<italic>A</italic>) and 120-min postprandial glucose (G<sub>120</sub>) (<italic>B</italic>) in overweight-obese older adults with IGT. Bivariate correlation coefficients are shown in the figures; partial correlation coefficients from regression models are <italic>r</italic> = 0.74, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006 and <italic>r</italic> = −0.55, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04, respectively.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="1469fig2"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s16">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Insulin resistance and diabetes are health problems that affect more than one-third of older adults. Although lifestyle interventions including exercise and weight loss can improve glucose tolerance and reduce risk for type 2 diabetes (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), many of the underlying mechanisms remain elusive. The current study shows that despite the capillary rarefaction found in the skeletal muscle of sedentary, older adults with IGT, AEX+WL significantly increases skeletal muscle capillarization. Furthermore, this is the first study to show that increases in capillarization are directly associated with improvements in glucose tolerance and insulin sensitivity measured during a hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp to our knowledge. Therefore, despite impaired angiogenesis and capillary rarefaction in sedentary people with insulin resistance and IGT, the ability to increase capillarization in skeletal muscle is maintained and likely contributes to AEX+WL-induced improvements in insulin sensitivity in older adults at risk for type 2 diabetes.</p>
              <p>Skeletal muscle capillarization increases after AEX training in healthy young (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and older (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) subjects; however, few studies have examined the effects of AEX training with or without WL on capillarization in subjects with IGT or type 2 diabetes to date. In one study, AEX training increased capillarization by 10% in a small group of men with IGT (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Our results are concordant with these findings, indicating that skeletal muscle capillarization does increase with AEX+WL in both men and women with IGT. Another study using a combined AEX and strength training intervention showed an increase in the number of capillaries per fiber and in muscle fiber size, but no change in CD in subjects with type 2 diabetes (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The maintenance of CD with increases in fiber size in that study suggests that angiogenesis occurred in skeletal muscle and that diabetes-associated capillary rarefaction may be reversible. As there were no changes in fiber size after AEX+WL in our study, increases in capillarization were consistent across the measurements we report. Weight loss independent of AEX may not be associated with an increase in skeletal muscle capillarization (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>); however, one study showed increases in CD with large amounts (&gt;20%) of weight loss (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Additional study is required to distinguish the independent effects of AEX and WL on skeletal muscle capillarization in older subjects with IGT.</p>
              <p>Previous cross-sectional studies from our group and others demonstrate relationships between skeletal muscle capillarization and insulin sensitivity or glucose tolerance (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The longitudinal study design in the present report allowed us to test the effects of an AEX+WL intervention that targets skeletal muscle, and to examine its effects on skeletal muscle capillarization and changes in glucose metabolism. Concordant with previous studies (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), we find a direct relationship between capillarization and insulin sensitivity at baseline. Furthermore, our results show a strong relationship between AEX+WL-induced changes in capillarization and insulin sensitivity in people at high risk for type 2 diabetes. Although these data do not demonstrate true causality, data from animal models do demonstrate a direct role of capillarization in determining insulin sensitivity. For example, Vollus et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) show that a graded occlusion of capillaries in a rodent model reduces insulin action and causes a stepwise reduction in insulin-stimulated glucose uptake in skeletal muscle ranging from 9 to 60%. Impairments in the recruitment and perfusion of capillaries by insulin also contribute to insulin resistance in humans and animals (see reference <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> for review); thus, it stands to reason that by having more capillaries in skeletal muscle, there is a larger capillary surface area that can be recruited and perfused in response to insulin. AEX training also improves endothelial vasoreactivity in subjects with IGT, which may play a role in improving insulin sensitivity through increased blood flow (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>); however, the effects of capillarization and capillary recruitment appear to be independent of blood flow (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Collectively, these findings support the conclusion that AEX+WL-induced increases in capillarization contribute to improvements in insulin sensitivity in older subjects with IGT.</p>
              <p>In this study, subjects with IGT improved insulin sensitivity by &gt;20% and improved glucose tolerance to near-normal levels (G<sub>120</sub> = 7.85 mmol/L), with 9 of the 16 subjects reverting to normal glucose tolerance after 6 months of AEX+WL. Apart from skeletal muscle capillarization, other mechanisms including improvements in insulin signaling, gene and protein expression, GLUT4 content and translocation (see reference <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> for review), and body composition (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) may contribute to these metabolic improvements. We did not find a significant relationship between changes in insulin sensitivity and body weight or body composition in the current study, but our group previously showed that AEX+WL-induced increases in glycogen synthase activity are directly associated with improvements in insulin sensitivity (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). We did not assess these intramuscular mechanisms in the current study; thus, it is likely that increases in skeletal muscle capillarization work in tandem with these mechanisms to increase insulin action and improve insulin sensitivity in people with IGT. Studies are in progress to determine the relative contribution of capillarization and intramuscular mechanisms to AEX- and WL-induced improvements in insulin sensitivity.</p>
              <p>In summary, these results show that skeletal muscle capillarization significantly increases after a 6-month AEX+WL intervention in previously sedentary older adults with IGT, and that there is a direct relationship between the increase in capillarization and the improvements in glucose tolerance and insulin sensitivity. These findings add further support to the concept that lifestyle interventions including AEX+WL will improve insulin sensitivity and reduce risk for type 2 diabetes, and indicate that increased skeletal muscle capillarization is one mechanism by which these metabolic improvements occur in overweight-obese, older adults with IGT.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn1">
                <p>Clinical trial reg. nos. NCT00882141 and NCT00971594, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Article Information</title>
              <p><bold>Acknowledgments.</bold> The authors extend their appreciation to the subjects who participated in this study and to their research staff.</p>
              <p><bold>Funding.</bold> S.J.P. was supported by a VA Career Development Award and a Paul B. Beeson Career Development Award in Aging (K23-AG-040775 and the American Federation for Aging Research). J.B.B. was supported by a VA Advanced Research Career Development Award, and A.S.R. is supported by a VA Research Career Scientist Award. This research was supported by National Institutes of Health R01-AG-019310 (to A.S.R.); a Veterans Affairs Merit Review Award (to A.S.R.); the Baltimore Veterans Affairs Medical Center Geriatric Research, Education, and Clinical Center; the University of Maryland Claude D. Pepper Center (P30-AG-028747); and the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases Mid-Atlantic Nutrition Obesity Research Center (P30-DK-072488).</p>
              <p><bold>Duality of Interest.</bold> No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p>
              <p><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> S.J.P. conceived and designed the research, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript. J.B.B. performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and edited and revised the manuscript. L.I.K. and A.P.G. conceived and designed the research and edited and revised the manuscript. A.S.R. conceived and designed the research, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and edited and revised the manuscript. S.J.P. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
              <p><bold>Prior Presentation.</bold> This study was presented at the 72nd Scientific Sessions of the American Diabetes Association, Philadelphia, PA, 8–12 June 2012.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full accounting of diabetes and pre-diabetes in the U.S. population in 1988-1994 and 2005-2006</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19017771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduced skeletal muscle capillarization and glucose intolerance</article-title>. <source>Microcirculation</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19225985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low clonogenic potential of circulating angiogenic cells is associated with lower density of capillaries in skeletal muscle in patients with impaired glucose tolerance</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Metab Res Rev</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23390082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progressive hyperglycemia across the glucose tolerance continuum in older obese adults is related to skeletal muscle capillarization and nitric oxide bioavailability</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1377</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21289242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lillioja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Culter</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle capillary density and fiber type are possible determinants of in vivo insulin resistance in man</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1987</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3301899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3301899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Ader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of transcapillary insulin transport to dynamics of insulin action after intravenous glucose</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1994</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>E17</fpage>–<lpage>E25</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8304440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8304440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herkner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Joukhadar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcapillary insulin transfer in human skeletal muscle</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Invest</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12588288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12588288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Ader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin transport across capillaries is rate limiting for insulin action in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1989</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>1628</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2681272?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2681272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudbjörnsdóttir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjöstrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strindberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lönnroth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased muscle capillary permeability surface area in type 2 diabetic subjects</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1078</fpage>–<lpage>1082</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15536160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15536160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkney</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Stehouwer</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppack</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudkin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endothelial dysfunction: cause of the insulin resistance syndrome</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>):<fpage>S9</fpage>–<lpage>S13</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9285492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9285492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemodynamic actions of insulin in rat skeletal muscle: evidence for capillary recruitment</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1381</fpage>–<lpage>1388</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9287035?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9287035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knowler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett-Connor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Diabetes Prevention Program Research Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes with lifestyle intervention or metformin</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11832527?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuomilehto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Finnish Diabetes Prevention Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Prevention of type 2 diabetes mellitus by changes in lifestyle among subjects with impaired glucose tolerance</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>344</volume>:<fpage>1343</fpage>–<lpage>1350</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11333990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11333990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingjer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capillary supply of skeletal muscle fibers in untrained and endurance-trained men</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1977</year>;<volume>232</volume>:<fpage>H705</fpage>–<lpage>H712</lpage><?supplied-pmid 879309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">879309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepple</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackinnon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Plyley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance and aerobic training in older men: effects on VO2peak and the capillary supply to skeletal muscle</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>1305</fpage>–<lpage>1310</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9104869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9104869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olfert</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathieu-Costello</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle capillarity and angiogenic mRNA levels after exercise training in normoxia and chronic hypoxia</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1176</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11509513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Charifi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Verney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of endurance training on muscle microvascular filtration capacity and vascular bed morphometry in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol (Oxf)</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>187</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16776665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16776665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Passos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangsbo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellsten</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intense intermittent exercise provides weak stimulus for vascular endothelial growth factor secretion and capillary growth in skeletal muscle</article-title>. <source>Exp Physiol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22962287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22962287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of exercise training on muscle glucose transporter 4 protein and intramuscular lipid content in elderly men with impaired glucose tolerance</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15480742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15480742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortmeyer</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorkin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise with calorie restriction improves insulin sensitivity and glycogen synthase activity in obese postmenopausal women with impaired glucose tolerance</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>302</volume>:<fpage>E145</fpage>–<lpage>E152</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22008454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22008454</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzel</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McLenithan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortmeyer</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic exercise plus weight loss improves insulin sensitivity and increases skeletal muscle glycogen synthase activity in older men</article-title>. <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>. 19 December 2013 [Epub ahead of print]<?supplied-pmid 24357038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357038</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>S64</fpage>–<lpage>S71</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22187472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brands</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/><collab>American Heart Association Nutrition Committee</collab></person-group><article-title>Diet and lifestyle recommendations revision 2006: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Nutrition Committee</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16785338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karvonen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kentala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustala</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of training on heart rate; a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Ann Med Exp Biol Fenn</source><year>1957</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage><?supplied-pmid 13470504?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13470504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosker</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenski</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Treacher</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homeostasis model assessment: insulin resistance and beta-cell function from fasting plasma glucose and insulin concentrations in man</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source><year>1985</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3899825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3899825</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Andres R, Swerdloff RS, Pozefsky T, Coleman D. Manual feedback technique for the control of blood glucose concentration. In <italic>Automation in Analytical Chemistry (Technician Symposium)</italic> Scova N. Beal, Ed. New York, Mediad, 1966, p. 489–491</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFronzo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose clamp technique: a method for quantifying insulin secretion and resistance</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1979</year>;<volume>237</volume>:<fpage>E214</fpage>–<lpage>E223</lpage><?supplied-pmid 382871?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">382871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hennessey</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chromiak</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Della Ventura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guertin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increase in percutaneous muscle biopsy yield with a suction-enhancement technique</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>1739</fpage>–<lpage>1742</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9173935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9173935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boij</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lexell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capillary supply of the tibialis anterior muscle in young, healthy, and moderately active men and women</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1457</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11896009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koolage</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lexell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biopsy sampling requirements for the estimation of muscle capillarization</article-title>. <source>Muscle Nerve</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12362422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12362422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lithell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krotkiewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Non-response of muscle capillary density and lipoprotein-lipase activity to regular training in diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Res</source><year>1985</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3995872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3995872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Ciuceis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Porteri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circulating endothelial progenitor cells, microvascular density and fibrosis in obesity before and after bariatric surgery</article-title>. <source>Blood Press</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23286244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23286244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simsolo</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of weight loss on muscle fiber type, fiber size, capillarity, and succinate dehydrogenase activity in humans</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>4185</fpage>–<lpage>4190</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10566670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10566670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vollus</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Graded occlusion of perfused rat muscle vasculature decreases insulin action</article-title>. <source>Clin Sci (Lond)</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17147515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17147515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rattigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussey</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obesity, insulin resistance, and capillary recruitment</article-title>. <source>Microcirculation</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17613803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17613803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Filippis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ocampo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exercise-induced improvement in vasodilatory function accompanies increased insulin sensitivity in obesity and type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>4903</fpage>–<lpage>4910</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17018657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17018657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wojtaszewski</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of acute exercise and training on insulin action and sensitivity: focus on molecular mechanisms in muscle</article-title>. <source>Essays Biochem</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17144878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17144878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetzer</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise-induced reversal of insulin resistance in obese elderly is associated with reduced visceral fat</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1584</fpage>–<lpage>1589</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16373444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagnone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduction in obesity and related comorbid conditions after diet-induced weight loss or exercise-induced weight loss in men. A randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10896648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10896648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagberg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dengel</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogus</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic exercise training-induced reductions in abdominal fat and glucose-stimulated insulin responses in middle-aged and older men</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1055</fpage>–<lpage>1061</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10983904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10983904</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
