<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:41:46Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10481929" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10481929</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-09-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>lwwopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AIDS</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AIDS</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AIDS</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>AIDS (London, England)</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0269-9370</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1473-5571</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10481929</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10481929</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10481929</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37450602</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37450602</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AIDS-D-23-00092</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAD.0000000000003656</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00009</article-id>
              <article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Clinical Science</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>An open label randomized controlled trial of atorvastatin versus aspirin in elite controllers and antiretroviral-treated people with HIV</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mystakelis</surname>
                    <given-names>Harry A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>Eleanor</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Laidlaw</surname>
                    <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Poole</surname>
                    <given-names>April</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Krishnan</surname>
                    <given-names>Sonya</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>b</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rupert</surname>
                    <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>c</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Welker</surname>
                    <given-names>Jorden L.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>d</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gorelick</surname>
                    <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>d</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lisco</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Manion</surname>
                    <given-names>Maura</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                    <given-names>Jason V.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>e</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>f</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Migueles</surname>
                    <given-names>Stephen A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sereti</surname>
                    <given-names>Irini</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>a</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Laboratory of Immunoregulation, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Bethesda</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Johns Hopkins University, Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, Baltimore</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Leidos Biomedical Research Inc., Frederick National Laboratory for Cancer Research, Frederick</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>AIDS and Cancer Virus Program, Frederick National Laboratory for Cancer Research, Frederick, Maryland</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Hennepin Healthcare Research Institute</aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp>Correspondence to Irini Sereti, MD, MHS National Institutes of Health-NIAID, Bethesda, MD, 20892, USA. E-mail: <email>isereti@niaid.nih.gov</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>37</volume>
              <issue>12</issue>
              <fpage>1827</fpage>
              <lpage>1835</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>6</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>6</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Written work prepared by employees of the Federal Government as part of their official duties is, under the U.S. Copyright Act, a “work of the United States Government” for which copyright protection under Title 17 of the United States Code is not available. As such, copyright does not extend to the contributions of employees of the Federal Government.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="aids-37-1827.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec sec-type="background">
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>Residual inflammation in people with HIV (PWH) despite suppression of HIV replication is associated with many comorbidities including cardiovascular disease. Targeting inflammation may decrease the risk of cardiovascular disease.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="methods">
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>An open label randomized study was conducted to evaluate the effect of nine months of 81 mg aspirin versus 40 mg atorvastatin in antiretroviral therapy (ART) treated PWH and elite controllers (EC), not on ART. Biomarkers associated with inflammation and virologic indices were measured and analyzed using nonparametric and linear mixed effect models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="results">
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>Fifty-three participants were randomized and 44 were included in the final analysis. Median age was 54 years, 72% were male, 59% were Black. Median CD4<sup>+</sup> count was 595 cells/μl in the aspirin and 717 cells/μl in the atorvastatin arm. After 9 months of treatment, plasma soluble (s) CD14<sup>+</sup> was reduced in the aspirin group within both treated PWH and EC (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0229), yet only within treated PWH in the atorvastatin group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0128). A 2.3% reduction from baseline in tissue factor levels was also observed in the aspirin arm, driven by the EC group. In the atorvastatin arm, there was a 4.3% reduction in interleukin-8 levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) and a small decrease of activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). No statistically significant differences were observed in the plasma HIV viral load and cell-associated (CA) HIV DNA and RNA.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="conclusion">
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p>Aspirin and atorvastatin could play a role in targeting HIV-associated inflammation. Elite controllers may warrant special consideration for anti-inflammatory strategies.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>elite controllers</kwd>
                <kwd>HIV</kwd>
                <kwd>inflammation</kwd>
                <kwd>sCD14</kwd>
                <kwd>statins</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>People with HIV (PWH) are living longer since the introduction and optimization of combination antiretroviral therapy (ART). This has shifted the disease spectrum from acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)-associated infections to noninfectious complications including cardiovascular disease (CVD), non-AIDS malignancies and other diseases linked to aging [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Age, hypertension, diabetes and smoking are recognized as important contributors to the risk of cardiovascular disease in PWH [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]; HIV associated inflammation is also thought to play a role in its pathogenesis [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In PWH with suppressed plasma HIV viremia, biomarkers of inflammation and coagulation such as soluble (s) CD14<sup>+</sup>, D-dimer, interleukin (IL)-6 and C-reactive protein (CRP) are higher than in HIV seronegative people and have been found to be independent predictors of non-AIDS complications and mortality [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
              <p>Elite controllers (ECs) represent a small subset of PWH able to maintain suppressed HIV RNA and stable CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell counts in the absence of ART [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Despite the suppressed viral replication, they appear to have similar levels of immune activation and underlying inflammation to ART-treated individuals as well as evidence of increased risk of cardiovascular disease [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The etiology of chronic inflammation in PWH is multifactorial and includes residual viral replication, gut mucosal injury, co-infections such as CMV or HCV, tissue fibrosis and comorbidities including smoking or obesity [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Many strategies have been proposed to reduce coagulation and inflammation in PWH in order to improve cardiovascular health; these have included statins (rosuvastatin and atorvastatin [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]), lactoferrin or sevelamer to target gut mucosa and microbial translocation [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], aspirin [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], renin-angiotensin system inhibitors (i.e. lisinopril [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], telmisartan [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] or losartan [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]), and the two anticoagulants vorapaxar [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and edoxaban [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p>
              <p>Atorvastatin, an 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase inhibitor, has several treatment effects beyond reduction of low-density cholesterol (LDL)-cholesterol and has been shown to reverse cardiovascular disease and atherosclerosis [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Several statins have already been used for their anti-inflammatory action in PWH and were found to not only reduce lipid levels but also reduce sCD14 after 6 months of treatment, with the caveat that participants had elevated levels of immune activation at baseline [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, a trial of a lower dose of atorvastatin in PWH showed changes in lipid levels (oxLDL and LpPLA2) but not sCD14 [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Aspirin, a COX-1 inhibitor, has been evaluated in numerous studies for its antithrombotic and anti-inflammatory properties [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and could potentially decrease inflammation and subsequent atherosclerosis associated with higher expression of P-selectin and sVCAM-1 in PWH. In addition, different doses and duration of aspirin treatment have been tried with an uncontrolled trial showing significant immunological benefit that was not replicated in a larger placebo controlled 3-month trial [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
              <p>In this study, the treatment effect of 81 mg of aspirin or 40 mg of atorvastatin was tested in two groups of PWH, a group of virologically suppressed ART-treated PWH (TPs) and ECs, who were virologically suppressed without receiving ART. This population was selected in order to assess the effect that the two drugs have in HIV-associated inflammation, as measured by sCD14, a marker of monocyte activation [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and to also test the potential effect of ART in therapeutic responses to anti-inflammatory drugs.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>Elite Controller and ART-treated HIV+ Statin Versus ASA Treatment Intervention Study (ECSTATIN) was an open label two group randomized controlled trial of either aspirin or atorvastatin given for 9 months to study their potential effect in immune activation and inflammation.</p>
                <p>Study participants were recruited from the NIH Clinical Center (Bethesda, Maryland, USA) and Hennepin Healthcare System (Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA). All study visits were performed at the NIH Clinical Center (NIHCC). The protocol was approved by the NIH Institutional Review Board (IRB) and by the Hennepin Healthcare Human Subjects Research Committee (NCT02081638). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants prior to any study procedures.</p>
                <p>To be eligible for the study, participants had to be 18 years or older, have plasma viremia &lt;40 copies/ml, be willing to have blood samples stored, and not taking any statin or aspirin or meeting the 2013 Guidelines for treatment of blood cholesterol criteria for statin initiation [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. For the EC group, participants had to have viral load (VL) less than the lower limit of detection (LLD) for more than 5 years, no history of opportunistic infections and stable CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell counts on no ART. TP group participants had to be on continuous ART for more than 5 years and to have VL &lt; LLD for more than 3 years. For both groups, women of childbearing potential had to use two methods of birth control.</p>
                <p>Women who were lactating or were pregnant, or actively trying to become pregnant were excluded from participation. Other exclusion criteria were known hypersensitivity or allergy or other contraindication to study medications, diagnosis of cardiovascular disease or hypercholesterolemia (LDL cholesterol ≥ 190 mg/dl), any chronic inflammatory condition requiring treatment with anti-inflammatory medications, active drug or alcohol use disorder, ART with tipranivir, or any therapy which combined nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors with protease inhibitors, INR &gt;2 upper limit of normal (ULN), platelets &lt;75 000, glomerular filtration rate &lt;60, ALT or alkaline phosphatase or direct bilirubin &gt;2× ULN, aldolase &gt;1.5 ULN and anemia (Hg &lt;9 mg/dl).</p>
                <p>Participants meeting the eligibility criteria were randomized based on a random number generator; ECs and TPs were separately randomized 1 : 1 to 81 mg aspirin or 40 mg atorvastatin. In subjects on protease inhibitor (other than tipranavir) or elvitegravir-based regimens, the atorvastatin dose was decreased to 20 mg daily. In contrast, for efavirenz or etravirine-based regimens the dose of atorvastatin was increased to 80 mg daily. After the initial screening and enrollment visits, participants had a 3-month observation period to establish baseline values before randomization and study drug initiation. Follow-up visits occurred at months 6, 9, 12, and 15, and study drug was stopped after the month 12 visit. At each study visit, blood was drawn for safety labs, flow cytometry analysis and biomarker measurements. A carotid MRI was also performed at month 0 and month 12.</p>
                <p>The primary outcome was to evaluate the change from baseline in plasma levels of sCD14 after 9 months of treatment between aspirin or atorvastatin study arms with the EC and TP groups combined. Secondary outcomes included the change from baseline in plasma levels of sCD14 within each of the two subgroups (ECs and TPs). Additional exploratory outcomes included the change from baseline in plasma biomarkers associated with inflammation and coagulation, T-cell and monocyte subsets. The study was powered (power = 95%, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> = 0.05) to detect a 10% change from baseline with 40 patients per treatment arm based on characteristics from the SMART Study (A Comparison of Two Ways to Manage Anti-HIV Treatment) [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Participants enrolled in the study between April 2014 and April 2018. Study enrollment was ended due to low accrual after the opening of the REPRIEVE [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] study and more widespread use of statins and ART in ECs [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Laboratory measurements</title>
                <p>Complete blood count, basic metabolic panel, lipid, and liver panel were measured in fasting participants at the NIH-CC. The complete list of tested biomarkers and T-cell and monocyte subsets can be found in Table 1, Supplemental Digital Content. Flow cytometry analysis was performed for lymphocyte and monocyte subsets on all study visits. Cryopreserved plasma was used for measurements of biomarkers of inflammation, coagulation and fibrosis which included IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, TNF-a, IP-10, CRP, SAA, IL-18, TNFR1 (Electrochemiluminescence, Mesoscale Discovery), sCD14, TF, FABP2, PAI-1 (Elisa, R&amp;D), HA (Elisa, Corgenix), sCD163 (Elisa, Aviscera), D-dimer (Elisa, BioM), DPP4 (Elisa, Aviva Systems), Kuynurine and Tryptophan (Elisa, ImmuSmol). Plasma and cell associated HIV RNA and DNA were quantified using a previously described ultrasensitive quantitative real-time PCR assay (HMMCgag assay) targeting the noncoding 5’ region of HIV gag [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Viral nucleic acid isolations and quantification were performed as previously described [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Statistical methods</title>
                <p>Participant baseline characteristics and laboratory measurements were calculated using median (IQR), mean (SD) or proportion (count). Baseline characteristics of participants were compared using chi-square or nonparametric tests (Mann−Whitney). The average between Month 0 and Month 3 was calculated and was used as baseline measurement according to per protocol analysis. For the primary end point, the Wilcoxon rank sum test was used to compare the change of sCD14 from baseline and month 12 measurement and the ANOVA Friedman test with Dunn's correction for multiple comparisons was used to compare baseline, month 9 and month 12. For each participant the delta between month 12 and baseline sCD14 was calculated and the Mann−Whitney rank sum test was used to compare the changes between drugs in the two study groups. In exploratory analysis, plasma biomarkers were log(e) transformed and a linear mixed effect model with the biomarker as outcome and with random slope per participant used to calculate the percentage of change from baseline. Analysis of monocyte and lymphocyte subsets identified by flow cytometry was done in a similar way without log(e) transformation. Prism v8, Python 3.5 (packages: pandas, seaborn, and scipy) and R (packages: lme4, lme, and ggplot) were used for the analysis. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value less than 0.05 was deemed statistically significant due to the exploratory nature of the performed analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Enrollment and retention</title>
                <p>Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> presents the Consort flow diagram for screening and enrollment in the study. Sixty-two patients were assessed for eligibility, and 53 were randomized. From those, 26 were allocated in the aspirin arm, and 27 in the atorvastatin arm. After being randomized, two participants in the aspirin arm and five participants in the atorvastatin arm did not receive the study drug, due to early withdrawal. Finally, two participants in the atorvastatin arm were excluded after the randomization due to noncompliance or loss to follow up. In the end, 24 participants in the aspirin arm and 20 in the atorvastatin arm received study medication for at least three months. No participant experienced an AE of grade 3 or higher during participation.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Fig. 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Consort flow diagram.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="aids-37-1827-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="subjects">
                <title>Participant characteristics</title>
                <p>The groups and the arms were similar in terms of baseline demographics, cardiovascular disease markers and HIV related characteristics. Median age was 54 years in both arms, with male sex at birth in 75 and 70% of participants in the aspirin and atorvastatin arms, respectively. Fifty-four percent and 65% were Black, 33.3 and 20% were current smokers, 25 and 20% had hypertension diagnosis. Baseline body mass index (BMI) was 28 and 28.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup> at baseline, total cholesterol 174 and 173 mg/dl respectively. Median CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count was 595 and 717 cells/μl, respectively. Within participants receiving antiretroviral therapy, 53.3 and 66.7% included a nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI), 6.7 and 33.3% included a protease inhibitor and 60 and 9% included an integrase inhibitor respectively. No differences were observed at baseline BMI (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Table 2, Supplemental Digital Content).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Baseline characteristics of study participants.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspirin</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atorvastatin</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (48.25–57.75)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (40–58.75)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex at birth % (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75% (18)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70% (14)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race/ethnicity % (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5% (9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20% (4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54% (13)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65% (13)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic or Latino</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% (2)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiple race</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular disease characteristics</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoking (current)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (8)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20% (4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoking (ever)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2% (13)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35% (7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3% (2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25% (6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20% (4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24–33.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5 (25.7–36.1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Systolic blood pressure, mmHg</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (112–131)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (113–135)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diastolic blood pressure, mmHg</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (67–81)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5 (70–79)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.99</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total cholesterol, mg/dl</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (160–203)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (144–200)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HDL cholesterol, mg/dl</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (40–63)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (42–59)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Triglycerides</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (87–132)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (61–114)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">HIV-related history and clinical characteristics</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count, cells/μl</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">595 (485–826)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">717 (509–843)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nadir CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count, cells/μl</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">474 (394–595)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428 (90–583)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CD8<sup>+</sup> cell count, cells/μl</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">714 (564 -953)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">578 (441–761)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CD4<sup>+</sup>:CD8<sup>+</sup></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.62–1.49)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.78–1.91)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Current antiretroviral regimen</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Includes NNRTI</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3% (8)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7% (8)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Includes protease inhibitor</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7% (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Includes integrase inhibitor</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60% (9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3% (1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anti-HBc positive</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46% (11)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30% (6)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn fn-type="other">
                      <p>NNRTI, nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Total CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> cell counts remained stable throughout the treatment in both aspirin and atorvastatin groups with no significant differences over the follow up period (Figure 3, Supplemental Digital Content).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Primary and secondary outcomes</title>
                <p>The primary objective of the study was to evaluate the changes from baseline in sCD14 levels after 9 months of treatment with aspirin versus atorvastatin; secondary outcomes included effects of treatment on sCD14 levels between study groups and treatment arms. The primary outcome is being presented in Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. There was no significant difference between the effect that either atorvastatin or aspirin had to the groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.34, Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a) with a median change of −0.13 μg/ml for the aspirin arm and –0.09 μg/ml for the atorvastatin arm. A statistically significant difference in the change of sCD14 was observed between the aspirin and the atorvastatin arm in ECs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02, Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). For the ECs, the median change at month 12, from baseline, was −0.13 μg/ml for the aspirin arm and +0.17 μg/ml for the atorvastatin. No such difference was observed in the TPs group, in which the median change was −0.12 μg/ml for the aspirin arm and −0.32 μg/ml for the atorvastatin arm (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.9, Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Fig. 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Change from baseline in soluble CD14 plasma levels after 9 months of study drug administration in all study participants (a), elite controllers (b) and treated progressors (c).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="aids-37-1827-g002" position="float"/>
                  <p>Elite controllers are represented with pink polygon while treated progressors with blue triangles. Wilcoxon signed ranked test was used for comparisons between baseline and month 12.</p>
                </fig>
                <p>In the aspirin arm, the baseline median sCD14 level was 1.66 μg/ml (IQR: 1.46–2.43) and in the atorvastatin arm 1.73 μg/ml (IQR: 1.43–1.91). Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> presents the secondary outcome comparisons of baseline-to-month 12 changes within the two treatment groups, and for EC and TP participants separately. There was a statistically significant reduction in sCD14 after 9 months of treatment within the aspirin arm, (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) from 1.66 to 1.58 μg/ml (IQR: 1.25–1.88) (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). This difference within the aspirin group was not statistically significant when studying changes over all follow-up time points. When examining changes within the EC and TP groups separately, and for each drug, there was no significant reduction in sCD14 in either group using aspirin over 9 months (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F3">
                  <label>Fig. 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Treatment effect of aspirin (a, b) and atorvastatin (c, d) on soluble CD14 plasma levels after 9 months of administration.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="aids-37-1827-g003" position="float"/>
                  <p>Baseline value is the average of month 0 and month 3. Elite Controllers are represented with pink polygon while treated progressors with blue triangles. Wilcoxon signed ranked test was used for comparisons between baseline and month 12.</p>
                </fig>
                <p>No statistically significant differences were detected in participants over follow-up for the atorvastatin arm (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). In comparison, a statistically significant reduction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) in sCD14 levels was observed in TPs treated with atorvastatin for 9 months from 1.78 μg/ml (IQR: 1.52–2.39) to 1.49 μg/ml (IQR: 1.32–2.04) (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d). No such difference was observed in ECs receiving atorvastatin [baseline median sCD14 of 1.56 μg/ml (IQR: 1.20–1.75) and 1.62 μg/ml after 9 months of treatment (IQR 1.48–1.84)] (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Exploratory outcomes</title>
                <p>The effect of study drugs after 9 months of treatment in plasma biomarkers was assessed. There was a statistically significant reduction (2.3% from baseline) in the aspirin arm in the soluble (s) tissue factor (TF) levels. Based on the interaction term between the time effect and the patient group, in the subgroup analysis, this effect was driven by the EC group (2.3% reduction, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01). In the atorvastatin arm, there was a 4.3% reduction from baseline in IL-8 levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02). The effect of drugs after 9 months of treatment in the T-cell and monocyte subsets was also assessed. Apart from a small reduction of the CD4<sup>+</sup> HLA-DR<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup> T cells in the atorvastatin arm (−0.103% (CI: reduction from baseline, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), no other significant changes were seen (Figures 1 and 2, Supplemental Digital Content). Finally, 41 out of the 44 participants had clinical magnetic resonance angiographies (MRA) at month 3 and month 12. Two were excluded due to technical limitations and one had a contraindication to MRA. Only qualitative data were available, and all 41 participants had stable MRAs over 9 months.</p>
                <p>Lastly, the effect of either aspirin or atorvastatin on residual plasma viremia by single copy assay and on cell-associated (CA) DNA and RNA in PBMC was evaluated. Neither of the treatments had a statistically significant impact (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.5 in all comparisons) (Figure 4, Supplemental Digital Content) in these measurements of HIV reservoir.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this open label randomized controlled trial, the hypothesis that daily low dose aspirin or atorvastatin can reduce systemic inflammation in PWH with suppressed viral load with (TP subgroup) or without (EC subgroup) the use of ART was tested. There was no difference in inflammatory biomarkers between aspirin and atorvastatin treatment arms over 9 months. Participants treated with aspirin were found to have a reduction in sCD14 levels in both groups combined and only TPs who received atorvastatin were found to have a statistically significant reduction of sCD14 after 9 months of treatment. Both drugs were well tolerated without any significant adverse effects. Overall, there seemed to be an association between aspirin and atorvastatin treatment and changes in inflammatory markers, especially in EC who received aspirin and experienced decreases in sCD14 and sTF levels, and in TPs who received atorvastatin and had reduction in levels of IL-8 and activated T cells.</p>
              <p>Studies have shown that statins could be useful in reducing markers of monocyte activation, such as sCD14 in PWH [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Their pharmacological profile includes not only the reduction of LDL cholesterol and a modest increase of HDL cholesterol but also the reduction of C-reactive protein. In this study, a decrease in LDL and total cholesterol was observed but no further effects of atorvastatin in other biomarkers could be demonstrated. A 10% reduction in sCD14, which is a marker of monocyte activation, and has been shown to be an independent mortality predictor in PWH [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] could translate in a similar reduction in all-cause mortality. Studies showing that rosuvastatin decreased tissue factor expressing monocytes after 24 weeks of treatment in addition to plasma sCD14 levels [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] could not be replicated possibly due to the small sample size. Tissue factor expression is induced by inflammatory stimuli and has been associated with a specific monocyte subset that drives coagulation in HIV-infected individuals [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In the current study, a reduction in the tissue factor expressing monocytes was not observed with either aspirin or atorvastatin, but a small reduction (2.3% from baseline) in plasma sTF was observed in EC but not in TPs treated with aspirin. In a pilot study of daily aspirin (325 mg loading dose followed by 81 mg daily) in HIV-infected individuals and healthy controls, a statistically significant reduction in sCD14 was observed after one week [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In a larger and placebo controlled trial follow up study, however, that tested two different doses of aspirin (100 or 300 mg) for 12 weeks in 121 PWH that were suppressed for more than 48 weeks, no difference was found between either aspirin doses and placebo in sCD14 and other inflammatory biomarkers [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
              <p>One novel aspect of our study was the inclusion of EC, a rare subset of HIV patients that can control HIV infection without ART. Studies have shown that these patients, despite suppressed plasma viremia, have higher levels of inflammation and cardiovascular disease compared to seronegative people [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the current study, we assessed potential modifiers of inflammation in ECs without targeting HIV replication. Atorvastatin showed no effect in sCD14 levels in contrast to aspirin, which produced a similar reduction in sCD14 in both TPs and ECs. The observed decrease in sTF, which has been found to be elevated in EC [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] in the aspirin arm was also driven by EC. Although this could be due to the small sample size or additional effects of antiretroviral medications, the possibility of unique features in the pathogenesis of inflammation in EC cannot be dismissed and may have important implications in optimizing their management.</p>
              <p>Our study was powered to detect a difference in sCD14 levels based on estimates from the SMART study [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In the current study though, participants had a median sCD14 levels, which was approximately 30% lower compared to the initial assumption and translates to lower cardiovascular disease risk and all-cause mortality risk. The lower levels of systemic inflammation compared to older studies is not uncommon and has also been noted in Strategic Timing of Antiretroviral Treatment (START) [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and more recently in a study of edoxaban in PWH [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], suggesting that earlier HIV cohorts had higher levels of inflammation compared to contemporary ones, which could be attributed to earlier ART initiation [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], less toxic drugs [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] or better cardiovascular disease control such as exercise and smoking cessation [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>
              <p>Our study has several limitations including the small sample size with low power to fully assess the effect of the treatment interventions in the HIV-associated inflammation. Another important limitation of the study was the absence of a placebo-controlled arm that would have further clarified if the changes observed were causal and connected to the medication administered. In addition, the medications were given for a short period of time potentially limiting long-term effects on cardiovascular inflammation. Finally, studies have shown that other modifiable risk factors such as smoking cessation, exercise initiation or weight loss could play a bigger role in cardiovascular inflammation compared to pharmacologic interventions [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Lastly, due to the multifactorial etiology of the cardiovascular inflammatory disease in PWH targeting of multiple pathways could result in a synergistic benefit.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, low dose aspirin treatment in patients living with HIV and well suppressed viremia was associated with reduced sCD14 levels while atorvastatin reduced sCD14 levels only in suppressed patients concurrently treated with ARTs. These results are consistent with the presence of ongoing inflammation among PWH despite suppressed plasma viral load, although levels of inflammation may be lower among contemporary PWH when compared to older cohorts. The difference response of EC to aspirin versus atorvastatin highlights the need to study further the pathogenesis of inflammation in this subset and the importance of including this unique population in anti-inflammatory clinical trials if feasible. Further studies are needed to better understand the pathogenesis and therapeutic strategies to mitigate inflammation during chronic HIV disease. Lastly, an additive potential effect of combination treatment with both aspirin and atorvastatin may be worth exploring in future studies since both pharmacologic interventions act in a different way to target inflammation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Disclosures: This project has been funded with Federal funds from the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, under contract number 75N91019D00024 and from the intramural research program of NIAID/NIH. The content of this publication does not necessarily reflect the views or policies of the Department of Health and Human Services, nor does mention of trade names, commercial products, or organizations imply endorsement by the US Government.</p>
              <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
                <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <caption>
                  <title>Supplemental Digital Content</title>
                </caption>
                <media id="s001" content-type="document" xlink:href="aids-37-1827-s001.pdf" position="anchor"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Supplemental digital content is available for this article.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>HIV infection, antiretroviral treatment, ageing, and non-AIDS related morbidity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source><year>2009</year>; <volume>338</volume>:<fpage>a3172</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DRJr</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Calmy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duprez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>La Rosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Markers of inflammation, coagulation, and renal function are elevated in adults with HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2010</year>; <volume>201</volume>:<fpage>1788</fpage>–<lpage>1795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20446848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Richterman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutcher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Badralmaa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Traditional risk factors and D-dimer predict incident cardiovascular disease events in chronic HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIDS</italic></source><year>2010</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1509</fpage>–<lpage>1517</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20505494</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuller</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Belloso</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>De Wit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory and coagulation biomarkers and mortality in patients with HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Med</italic></source><year>2008</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e203</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18942885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musselwhite</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Penzak</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Markers of endothelial dysfunction, coagulation and tissue fibrosis independently predict venous thromboembolism in HIV</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIDS</italic></source><year>2011</year>; <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21412059</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambotte</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Boufassa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goujard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>HIV controllers: a homogeneous group of HIV-1-infected patients with spontaneous control of viral replication</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2005</year>; <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1053</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16142675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence for innate immune system activation in HIV type 1-infected elite controllers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2014</year>; <volume>209</volume>:<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24185941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grinspoon</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Overton</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichtenbaum</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanni</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberg</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rationale and design of the randomized trial to prevent vascular events in HIV (REPRIEVE)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Heart J</italic></source><year>2019</year>; <volume>212</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928825</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsue</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunologic basis of cardiovascular disease in HIV-infected adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2012</year>; <volume>205</volume>: <issue>(Suppl 3)</issue>: <fpage>S375</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22577211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananworanich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serious Non-AIDS events: Immunopathogenesis and interventional strategies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIDS Res Ther</italic></source><year>2013</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funderburg</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Debanne</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Storer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Labbato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clagett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rosuvastatin treatment reduces markers of monocyte activation in HIV-infected subjects on antiretroviral therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2014</year>; <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24253250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crum-Cianflone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High dose atorvastatin decreases cellular markers of immune activation without affecting HIV-1 RNA levels: results of a double-blind randomized placebo controlled clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2011</year>; <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>764</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21325137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sortino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hullsiek</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schminke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetekpor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of recombinant human lactoferrin on immune activation and the intestinal microbiome among persons living with human immunodeficiency virus and receiving antiretroviral therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2019</year>; <volume>219</volume>:<fpage>1963</fpage>–<lpage>1968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montenont</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Merolla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aspirin attenuates platelet activation and immune activation in HIV-1-infected subjects on antiretroviral therapy: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</italic></source><year>2013</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23406976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitch</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Funderburg</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A randomized placebo controlled trial of aspirin effects on immune activation in chronically human immunodeficiency virus-infected adults on virologically suppressive antiretroviral therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Forum Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2017</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>ofw278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28480270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yukl</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Somsouk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of lisinopril to decrease lymphoid fibrosis in antiretroviral-treated, HIV-infected individuals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathog Immun</italic></source><year>2017</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28936485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utay</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitch</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichtenbaum</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lederman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Telmisartan therapy does not improve lymph node or adipose tissue fibrosis more than continued antiretroviral therapy alone</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2018</year>; <volume>217</volume>:<fpage>1770</fpage>–<lpage>1781</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29401318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhame</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liappis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Losartan to reduce inflammation and fibrosis endpoints in HIV disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIDS</italic></source><year>2021</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33252490</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>group</surname><given-names>As</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vorapaxar for HIV-associated inflammation and coagulopathy (ADVICE): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet HIV</italic></source><year>2018</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e553</fpage>–<lpage>e559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30257802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooberry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mystakelis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Factor Xa inhibition reduces coagulation activity but not inflammation among people with HIV: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Forum Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2020</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>ofaa026</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32055640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Colangeli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocaterra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rosuvastatin, pravastatin, and atorvastatin for the treatment of hypercholesterolaemia in HIV-infected patients receiving protease inhibitors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr HIV Res</italic></source><year>2008</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18991624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Funderburg</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of atorvastatin on biomarkers of immune activation, inflammation, and lipids in virologically suppressed, human immunodeficiency virus-1-infected individuals with low-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;130 mg/dL (AIDS Clinical Trials Group Study A5275)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Lipidol</italic></source><year>2017</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28391912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Montalescot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinhubl</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aspirin dose for the prevention of cardiovascular disease: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source><year>2007</year>; <volume>297</volume>:<fpage>2018</fpage>–<lpage>2024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nudy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghahramani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzieh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandrola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aspirin for primary atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease prevention as baseline risk increases: a meta-regression analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Med</italic></source><year>2020</year>; <volume>133</volume>:<fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>1064</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenchley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacker</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvestri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial translocation is a cause of systemic immune activation in chronic HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Med</italic></source><year>2006</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1365</fpage>–<lpage>1371</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bairey Merz</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckel</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2013 ACC/AHA guideline on the treatment of blood cholesterol to reduce atherosclerotic cardiovascular risk in adults: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source><year>2014</year>; <volume>63</volume><issue>(Pt B)</issue>:<fpage>2889</fpage>–<lpage>2934</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grinspoon</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribaudo</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Leveraging a landmark trial of primary cardiovascular disease prevention in human immunodeficiency virus: introduction from the REPRIEVE Coprincipal Investigators</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2020</year>; <volume>222</volume>: <issue>(Suppl 1)</issue>: <fpage>S1</fpage>–<lpage>S7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32645161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Olalere</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rationale and design of the mechanistic substudy of the randomized trial to prevent vascular events in HIV (REPRIEVE): effects of pitavastatin on coronary artery disease and inflammatory biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Heart J</italic></source><year>2019</year>; <volume>212</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somsouk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Mohsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liegler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The immunologic effects of mesalamine in treated HIV-infected individuals with incomplete CD4+ T cell recovery: a randomized crossover trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source><year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e116306</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25545673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulougoura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laidlaw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Khetani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A phase I, randomized, controlled clinical study of CC-11050 in people living with HIV with suppressed plasma viremia on antiretroviral therapy (APHRODITE)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Forum Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2019</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>ofz246</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31211164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nason</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma levels of soluble CD14 independently predict mortality in HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2011</year>; <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>780</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21252259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosh</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Policicchio</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory monocytes expressing tissue factor drive SIV and HIV coagulopathy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Transl Med</italic></source><year>2017</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>eaam5441</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28855397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereyra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Triant</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased coronary atherosclerosis and immune activation in HIV-1 elite controllers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIDS</italic></source><year>2012</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2409</fpage>–<lpage>2412</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23032411</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strategies for Management of Antiretroviral Therapy Study Group</surname></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Babiker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sadr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grund</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inferior clinical outcome of the CD4+ cell count-guided antiretroviral treatment interruption strategy in the SMART study: role of CD4+ cell counts and HIV RNA levels during follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2008</year>; <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>1145</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18476293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Group</surname><given-names>ISS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Babiker</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grund</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Initiation of antiretroviral therapy in early asymptomatic HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source><year>2015</year>; <volume>373</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26192873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petoumenos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lipid profiles in HIV-infected adults receiving atazanavir and atazanavir/ritonavir: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source><year>2010</year>; <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1878</fpage>–<lpage>1888</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20554568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Althoff</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebo</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Contributions of traditional and HIV-related risk factors on non-AIDS-defining cancer, myocardial infarction, and end-stage liver and renal diseases in adults with HIV in the USA and Canada: a collaboration of cohort studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet HIV</italic></source><year>2019</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e93</fpage>–<lpage>e104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30683625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
