<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T02:05:16Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10200876" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10200876</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-05-23</datestamp>
        <setSpec>frontendo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Endocrinol.</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Frontiers in Endocrinology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1664-2392</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10200876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10200876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10200876</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37223011</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1104441</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Endocrinology</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Original Research</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Vigorous-intensity exercise as a modulator of cardiac adipose tissue in women with obesity: a cross-sectional and randomized pilot study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Thapa</surname>
                    <given-names>Sumsen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Selvaraj</surname>
                    <given-names>Bharath S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davis</surname>
                    <given-names>Paige N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>Bryan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/923651"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Givan</surname>
                    <given-names>Amy H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Perez-Rivera</surname>
                    <given-names>Jose A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2227705"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Woodard</surname>
                    <given-names>Pamela K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>7</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/994424"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Klingensmith</surname>
                    <given-names>Jon D.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>8</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fernandez-del-Valle</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>9</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>10</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1196255"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Applied Health, Southern Illinois University Edwardsville</institution>, <addr-line>Edwardsville, IL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Iowa Digestive Disease Center, Heartland Medical Research, Inc.</institution>, <addr-line>Clive, IA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Cardiopulmonary Rehabilitation, Charleston Area Medical Center (CAMC) Memorial Hospital at West Virginia</institution>, <addr-line>Charleston, WV</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Division of Rehabilitation Sciences, University of Texas Medical Branch at Galveston</institution>, <addr-line>Galveston, TX</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Cardiology, University Hospital of Burgos</institution>, <addr-line>Burgos</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Facultad de Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad Isabel I</institution>, <addr-line>Isabel</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Mallinckrodt Institute of Radiology, Washington University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>St. Louis, MO</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup><institution>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Southern Illinois University Edwardsville</institution>, <addr-line>Edwardsville, IL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff9"><sup>9</sup><institution>Department of Functional Biology, University of Oviedo</institution>, <addr-line>Oviedo</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff10"><sup>10</sup><institution>Health Research Institute of the Principality of Asturias (ISPA)</institution>, <addr-line>Oviedo</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                  <p>Edited by: Frederic Castinetti, Aix-Marseille Université, France</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                  <p>Reviewed by: Ewa Śliwicka, Poznan University of Physical Education, Poland; Hao Su, Beijing Sport University, China; Pei-Tzu Wu, Pacific University, United States</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Maria Fernandez-del-Valle, <email xlink:href="mailto:dr.maria@fdelvalle.net">dr.maria@fdelvalle.net</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>08</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>14</volume>
              <elocation-id>1104441</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2023 Thapa, Selvaraj, Davis, Smith, Givan, Perez-Rivera, Woodard, Klingensmith and Fernandez-del-Valle</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Thapa, Selvaraj, Davis, Smith, Givan, Perez-Rivera, Woodard, Klingensmith and Fernandez-del-Valle</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Cardiac adipose tissue (CAT) has become an important target for the reduction of disease risk. Supervised exercise programs have shown potential to "significantly" reduce CAT; however, the impact of different exercise modalities is not clear, and the relationships between CAT, physical activity (PA) levels and fitness (PFit) remain unknown. Therefore, the purpose of this study was to analyze the relationships between CAT, PA and PFit, and to explore the effects of different exercise modalities in a group of women with obesity. A total of 26 women (age: 23.41 ± 5.78 years-old) were enrolled in the cross-sectional study. PA, cardiorespiratory fitness, muscular strength, body composition and CAT were evaluated. The pilot intervention included 16 women randomized to a control (CON, n=5), high intensity interval training (HIIT, n = 5) and high-intensity circuit training (HICT, n=6) groups. Statistical analysis showed negative correlations between CAT and vigorous PA (VPA) (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>=-0.41, <italic>p</italic>=0.037); and between percent body fat (%BF), fat mass (FM), and all PA levels (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>=-0.41– -0.68, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05); while muscle mass was positively associated with moderate-to-vigorous PA, and upper-body lean mass with all PA levels (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> =0.40–0.53, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). The HICT intervention showed significant improvements (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) in %BF, FM, fat free mass, and whole-body and lower extremities lean mass and strength after three weeks; however, only leg strength and upper extremities’ FM improved significantly compared to CON and HICT. In conclusion, although all types of PA showed a positive influence on body fat content, only VPA significantly impacted on CAT volume. Moreover, three weeks of HICT induced positive changes in PFit in women with obesity. Further research is needed to explore VPA levels and high-intensity exercise interventions for short- and long-term CAT management.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>cardiac adipose tissue</kwd>
                <kwd>obesity</kwd>
                <kwd>physical fitness</kwd>
                <kwd>vigorous physical activity</kwd>
                <kwd>women</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source id="cn001">
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute
</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000050</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <funding-statement>Research reported in this article was supported by National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health under award number R15HL145576; the Institute of Clinical and Translational Sciences (ICTS) at Washington University School of Medicine through the J<italic>ust-In-Time (JIT) Core Usage Funding Program</italic> (JIT485M); and Southern Illinois University Edwardsville through both the <italic>Seed Grants for Transitional and Exploratory Projects (SETP program)</italic>.</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="2"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="99"/>
                <page-count count="13"/>
                <word-count count="6694"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>Obesity</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Obesity is a known risk factor for cardiovascular disease (CVD), diabetes, hypertension, and other diseases and it is characterized by excess adipose tissue (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In normal conditions, Cardiac Adipose Tissue (CAT) accumulates in two distinct depots adjacent to the myocardium and within the pericardium: epicardial adipose tissue (EAT) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and pericardial adipose tissue (PAT) (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). EAT is mostly deposited at perivascular interventricular and atrioventricular grooves and has the same embryological genesis as intra-abdominal visceral adipose tissue (VAT) (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), while PAT is deposited between the two pericardial layers (visceral and parietal) as well as on the parietal pericardium’s exterior surface (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p>
              <p>Under normal physiological conditions, CAT deposits protect the heart by secreting various molecules (e.g., anti-inflammatory and anti-atherogenic cytokines), however, excess CAT has been postulated as a distinct pathologic feature for CAD development (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) due to its altered biochemical activity (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Abnormal CAT accumulation stimulates the release of inflammatory cytokines [i.e. interleukin (IL)-1, IL-6, IL-8, IL-11, TNF-α (tumor necrosis factor-α), IL-16, IL-17, G-CSF (granulocyte colony stimulating factor and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF)] that could lead to the progression of atherosclerosis in coronary arteries, myocardial infarction, heart failure, atrial fibrillation, arrythmias, and other adverse cardiac events (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). As a consequence, excess CAT surrounding the myocardium has gained attention as a risk factor for CVD and other medical complications (e.g., metabolic syndrome, visceral adiposity, heart morphology, insulin resistance, sub-clinical atherosclerosis, or liver enzymes) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). More specifically, some research has linked PAT to coronary high-risk lesions (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In this context, quantification and prevention of CAT accumulation has become an important target for disease prevention and treatment (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p>
              <p>Various methods exist to estimate body fat (e.g., anthropometric measures, dual x-ray, magnetic resonance imaging, and radiation-exposing computed tomography) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging is considered a gold standard technique for measuring CAT. However, the selective quantification methods (such as single slice vs. multiple slice sampling, or regional vs. total) impact accuracy of adiposity evaluation (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Therefore, total CAT volume should be accurately measured – rather than estimated – by analyzing the entire thoracic region around the heart.</p>
              <p>Currently, the relationship between physical activity (PA) levels, physical health, and CAT accumulation is unknown (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). There is, however, a substantial correlation between sedentary behaviors and the risk of metabolic disease and CVD (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) as well as both cardiovascular-specific mortality and total mortality (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). This association is largely caused by vascular factors (i.e. vascular dysfunction, downregulating blood flow, altering glucose metabolism, and activating inflammatory and oxidative stress pathways) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Likewise, observational research in PA levels has shown a negative relationship with fat mass (FM) and dispersion (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The use of practical, accurate, and reliable tools for evaluating PA can help to identify the relationship between PA and disease and assist in the study of effect modification (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p>
              <p>In this context, vigorous exercise has shown to improve anti-inflammatory and metabolic function, and cardiovascular health on a dose response fashion (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). A recent meta-analysis on randomized controlled trials comparing short- to medium-term (2-16 weeks) supervised exercise programs concluded that exercise can reduce CAT ‘considerably’ in overweight individuals or those with obesity (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>); however, the duration of interventions was not associated to the magnitude of the effect on CAT. Lastly, the effect of exercise mode was not evaluated given the scarcity of resistance-based intervention studies. In physically inactive people with abdominal obesity, both aerobic and resistance training (RT) reduced CAT when meeting the recommendations for intensity and frequency (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). However, RT seems to be the only mode of exercise capable of reducing PAT (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Interestingly, these studies did not report nor matched aerobic and RT interventions by energy expenditure, hence, not allowing for realistic comparisons (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p>
              <p>The goal of this study was to analyze the relationships between PA, PFit, and CAT volume in obese women, and to pilot test the differential effects when comparing energy expenditure-matched high-intensity interval aerobic and resistance training interventions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <p>This study followed an observational cross-sectional design and was approved by the Institutional Review Board (ID: # 16-1208-4C). The reporting of observational studies (STROBE) recommendations was followed (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) The study was conducted between 2017 and 2020 in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki ethical principles. A total of 172 individuals were contacted to participate in the study (see <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). Inclusion criteria were: 18 to 45 years of age, female, BMI from 30 to 39.99 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, and sedentary lifestyle. Exclusion criteria were as follows: males, cardiovascular, metabolic, pulmonary, or musculoskeletal conditions, pregnant women, smokers, those taking medications, and individuals with schedule incompatibilities. A total of 136 participants were excluded for not meeting the criteria: 4 were male, 21 did not meet the age range, 73 participants did not meet the BMI criteria, 9 were on medications, 13 presented medical conditions, 11 were unable to participate due to a schedule conflict, and 5 participated in regular exercise. Thirty-six participants signed the consent form and were enrolled in the study. A total of 10 participants were discontinued due to loss of interest, schedule conflicts, and previously non-reported medical conditions. Finally, a total of 26 participants completed the cross-sectional study.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="f1">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Flow diagram.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="fendo-14-1104441-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Assessments were performed in four sessions with a minimum of one day of rest between them (see <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). All assessments were performed coinciding with the transition between two menstrual cycles. To determine the menstrual cycle, each participant was required to fill in a menstrual log documenting the length of three previous menstrual cycles (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="f2">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Study design.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="fendo-14-1104441-g002" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <sec id="s2_1">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Physical activity assessment</title>
                <p>Participants were asked to wear an Actigraph GT3X accelerometer for seven days. The device was worn on the right hip and held in place <italic>via</italic> an elastic belt. Participants were instructed to wear continuously while awake and to remove it only when sleeping, bathing, or swimming. A minimum of three days was required to be valid. General guidelines were followed as for minimum wear time (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Relative sedentary time (%ST) was reported, and activity was classified as either sedentary, light, moderate, vigorous, or very vigorous as defined by Freedson (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2_2">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Physical fitness assessment</title>
                <p><italic>Muscular strength test</italic>. To reduce the learning effect, ensure proper technique for each exercise, prevent injuries, and teach participants how to use the OMNI-Resistance Exercise Scale (OMNI-RES from 0 to 10), subjects completed three familiarization sessions during the first week of the project (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Each familiarization session included a warm-up and cool-down period, as well as a conditioning phase consisting of 2–3 sets of 5–8 repetitions of non-weighted exercises. The one maximum repetition (1RM) test was performed following standardized procedures following the familiarization sessions (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>).</p>
                <p><italic>Cardiorespiratory testing</italic>. Cardiorespiratory fitness was measured breath by breath (Parvo Medics’ TrueOne 2400, Sandy, UT, USA) on a treadmill (Trackmaster TMX425C, Newton, KS, USA) using the conventional Bruce methodology (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) up to 85% of the maximal heart rate (HR).</p>
                <p><italic>Body composition and anthropometric assessment.</italic> Fat mass content (FM), percent body fat (BF), fat free mass (FFM), and lean body mass (LBM) were measured using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (GE Lunar Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiometry iDXA, Madison, WI, USA) in accordance with manufacturer instructions. Skeletal muscle mass (SMM) was calculated (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). The waist and hip circumferences, as well as the body weight (BW), were all measured. BMI was calculated as weight/height<sup>2</sup> (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), waist-to-hip ratio (WtH) as waist/hip, and waist-to-height ratio (WtHR) as waist/height. At the beginning of the study and after three weeks of training, the same researcher measured each participant.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2_3">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Dietary controls</title>
                <p><italic>Dietary controls</italic>: Dietary habits were assessed using the Automated Self-administered 24-hour recall (ASA24h) at the beginning of session two (see <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). Total energy intake, proteins, total fats, saturated fatty acids (SFA), monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFA), polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA), carbohydrates, and sugars were reported (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2_4">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Cardiac adipose tissue assessment</title>
                <p><italic>Magnetic Resonance:</italic> A 3.0T MRI system was used to acquire cardiac MRI data (Vida, Siemens Healthineers, Erlangen, Germany). Electrocardiogram (ECG) and respiratory-navigator-gated MRI scans were performed in 1-cm increments along the cardiac short axis over the entire heart. The sequence used had an in-plane resolution of approximately 1.47 mm<sup>2</sup>. The volumes were created by obtaining still-frames corresponding to the diastole from the cine loops. The volumes were loaded into 3DSlicer, an open-source medical imaging software, and the CAT was manually identified on each slice from the apex to the mitral valve. The CAT volume in mm<sup>3</sup> was computed by multiplying the number of CAT voxels identified by the size of each voxel (~1.47mm x 1.47 mm x 10mm).</p>
                <p><italic>Echocardiography</italic>: A standard set of parasternal and apical echocardiographic images were obtained with the volunteer lying in the left lateral decubitus position. The echo-free space between the external wall of the myocardium and the visceral pericardium was identified as epicardial fat. The parasternal long-axis view images were utilized for quantification, but parasternal short-axis images were used when quality of the long-axis view was suboptimal. The thickness was measured on the surface of the right ventricle perpendicular to the free wall at end systole along the midline of the ultrasound beam, perpendicular to the aortic annulus in a total of three cardiac cycles (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2_5">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Pilot intervention study</title>
                <p>The pilot intervention was registered at <uri xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</uri> (ID: NCT03297333), and interventions were carried out following baseline evaluations (starting at early follicular phase). The objective was two-fold, first, to examine the differential effects of high-intensity interval training (HIIT) and high-intensity circuit training (HICT), and second to calculate the appropriate sample size for a larger scale randomized control trial. A total of 18 participants joining the pilot intervention study and were blocked by age, BMI, and %BF, and randomized to either HIIT, HICT, or non-exercising control (CON) group (n= 6 each group) (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Two participants were lost: one refused to continue when allocated to the CON group and one participant in the HIIT group started taking contraceptives. The intervention was suspended due to the COVID-19 (Corona virus) pandemic.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervised exercise programs</italic> were conducted three times per week for three weeks. Exercise sessions included a 10-minute warm-up and cool-down including dynamic and static stretching exercises of major muscle groups, respectively. Based on prior findings a goal was to reach an energy expenditure of ~500 kcals/session (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The core of the HICT sessions consisted of a circuit of seven exercises performed in the following order: LP (leg press), barbell bent-over row, back squat, weighted crunches, deadlift, BP (bench press), and weighted squat jumps. Further details on this training protocol are described elsewhere (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The intensity was set to a minimum of 7 of the OMNI-RES to ensure an intensity of 70–75% of 1RM after each exercise (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), and the circuit was repeated until the target energy expenditure was achieved. The HIIT sessions consisted of five-minute intervals divided into two periods where the intensity was controlled based on each participants’ HR and the Borg’s rating of perceived exertion (RPE). The first period of the interval included three minutes of high-intensity activity at 70-85% of predicted HR<sub>max</sub> and an RPE between 13-17 (15-17 at the end of the period), and the second period included two minutes of moderate intensity (60-65% of HR<sub>max</sub>) and an RPE between 10-12 (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Both HR and energy expenditure were monitored using a Polar FT4 (Polar Electro, Inc., NY, USA). The number of circuits and intervals completed was registered throughout all sessions. Participants in the CON group did not take part in the exercise sessions, and all groups were requested to maintain their physical activity and eating habits throughout the trial.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2_6">
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Statistical analyses</title>
                <p>Data are shown as mean and standard deviation (SD), unless otherwise stated. A Shapiro-Wilk test was performed to verify the normal distribution of the variables, where normality was assumed if p &gt; 0.05. Associations between CAT volume and levels of PA and PFit were examined by Pearson’s and Spearman correlation analyses, depending on normal or non-normal distribution. Non-parametric Mann-Whitney U test and related samples Wilcoxon signed-rank test were utilized to analyze between groups and within group effects of the pilot intervention, respectively. The strength of the associations (rs) and effect sizes (r) were classified as ≤ 0.1 (very small/very weak), 0.1- 0.29 (small/weak), 0.3- 0.49 (moderate), 0.5- 0.69 (high/strong), 0.7- 0.89 (very high/very strong), and 0.9- 1 (perfect). The level of significance was set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 20.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used to perform all the statistical analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s3_1">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Association study</title>
                <p>The mean age of the participants was 23.5 ±6.0 years of age. Data on PFit, PA, and diet are reported as means, standard deviations, minimum and maximum values as shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Characteristics of the sample (n=26).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Anthropometry</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Height (m)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> BW (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Waist (cm)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Hip (cm)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>DXA</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> % BF</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> LBM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> BMC (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FFM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> TA-Fat ratio</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> VAT (cm3)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">545.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1830</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> SMM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Cardiac-MR</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> CAT (mL)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Muscle Strength</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> 1RM-LP (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> 1RM-BP (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Functional Capacity</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> rVO<sub>2</sub>est (mL/kg/min)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> aVO<sub>2</sub>est (l/min)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Physical Activity</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> LPA (min/day)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1076.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> MPA (min/day)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> VPA (min/day)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> MVPA (min/day)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> %ST</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Diet</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Energy (kcal/day)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1647.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3145.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Proteins</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Protein %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Protein (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Fats</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Total Fat %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Total Fat (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> SFA %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> SFA (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> MUFA %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> MUFA (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> PUFA %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> PUFA (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">CHO</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> CHO %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> CHO (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.1</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Sugars %</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Sugars (g)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.3</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.0</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>CON, control group; HIIT, high-intensity interval training; HICT, high-intensity circuit training; BW, Body weight; BMI, Body Mass Index; %BF, % body fat; FM, Fat mass; LBM, Lean body mass; BMC, Bone Mineral Content; FFM, Free Fat Mass; TA-Fat ratio, (Appendicular + Trunk) to total Fat ratio; VAT, Visceral Adipose Tissue; SMM, Total Body Skeletal Muscle; CAT, Cardiac Adipose Tissue; 1RM-LP, 1 Max Rep Leg Press; 1RM-BP, 1 Rep Max Bench Press; rVO2, Relative VO2 peak; aVO2, Absolute VO2; LPA, Low Physical Activity; MPA, Moderate Physical Activity; VPA, Vigorous Physical Activity; MVPA, Moderate to Vigorous Physical Activity; %ST, percent sedentary time; SFA, Saturated Fatty Acids; MUFA, Monounsaturated Fatty Acids; PUFA, Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids; CHO, Carbohydrates.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Association analyses between CAT, PA, PFit levels, and dietary macronutrients and sugars revealed moderate to high (0.3 – 0.7) significant associations (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>). An association matrix table is available as <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material"><bold>Supplementary Table S1</bold></xref>. CAT and VPA levels (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.41, <italic>p</italic> = 0.037) were negatively associated, while positive associations were found between CAT and waist circumference (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.58, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002) and VAT (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.60, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001). No other associations between CAT and muscular or cardiorespiratory fitness were found.</p>
                <p>Analyses examining the PA data showed positive associations between all levels of activity and upper-body lean mass (LPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.52, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007; MPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.53, <italic>p</italic> = 0.005; VPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.40, <italic>p</italic> = 0.044; MVPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.65, <italic>p &lt;</italic>0.000). Similarly, MVPA levels positively impacted lower-body lean mass (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.45, <italic>p</italic> = 0.021) and SMM (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.43, <italic>p</italic> = 0.029). In addition, PA levels were negatively associated with %BF (LPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.65, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; MPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.62, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001; VPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.41, <italic>p</italic> = 0.037; MVPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = -0.68, <italic>p &lt;</italic>0.000) and lower-body FM (LPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.49, <italic>p</italic> = 0.011; MPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.034; VPA: <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.43, <italic>p</italic> = 0.027). Lastly, only LPA showed negative correlations with the heart rate reached at end-test (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.44, <italic>p</italic> = 0.024), and %ST was positively associated with lower-body FM (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.41, <italic>p</italic> = 0.039).</p>
                <p>Diet composition analyses revealed positive associations between daily energy intake and waist circumference (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.51, <italic>p</italic> = 0.008), VAT (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.034), upper-body muscle function (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.45, <italic>p</italic> = 0.019) and relative oxygen consumption (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.40, <italic>p</italic> = 0.043). In addition, carbohydrate and sugars intake correlated negatively with MPA (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.40, <italic>p</italic> = 0.043, and <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.034, respectively), and LPA was negatively associated with carbohydrate intake (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = - 0.40, <italic>p</italic> = 0.042).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3_2">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Pilot study</title>
                <p>Participants in the pilot study had a mean age of 23.7 ±7.6 years, a BMI of 32.7 ±1.7 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, a %BF of 44.1 ±2.1%. No significant differences were found for age, BMI, and %BF between groups (CON, HIIT and HICT) at baseline. Moreover, diet-related variables were similar between groups at the beginning of the pilot study (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material"><bold>Supplementary Table S2</bold></xref>). When comparing duration of exercise sessions (HIIT: 51.1 ±5.1 min; HICT: 53.9 ±6.0 min) and derived energy expenditure (HIIT: 534.7 ±15.6 kcals/session; HICT: 530.1 ±21.2 kcals/session) between exercising groups no significant differences were found (<italic>U</italic> = 9, z = - 0.640, <italic>p</italic> = 0.522, <italic>r</italic> = 0.19; and <italic>U</italic> = 8, z = - 0.853, <italic>p</italic> = 0.394, <italic>r</italic> = 0.26, respectively).</p>
                <p>The nonparametric Wilcoxon test for related samples revealed significant changes in body composition and muscular health (muscle mass and function) with very strong effect sizes (0.83 – 0.90) only for the HICT group. Specifically, %BF and FM were significantly reduced after three weeks of intervention (Z = - 2.207, <italic>p</italic> = 0.027, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90; Z = - 2.201, <italic>p</italic> = 0.028, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90, respectively). Furthermore, LBM (Z = - 2.201, <italic>p</italic> = 0.028, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90), FFM (Z = - 2.201, <italic>p</italic> = 0.028, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90), and lower extremities lean mass and strength (Z = -2.023, <italic>p</italic> = 0.043, <italic>r</italic> = 0.83; Z = - 2.023, <italic>p</italic> = 0.028, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90, respectively) improved significantly. No differences were found for CON, while the HIIT group showed a significant increase in WtH ratio (Z = - 2.023, <italic>p</italic> = 0.043, <italic>r</italic> = 0.90).</p>
                <p>The Mann-Whitney U test revealed a significant increase of WtHR in the HIIT group compared to controls (<italic>U</italic> = 7.0; z = - 1.149; <italic>p</italic> = 0.009; <italic>r</italic> = 0.37). Percent change in leg strength (1RM-LP) was significantly superior in the HICT group compared to controls (<italic>U</italic> = 0; z = - 2.739; <italic>p</italic> = 0.006; <italic>r</italic> = 0.00) and FM in the upper extremities was significantly reduced in HICT compared to HIIT (<italic>U</italic> = 8.0; z = - 1.095; <italic>p</italic> = 0.049; <italic>r</italic> = 0.33). Effect sizes varied from weak to strong (0.02 – 0.58). No other significant differences were found. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> shows mean values at baseline and percent change of body composition, muscular health, and cardiorespiratory fitness.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Effects of the pilot interventions on body composition, muscular health, and cardiorespiratory fitness.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="bottom" rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="center" rowspan="1">CON (n=5)</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="7" align="center" rowspan="1">HIIT (n=5)</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="6" align="center" rowspan="1">HICT (n=6)</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">baseline</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">% change</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Baseline</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">% change</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">baseline</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">% change</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="20" align="left" rowspan="1">Anthropometry</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> BW (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">88.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">32.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Waist (cm)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">99.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> Hip (cm)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">113.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> WtH ratio</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> WtHR ratio</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5**<xref rid="fnT2_1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>
</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="20" align="left" rowspan="1">DXA</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> % BF</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">45.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FM<sub>total</sub> (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">38.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FM<sub>Legs</sub> (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">12.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FM<sub>Arms</sub> (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">4.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5*<xref rid="fnT2_2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>
</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> LBM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">46.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> LM<sub>Legs</sub> (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">16.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> LM<sub>Arms</sub> (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">5.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> FFM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">47.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> SMM (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">29.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="20" align="left" rowspan="1">Muscle Strength</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> 1RM-LP (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">105</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16**<xref rid="fnT2_3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref>
</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> 1RM-BP (kg)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">40.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="middle" colspan="20" align="left" rowspan="1">Functional Capacity</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> rVO<sub>2</sub>est</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">29.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold> aVO<sub>2</sub>est</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                        <td valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±</td>
                        <td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>CON, control group; HIIT, high-intensity interval training; HICT, high-intensity circuit training; BW, Body weight; BMI, Body Mass Index; WtH, Waist to Hip; %BF, % body fat; FM, Fat mass; LBM, Lean body mass; LM, Lean Mass; FFM, Free Fat Mass; SMM, Total Body Skeletal Muscle; 1RM-LP, 1 Max Rep Leg Press; 1RM-BP, 1 Rep Max Bench Press; rVO<sub>2</sub>est, Estimated relative maximal oxygen consumption in ml/kg/min; aVO<sub>2</sub>est, Estimated absolute maximal oxygen consumption in L/min.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn>
                      <p>*p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="fnT2_1">
                      <label>a</label>
                      <p>CON versus HIIT.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="fnT2_2">
                      <label>b</label>
                      <p>HIIT versus HICT.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="fnT2_3">
                      <label>c</label>
                      <p>CON versus HICT.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn>
                      <p>Data reported as means and standard deviations.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Baseline MR-derived CAT values (CON: 58.5 ± 1.2 mL; HIIT: 39.9 ± 1.6 mL; HICT: 68.7 ± 0.9 mL) and echocardiography-derived CAT values (CON: 5.9 ± 0.09 mm; HIIT: 4.2 ± 0.16 mm; HICT: 5.1 ± 0.04 mm) were similar at baseline. The Mann-Whitney U test did not show significant differences between groups on change in CAT thickness (echocardiography) or volume (MR). <xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig"><bold>Figures 3</bold></xref>, <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><bold>4</bold></xref> show, respectively, the change in MR-derived and echocardiography-derived CAT and three MR-CAT scans representative of control, HIIT and HICT groups. Individual participant changes in CAT from all the groups (CON, HIIT and HICT) derived from both MRI and echocardiography are presented as <xref rid="SF1" ref-type="supplementary-material"><bold>Supplementary Figure S1</bold></xref>.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="f3">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Change in CAT. CON – control group; HIIT – high intensity interval training group; HICT – high intensity circuit training group; CAT (mm) – cardiac adipose tissue derived from echocardiography analysis; CAT (mL) – cardiac adipose tissue derived from magnetic resonance analysis. Data reported as means and standard error of mean.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="fendo-14-1104441-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="f4">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Magnetic resonance images representing pre- to post-intervention changes in cardiac fat of three participants. Close-up of the cardiac fat for a single subject in: <bold>(A)</bold> the control group; <bold>(B)</bold> the HICT group; and <bold>(C)</bold> the HIIT group. HICT – high-intensity circuit training; HIIT – high-intensity interval training.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="fendo-14-1104441-g004" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Overall, this study revealed that all types of PA are negatively associated with relative whole-body and lower-body fatness. Furthermore, this is the first study to reveal a significant negative link between CAT and VPA in women with obesity. In this study, only HICT showed significantly positive effects in body fat and lean mass content (i.e. %BF, WC, FM, LBM, FFM, lower-extremity LBM) and muscular strength after just three weeks of training. Since this is an exploratory study, larger samples are required to detect differences between groups (HIIT <italic>versus</italic> HICT) and determine which exercise modality has the greatest impact on CAT. When considered as a whole, our data highlight VPA and high-intensity exercise modalities as potential key modulators for the management of CAT and total adiposity. As CAT deposits are becoming identified as risk factors for CVD development, preventative measures to minimize CAT accumulation are crucial (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Therefore, our findings are clinically relevant as both VPA and HICT could be valuable strategies for health optimization.</p>
              <p>Studies in activity-related behaviors have revealed strong relationships between reduced PA, increased sedentary time and obesity (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). For example, activity time and MVPA are associated with lower levels of adiposity and BMI, and a decreased risk for obesity (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Excessive ST &gt;75% (&gt;9 hours/day) has been associated with poor body composition profile and lower muscle mass (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Conversely, light and higher intensity PA is favorably related with increased lean mass (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Our results are in agreement with these authors as %ST was associated with increased levels of lower-body fat, while all PA levels were linked to greater upper-body lean mass and reduced %BF and lower-extremities fat content.</p>
              <p>To the best of our knowledge, no other studies have reported nor analyzed the associations between CAT and VPA levels. Analysis of the body composition revealed positive associations of CAT with WC and VAT that is consistent with the literature (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>–<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). For example, Sironi et al. reported fat accumulation and increased CAT to be proportional to the degree of obesity (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). The <italic>Framingham Heart Study</italic> also revealed that high WC and VAT was more frequent in individuals with increased CAT (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). Despite these observations, CAT was only associated with vascular calcification (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Furthermore, insulin resistance (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>), and serum free fatty acid levels (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>) have been connected to increased EAT and CAT, respectively. The existing data supports the idea that whole CAT (EAT and PAT) may have harmful perivascular consequences (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Research has shown that higher EAT in those with coronary artery disease triggers inflammation and could play a role in the formation of plaque by secreting cytokines that are pro-inflammatory. Consequently, EAT is a biomarker of cardiovascular risk (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Additionally, the volume of pericardial fat is highly correlated with plaque eccentricity, supporting that pericardial fat is associated with atherosclerosis (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>).</p>
              <p>Regarding diet’s composition, participants diet was not different from current guidelines for Americans, except for sugars 21.3% which were above the 10% recommended (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). As for the relationship with PA, low levels of PA have been postulated as a risk factor for poor dietary habits and fat gain. Indeed, Shook and collaborators revealed that those individuals with the lowest PA levels consumed higher amounts of calories and had ~2–4 higher-risk of “gaining clinically significant amounts<italic>”</italic> of fat over one year (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Supporting these results, our data showed a positive association between daily calorie intake and both WC and VAT. Interestingly, our study also revealed positive correlations between both upper-LBM and all levels of PA. These results in agreement with previous research, as low PA levels have been consistently associated with poor functional capacity and muscle performance in normal weight, overweight and obesity (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>).</p>
              <p>Our data revealed negative correlations between consumption of both sugar and carbohydrates and MPA and LPA levels. Other studies have linked low levels of PA and increased sedentary behaviors (e.g., increased TV, video and computer time) with high sugar intake and other unhealthy dietary habits (e.g., poor vegetable and fruit consumption) (<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). Although we did not find significant relationships between sugar intake and CAT, prior research analyzing various ectopic fat deposits – “excess adipose tissue in locations not classically associated with adipose tissue storage” (<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>) such as VAT, PAT or EAT – revealed positive associations between sugar intake, and PAT and VAT volumes (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). The study by Yi and collaborators included 3070 participants studied over a 20-year period. Moreover, research has exposed that the diets rich in sugar my trigger feelings of exhaustion and loss of energy, attributing to the detrimental impact on PA and sedentary behaviors (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). However, the underlying mechanisms that sugars seem to have on PA and sedentary habits or <italic>vice versa</italic> are still unknown.</p>
              <p>There is considerable interest in learning how to prevent CAT accumulation. Recent studies in the effectiveness of exercise interventions, have shown CAT reduction associated with improvements in FM or %BF (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>) lipid profile (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>), ST (<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>), and inflammatory markers (<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>) in response to exercise. More importantly, resistance and aerobic exercise interventions have shown to reduce EAT in those individuals with abdominal obesity, but only high-intensity resistance exercise has been capable of decreasing PAT (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Overall, exercise intensity prescribed was insufficient and did not meet the recommendations for weight loss (225-420 min/week) (<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>), and the change in CAT after 12-24 weeks of exercise was &lt;10% (~1 mm) (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>–<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>) except for the high-intensity interventions (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). In addition, only three studies utilized resistance-based exercise for 12 weeks (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>) and 3 weeks (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), two utilized a high-intensity circuit format (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and only supervised interventions resulted in large reductions in CAT volume (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Similar to current findings, our research group reported a decrease in CAT (&gt;10%) and PFit improvement (i.e. %BF and muscle function) after a three weeks of a high-intensity progressive resistance training (RT). The intervention was conducted in young adult females with obesity (BMI=34.13 ± 3.16 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and included three RT sessions per week targeting large muscle groups (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Another program targeting primarily small muscle groups (e.g., arm curls, leg extensions, leg curls, triceps extensions, seated row and leg press) allowed for a rather modest CAT (~1 mm, thickness) reduction (<xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). Thus, resistance-based exercise programs of higher intensity appear to be key for CAT loss. In a randomized control trial, Jo and collaborators examined the impact of eight weeks, three times per week, of HIIT and moderate-intensity continuous training (MICT) on endothelial function and CAT content in individuals with hypertensive metabolic syndrome (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). The HIIT group exercised for 3 minutes at 40% heart-rate reserve (HRR), followed by 3 minutes at 80% HRR; whereas in the MICT group, participants exercised for 3 minutes at 60% of HRR. All sessions lasted 30-40 minutes. Although, patients in both groups significantly reduced CAT (HICT, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001; MICT <italic>p</italic> = 0.01), the effect of HIIT was larger. However, these differences cannot be attributed solely to intensity, as the duration of the programs and mode of exercise differed. In our study, energy expenditure and intensity were matched, and duration of sessions was similar. Therefore, we could speculate that the differences could have been caused by the exercise mode (HIIT vs HICT) implemented. Supporting our findings, Christensen and collaborators uncovered that only resistance exercise induced reductions in both EAT and PAT compared to HIIT that only reduced EAT (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The mechanisms underlying these selective changes are unknown; however, it is known that ectopic fat deposits have functional and structural characteristics (<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>) (e.g., adrenergic receptor-mediated lipolysis, etc.) that enable significant responses to higher-intensity exercise. Nevertheless, this hypothesis has to be investigated.</p>
              <p>Our results emphasize the importance of the selection of an adequate exercise “dose” (i.e. frequency, intensity and time), mode (i.e. resistance, endurance), and format (i.e. traditional vs circuit format). Circuit training is a particularly well-liked exercise program style due to its ability to combine high-intensity resistance and aerobic interventions (<xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>). Contrary to the WtHR increases found in the HIIT, researchers comparing high-intensity versus low-intensity interval exercise have reported improvements in body composition with higher intensities (<xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>). Based on prior research, this unusual finding could have been HIIT-mediated by increased feelings of hunger (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>). However, this remains a question as no dietary-records were collected during or after the intervention period. Supporting our results, resistance circuit-based training for an average duration of 10 weeks (range: 4–28) significantly reduces FM while increasing muscle mass, and upper and lower body strength (<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>). Furthermore, HICT has been successful in improving (+6.3%) cardiorespiratory fitness (maximal oxygen consumption or VO<sub>2</sub>max), (+0.3%) maximum aerobic speed or power, and (+2.6%) aerobic performance (<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>). Accordingly, our pilot HICT intervention showed a trend toward superior gains in lower body muscle strength and larger reduction in WtHR compared to HIIT.</p>
              <p>This research is not without limitations. One important limitation is the sample size which limits the generalization of our results, so caution should be used when interpreting both CAT volume associations and the optimal exercise mode (HIIT versus HICT) to reduce CAT. The reason behind this was the interruption caused by COVID-19 (Corona virus) pandemic. Furthermore, in order to avoid the probability of committing type II error (given the small sample size) we did not perform Bonferroni correction; however, this might have increased the risk of a type I error linked to multiple comparisons. This exploratory research did not include <italic>a priori</italic> sample size calculations which are essential to avoid underpowered or overpowered studies. Nevertheless, the sample was enough to reveal novel information related to the potential association between CAT and VPA. Likewise, the use of a 24-hour recalls has associated limitations (e.g., it is limited to the foods listed, only registers the last 24 hours, requires the participant to remember all food consumed, etc.) that could have caused the loss of information concerning dietary habits. Future research in VPA and CAT should include larger samples, so regression model analysis is viable and moderate to high effect sizes are achieved in association and interventional studies. Then, results could be generalized to the population.</p>
              <p>Some important features strengthen this study. The research was designed following the criteria for cross-sectional and randomized control trials. The sample was homogeneous (women with obesity but otherwise healthy) and menstrual cycle was monitored to ensure all participants were evaluated during the same hormonal phase. In addition, samples on the pilot intervention (CON, HICT and HIIT) were equivalent at baseline. Another feature that strengthens this exploratory study is that the intensity prescribed in this program met the recommendations, and energy expenditure was monitored and matched in both HIIT and HICT; hence, allowing for realistic comparisons. Lastly, total CAT was measured <italic>via</italic> cardiac MRI assessment rather than estimated which provides a more precise quantification; likewise, results obtained with DXA showed cardiac fat changes were accompanied by changes in body composition.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>All types of PA have a positive influence on whole-body and lower-body fat and muscle content. However, only VPA shows potential to significantly impact CAT volume. Moreover, short-term high-intensity exercise strategy in women with obesity shows promise, as three weeks of HICT induced positive changes in their body composition and muscular health. Future research is needed to explore vigorous intensity activity and high-intensity interval exercise interventions as tools for physical fitness optimization, CAT reduction and CVD risk management in women with obesity short- and long-term.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6">
              <title>Data availability statement</title>
              <p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7">
              <title>Ethics statement</title>
              <p>The studies involving human participants were reviewed and approved by Institutional Review Board (ID: # 16-1208-4C) at Southern Illinois University Edwardsville. The patients/participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>MF-d-V and JK conceived and designed the research, and PW, BS, PD, and AG edited and revised the manuscript. BSS, PD, BS, AG, PW, JK and MF-d-V performed the experiments. MF-d-V, JP-R, JK and ST analyzed the data. MF-d-V, ST and JP-R interpreted the results of the experiments, MF-d-V, ST and JK prepared figures, and MF-d-V, ST, JP-R, BS and JK drafted the manuscript. MF-d-V, BSS, PD, BS, AG, JP-R, PW, and JK approved the final version of the manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>The authors want to acknowledge all participants for their time and effort. We would also like to thank the undergraduate research assistants and the team at the Writing Center in Southern Illinois University Edwardsville for their help.</p>
            </ack>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s10">
              <title>Conflict of interest</title>
              <p>Author BSS was employed by Heartland Medical Research, Inc.</p>
              <p>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s11">
              <title>Publisher’s note</title>
              <p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s12">
              <title>Supplementary material</title>
              <p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fendo.2023.1104441/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fendo.2023.1104441/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p>
              <supplementary-material id="SF1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplementary Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Individual changes of CAT by group. CON, control group; HIIT, high intensity interval training group; HICT, high intensity circuit training group; CAT (mm), cardiac adipose tissue derived from echocardiography analysis; CAT (mL), cardiac adipose tissue derived from magnetic resonance analysis.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="Image_1.tif">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <media xlink:href="Table_1.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <media xlink:href="Table_2.xlsx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Després</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Abdominal obesity and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>444</volume>(<issue>7121</issue>):<page-range>881–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NATURE05488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotamisligil</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation and metabolic disorders</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>444</volume>(<issue>7121</issue>):<page-range>860–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NATURE05485</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Gaal</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>De Block</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms linking obesity with cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>444</volume>(<issue>7121</issue>):<page-range>875–80</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NATURE05487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchington</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattacks</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adipose tissue in the mammalian heart and pericardium: structure, foetal development and biochemical properties</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol B Comp Biochem</source> (<year>1989</year>) <volume>94</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>225–32</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0305-0491(89)90337-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of pericardial adipose tissue with left ventricular structure and function: a region-specific effect</article-title>? <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>1–9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S12933-021-01219-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Corradi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue: anatomic, biomolecular and clinical relationships with the heart</article-title>. <source>Nat Clin practice. Cardiovasc Med</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>536–43</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NCPCARDIO0319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cury</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mapping epicardial fat with multi-detector computed tomography to facilitate percutaneous transepicardial arrhythmia ablation</article-title>. <source>Eur J Radiol</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>417–22</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.EJRAD.2005.12.030</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jermendy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkely</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurovich-Horvat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical importance of epicardial adipose tissue</article-title>. <source>Arch Med Science : AMS</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>864</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/AOMS.2016.63259</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue volume is associated with high risk plaque profiles in suspect CAD patients</article-title>. <source>Oxid Med Cell Longevity</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>2021</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2021/6663948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazurek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalewski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannion</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Arafat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human epicardial adipose tissue is a source of inflammatory mediators</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>108</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<page-range>2460–6</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000099542.57313.C5</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Myocardial, perivascular, and epicardial fat</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>34</volume>(<issue>Supplement 2</issue>):<page-range>S371–9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/DC11-S250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Local and systemic effects of the multifaceted epicardial adipose tissue depot</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>363–71</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/NRENDO.2015.58</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue: emerging physiological, pathophysiological and clinical features</article-title>. <source>Trends Endocrinol metabolism: TEM</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>450–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.TEM.2011.07.003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellulu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patimah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaza’ai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and inflammation: the linking mechanism and the complications</article-title>. <source>Arch Med Science: AMS</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>851</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/AOMS.2016.58928</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28721154</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahammed MdS</surname></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory cytokines in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease and cancer</article-title>. <source>SAGE Open Med</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>205031212096575</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2050312120965752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>KHK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebers</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue as a mediator of cardiac arrhythmias</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circulatory Physiol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>322</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>H129–44</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/AJPHEART.00565.2021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sicari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Petz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Frassi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chubuchny</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pericardial rather than epicardial fat is a cardiometabolic risk marker: an MRI vs echo study</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Echocardiography : Off Publ Am Soc Echocardiography</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>24</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>1156–62</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ECHO.2011.06.013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial fat: a new cardiovascular therapeutic target</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Pharmacol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<page-range>13–8</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.COPH.2016.01.004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlett</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferencik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriegel</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghoshhajra</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of pericardial fat and coronary high-risk lesions as determined by cardiac CT</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>222</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>129–34</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ATHEROSCLEROSIS.2012.02.029</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabkin</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of reducing epicardial fat by exercise, diet or bariatric surgery weight loss strategies: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Obes reviews : an Off J Int Assoc Study Obes</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>406–15</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/OBR.12270</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Martel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>De Guise</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Avruch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adipose tissue distribution measured by magnetic resonance imaging in obese women</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>57</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>470–5</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/AJCN/57.4.470</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskill</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Waist circumference as the best predictor of noninsulin dependent diabetes mellitus (NIDDM) compared to body mass index, waist/hip ratio and other anthropometric measurements in Mexican americans–a 7-year prospective study</article-title>. <source>Obes Res</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/J.1550-8528.1997.TB00278.X</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9061711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Langefeld</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenchik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenknecht</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pericardial and visceral adipose tissues measured volumetrically with computed tomography are highly associated in type 2 diabetic families</article-title>. <source>Invest Radiol</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004424-200502000-00007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15654254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>De Guise</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guardo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of adipose tissue by MRI: relationship with anthropometric variables</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (Bethesda Md. : 1985)</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>72</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>787–95</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/JAPPL.1992.72.2.787</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajnal</surname><given-names>J V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brynes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstone</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging of total body fat</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (Bethesda Md. : 1985)</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>85</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>1778–85</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/JAPPL.1998.85.5.1778</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity in obesity and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Ann New York Acad Sci</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>1281</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/J.1749-6632.2012.06785.X</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23167451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buman</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Odegaard</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sedentary behaviors and cardiometabolic risk: An isotemporal substitution analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>187</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/AJE/KWX209</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28595346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hivert</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Alhassan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Camhi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzmarzyk</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sedentary behavior and cardiovascular morbidity and mortality: A science advisory from the American heart association</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>134</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<page-range>e262–79</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000440</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sedentary behaviors increase risk of cardiovascular disease mortality in men</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>42</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>879</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0B013E3181C3AA7E</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijssen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sedentary behavior and cardiovascular disease risk: Mediating mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Exercise Sport Sci Rev</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>80–6</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/JES.0000000000000106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wareham</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Sluijs</surname><given-names>EMF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekelund</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and obesity prevention: a review of the current evidence</article-title>. <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>229–47</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS2005423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frayn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and exercise in the regulation of human adipose tissue physiology</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>92</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>157–91</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/PHYSREV.00012.2011/ASSET/IMAGES/LARGE/Z9J0011226030009.JPEG</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagerros</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagiou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of physical activity and energy expenditure in epidemiological research of chronic diseases</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>353–62</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S10654-007-9154-X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wareham</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and obesity prevention</article-title>. <source>Obes reviews: an Off J Int Assoc Study Obes</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>1</volume>(<issue>SUPPL. 1</issue>):<page-range>109–14</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/J.1467-789X.2007.00328.X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bairapareddy</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiya</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guddattu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of aerobic exercise on echocardiographic epicardial adipose tissue thickness in overweight individuals</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Metab Syndrome Obesity: Targets Ther</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<page-range>303–12</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DMSO.S145862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Launbo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zobel</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>von Scholten</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Færch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Targeting epicardial adipose tissue with exercise, diet, bariatric surgery or pharmaceutical interventions: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/OBR.13136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyawo</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pheiffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazibuko-Mbeje</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mthembu</surname><given-names>SXH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyambuya</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkambule</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Physical exercise potentially targets epicardial adipose tissue to reduce cardiovascular disease risk in patients with metabolic diseases: Oxidative stress and inflammation emerge as major therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants (Basel)</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1758</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox10111758</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34829629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saco-Ledo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo-García</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>León-Sanz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruilope</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Physical exercise and epicardial adipose tissue: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<elocation-id>e13103</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/obr.13103</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of cardioprotective benefits of vigorous versus moderate intensity aerobic exercise</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>97</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>141–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.AMJCARD.2005.07.130</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisløff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Støylen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Loennechen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruvold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognmo</surname><given-names>Ø</given-names></name><name><surname>Haram</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Superior cardiovascular effect of aerobic interval training versus moderate continuous training in heart failure patients: A randomized study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>115</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<page-range>3086–94</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.675041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garber</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blissmer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamonte</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>American College of sports medicine position stand. quantity and quality of exercise for developing and maintaining cardiorespiratory, musculoskeletal, and neuromotor fitness in apparently healthy adults: guidance for prescribing exercise</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>43</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1334–59</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0B013E318213FEFB</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rognmo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Moholdt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hole</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mølstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular risk of high-versus moderate-intensity aerobic exercise in coronary heart disease patients</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>126</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>1436–40</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.123117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-del-Valle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloiber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingensmith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Larumbe-Zabala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of resistance training on MRI-derived epicardial fat volume and arterial stiffness in women with obesity: a randomized pilot study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>118</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1231–40</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-018-3852-9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedell-Neergaard</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrskov</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Legaard</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorph</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of aerobic and resistance exercise on cardiac adipose tissues: Secondary analyses from a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Cardiol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>778</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/JAMACARDIO.2019.2074</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31268469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckel</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakicic</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ard</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jesus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Houston Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2013 AHA/ACC guideline on lifestyle management to reduce cardiovascular risk: a report of the American college of Cardiology/American heart association task force on practice guidelines</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>129</volume>(<issue>25 Suppl 2</issue>):<page-range>S76–99</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000437740.48606.D1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exercise training on cardiorespiratory fitness and biomarkers of cardiometabolic health: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>7</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.115.002014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuschieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The STROBE guidelines</article-title>. <source>Saudi J Anaesthesia</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S31</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/SJA.SJA_543_18</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janse DE Jonge</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methodological recommendations for menstrual cycle research in sports and exercise</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>2610–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0000000000002073</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riddoch</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedderkopp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klasson-Heggebø</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardinha</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity levels and patterns of 9- and 15-yr-old European children</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/01.MSS.0000106174.43932.92</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Geraci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dezateux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortina-Borja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quality control methods in accelerometer data processing: defining minimum wear time</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/JOURNAL.PONE.0067206</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B51">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tudor-Locke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreira</surname><given-names>T V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuna</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mire</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaput</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogelholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Improving wear time compliance with a 24-hour waist-worn accelerometer protocol in the international study of childhood obesity, lifestyle and the environment (ISCOLE)</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Activity</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S12966-015-0172-X/FIGURES/2</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B52">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freedson</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Melanson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Calibration of the computer science and applications, Inc. accelerometer</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>777–81</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005768-199805000-00021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B53">
                <label>53</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naclerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodríguez-Romo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barriopedro-Moro</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiménez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvar</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Control of resistance training intensity by the omni perceived exertion scale</article-title>. <source>J Strength Conditioning Res</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1879–88</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JSC.0B013E3181E501E9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B54">
                <label>54</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haff</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essentials of strength training and conditioning</article-title>. <source>Hum Kinet</source> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B55">
                <label>55</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riebe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrman</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liguori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Magal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><collab>American college of sports medicine</collab></person-group>. editors. <article-title>ACSM's guidelines for exercise testing and prescription</article-title>. <source>Wolters Kluwer</source> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B56">
                <label>56</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusumi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosmer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maximal oxygen intake and nomographic assessment of functional aerobic impairment in cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source> (<year>1973</year>) <volume>85</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>546–62</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-8703(73)90502-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B57">
                <label>57</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heymsfield</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Total-body skeletal muscle mass: estimation by a new dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry method</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>378–83</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/AJCN/76.2.378</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B58">
                <label>58</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subar</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The automated self-administered 24-hour dietary recall (ASA24): a resource for researchers, clinicians, and educators from the national cancer institute</article-title>. <source>J Acad Nutr Dietetics</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>112</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1134–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.JAND.2012.04.016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B59">
                <label>59</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Willens</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Echocardiographic epicardial fat: a review of research and clinical applications</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Echocardiography : Off Publ Am Soc Echocardiography</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>1311–9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.ECHO.2009.10.013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B60">
                <label>60</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<page-range>1–9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-8-18</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B61">
                <label>61</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scherr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfarth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Christle</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pressler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenpfeil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Halle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations between borg’s rating of perceived exertion and physiological measures of exercise intensity</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>113</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>147–55</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S00421-012-2421-X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B62">
                <label>62</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruzdeva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Borodkina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchasova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyleva</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbarash</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Localization of fat depots and cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>Lipids Health Dis</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S12944-018-0856-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B63">
                <label>63</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippaerts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patterns of physical activity and sedentary behavior in normal-weight, overweight and obese adults, as measured with a portable armband device and an electronic diary</article-title>. <source>Clin Nutr (Edinburgh Scotland)</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>756–64</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.CLNU.2012.04.011</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B64">
                <label>64</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dyck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteban-Cornejo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinckson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of accelerometer measured school- and non-school based physical activity and sedentary time with body mass index: IPEN adolescent study</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys activity</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S12966-022-01324-X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B65">
                <label>65</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijndaele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmet</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Objectively measured sedentary time, physical activity, and metabolic risk: the Australian diabetes, obesity and lifestyle study (AusDiab)</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>369–71</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/DC07-1795</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B66">
                <label>66</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fortune</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A pilot study of physical activity and sedentary behavior distribution patterns in older women</article-title>. <source>Gait Posture</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<page-range>74–9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.GAITPOST.2017.05.014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B67">
                <label>67</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caserotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berrigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>van Domelen</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of sedentary time with mortality independent of moderate to vigorous physical activity</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e37696</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/JOURNAL.PONE.0037696</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22719846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B68">
                <label>68</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A cut-off of daily sedentary time and all-cause mortality in adults: A meta-regression analysis involving more than 1 million participants</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S12916-018-1062-2/FIGURES/3</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B69">
                <label>69</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shephard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Objectively measured physical activity and progressive loss of lean tissue in older Japanese adults: longitudinal data from the nakanojo study</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatrics Soc</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>61</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>1887–93</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/JGS.12505</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B70">
                <label>70</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosito</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruberg</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahabadi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pericardial fat, visceral abdominal fat, cardiovascular disease risk factors, and vascular calcification in a community-based sample: the framingham heart study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>117</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>605–13</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.743062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B71">
                <label>71</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanassoulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahabadi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Donnell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>‘Prevalence, distribution and risk factor correlates of high pericardial and intra-thoracic fat depots in the framingham heart study’, circulation</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Imaging</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCIMAGING.110.956706</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B72">
                <label>72</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Petz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzzigoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciociaro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Positano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of increased visceral and cardiac fat on cardiometabolic risk and disease</article-title>. <source>Diabetic medicine : J Br Diabetic Assoc</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>622–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/J.1464-5491.2011.03503.X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B73">
                <label>73</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue and insulin resistance in obese subjects</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>90</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>6300–2</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/JC.2005-1087</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B74">
                <label>74</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kankaanpää</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehto</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pärkkä</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Komu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Viljanen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrannini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Myocardial triglyceride content and epicardial fat mass in human obesity: relationship to left ventricular function and serum free fatty acid levels</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>91</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>4689–95</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/JC.2006-0584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B75">
                <label>75</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial fat in the maintenance of cardiovascular health</article-title>. <source>Methodist DeBakey Cardiovasc J</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>20</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14797/MDCJ-13-1-20</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28413578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B76">
                <label>76</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The association of pericardial fat with coronary artery plaque index at MR imaging: The multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis (MESA)</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>261</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>109–15</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/RADIOL.11110346</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B77">
                <label>77</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snetselaar</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jesus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Desilva</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoody</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary guidelines for americans 2020–2025: Understanding the scientific process, guidelines, and key recommendations</article-title>. <source>Nutr Today</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/NT.0000000000000512</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34987271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B78">
                <label>78</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hand</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenowatz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluch</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Low levels of physical activity are associated with dysregulation of energy intake and fat mass gain over 1 year</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>102</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1332–8</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/AJCN.115.115360</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B79">
                <label>79</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavie</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Despres</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Arena</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokkinos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and cardiorespiratory fitness as major markers of cardiovascular risk: Their independent and interwoven importance to health status</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>57</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>306–14</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.PCAD.2014.09.011</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B80">
                <label>80</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Associations between physical activity and other health behaviors in a representative sample of US adolescents</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>86</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>1577–81</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.86.11.1577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B81">
                <label>81</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranjit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrd-Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoelscher</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary and activity correlates of sugar-sweetened beverage consumption among adolescents</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>126</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<elocation-id>e754–e761</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/PEDS.2010-1229</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B82">
                <label>82</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ectopic fat depots and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>124</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<elocation-id>e837–e841</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.077602</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22156000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B83">
                <label>83</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>R D</given-names></name><name><surname>Duprez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Added sugar intake is associated with pericardial adipose tissue volume</article-title>. <source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<page-range>2016–23</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2047487320931303</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B84">
                <label>84</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Reilly</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Antunez-Castillo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of high sugar and high fiber meals on physical activity behaviors in Latino and African American adolescents</article-title>. <source>Obes (Silver Spring Md.)</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1886</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/OBY.21169</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B85">
                <label>85</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of regular taekwondo intervention on health-related physical fitness, cardiovascular disease risk factors and epicardial adipose tissue in elderly women with hypertension</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health 2021</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>2935</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/IJERPH18062935</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B86">
                <label>86</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talman</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Psaltis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>DTL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epicardial adipose tissue: far more than a fat depot</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc diagnosis Ther</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>416–29</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3978/J.ISSN.2223-3652.2014.11.05</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B87">
                <label>87</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pescatello</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>VanHeest</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity mediates a healthier body weight in the presence of obesity</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/BJSM.34.2.86</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10786862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B88">
                <label>88</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yorgun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Canpolat</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazirolan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ateş</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dural</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased epicardial fat tissue is a marker of metabolic syndrome in adult patients</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>165</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>308–13</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.IJCARD.2011.08.067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B89">
                <label>89</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakicic</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manore</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>American College of sports medicine position stand. appropriate physical activity intervention strategies for weight loss and prevention of weight regain for adults</article-title>. <source>Med Sci sports Exercise</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>459–71</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181949333</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B90">
                <label>90</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic exercise training reduces epicardial fat in obese men</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol (Bethesda Md. : 1985)</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>106</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.90756.2008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B91">
                <label>91</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilund</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomayko</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryong Chung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallurupalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakshminarayanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intradialytic exercise training reduces oxidative stress and epicardial fat: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Nephrology dialysis transplantation : Off Publ Eur Dialysis Transplant Assoc - Eur Renal Assoc</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>25</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>2695–701</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfq106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B92">
                <label>92</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornieles González</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ángel Rosety Rodríguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonia Rodríguez Pareja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz Ordóñez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosety Rodríguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teresa Pery Bohorquez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A home-based treadmill training reduced epicardial and abdominal fat in postmenopausal women with metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nutrición Hospitalaria</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>30303030</volume>(<issue>33</issue>):<page-range>609–13</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3305/nh.2014.30.3.7129</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B93">
                <label>93</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosety</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pery</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonia Rodríguez-Pareja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosety</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>García</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A short-term circuit resistance program reduced epicardial fat in obese aged women</article-title>. <source>Nutricion hospitalaria</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>2193–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3305/nh.2015.32.5.9696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B94">
                <label>94</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of high-intensity interval training versus moderate-intensity continuous training on epicardial fat thickness and endothelial function in hypertensive metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Metab syndrome related Disord</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/MET.2018.0128</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B95">
                <label>95</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosety</surname><given-names>MÁ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pery</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodríguez-Pareja</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosety</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>García</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A short-term circuit resistance programme reduced epicardial fat in obese aged women</article-title>. <source>Nutr Hosp</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>2193–7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3305/nh.2015.32.5.9696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B96">
                <label>96</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Subcutaneous and visceral adipose tissue: structural and functional differences</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>11–8</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/J.1467-789X.2009.00623.X</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B97">
                <label>97</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargossi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcolin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzzinati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of three distinct protocols of fitness training on body composition, strength and blood lactate</article-title>. <source>J Sports Med Phys Fitness</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20308971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B98">
                <label>98</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aschehoug</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludviksen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisloff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-intensity interval training, appetite, and reward value of food in the obese</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exercise</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>49</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>1851–8</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0000000000001296</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B99">
                <label>99</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos-Campo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Caravaca</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martínez-Rodríguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio-Arias</surname><given-names>JÁ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of resistance circuit-based training on body composition, strength and cardiorespiratory fitness: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Biology</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/BIOLOGY10050377/S1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33924785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
