<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:43:45Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10273022" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10273022</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-06-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10273022</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10273022</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10273022</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37318808</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37318808</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18411</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230560</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-only">
                  <subject>Online Only</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area">
                  <subject>Psychiatry</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A Cognitive Biotype of Depression and Symptoms, Behavior Measures, Neural Circuits, and Differential Treatment Outcomes</article-title>
                <subtitle>A Prespecified Secondary Analysis of a Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Cognitive Biotype of Depression and Symptoms, Behavior Measures, Neural Circuits, and Treatment Outcomes</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cognitive Biotype of Depression and Symptoms, Behavior Measures, Neural Circuits, and Treatment Outcomes</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hack</surname>
                    <given-names>Laura M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tozzi</surname>
                    <given-names>Leonardo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zenteno</surname>
                    <given-names>Samantha</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BA</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Olmsted</surname>
                    <given-names>Alisa M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hilton</surname>
                    <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSN</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jubeir</surname>
                    <given-names>Jenna</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BS</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Korgaonkar</surname>
                    <given-names>Mayuresh S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Schatzberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Alan F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yesavage</surname>
                    <given-names>Jerome A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>O’Hara</surname>
                    <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                    <given-names>Leanne M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi230560aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="zoi230560aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Stanford University, Stanford, California</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230560aff2"><label>2</label>Sierra-Pacific Mental Illness Research, Education, and Clinical Center (MIRECC) Veterans Affairs Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, California</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230560aff3"><label>3</label>Brain Dynamic Centre, Westmead Institute for Medical Research, The University of Sydney, Westmead, New South Wales, Australia</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> April 27, 2023.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> June 15, 2023. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18411</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2023 Hack LM et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="zoi230560cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Leanne M. Williams, PhD, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305 (<email xlink:href="leawilliams@stanford.edu">leawilliams@stanford.edu</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Williams had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
                <p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Schatzberg, O’Hara, Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Hack, Tozzi, Zenteno, Olmsted, Hilton, Jubeir, Korgaonkar, Schatzberg, Yesavage, Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Hack, Zenteno, Hilton, Jubeir, Schatzberg, Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Tozzi, Olmsted, Hilton, Jubeir, Korgaonkar, Yesavage, O’Hara, Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Hack, Olmsted, Schatzberg, Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Williams.</p>
                <p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Olmsted, Hilton, Jubeir, Korgaonkar, Yesavage, O’Hara.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Tozzi, Hilton, Jubeir, Williams.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Hack reported personal fees from Roche Advisory Board outside the submitted work. Dr Korgaonkar reported grants from Takeda Pharmaceutical Ltd outside the submitted work. Dr Schatzberg reported personal fees from ANeuroTech, personal fees from NeuroWell, personal fees from SAGE, nonfinancial support from ALTO, nonfinancial support from Magnus Health, personal fees from Delpor, and personal fees from Douglas outside the submitted work. Dr Yesavage reported grants from Stanford University, National Institutes of Health, US Veterans Administration during the conduct of the study. Dr Williams reported receiving grant funding from National Institutes of Mental Health for data acquisition and research personnel during the conduct of the study; she reported receiving personal fees for advisory board from One Mind Psyberguide and Laureate Institute for Brain Research outside the submitted work; she reported service on the advisory board for Roche outside the submitted work; in addition, Dr Williams reported holding a patent (No. 16921388) issued to Et Cere Inc. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> The International Study to Predict Optimized Treatment in Depression (iSPOT-D) is sponsored by Brain Resource Company Operations Pty Ltd. This work was also supported by Stanford’s Clinical and Translational Science Award Program overseen by the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences at the National Institutes of Health (UL1TR003142-01, O’Hara).</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and the decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> The authors would like to extend their appreciation to the patients in the study, who were compensated for their participation. We would also like to acknowledge the editorial support of Jon Kilner, MS, MA, who received compensation for his role. We acknowledge the iSPOT-D Investigators Group, and the contributions of principal investigators at each site: <italic>academic principal investigator</italic>, Leanne M. Williams, PhD, Stanford University; <italic>sponsor investigator</italic>, Evian Gordon, PhD; <italic>iSPOT-D investigators group</italic>, Martijn Arns, Nijmegen; XiaoLei Yu Baran, Cornell University; Charles Debattista, Stanford University; Steven Bruce, University of Missouri, St Louis; C. Richard Clark, Flinders University; Barbara A. Cohen, Center for Healing the Human Spirit; Roger deBeus, Skyland Behavioral Health Associates; Kamran Fallahpour, Brain Resource Center; Paul Fitzgerald, Monash University and Alfred Hospital; Anthony W. F. Harris, University of Sydney–Westmead Clinical School; Lawrence Hirshberg, Neurodevelopmental Center; Jayashri Kulkarni, Alfred Hospital and Delmont Hospital; Harbans Multani, Shanti Clinical Trials; Bruce Russell, University of Auckland; Radu Saveanu, Miami University; Con Stough, Swinburne University; Subhdeep Virk, Ohio State University; Elizabeth Wallis, Brain Health Lab, Medical University of South Carolina. Claire Day, PhD, was the global trial manager for iSPOT-D from 2009 to 2015.</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-06-15T10:00">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>6</volume>
              <issue>6</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2318411</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>8</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Hack LM et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2318411.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.18411"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-1">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>How are objective cognitive deficits in depression associated with symptoms, neural circuits, and treatment outcomes?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-2">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial in 1008 patients with major depression, 27% exhibited pretreatment global cognitive impairment and significantly decreased brain response to a cognitive task as well as worse response to standard pharmacotherapy, defining what may be categorized as a cognitive biotype. Changes in cognitive symptoms over the course of treatment mediated the association between pretreatment cognitive status and improvement in overall symptoms and psychosocial functioning.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-3">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>These results suggest that consideration of treatments targeting cognitive dysfunction in a subset of patients with depression is warranted to attain symptomatic and psychosocial improvement.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic">
                <p>This secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial tests whether a cognitive biotype is associated with diagnosed depression with symptoms, neural circuits, and treatment outcomes.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-4">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>Cognitive deficits in depression have been associated with poor functional capacity, frontal neural circuit dysfunction, and worse response to conventional antidepressants. However, it is not known whether these impairments combine together to identify a specific cognitive subgroup (or “biotype”) of individuals with major depressive disorder (MDD), and the extent to which these impairments mediate antidepressant outcomes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-5">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To undertake a systematic test of the validity of a proposed cognitive biotype of MDD across neural circuit, symptom, social occupational function, and treatment outcome modalities.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-6">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>This secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial implemented data-driven clustering in findings from the International Study to Predict Optimized Treatment in Depression, a pragmatic biomarker trial in which patients with MDD were randomized in a 1:1:1 ratio to antidepressant treatment with escitalopram, sertraline, or venlafaxine extended-release and assessed at baseline and 8 weeks on multimodal outcomes between December 1, 2008, and September 30, 2013. Eligible patients were medication-free outpatients with nonpsychotic MDD in at least the moderate range, and were recruited from 17 clinical and academic practices; a subset of these patients underwent functional magnetic resonance imaging. This prespecified secondary analysis was performed between June 10, 2022, and April 21, 2023.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-7">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>Pretreatment and posttreatment behavioral measures of cognitive performance across 9 domains, depression symptoms assessed using 2 standard depression scales, and psychosocial function assessed using the Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale and World Health Organization Quality of Life scale were analyzed. Neural circuit function engaged during a cognitive control task was measured using functional magnetic resonance imaging.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-8">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>A total of 1008 patients (571 [56.6%] female; mean [SD] age, 37.8 [12.6] years) participated in the overall trial and 96 patients participated in the imaging substudy (45 [46.7%] female; mean [SD] age, 34.5 [13.5] years). Cluster analysis identified what may be referred to as a cognitive biotype of 27% of depressed patients with prominent behavioral impairment in executive function and response inhibition domains of cognitive control. This biotype was characterized by a specific profile of pretreatment depressive symptoms, worse psychosocial functioning (<italic>d</italic> = −0.25; 95% CI, −0.39 to −0.11; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and reduced activation of the cognitive control circuit (right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex: <italic>d</italic> = −0.78; 95% CI, −1.28 to −0.27; <italic>P</italic> = <italic>.</italic>003). Remission was comparatively lower in the cognitive biotype positive subgroup (73 of 188 [38.8%] vs 250 of 524 [47.7%]; <italic>P</italic> = .04) and cognitive impairments persisted regardless of symptom change (executive function: <italic>η<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.241; <italic>P</italic> <italic>&lt;</italic> .001; response inhibition: <italic>η<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.750; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). The extent of symptom and functional change was specifically mediated by change in cognition but not the reverse.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-9">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>Our findings suggest the presence of a cognitive biotype of depression with distinct neural correlates, and a functional clinical profile that responds poorly to standard antidepressants and instead may benefit from therapies specifically targeting cognitive dysfunction.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230560-10">
                  <title>Trial Registration</title>
                  <p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00693849?term=ispot-D&amp;rank=1" ext-link-type="uri">NCT00693849</ext-link></p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-ZOI230560">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Major depressive disorder (MDD) is a serious, often chronic condition with a staggering burden that disrupts psychosocial, interpersonal, and workplace function. Cognitive impairment is recognized as a major contributor to both poor functional outcomes and lack of symptom relief from antidepressant treatments.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Such impairment encompasses deficits in executive control, attention, and working memory relevant to the research domain criteria cognitive system<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and to the MDD <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (Fifth Edition, text revision) diagnostic criterion of poor concentration and indecisiveness.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> We undertook a systematic evaluation of what we describe as a cognitive dyscontrol biotype of depression, using behavioral measures to identify the biotype prevalence, clinical ratings to assess its association with symptoms and function, functional neuroimaging to reveal neural mechanistic underpinnings, and a randomized clinical trial to determine whether cognitive impairment is a causal mediator of poor outcomes following antidepressant treatment (ADT).</p>
              <p>A growing pool of studies document cognitive impairment in MDD across the adult lifespan and assess treatments for it.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> These studies lack a consistent battery of cognitive measures and do not stratify depressed patients based on the extent of cognitive impairment, possibly leading to mixed treatment results on efficacy. Given this, we lack data specific to the patients with MDD distinguished by moderate-to-severe cognitive impairment, which may form a specific biotype subgroup.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Our previous work has shown that patients with MDD, in young to mid-adulthood, are distinguished from healthy patients by a group mean reduction in cognitive performance, which persists despite ADTs<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and is implicated in nonremission.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> We have also observed that nonremission is characterized by a mean reduction in activation of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (dLPFC),<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> a brain region essential in the cognitive control circuit, and by alterations in the connectivity of this circuit.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> In this study, we pursued a systematic, multimodal characterization of our prior proposed putative clinical biotype of depression called the cognitive dyscontrol biotype<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> (hereafter referred to as <italic>cognitive biotype</italic> for brevity).</p>
              <p>We used a machine learning method of cluster analysis to identify the cognitive biotype within the broader MDD diagnosis. Our primary research goal was to validate the cognitive biotype of depression by assessing whether it is distinguished by baseline symptom and function profiles, by baseline neural dysfunctions in the cognitive control circuit, and by poorer response to standard antidepressants. We also sought to determine whether lack of amelioration of cognitive impairment mediates poorer symptom and function outcomes during the treatment period (but not the reverse).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-ZOI230560">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="H2-1-ZOI230560">
                <title>Overview and Patients</title>
                <p>Data were from 1008 adults with MDD who participated in the International Study to Predict Optimized Treatment in Depression (iSPOT-D)<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> and were enrolled between December 1, 2008, and September 30, 2013 (<xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Of these, 96 completed the iSPOT-D imaging substudy and were used in this analysis.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> The study protocol was reviewed and received institutional review board approval at each clinical site. Participants provided written informed consent. This prespecified secondary analysis was performed between June 10, 2022, and April 21, 2023. Both sample size and power calculations were established in the full sample.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> The full sample was used for all analyses except the functional and structural neuroimaging analyses, for which the imaging subsample was used. This study follows the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" ext-link-type="uri">CONSORT</ext-link>) reporting guideline for randomized studies (eFigure 1 and eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>Patients were assessed on cognitive testing, symptoms, functional capacity, and functional neuroimaging at baseline, randomized in a 1:1:1 ratio to 1 of 3 widely prescribed antidepressants—escitalopram (336 patients), sertraline (336 patients), or venlafaxine-XR<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> (336 patients)—and then reassessed on the same measures after 8 weeks of treatment. Of the total sample, 712 patients completed treatment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-2-ZOI230560">
                <title>Cognitive Testing</title>
                <p>Cognitive performance was assessed using a standardized, computerized test battery, IntegNeuro (Brain Resource), which has established norms across 9 decades of the healthy lifespan,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> test-retest reliability,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> construct validity with respect to traditional neuropsychological batteries and brain measures,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and utility in distinguishing cognitive impairments in psychiatric groups.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> IntegNeuro assessed 9 cognitive domains (and tests), including sustained attention (Continuous Performance Test), cognitive flexibility (Stroop), decision speed (Choice Reaction Time), executive function (Maze), information processing speed (Switching of Attention), psychomotor response speed (Motor Tapping), response inhibition (Go/No-Go), verbal memory (Verbal Learning and Memory), and working memory (Digit Span). Performance was expressed as a standard deviation score referenced to a healthy norm mean of zero for each test and quantified by accuracy, reaction time, and/or completion time. Composite scores were obtained by averaging performance on each test within a domain (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>Depressive symptom severity was assessed using criterion standard scales, the 17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD-17) with masked clinician ratings and 16-item Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology–Self-Report (QIDS-SR-16)<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> for patient reports. Function was assessed using the Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale (SOFAS)<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> on a scale of 0 to 100.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-3-ZOI230560">
                <title>Functional Neuroimaging</title>
                <p>The imaging subsample underwent functional magnetic resonance imaging using 3.0 Tesla Signa HDx (GE Healthcare) with an 8-channel head coil during an established cognitive Go/No-Go task,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> engaging an equivalent domain of cognitive control as the cognitive battery (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). Blood-oxygen-level–dependent contrast functional images were acquired with echo-planar T2-weighted imaging (repetition time, 2500 ms; time to echo, 27.5 ms; matrix, 64 × 64; field of view, 24 cm; flip angle, 90 degrees; 40 slices, 3.5 mm–slice thickness, 123 volumes). The cognitive task robustly engages the dorsolateral prefrontal (dLPFC) and dorsal anterior cingulate (dACC) regions that define the cognitive control circuit.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> DLPFC and dACC activation, and functional connectivity between them, was quantified for each patient using our prior established method (PanLab Imaging Pipeline) and expressed as a standard deviation value relative to a healthy reference group,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> equivalent to our procedure for cognitive tests. A high-resolution T1-weighted structural scan was acquired for registration of functional images.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-4-ZOI230560">
                <title>Exploratory Measures</title>
                <p>We included 3 additional measures of factors that might be alternative explanations for cognitive impairment: body mass index (BMI; calculated as weight in kilograms divided by height in meters squared), anxiety assessed using the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale-42 (DASS-42) anxiety subscale,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> and brain volume quantified from the structural scan using voxel-wise brain morphometry for 120 regions defined by the Automated Anatomical Atlas, an established procedure for iSPOT-D.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p>
                <p>Response was defined as an improvement of at least 50% on the HRSD-17 or QIDS-SR-16. We defined symptom remission as an HRSD-17 score of 7 or below or a QIDS-SR-16 score of 5 or below.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-5-ZOI230560">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>Analyses were undertaken in SPSS version 28 (IBM Corp). We imputed missing values that were less than 5% of the sample. Hypothesis tests were 2-tailed except for χ<sup>2</sup> tests examining secondary treatment type differences. A nominal α = .05 was used for significance for all tests except symptoms, for which we used the Benjamini-Hochberg method<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> with false discovery rate (FDR) of α = .05. This method adjusts the <italic>P</italic> values of the individual tests, considering the number of tests conducted and the expected proportion of false positives. We calculated effect sizes as Cohen <italic>d.</italic></p>
                <sec id="H3-1-ZOI230560">
                  <title>Deriving the Cognitive Biotype</title>
                  <p>Data-driven clustering was used to identify a cognitive biotype based on impaired cognitive performance. Expanding on a prior preliminary approach,<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> the 9 cognitive composite scores were entered into a k-means clustering algorithm, generating 1 through 10 cluster solutions. The optimal solution was selected by convergence across multiple criteria: (1) scree plot elbow method using sum of squared Euclidean distances, (2) silhouette metric, and (3) clusters differ on a maximum number of inputs. We validated the cluster solution for clinical and mechanistic meaning using symptom, functional, neural circuit, and treatment outcome measures not used as inputs to generate the clusters.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-2-ZOI230560">
                  <title>Depressive Symptoms, Functional Capacity, Neural Circuit Function, and Other Considerations</title>
                  <p>Cognitive biotypes (positive and negative) were compared on overall pretreatment depressive symptom severity, individual depressive symptoms, functional capacity, neural circuit function, and exploratory BMI, anxiety, and brain volume metrics using independent sample <italic>t</italic> tests where the independent variable was the cognitive biotype and the dependent variable is the depressive symptom severity. We also compared clusters on individual symptoms using independent sample <italic>t</italic> tests corrected for multiple testing to determine whether the cognitive biotype is specifically associated with particular depressive symptoms.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-3-ZOI230560">
                  <title>Treatment Outcomes</title>
                  <p>χ<sup>2</sup> tests were used to compare clusters on binary response and remission with antidepressant treatment and type of treatment at 8 weeks. Clusters were compared on change in function and cognitive measures using mixed model analysis of variance.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-4-ZOI230560">
                  <title>Treatment Outcomes as a Function of Cognitive Impairment</title>
                  <p>To further assess clinical meaningfulness of the cognitive biotype, we undertook mediation analyses to test whether symptom and functional improvement following 8 weeks of treatment rely on improvement in cognition at 8 weeks. Mediation models were implemented using the Preacher-Hayes bootstrapping method for estimating a simple mediation model with a binary predictor <italic>X</italic>, a continuous mediator <italic>M</italic>, and outcome variable <italic>Y</italic>. PROCESS Macro was used to implement the Preacher-Hayes method in SPSS<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> (with <italic>X</italic> being cognitive biotype; <italic>M</italic>, change in executive function or response inhibition; <italic>Y</italic>, change in HRSD-17 symptom rating or SOFAS; confidence interval based on 5000 bootstrapped samples) (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). We note that, while temporal precedence is ideal in mediation models, the method we used does not require this to be the case. Age, baseline HRSD-17, and family history of MDD were used as covariates in the mediation models.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-ZOI230560">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="H2-6-ZOI230560">
                <title>Demographic Information</title>
                <p>The 1008 MDD patients were 18 to 65 years old (mean [SD] age, 37.8 [12.6] years) and 57% female (167 [17%] Black, 83 [8%] Hispanic, 625 [62%] White). The 96 patients who participated in the imaging substudy were 47% female and had a mean age of 34.5 (13.5) years (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-7-ZOI230560">
                <title>Deriving a Cognitive Biotype</title>
                <p>Scree plot and the silhouette metric indicated a 2-cluster solution was optimal (eResults, eFigure 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). The 2-cluster solution differed across all cognitive test scores (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), thus meeting our third criterion. The cluster characterized by marked impairment on all cognitive measures was present in 27% of individuals. Impairments were most pronounced for goal-directed executive function and response inhibition domains (<xref rid="zoi230560f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) relevant to the research domain criteria cognitive control construct (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). The second cluster was an intact cognitive subgroup characterized by performance well within the healthy range (<xref rid="zoi230560f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Hereafter, we refer to these subgroups as cognitive biotype positive and cognitive biotype negative based on the rationale that the neurocognitive tests are tapping into biologically based function.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230560f1" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 1. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Baseline Cognitive Performance for Composite Measures in 2-Cluster Solution</title>
                    <p>Standardized mean performance for baseline cognitive composite scores across 9 domains for the 2-cluster solution obtained via k-means clustering. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean. We have designated the 2 clusters cognitive biotype positive and cognitive biotype negative.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-8-ZOI230560">
                <title>Baseline Symptom Profiles and Neural Function</title>
                <p>HRSD-17 depressive symptom severity was significantly greater for the cognitive biotype positive than the negative subgroup (mean difference, 0.73; <italic>d</italic> = 0.18; 95% CI, 0.04 to 0.32; <italic>P</italic> = .01), yet this difference represented less than 1 symptom point. Clusters did not differ on overall self-reported severity on the QIDS-SR-16. Regarding individual symptoms, the cognitive biotype positive subgroup was distinguished by similar profiles on both the HRSD-17 and QIDS-SR-16, including slower information processing and effortful thinking or psychomotor retardation (HRSD-17 item 8, QIDS-SR-16 item 15), more waking during the night (HRSD-17 item 5), awaking early (HRSD-17 item 6, QIDS-SR-16 item 3), and sleeping too little (QIDS-SR-16 item 4) but significantly less self-blame (QIDS-SR-16 item 11) (<xref rid="zoi230560f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230560f2" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 2. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Baseline Individual Depression Scale Items Across Cognitive Biotypes</title>
                    <p>Difference between cognitive biotypes on individual items of the 17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HDRS-17) and the 16-item Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms–Self Report (QIDS). Significant items grouped according to symptom domain were as follows: H8 (<italic>d</italic> = .23; 95% CI, 0.09 to 0.37; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery<italic> = </italic>.009), Q15 (<italic>d</italic> = .26; 95% CI, 0.12 to 0.41; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery &lt; .001), H5 (<italic>d</italic> = .20; 95% CI, 0.06 to 0.34; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery = <italic>.</italic>03), Q2 (<italic>d</italic> = .29; 95% CI, 0.15 to 0.44; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery <italic>&lt;</italic> <italic>.</italic>001), H6 (<italic>d</italic> = .33; 95% CI, 0.19 to 0.47; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery <italic>&lt;</italic> <italic>.</italic>001), Q3 (<italic>d</italic> = .26; 95% CI, 0.12 to 0.40; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery <italic>&lt;</italic> <italic>.</italic>001), Q4 (<italic>d</italic> = −.22; 95% CI, −0.36 to −0.07; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery = <italic>.</italic>01), and Q11 (<italic>d</italic> = −.26; 95% CI, −0.40 to −0.12; <italic>P</italic> for false discovery <italic>&lt;</italic> <italic>.</italic>001). Error bars represent the standard error of the mean. GI indicates gastrointestinal.</p>
                    <p><sup>a</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
                    <p><sup>b</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
                    <p><sup>c</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The cognitive biotype positive subgroup had significantly greater functional impairment pretreatment compared with the negative subgroup (<italic>d</italic> = −0.25; 95% CI, −0.39 to −0.11; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) as measured by the SOFAS (<xref rid="zoi230560f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Cognitive task-evoked neural activation was significantly reduced for the cognitive biotype positive subgroup compared with the negative subgroup in right dLPFC (<italic>d</italic> = −0.78; 95% CI, −1.28 to −0.27; <italic>P</italic> = <italic>.</italic>003) and dACC (<italic>d</italic> = −0.52; 95% CI, −1.02 to −0.02; <italic>P</italic> = .04) regions of the cognitive control circuit (<xref rid="zoi230560f4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). We did not find any meaningful differences between clusters in anxiety severity, BMI, or structural brain volume (eResults in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230560f3" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 3. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Baseline Social and Occupational Functioning Across Cognitive Biotypes</title>
                    <p>Difference between cognitive biotypes on the Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale (SOFAS). Error bars represent the standard error of the mean.</p>
                    <p><sup>a</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230560f4" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 4. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Illustration of the Cognitive Control Circuit and Baseline Task-Evoked Activation in the Cognitive Control Circuit Across Cognitive Biotypes</title>
                    <p>Error bars represent the standard error of the mean. dACC indicates dorsal anterior cingulate cortex; dLPFC, dorsolateral prefrontal cortex.</p>
                    <p><sup>a</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
                    <p><sup>b</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-g004" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-9-ZOI230560">
                <title>Cognitive Biotype and Treatment Outcomes at 8 Weeks</title>
                <p>The cognitive biotype positive subgroup was distinguished by significantly lower rates of response and remission to antidepressants (HRSD-17 response, 103 of 188 [54.8%] vs 340 of 524 [64.9%]; <italic>P</italic> = .02; HRSD-17 remission, 73 of 188 [38.8%] vs 250 of 524 [47.7%]; <italic>P</italic> = .04). This biotype also had significantly lower response and remission rates for sertraline in particular (HRSD-17 response, 31 of 64 [48.4%] vs 132 of 182 [72.5%]; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001; HRSD-17 remission, 23 of 64 [35.9%] vs 91 of 182 [50.0%]; <italic>P</italic> = .04). Subgroups did not differ in profiles of individual symptom improvement within response and remission categories. Regarding functional impairment posttreatment, there was no interaction of the cognitive biotype with pretreatment vs posttreatment change in psychosocial function as measured by SOFAS. For cognitive impairment posttreatment, there was a significant interaction of cognitive subtype with pretreatment vs posttreatment change (or lack of change) in cognitive performance (executive function: <italic>η<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.241; <italic>P</italic> <italic>&lt;</italic> .001; response inhibition: <italic>η<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.750; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Cognitive impairments persisted posttreatment in the cognitive biotype positive subgroup, remaining at least 0.2 standard deviations below the healthy mean, whereas performance improved during the treatment period for the biotype negative subgroup, especially for cognitive control domains of executive function and response inhibition (eFigure 3 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-10-ZOI230560">
                <title>Cognitive Impairment and Overall Symptom Response Following 8 Weeks of Treatment</title>
                <p>Mediation models focused on executive function and response inhibition because they were most significantly impaired in the cognitive biotype positive subgroup. Lack of change in cognitive control performance was a significant mediator of the association between pretreatment cognitive biotype and lack of overall symptom relief following treatment (indirect effect a × b = −0.24; bootstrapped 95% CI, −0.49 to −0.02) (<xref rid="zoi230560f5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>A), but the reverse was not true. This mediator significantly contributed to the total effect model (<italic>t</italic> = −2.09; β = −1.17; <italic>P</italic> = .03) but there was no direct effect between cognitive biotype and symptom relief (<italic>t</italic> = −1.63; <italic>P</italic> = .10). See eResults in <xref rid="note-ZOI230560-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref> for further discussion of mediation results.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230560f5" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 5. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Mediation Models for Response Inhibition and Executive Function Using Depressive Symptoms and Functional Capacity as Outcomes</title>
                    <p>Depressive symptoms were measured using the 17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression and functional capacity using the Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale. Coefficients are unstandardized. Gray arrows indicate positive associations; orange arrows, negative associations.</p>
                    <p><sup>a</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                    <p><sup>b</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
                    <p><sup>c</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; .10.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-g005" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-ZOI230560">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Overall, our multimodal findings suggest the presence of a cognitive biotype of depression that represents about a quarter of all depressed patients and is characterized by prominent impairments in 2 domains of cognitive control (executive function and response inhibition). This cognitive biotype has greater severity in baseline symptoms of slowed information processing and insomnia, poor psychosocial function, reduced neural function of the brain’s cognitive control circuit, and poorer outcomes following first-line antidepressant treatment. The extent of cognitive control impairment also mediated the extent of (or lack of) symptom and psychosocial improvement posttreatment.</p>
              <p>The identification of a distinctive cognitive biotype identified by a machine learning clustering algorithm highlights the value of disentangling the heterogeneity of depression to understand the source of mean cognitive impairments within the diagnosis of depression as a broad category. This biotype might be a major contributor to prior mean observations of impaired executive function and response inhibition within the depression diagnosis compared with healthy peers.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Adding further to the value of disentangling heterogeneity in depression, the cognitive biotype identified in this study was distinguished more by a specific profile of individual symptoms than by overall depression severity. This biotype was characterized by slowed thinking (which could be anticipated given the cognitive focus of this biotype) as well as sleep problems, and aligns with prior observed associations between depression, executive function, and sleep.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> On psychosocial ratings, the cognitive biotype was further distinguished by poor social and occupational function, adding specificity to evidence that cognitive impairment is a major contributor to disability in depression.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Our observation that the cognitive subtype was characterized by reduced activation of the dLPFC and dACC within the cognitive control circuit suggests a distinct neural mechanistic process underlying this biotype. Reduced activation in these prefrontal regions aligns with the prior proposed cognitive control biotype based on a synthesis of neuroimaging findings<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and the role of these regions in cognitive control performance. A unique feature of our data set was the opportunity to assess the impact of the specific cognitive biotype on outcomes following treatment. This cognitive biotype had low rates of both symptom response and remission following antidepressants, particularly for treatment with sertraline. Posttreatment, the cognitive biotype also showed continued cognitive control impairment and less improvement in psychosocial function regardless of symptom change. In mediation models, we demonstrated that less improvement in cognitive control specifically mediated the relationship between pretreatment biotype and extent of posttreatment relief from depressive symptoms. Similarly, less change in cognitive control performance mediated less improvement in psychosocial function following treatment. These mediation findings suggest that for a substantial minority of depressed patients it is necessary to improve cognition in order to improve overall depressed mood and function. The findings challenge the prevailing assumption that cognitive impairments resolve as a secondary effect of improving overall severity.</p>
              <p>Our findings add to the growing evidence that treatments specifically targeting cognitive impairment and its mechanisms in depression are urgently needed.<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230560r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> Only 1 FDA-approved antidepressant—vortioxetine—has shown promise for improving cognition<sup><xref rid="zoi230560r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>; however, the mechanisms underlying vortioxetine’s cognitive-enhancing effects are unknown. Future studies should utilize biomarker designs to evaluate whether outcomes for the cognitive biotype are enhanced when matched to a treatment with mechanisms targeting cognitive control circuitry and behaviors.</p>
              <sec id="H2-11-ZOI230560">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>Our findings must be considered in the context of several potential limitations. First, although we rule out disorders and other factors that could affect cognitive impairment, it remains possible that other as yet unidentified behavioral or neurobiological factors contribute to the cognitive biotype. Second, although our sample was representative of multiple racial and ethnic backgrounds and clinical settings, the findings must be evaluated for generalizability. Third, the pragmatic biomarker design of the trial focused on 3 commonly prescribed antidepressants and the relevance of our approach to other antidepressants and treatment modalities requires investigation. Finally, within the mediation models, we acknowledge some overlap in measures used to allocate <italic>X</italic> and assess change in <italic>M</italic>, but not to the extent of a confounder. Future studies are warranted to test stronger causal inferences in a design optimized by experimental manipulation of cognitive biotype (<italic>X</italic>) and through establishing an explicit temporal precedence between <italic>M</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>. Our putative mediator, cognitive change, is suitable to such designs, as it is amenable to both measurement and manipulation. Likewise, we also acknowledge there is some circularity in using the Go/No-Go task to both generate the cognitive biotype categories (positive and negative) and link the biotypes to Go/No-Go–evoked brain response.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-ZOI230560">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to combine biological and nonbiological measures to verify a distinct, clinically actionable cognitive biotype of depression. If the prevalence of cognitive deficits in our sample is generalized to the US population, then approximately 5.7 million individuals with depression have cognitive impairments (27% of 21 million). Incorporating neural circuit measures enables a deeper understanding of the neurobiological mechanisms that underpin these cognitive impairments and has implications for precision treatment approaches in future studies and in practice. Biomarker trials targeting the cognitive biotype with more selective treatment strategies are urgently needed.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-ZOI230560">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zoi230560r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mclntyre</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khullar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive dysfunction in major depressive disorder: effects on psychosocial functioning and implications for treatment</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>-<lpage>654</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674371405901206</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25702365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25702365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garvey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Research domain criteria (RDoC): toward a new classification framework for research on mental disorders</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>748</fpage>-<lpage>751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2010.09091379</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20595427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20595427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group>. <source>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders.</source><edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Soczynska</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Styra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of bupropion XL and escitalopram on memory and functional outcomes in adults with major depressive disorder: results from a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>220</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2014.06.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25124683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25124683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Vieta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sluth</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of vortioxetine on cognitive dysfunction in patients with inadequate response to current antidepressants in major depressive disorder: a short-term, randomized, double-blind, exploratory study versus escitalopram</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>227</volume>:<fpage>803</fpage>-<lpage>809</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2017.11.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29673132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29673132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schüssler-Fiorenza Rose</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heinemeyer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Depression, health comorbidities, cognitive symptoms and their functional impact: not just a geriatric problem</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.05.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34087515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34087515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Perini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cotta Ramusino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinforiani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrachi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment in depression: recent advances and novel treatments</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1249</fpage>-<lpage>1258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S199746</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31190831?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31190831</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recognition and treatment of cognitive dysfunction in major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>655</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00655</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30564155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30564155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Shilyansky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gyurak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usherwood</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of antidepressant treatment on cognitive impairments associated with depression: a randomised longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(16)00012-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26995298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26995298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patenaude</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A cognitive-emotional biomarker for predicting remission with antidepressant medications: a report from the iSPOT-D trial</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1332</fpage>-<lpage>1342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2014.333</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25547711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25547711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gyurak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patenaude</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korgaonkar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grieve</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Frontoparietal activation during response inhibition predicts remission to antidepressants in patients with major depression</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.02.037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25891220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25891220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldstein-Piekarski</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korgaonkar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Connectivity of the cognitive control network during response inhibition as a predictive and response biomarker in major depression: evidence from a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>-<lpage>472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.08.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31601424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31601424</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Precision psychiatry: a neural circuit taxonomy for depression and anxiety</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>-<lpage>480</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(15)00579-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27150382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27150382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koslow</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>International Study to Predict Optimized Treatment for Depression (iSPOT-D), a randomized clinical trial: rationale and protocol</article-title>. <source>Trials</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1745-6215-12-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21208417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21208417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Grieve</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korgaonkar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Brain imaging predictors and the international study to predict optimized treatment for depression: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Trials</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1745-6215-14-224</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23866851?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23866851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Standardized assessment of cognitive functioning during development and aging using an automated touchscreen battery</article-title>. <source>Arch Clin Neuropsychol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>-<lpage>467</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.acn.2006.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16904862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16904862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The test-retest reliability of a standardized neurocognitive and neurophysiological test battery: “neuromarker”</article-title>. <source>Int J Neurosci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1605</fpage>-<lpage>1630</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207450590958475</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16287629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16287629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary validity of “integneuro”: a new computerized battery of neurocognitive tests</article-title>. <source>Int J Neurosci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1549</fpage>-<lpage>1567</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207450590957890</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16223701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16223701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liddell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain structure and function correlates of general and social cognition</article-title>. <source>J Integr Neurosci</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S021963520700143X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17472224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17472224</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hermens</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using brain-based cognitive measures to support clinical decisions in ADHD</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Neurol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2009.08.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20117748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20117748</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Braund</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tillman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AWF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Verbal memory predicts treatment outcome in syndromal anxious depression: an iSPOT-D report</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>260</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2019.09.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31513968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31513968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>General and social cognition in first episode schizophrenia: identification of separable factors and prediction of functional outcome using the IntegNeuro test battery</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>1-3</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2007.10.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18053688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18053688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In first presentation adolescent anorexia nervosa, do cognitive markers of underweight status change with weight gain following a refeeding intervention?</article-title><source>Int J Eat Disord</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eat.20695</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19434607?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19434607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The 16-Item Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (QIDS), clinician rating (QIDS-C), and self-report (QIDS-SR): a psychometric evaluation in patients with chronic major depression</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>573</fpage>-<lpage>583</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 12946886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12946886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skodol</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lave</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Revising axis V for DSM-IV: a review of measures of social functioning</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1148</fpage>-<lpage>1156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.149.9.1148</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1386964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1386964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Korgaonkar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grieve</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koslow</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Using standardized fMRI protocols to identify patterns of prefrontal circuit dysregulation that are common and specific to cognitive and emotional tasks in major depressive disorder: first wave results from the iSPOT-D study</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>863</fpage>-<lpage>871</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2012.252</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23303059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303059</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Goldstein-Piekarski</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samara</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mapping neural circuit biotypes to symptoms and behavioral dimensions of depression and anxiety</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>-<lpage>571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2021.06.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34482948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34482948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lovibond</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lovibond</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Manual for the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales</source>. <publisher-name>Psychology Foundation of Australia</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc B</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schatzberg</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeBattista</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazzeroni</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>GM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>ABCB1 genetic effects on antidepressant outcomes: a report from the iSPOT-D Trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>751</fpage>-<lpage>759</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.14050680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25815420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Introduction to Mediation, Moderation, and Conditional Process Analysis: A Regression-Based Approach</source>. <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Culpepper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment in patients with depression: awareness, assessment, and management</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1383</fpage>-<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.tk16043ah5c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29345866</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Wilckens</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does objectively-assessed sleep moderate the association between history of major depressive disorder and task-switching?</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>265</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32090744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32090744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prefrontal dysfunction in depressed patients performing a complex planning task: a study using positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>-<lpage>942</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291797005187</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9234470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9234470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Setoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between cognitive deficits and suicidal ideation in patients with major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11637</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-12142-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28912439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28912439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230560r36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bennabi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haffen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Waes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Vortioxetine for cognitive enhancement in major depression: from animal models to clinical research</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>771</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00771</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31780961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31780961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230560-1">
              <supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230560-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Trial Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-s001.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>eMethods.</bold> Supplemental Methods</p>
                  <p><bold>eResults.</bold> Supplemental Results</p>
                  <p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of Participants at Baseline</p>
                  <p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Neurocognitive Domains, Tests, and Descriptions</p>
                  <p><bold>eFigure 1.</bold> CONSORT Diagram</p>
                  <p><bold>eFigure 2.</bold> Scree Plot of the k-means Clustering Solutions with Different Numbers of Clusters</p>
                  <p><bold>eFigure 3.</bold> Posttreatment Cognitive Performance for Composite Measures in Cognitive Biotypes</p>
                  <p>
eReferences.
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-s002.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2318411-s003.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
