<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T03:51:07Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7328473" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7328473</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-07-13</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jnutr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Nutr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Nutr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jn</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The Journal of Nutrition</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3166</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1541-6100</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7328473</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7328473</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7328473</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29659963</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29659963</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/nxy014</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">nxy014</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Nutrition and Disease</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Saturated Fats from Butter but Not from Cheese Increase HDL-Mediated Cholesterol Efflux Capacity from J774 Macrophages in Men and Women with Abdominal Obesity</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brassard</surname>
                    <given-names>Didier</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Arsenault</surname>
                    <given-names>Benoît J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Boyer</surname>
                    <given-names>Marjorie</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bernic</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tessier-Grenier</surname>
                    <given-names>Maude</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Talbot</surname>
                    <given-names>Denis</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tremblay</surname>
                    <given-names>Angelo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Levy</surname>
                    <given-names>Emile</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Asztalos</surname>
                    <given-names>Bela</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>Peter JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Couture</surname>
                    <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lamarche</surname>
                    <given-names>Benoît</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <!--<email>benoit.lamarche@fsaa.ulaval.ca</email>-->
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Institute of Nutrition and Functional Foods (INAF), School of Nutrition, Centre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Québec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>School of Nutrition, Centre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Québec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Centre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Québec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>CHU Sainte-Justine Research Center, Montréal, Canada</aff>
              <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Cardiovascular Nutrition Laboratory, Human Nutrition Research Center on Aging, Tufts University, Boston, MA</aff>
              <aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Richardson Centre for Functional Foods and Nutraceuticals (RCFFN), University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Canada</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to BL (e-mail: <email>benoit.lamarche@fsaa.ulaval.ca</email>).</corresp>
                <fn id="afn1">
                  <p>Author disclosures: D Brassard, BJA, MB, D Bernic, MT-G, and EL, no conflicts of interest. DT received funding in the last 5 years from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, the Fondation du Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Québec—Université Laval, and the Green Fund of the Government of Québec. AT serves on the Yogurt in Nutrition Initiative for Health Advisory Board for Danone Institute International and on the board of the Danone Institute of Canada. His research has been funded, in part, by Dairy Farmers of Canada, the National Dairy Council of the United States, Wyeth Consumer Healthcare, and Nestlé. BA holds a junior scholar award from the Fonds de recherche du Québec: Santé. In the past 5 years, he has received funding from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Fondation de l'IUCPQ, the Banting Research Foundation, Diabète Québec, Merck, Pfizer, and Ionis. PJHJ has received funding in the past from the DFC, Danone, Inc., and Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada. PJHJ also reports having received grants from Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada (Growing Forward program supported by the DFC, Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, and Dow Agrosciences), from Advanced Foods and Materials Network, Danone, Enzymotec, Unilever, the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, and Canada Research Chair Endowment of the Federal Government of Canada. PC received funding in the last 5 years from the Canadian Institutes for Health Research, Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada (Growing Forward program supported by the DFC, Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, and Dow Agrosciences), National Dairy Council, Dairy Australia, Danone Institute, Merck Frosst, Pfizer, Amgen, Sanofi, Kaneka Corporation, and Atrium Innovations. BL is Chair of Nutrition at Laval University, which is supported by private endowments from Pfizer, La Banque Royale du Canada, and Provigo-Loblaws. BL has received funding in the last 5 years from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, Dairy Cluster Initiative (Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, the DFC, the Canadian Dairy Network, and the Canadian Dairy Commission), Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, Dow Agrosciences, National Dairy Council, Dairy Australia, Merck Frosst, Pfizer, and Atrium Innovations. BL is an Advisory Board member of the Canadian Nutrition Society, the Conseil pour les initiatives de progrès en alimentation, and has served as Advisory Expert for the Saturated Fat panel of the Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada. BL has received honoraria from the International Chair on Cardiometabolic Risk, DFC, and the World Dairy Platform as an invited speaker at various conferences.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-04-11">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
              <!-- oupReleaseDelayRemoved from OA Article (10.1093/jn/nxy014nxy014Nutrition and DiseaseSaturated Fats from Butter but Not from Cheese Increase HDL-Mediated Cholesterol Efflux Capacity from J774 Macrophages in Men and Women with Abdominal ObesityBrassardDidierArsenaultBeno&#x000ee;t JBoyerMarjorieBernicDanielaTessier-GrenierMaudeTalbotDenisTremblayAngeloLevyEmileAsztalosBelaJonesPeter JHCouturePatrickLamarcheBeno&#x000ee;tbenoit.lamarche@fsaa.ulaval.caInstitute of Nutrition and Functional Foods (INAF), School of Nutrition, Centre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Qu&#x000e9;bec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaSchool of Nutrition, Centre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Qu&#x000e9;bec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaCentre de recherche de l'Institut universitaire de cardiologie et de pneumologie de Qu&#x000e9;bec (CRIUCPQ) and Department of Medicine, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaDepartment of Social and Preventive Medicine, CHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaCHU de Quebec Research Center, and Department of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaDepartment of Kinesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Laval University, Quebec, CanadaCHU Sainte-Justine Research Center, Montr&#x000e9;al, CanadaCardiovascular Nutrition Laboratory, Human Nutrition Research Center on Aging, Tufts University, Boston, MARichardson Centre for Functional Foods and Nutraceuticals (RCFFN), University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, CanadaAddress correspondence to BL (e-mail: benoit.lamarche@fsaa.ulaval.ca).Author disclosures: D Brassard, BJA, MB, D Bernic, MT-G, and EL, no conflicts of interest. DT received funding in the last 5 years from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, the Fondation du Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Qu&#x000e9;bec&#x02014;Universit&#x000e9; Laval, and the Green Fund of the Government of Qu&#x000e9;bec. AT serves on the Yogurt in Nutrition Initiative for Health Advisory Board for Danone Institute International and on the board of the Danone Institute of Canada. His research has been funded, in part, by Dairy Farmers of Canada, the National Dairy Council of the United States, Wyeth Consumer Healthcare, and Nestl&#x000e9;. BA holds a junior scholar award from the Fonds de recherche du Qu&#x000e9;bec: Sant&#x000e9;. In the past 5 years, he has received funding from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Fondation de l'IUCPQ, the Banting Research Foundation, Diab&#x000e8;te Qu&#x000e9;bec, Merck, Pfizer, and Ionis. PJHJ has received funding in the past from the DFC, Danone, Inc., and Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada. PJHJ also reports having received grants from Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada (Growing Forward program supported by the DFC, Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, and Dow Agrosciences), from Advanced Foods and Materials Network, Danone, Enzymotec, Unilever, the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, and Canada Research Chair Endowment of the Federal Government of Canada. PC received funding in the last 5 years from the Canadian Institutes for Health Research, Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada (Growing Forward program supported by the DFC, Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, and Dow Agrosciences), National Dairy Council, Dairy Australia, Danone Institute, Merck Frosst, Pfizer, Amgen, Sanofi, Kaneka Corporation, and Atrium Innovations. BL is Chair of Nutrition at Laval University, which is supported by private endowments from Pfizer, La Banque Royale du Canada, and Provigo-Loblaws. BL has received funding in the last 5 years from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, Dairy Cluster Initiative (Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, the DFC, the Canadian Dairy Network, and the Canadian Dairy Commission), Canola Council of Canada, Flax Council of Canada, Dow Agrosciences, National Dairy Council, Dairy Australia, Merck Frosst, Pfizer, and Atrium Innovations. BL is an Advisory Board member of the Canadian Nutrition Society, the Conseil pour les initiatives de progr&#x000e8;s en alimentation, and has served as Advisory Expert for the Saturated Fat panel of the Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada. BL has received honoraria from the International Chair on Cardiometabolic Risk, DFC, and the World Dairy Platform as an invited speaker at various conferences.04201801042018110420181484573580Supplemental data070920171310201716012018&#x000a9; 2018 American Society for Nutrition.2018This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.comAbstractBackgroundRecent evidence suggests that the association between dietary saturated fatty acids (SFAs) and coronary artery disease risk varies according to food sources. How SFAs from butter and cheese influence HDL-mediated cholesterol efflux capacity (CEC), a key process in reverse cholesterol transport, is currently unknown.ObjectiveIn a predefined secondary analysis of a previously published trial, we have examined how diets rich in SFAs from either cheese or butter influence HDL-mediated CEC, compared with diets rich in either monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) or polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs).MethodsIn a randomized crossover controlled consumption trial, 46 men and women with abdominal obesity consumed 5 isocaloric diets, each for 4 wk. Two diets were rich in SFAs either from cheese (CHEESE) or butter (BUTTER) [12.4&#x02013;12.6% of energy (%E) as SFAs, 32%E as fat, 52%E as carbohydrates]. In 2 other diets, SFAs (5.8%E) were replaced with either MUFAs from refined olive oil (MUFA) or PUFAs from corn oil (PUFA). Finally, a lower fat and carbohydrate diet was used as a control (5.8%E as SFAs, 25.0%E as fat, 59%E as carbohydrates; CHO). Post-diet HDL-mediated CEC was determined ex vivo using radiolabelled J774 macrophages incubated with apolipoprotein B&#x02013;depleted serum from the participants.ResultsMean (&#x000b1;SD) age was 41.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.2 y, and waist circumference was 107.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.5 cm in men and 94.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.4 cm in women. BUTTER and MUFA increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with CHEESE (+4.3%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.026 and +4.7%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.031, respectively). Exploring the significant diet &#x000d7; sex interaction (P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.044) revealed that the increase in HDL-mediated CEC after BUTTER compared with CHEESE was significant among men (+6.0%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.047) but not women (+2.9%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.19), whereas the increase after MUFA compared with CHEESE was significant among women (+9.1%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.008) but not men (&#x02013;0.6%, P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.99).ConclusionThese results provide evidence of a food matrix effect modulating the impact of dairy SFAs on HDL-mediated CEC with potential sex-related differences that deserve further investigation. This trial was registered at clinicaltrials.gov as NCT02106208.high-density lipoproteinsdietdairycheesebuttersaturated fatty acidsmonounsaturated fatty acidspolyunsaturated fatty acidscholesterol efflux capacityJ774 macrophagesNIH10.13039/100000002) -->
              <volume>148</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>573</fpage>
              <lpage>580</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>07</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2018 American Society for Nutrition.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="nxy014.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="abs1">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>Recent evidence suggests that the association between dietary saturated fatty acids (SFAs) and coronary artery disease risk varies according to food sources. How SFAs from butter and cheese influence HDL-mediated cholesterol efflux capacity (CEC), a key process in reverse cholesterol transport, is currently unknown.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="abs2">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>In a predefined secondary analysis of a previously published trial, we have examined how diets rich in SFAs from either cheese or butter influence HDL-mediated CEC, compared with diets rich in either monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) or polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="abs3">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>In a randomized crossover controlled consumption trial, 46 men and women with abdominal obesity consumed 5 isocaloric diets, each for 4 wk. Two diets were rich in SFAs either from cheese (CHEESE) or butter (BUTTER) [12.4–12.6% of energy (%E) as SFAs, 32%E as fat, 52%E as carbohydrates]. In 2 other diets, SFAs (5.8%E) were replaced with either MUFAs from refined olive oil (MUFA) or PUFAs from corn oil (PUFA). Finally, a lower fat and carbohydrate diet was used as a control (5.8%E as SFAs, 25.0%E as fat, 59%E as carbohydrates; CHO). Post-diet HDL-mediated CEC was determined ex vivo using radiolabelled J774 macrophages incubated with apolipoprotein B–depleted serum from the participants.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="abs4">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Mean (±SD) age was 41.4 ± 14.2 y, and waist circumference was 107.6 ± 11.5 cm in men and 94.3 ± 12.4 cm in women. BUTTER and MUFA increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with CHEESE (+4.3%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.026 and +4.7%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.031, respectively). Exploring the significant diet × sex interaction (<italic>P </italic>= 0.044) revealed that the increase in HDL-mediated CEC after BUTTER compared with CHEESE was significant among men (+6.0%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.047) but not women (+2.9%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.19), whereas the increase after MUFA compared with CHEESE was significant among women (+9.1%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.008) but not men (–0.6%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.99).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="abs5">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>These results provide evidence of a food matrix effect modulating the impact of dairy SFAs on HDL-mediated CEC with potential sex-related differences that deserve further investigation. This trial was registered at clinicaltrials.gov as NCT02106208.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="keywords">
                <kwd>high-density lipoproteins</kwd>
                <kwd>diet</kwd>
                <kwd>dairy</kwd>
                <kwd>cheese</kwd>
                <kwd>butter</kwd>
                <kwd>saturated fatty acids</kwd>
                <kwd>monounsaturated fatty acids</kwd>
                <kwd>polyunsaturated fatty acids</kwd>
                <kwd>cholesterol efflux capacity</kwd>
                <kwd>J774 macrophages</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>NIH</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                    <?release-delay 12|0?>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="8"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The association between dietary SFAs and the risk of coronary artery disease (CAD) has become controversial over the years (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Epidemiologic studies have suggested that the association between SFAs and CAD risk varies according to food source (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), with high dairy SFA intake being associated with a lower risk of CAD. Accordingly, results from our group (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and others (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) have shown that the LDL-cholesterol-raising effect of SFAs is attenuated when their food source is cheese rather than butter. Previous investigations about dairy SFAs have focused primarily on their LDL-cholesterol-raising effects. However, SFAs also increase serum HDL-cholesterol concentrations when substituted for carbohydrates (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The extent to which such an increase in HDL-cholesterol concentrations with SFAs relates to longer-term CAD risk is unclear.</p>
              <p>Indeed, the association between HDL-cholesterol and CAD risk has also become contentious. While epidemiologic studies have shown that higher HDL-cholesterol concentrations are almost invariably associated with a lower risk of CAD (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), data from Mendelian randomization studies suggest that low HDL-cholesterol is not causal in the etiology of CAD (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Large clinical trials showing failure of HDL-cholesterol-raising drugs to reduce CAD risk further support the notion that HDL-cholesterol may not be a causal risk factor for CAD (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). It is stressed that the cholesterol content of HDLs represents only 1 of numerous features of these lipoproteins, and may only poorly reflect HDL functional properties. In this regard, it is well established that HDLs play an important role in the reverse cholesterol transport process by promoting cholesterol efflux from cholesterol-loaded cells (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Studies have suggested that HDL-mediated cholesterol efflux capacity (CEC) is inversely associated with the risk of CAD (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), although this has not been a unanimous finding (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p>
              <p>To the best of our knowledge, no study has yet assessed the impact of different dietary fats and dairy SFAs from different foods on HDL-mediated CEC measured ex vivo. How the food source modifies the effect of SFAs on HDL physical and functional characteristics is also unknown.</p>
              <p>This randomized, fully controlled consumption trial was designed (1) to compare the effect of diets rich in SFAs from either cheese or butter on HDL-mediated CEC and several physico-chemical features of HDL and (2) to assess how diets rich in SFAs from butter and cheese influence these study outcomes compared with diets rich in monounsaturated (MUFAs) or in polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs). We hypothesized that consumption of SFAs increases HDL-mediated CEC and that the magnitude of these effects varies according to the SFA food source.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Study design and population</title>
                <p>This paper presents secondary analyses of a study for which methods have been detailed elsewhere (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Briefly, 92 men and women completed ≥1 dietary phase of this multicenter randomized crossover controlled consumption trial. To be eligible, participants had to be 18–65 years old and to have a waist circumference ≥94 cm and ≥80 cm for men and women, respectively. Participants also had to have HDL-cholesterol concentrations below an age- and sex-specific 75th percentile value (≤1.34 mmol/L and ≤1.53 mmol/L for men and women, respectively) in order to exclude individuals with high HDL-cholesterol concentrations, which was the primary outcome of the original study. Participants were otherwise healthy, had no history of cardiovascular disease, type 2 diabetes, or monogenic dyslipidemia, and did not use lipid-lowering, anti-diabetic, or anti-inflammatory medications. A subsample of 46 subjects from 1 of the participating centers (Institute of Nutrition and Functional Foods in Québec City) who had completed at least the carbohydrate and the cheese diets were included in this sub-study (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplemental Figure 1</xref></bold>). Their screening characteristics were similar to those of the original study (data not shown). This protocol is registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">http://www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> (NCT02106208).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Diets</title>
                <p>The dietary intervention consisted of 5 isocaloric diets allocated in random order. Dietetic technicians prepared all recipes and meals in the metabolic kitchen of the Institute of Nutrition and Functional Foods. Diets were provided under isoenergetic conditions to maintain a constant body weight. As indicated previously (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), energy (E) levels at baseline were estimated using validated equations and with the use of a quantitative web-based food-frequency questionnaire completed before the beginning of the first dietary phase.</p>
                <p>Detailed nutritional composition of the experimental diets consumed by participants in this controlled feeding study is shown in <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplemental Table 1</xref></bold>. Two diets were rich in SFAs from either cheese (CHEESE) or butter (BUTTER) (12.4–12.6%E as SFAs, 32%E as fat, 52%E as carbohydrates). In the other 2 higher-fat diets, SFAs (5.8%E) were replaced by MUFAs (MUFA) or PUFAs (PUFA). The grams of fat from cheese in CHEESE were replaced by corresponding amounts of butter fat, refined olive oil, and corn oil in BUTTER, MUFA, and PUFA, respectively. The fifth diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrate was used as a control reference diet (5.8%E as SFAs, 25.0%E as fat, 59%E as carbohydrates; CHO). Total energy, protein, dietary cholesterol, fiber, and sodium were matched across diets. CHEESE was higher in calcium and potassium than all other diets.</p>
                <p>Each diet lasted 4 weeks with a minimum washout of 4 weeks between diets. Previous studies have shown that 4 weeks of diet supplementation and of washout are sufficient to maximize effects on the HDL pool (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Alcohol consumption was forbidden to participants 48 h before and during all dietary phases. Compliance to treatments was assessed by checklists filled out by participants on a weekly basis, which allowed the identification of foods that were consumed and foods not consumed. Checklists provided information on beverage intake as well as on current medication. Participants were asked to notify the coordinator in charge of the project before starting any new medication.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>Blood sampling</title>
                <p>Blood samples were taken from the antecubital vein at the beginning and end of each diet after a 12-h fast. Most analyses in the present study were performed on samples taken at the end of each treatment phase. All laboratory analyses were carried out by staff blinded to study treatments.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>HDL isolation</title>
                <p>HDLs were isolated by sequential ultracentrifugation of fresh and whole plasma (5 mL) at consecutive densities (<italic>d</italic>) of 1.063 g/mL for 22 h and 1.21 g/mL for 24 h at 312,200 × <italic>g</italic> at 4°C in a Beckman 50.4 Ti rotor (Beckman Instruments Inc., Missisauga, Ontario, Canada) and then dialyzed overnight at 4°C in a buffer containing 0.15 M NaCl, 0.01 M Tris-base, 0.01% EDTA, and 0.03 mM NaN<sub>3</sub> (pH 8.0). Isolated HDLs were rapidly frozen at –80°C until use.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5">
                <title>HDL composition and apoA-I</title>
                <p>Fatty acid composition in the isolated HDL fraction was assessed as described previously (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Serum HDL-cholesterol concentration was assessed on a Roche/Hitachi Modular system (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany) according to the manufacturer's specifications and using proprietary reagents. Serum LDL-cholesterol concentrations were estimated using the Friedewald equation. Plasma apoA-I concentrations were measured with the use of the DuoSet ELISA (R&amp;D Systems #DY3664-05; (Minneapolis, MN).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-6">
                <title>Mean HDL size and HDL subclasses</title>
                <p>Mean HDL size and HDL subclasses were measured by nondenaturing 4–30% polyacrylamide gradient gel electrophoresis and image analysis as previously described (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Plasma concentrations of apoA-I–containing HDL subclasses were measured by 2-dimensional nondenaturing agarose-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, immunoblotting, and image analysis (Tufts University) as described previously (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-7">
                <title>CEC</title>
                <p>Ex vivo CEC was assessed using serum samples stored at –80°C immediately after sampling and taken specifically for that purpose. Serum samples were first depleted of apoB using 40% polyethylene glycol-6000. In that context, CEC is considered to be mediated primarily by HDL (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The J774 macrophages used in this experiment were cultured in basal condition in the absence of cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP). Hence, HDL-mediated CEC reflects total efflux from ATP-binding cassette transporter 1 (ABCA1), scavenger receptor class B type 1 (SR-B1), and non-receptor dependent efflux (aqueous diffusion) (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). J774 macrophages were plated and incubated in Roswell Park Memorial Institute media containing 1% bovine growth serum and 2 µCi of 3H-cholesterol/mL for 24 h. Cells were then equilibrated for 16–18 h in media containing 0.2% endotoxin-free, low free fatty acids bovine serum albumin. Subsequently, cells were incubated with efflux medium containing 2.8% apoB-depleted serum of study participants for 4 h. Media were then collected and cells were harvested in 0.5 N NaOH. Liquid scintillation counting was used to measure the efflux of radiolabelled 3H-cholesterol from the cells. HDL-mediated CEC was calculated by the following formula: [cpm in media/(cpm in media + cpm in cell lysates)]. HDL-mediated CEC was also measured in serum-free media. The latter was subtracted from HDL-mediated CEC using sera from the study participants. A control sample of pooled plasma from healthy volunteers was used as an internal standard in each assay to normalize values across batches. All measurements were performed in triplicates and all samples from 1 individual were tested on the same plate. CVs for each assay were calculated. Triplicates with CV greater than 20% were further examined. Within a triplicate, a single measure that digressed by &gt;15% from the mean of the other 2 measures was considered as an outlier and was discarded. The mean of the 3 measures was used in the analysis when the CV within the triplicate could not be ascribed to 1 single measure. Mean intra-assay CV based on triplicates was 10.2 ± 9.3% and 8.0 ± 4.6% before and after removal of outliers, respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-8">
                <title>Sample size calculations and statistical analyses</title>
                <p>Based on data from de Vries et al. (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), we had estimated that a sample size of 50 would detect a 2.2% difference in HDL-mediated CEC between diets, the primary outcome of this study, assuming a mean baseline CEC value of 16% and an SD of 3.6%. Based on preliminary analyses, we found that the SD of the HDL-mediated CEC was lower than anticipated. We therefore used samples from only 1 center (<italic>n</italic> = 46 participants) of the original study to assess the impact of the various diets on HDL-mediated CEC.</p>
                <p>As indicated earlier, the primary objective of this study was to assess how different sources of SFAs influence HDL-mediated CEC compared with other dietary fats. In this context, CHO was used as a reference, control diet in the analyses. Changes in study outcomes with each of the 4 high-fat diets versus CHO were compared among themselves using mixed models for repeated measures in SAS (v9.4, Cary, NC). Pairwise comparisons of the 4 high-fat diets were considered only when the overall <italic>P</italic> for the main treatment effect in the mixed models was &lt;0.05. Treatment, sex, treatment × sex, sequence of treatments, age, and BMI or waist circumference were defined as fixed effects and subjects as the random effect. The analysis of the treatment × sex interaction was predetermined in our analytic plan. Using a most parsimonious modeling approach, potential confounders of the changes in outcome measures with treatment were included in the final mixed models only when they were found to be significant at <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. The Holm–Bonferroni procedure was used to adjust for multiple comparisons of the high-fat diets (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), as previously described (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The multiple comparisons under consideration were defined a priori to reflect the study objectives: CHEESE compared with BUTTER; MUFA, PUFA, and BUTTER compared with MUFA and PUFA. The MUFA and PUFA comparisons were not considered because they were not part of the primary aim of this analysis. Although not part of the study objectives per se, the statistical comparison of the high-fat diets with CHO was directly provided by the least squares means (LSMEANS) statement in the mixed model. Characteristics of men and women at screening and self-reported compliance during the intervention were compared using 2-sided Student’s <italic>t</italic> tests and Wilcoxon’s Signed Rank test, respectively. Spearman rank correlation coefficients were calculated between variation (compared with CHO) in serum lipids and variation (compared with CHO) in HDL-mediated CEC. The normality in the distribution of residual of all study outcome models was considered and BMI, TG, fasting blood glucose, HDL-mediated CEC, and HDL-TG were log-transformed.</p>
                <table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Screening characteristics of the 46 men and women<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb1fn1">1</xref></sup></p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (<italic>n </italic>= 21)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (<italic>n </italic>= 25)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postmenopausal women, % (<italic>n</italic>)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0 (9)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Ethnicity, % (<italic>n</italic>)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Caucasian</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (21)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0 (23)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6 ± 13.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0 ± 15.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight, kg</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5 ± 18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.8 ± 16.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb1fn2">2</xref></sup> kg/m<sup>2</sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7 ± 5.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0 ± 6.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference, cm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.6 ± 11.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.3 ± 12.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0005</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Blood pressure, mmHg</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Systolic</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.6 ± 10.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.9 ± 10.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diastolic</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 ± 9.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0 ± 10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Serum lipids, mmol/L</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total C</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.26 ± 1.02</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16 ± 1.06</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LDL-C</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 ± 0.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18 ± 0.84</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HDL-C</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 ± 0.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 ± 0.17</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TGs<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb1fn2">2</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 ± 0.66</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 ± 0.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total C:HDL-C ratio</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79 ± 0.87</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 ± 0.95</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting blood glucose,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb1fn2">2</xref></sup> mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 ± 0.37</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 ± 0.55</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="tb1fn1">
                      <p><sup>1</sup>Values are means ± SDs unless otherwise indicated. <italic>P</italic> values between men and women were determined by a Student's <italic>t</italic> test. C, cholesterol.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="tb1fn2">
                      <p><sup>2</sup>Analyses were performed on log-transformed data.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec3-1">
                <title>Participants’ characteristics</title>
                <p>Screening characteristics of the 46 subjects included in this study are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>. Men and women had HDL-cholesterol concentrations around the 50th percentile of their age group and had large waist circumferences as per the eligibility criteria. Mean ± SD self-reported compliance to the diets was high (99.5 ± 1.1%), with no difference among diets (<italic>P </italic>= 0.69) or between men and women (Wilcoxon’s Signed Rank test <italic>P </italic>= 0.99). There was no difference in mean body weight (<italic>P </italic>= 0.37) or waist circumference (<italic>P </italic>= 0.11) among treatments (data not shown).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3-2">
                <title>HDL cholesterol, size, and subclasses</title>
                <p><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table"><bold>Table 2</bold></xref> shows the changes in serum HDL-cholesterol concentration, HDL size, and HDL subclass distribution after CHEESE, BUTTER, MUFA, and PUFA relative to CHO. No significant differences were observed in HDL-cholesterol concentrations after consumption of the 4 high-fat diets, which all resulted in similar increases in HDL-cholesterol concentrations compared with CHO (all <italic>P</italic> values &lt;0.01). BUTTER, MUFA, and PUFA similarly increased apoA-I compared with CHEESE (all <italic>P</italic> values &lt;0.01). CHEESE, BUTTER, and PUFA had relatively similar effects on HDL particle size distribution. Compared with CHO, CHEESE increased the proportion of HDL<sub>2b</sub> (<italic>P </italic>= 0.019) and reduced the proportion of HDL<sub>3b</sub> (<italic>P </italic>= 0.004), while BUTTER increased total HDL<sub>2</sub> and HDL<sub>2b</sub> (<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05) and decreased total HDL<sub>3</sub>, HDL<sub>3a</sub>, and HDL<sub>3b</sub> (<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05). Some of these changes with BUTTER were also significant compared with MUFA.</p>
                <table-wrap id="tbl2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Changes in endpoint HDL characteristics after consuming the 4 high-fat diets compared with CHO (reference diet) in men and women with abdominal obesity<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">1</xref></sup></p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">∆ vs. CHO</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHO (<italic>n </italic>= 46)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHEESE (<italic>n </italic>= 46)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUTTER (<italic>n </italic>= 44)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MUFA (<italic>n </italic>= 44)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PUFA (<italic>n </italic>= 43)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P</italic>
                          <sup>
                            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn2">2</xref>
                          </sup>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-C, mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 ± 0.18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 ± 0.10<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 ± 0.09<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 ± 0.09<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.10<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ApoA-I, mg/mL</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 ± 0.25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02 ± 0.18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 ± 0.19<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 ± 0.19<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.21<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL size, nm</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.35 ± 0.36</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 ± 0.20</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 ± 0.17</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 ± 0.21<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">1-dimensional gradient gel electrophoresis subclasses, %</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HDL<sub>2</sub> (total)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1 ± 9.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 ± 2.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 ± 4.5<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 ± 4.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 ± 4.7<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  HDL<sub>2b</sub></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5 ± 8.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 ± 2.3<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 ± 4.6<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 ± 3.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 ± 4.4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  HDL<sub>2a</sub></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7 ± 2.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.2 ± 1.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6 ± 1.4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4 ± 1.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4 ± 1.3<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HDL<sub>3</sub> (total)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9 ± 9.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4 ± 2.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9 ± 4.5<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.5 ± 4.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2 ± 4.7<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  HDL<sub>3a</sub></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 ± 2.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7 ± 1.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 ± 1.6<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7 ± 1.5<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  HDL<sub>3b</sub></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 ± 2.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6 ± 0.9<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6 ± 1.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 ± 1.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">c</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6 ± 1.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  HDL<sub>3c</sub></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 ± 6.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4 ± 1.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6 ± 2.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4 ± 2.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9 ± 2.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">2-dimensional gel electrophoresis subclasses, mg ApoA-I/mL</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-β-1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 ± 2.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 ± 1.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 2.6<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 ± 2.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 2.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-β-2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 ± 1.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 ± 0.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 ± 1.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> α-1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3 ± 6.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 3.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 ± 4.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 4.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 ± 4.4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> α-2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1 ± 10.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9 ± 7.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 ± 9.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 ± 8.7<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 ± 9.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> α-3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 ± 5.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3 ± 5.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 4.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 ± 4.6<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 ± 4.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> α-4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6 ± 4.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.2 ± 3.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 ± 3.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 ± 4.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 ± 4.0<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-α-1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 ± 2.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 ± 1.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 1.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 ± 1.1<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 1.3<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-α-2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 ± 2.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.2 ± 1.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 ± 1.5<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 ± 1.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 1.7<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-α-3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.3 ± 0.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.7<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.5<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 ± 0.8<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pre-α-4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 ± 0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1 ± 0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.4<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb2fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="tb2fn1">
                      <p><sup>1</sup>Values are expressed as means ± SDs. Number of participants for apoA-I and 2-dimensional gel electrophoresis subclasses were 42 for all diets. <sup>a</sup>Significantly different from CHO, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. <sup>b</sup>Significantly different from CHEESE, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. <sup>c</sup>Significantly different from BUTTER, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. BUTTER, diet rich in SFAs from butter; CHEESE, diet rich in SFAs from cheese; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrates; HDL-C, HDL cholesterol; MUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by MUFAs; PUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by PUFAs; ∆, change.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="tb2fn2">
                      <p><sup>2</sup><italic>P</italic> values are for the main treatment effects in mixed models, comparing the effects of the 4 high-fat diets among themselves. As indicated in the Methods section, values after CHO were used as reference in the analyses. Pairwise comparisons of the high-fat diets were examined only when the <italic>P</italic> value of the main treatment effect was &lt;0.05. Covariates (baseline values of the selected variable when available, sequence, sex, age, BMI or waist circumference) were included in the mixed models only when they were shown to be significant at <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. The MUFA and PUFA diets were not compared specifically because they were not part of the primary objectives of the study (see Methods).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap id="tbl3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Changes in endpoint serum lipid and apoB concentrations after consuming the 4 high-fat diets compared with CHO (reference diet) in men and women with abdominal obesity<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">1</xref></sup></p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">∆ vs. CHO</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHO (<italic>n </italic>= 46)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHEESE (<italic>n </italic>= 46)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUTTER (<italic>n </italic>= 44)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MUFA (<italic>n </italic>= 43)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PUFA (<italic>n </italic>= 43)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>P</italic>
                          <sup>
                            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn2">2</xref>
                          </sup>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol, mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87 ± 0.95</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 ± 0.35<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 ± 0.33<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05 ± 0.42<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18 ± 0.46<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol, mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09 ± 0.81</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 ± 0.33<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 ± 0.30<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07 ± 0.33<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16 ± 0.39<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ApoB, g/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 ± 0.46</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 ± 0.25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 ± 0.26<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 ± 0.24<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11 ± 0.24<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGs,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn3">3</xref></sup> mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 ± 0.58</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 ± 0.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07 ± 0.37<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10 ± 0.36<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19 ± 0.28<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-HDL cholesterol, mmol/L</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78 ± 0.93</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 ± 0.32<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.33<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11 ± 0.39<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.24 ± 0.42<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tb3fn1">c</xref></sup></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="tb3fn1">
                      <p><sup>1</sup>Values are means ± SDs. These are data of a subset of participants from a larger trial. Serum lipid data of all participants in the trial have been published elsewhere (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). <sup>a</sup>Significantly different from CHO, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. <sup>b</sup>Significantly different from CHEESE, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. <sup>c</sup>Significantly different from BUTTER, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. BUTTER, diet rich in SFAs from butter; CHEESE, diet rich in SFAs from cheese; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrate; MUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by MUFAs; PUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by PUFAs; ∆, change.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="tb3fn2">
                      <p><sup>2</sup><italic>P</italic> values are for the main treatment effects in mixed models, comparing the effects of the 4 high-fat diets among themselves. As indicated in the Methods section, values after CHO were used as reference in the analyses. Pairwise comparisons of the high-fat diets were examined only when the <italic>P</italic> value of the main treatment effect was &lt;0.05. Covariates (sex, age, sequence, BMI or waist circumference) were included in the mixed models only when they were shown to be significant at <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. MUFA and PUFA were not compared specifically because they were not part of the primary objectives of the study (see Methods).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="tb3fn3">
                      <p><sup>3</sup>Analyses were performed on log-transformed data.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>The 2-dimensional gel electrophoresis characterization of HDL showed that BUTTER increased the concentration of all α HDLs compared with CHEESE (all <italic>P</italic> values &lt;0.05). The MUFA diet also increased the concentration of α-2, α-3, and α-4 HDLs compared with CHEESE (all <italic>P</italic> values &lt;0.03). BUTTER but not CHEESE increased the proportion of pre-β-1 and pre-β-2 HDLs compared with CHO (both <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.02).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3-3">
                <title>HDL composition</title>
                <p>CHEESE, BUTTER, MUFA, and PUFA had similar effects on the TGs, free cholesterol, cholesteryl esters, phospholipids, or total protein content of HDLs (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplemental Table 2</xref></bold>). BUTTER and PUFA slightly decreased TGs in HDLs compared with CHO (both <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3-4">
                <title>HDL-mediated CEC</title>
                <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>, there was a significant difference among the 4 high-fat diets on HDL-mediated CEC (<italic>P </italic>= 0.029). Specifically, BUTTER (+4.3%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.026) and MUFA (+4.7%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.031) increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with CHEESE, while the variation in HDL-mediated CEC after PUFA was not statistically different from the other high-fat diets. BUTTER (+3.3%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.043) and MUFA (+3.8%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.048) also significantly increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with CHO, which was not the case for CHEESE and PUFA. The pre-specified test for a diet × sex interaction on HDL-mediated CEC was significant (<italic>P </italic>= 0.044, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). The increase in HDL-mediated CEC after BUTTER compared with CHEESE was significant among men (+6.0%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.047) but not women (+2.9%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.19), while the increase after MUFA compared with CHEESE was significant among women (+9.1%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.008) but not men (–0.6%, <italic>P </italic>= 0.99).</p>
                <fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>FIGURE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Change in endpoint HDL-mediated CEC measured in J774 macrophages after consuming the 4 high-fat diets compared with CHO (reference diet) in men and women with abdominal obesity. Results are expressed as the post-intervention mean (±SEM) HDL-mediated CEC differences between CHEESE, BUTTER, MUFA, or PUFA and CHO. Analyses were performed on log-transformed data. <italic>n </italic>= 46 (CHEESE, CHO), <italic>n </italic>= 44 (BUTTER, MUFA), <italic>n </italic>= 43 (PUFA). *Significantly different from CHO, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. #Significantly different from CHEESE, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. BUTTER, diet rich in SFAs from butter; CEC, cholesterol efflux capacity; CHEESE, diet rich in SFAs from cheese; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrates; MUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by MUFAs; PUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by PUFAs; tx, treatment.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="nxy014fig1"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>FIGURE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Change in endpoint HDL-mediated CEC measured in J774 macrophages after consuming the 4 high-fat diets compared with CHO (reference diet) in men (A) and women (B) with abdominal obesity. Results are expressed as the post-intervention mean (±SEM) HDL-mediated CEC differences between CHEESE, BUTTER, MUFA, or PUFA and CHO in men (<italic>n </italic>= 21) and women (<italic>n </italic>= 25). Analyses were performed on log-transformed data. <italic>P</italic>-treatment by sex interaction = 0.044 (mixed model). *Significantly different from CHO, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. #Significantly different from CHEESE, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. †Significantly different from PUFA, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. BUTTER, diet rich in SFAs from butter; CEC, cholesterol efflux capacity; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrates; MUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by MUFAs; PUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by PUFAs; tx, treatment.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="nxy014fig2"/>
                </fig>
                <p>As shown previously, BUTTER increased serum LDL-cholesterol concentrations compared with the other diets in the entire sample of participants (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and also in this sample except when compared to CHEESE (<italic>P </italic>= 0.066, <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). The increase in LDL-cholesterol after BUTTER (compared with CHO) was significantly correlated with the concurrent increase in HDL-mediated CEC in men (<italic>r</italic> = 0.45, <italic>P </italic>= 0.048), but not in women (<italic>r</italic> = 0.27, <italic>P </italic>= 0.20, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3"><bold>Figure 3</bold></xref><bold>A, B</bold>). Finally, variations (compared with CHO) in HDL-cholesterol, apoA-I, and apoB after BUTTER or CHEESE were not correlated with concurrent variations in HDL-mediated CEC in men, women, or in both groups combined (data not shown).</p>
                <fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>FIGURE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Spearman rank correlation coefficients between the changes in HDL-mediated CEC from J774 macrophages and concurrent changes in LDL cholesterol (SFAs from butter compared with CHO) in men (A) (<italic>n </italic>= 20) and women (B) (<italic>n </italic>= 24). Correlation was significant in men (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> = 0.45, <italic>P </italic>= 0.048) but not in women (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> = 0.27, <italic>P </italic>= 0.20). CEC, cholesterol efflux capacity; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrate; LDL-C, LDL cholesterol; ∆, change.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="nxy014fig3"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the largest controlled consumption trial to date examining the effects of different dietary fats on HDL-mediated CEC. Moreover, it is the first time that the impact of SFAs from 2 dairy sources, namely butter and cheese, on this important HDL function is compared. The diet rich in SFAs from butter significantly increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with SFAs from cheese. Consumption of MUFAs also increased HDL-mediated CEC, while PUFAs had no effect. Finally, data suggested a sex dimorphism in the HDL-mediated CEC response to dietary fat, with men being more responsive to SFAs from butter and women being more responsive to MUFAs.</p>
              <p>Cheese consumption has not been associated with an increased risk of CAD in epidemiologic studies (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), despite the fact that cheese is an important source of dietary SFAs and sodium (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The neutral effect of SFAs from cheese on HDL-mediated CEC as well as on LDL-cholesterol concentrations (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) is consistent with the absence of an association between cheese consumption and CAD risk. On the other hand, SFAs from butter significantly increased HDL-mediated CEC compared with the same amount of SFAs consumed as cheese and also compared with CHO. This is consistent with the emerging concept that the food matrix may modify the impact of SFAs on cardiometabolic outcomes (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). As indicated earlier, results of several trials (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and from our group (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) have shown an attenuation of the LDL-cholesterol-raising effects of SFAs when the latter are consumed as cheese rather than as butter.</p>
              <p>Cholesterol derivatives, such as oxysterols, have been shown to upregulate ABCA1 expression through activation of the nuclear liver X receptor and retinoid X receptor (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Higher circulating LDL-cholesterol (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and, possibly, cholesterol derivatives (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) seen after consumption of SFAs from butter may stimulate ABCA1 expression in various tissues, which in turn results in increased efficiency of HDL interacting with this receptor given the crucial role of ABCA1 in HDL biogenesis (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Interestingly, the significant correlation between increased LDL-cholesterol and increased HDL-mediated CEC after consumption of SFAs from butter is consistent with such a compensatory mechanism. A recent meta-analysis of epidemiologic studies has shown relatively small or neutral associations between butter consumption and risk of mortality, cardiovascular disease, and diabetes (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Moreover, consumption of SFAs from butter increased the concentrations of large HDL particles in the present study (HDL<sub>2b</sub> or α-1 and α-2), which in turn has been associated with increased HDL-mediated CEC via the SR-B1 pathway (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The extent to which a compensatory increase in HDL-mediated CEC contributes to attenuate the effects on risk of LDL-cholesterol-raising SFAs from butter is an intriguing hypothesis to pursue.</p>
              <p>Few studies have compared the effects of dietary fats on HDL-mediated CEC. Hernáez et al. (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) investigated HDL-mediated CEC changes from THP-1 human monocyte-derived macrophages after 1 year on a traditional Mediterranean diet rich in either virgin olive oil or walnut or a low-fat diet in 296 subjects from the PREDIMED (Prevención con Dieta Mediterránea) study. Both supplemented Mediterranean diets similarly increased HDL-mediated CEC relative to baseline values, but not compared to the low-fat diet. In our trial, MUFA, which was rich in refined olive oil, increased HDL-mediated CEC more than CHO and CHEESE. The controlled consumption and crossover nature of our study may have yielded greater capacity to detect the effects of MUFAs on HDL-mediated CEC, compared with PREDIMED.</p>
              <p>Our data also suggested that HDL-mediated CEC in men might be more responsive to changes in dietary SFAs while HDL-mediated CEC in women may be more sensitive to changes in dietary MUFAs. Others have also observed a potential sex dimorphism in the CEC response to dietary fat. Montoya et al. (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) have shown that consumption of diets enriched in n–3 PUFAs or in n–6 PUFAs compared with a diet rich in SFAs from palm oil increased whole serum-mediated CEC from Fu5AH hepatoma cells in women, whereas only n–3 PUFAs increased CEC in men compared with the high-SFA diet. Recent data have shown that pro-inflammatory remodeling of the HDL proteome impairs CEC (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In our trial, men had higher screening waist circumference compared with women (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), which is consistent with greater visceral adipose tissue levels (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and with a higher degree of subclinical inflammation (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The extent to which potential differences in the pro-inflammatory status between men and women may have modulated the HDL-mediated CEC responses to various dietary fats is unclear and merits further consideration in future studies on this topic.</p>
              <p>Cholesterol efflux via the ABCA1 pathway has been associated primarily with smaller HDL particles, notably HDL<sub>3b</sub>, HDL<sub>3c</sub>, and lipid-poor apoA-I like pre-β-1 (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In the present study, consumption of SFAs from CHEESE increased the proportion of the large HDL<sub>2b</sub> fraction and reduced the proportion of smaller HDL<sub>3b</sub> compared with CHO, consistent with the lack of change in HDL-mediated CEC. This remodeling of HDL from small to large HDL particles was amplified after consumption of SFAs from BUTTER although concentrations of the smaller pre-β-1 HDL particles were also increased, along with a significant increase in HDL-mediated CEC, at least in men. There was no significant correlation between the change in HDL particle distribution after BUTTER and the change in HDL-mediated CEC (data not shown). MUFA did not alter HDL subclass distribution compared with CHO, but induced significant increase in HDL-mediated CEC, at least among women. Overall, these results suggest that the pattern of change in HDL subclasses observed via 2-dimensional gel electrophoresis after CHEESE and BUTTER is also consistent with an attenuation of the effect of dairy SFAs by the cheese matrix.</p>
              <p>This study has several strengths, including its controlled consumption conditions and crossover design, according to which multiple diets were examined. The careful statistical handling of HDL-mediated CEC measurements and the relatively larger sample size compared with previously published studies on this topic are also unique elements of this trial. This study was not conducted under metabolic ward conditions, which reduce the risk of noncompliance and deviation from the protocol. However, compliance assessed using checklists was high across all diets, indicating that nearly all foods and caloric drinks provided were consumed. Furthermore, a large proportion (approximately 30–40%) of the prescribed diets was consumed on-site, under supervision of the research staff (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In this context, the risk of deviance and noncompliance is very low, and the effects seen are very likely to be due to the interventions per se. Studies suggest that the capacity of HDL to promote CEC is inversely associated with carotid intima-media thickness, angiographically diagnosed coronary artery disease, and incidence of cardiac events, independent of variations in HDL-cholesterol, but not in pre-β-1 concentrations (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). In these studies, HDL-mediated CEC was assessed using J774 macrophages in which the ABCA1 transporters had been upregulated by cAMP (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Of note, the J774 macrophage cells used in this study were cultured in basal condition, i.e., the ABCA1 transporter was not upregulated with cAMP. Thus, the ex vivo measure of HDL-mediated CEC in the present study reflects the contributions of the ABCA1 transporters as well as of SR-B1 and aqueous diffusion (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Finally, HDL-mediated CEC and overall reverse cholesterol transport are highly complex pathways that are measured ex vivo. The extent to which such measurements reflect in vivo physiology remains to be determined.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, data from this randomized controlled trial suggest that SFAs from butter have a greater influence on ex vivo HDL-mediated CEC and on HDL physical characteristics than SFAs from cheese. This provides further support to the hypothesis that the food matrix modifies the association between SFAs and CAD risk. The increase in HDL-mediated CEC seen with SFAs from butter paralleled the increase in LDL-cholesterol among men, but not among women, which may reflect a sex-dependent compensatory mechanism required for the management of excess cholesterol in the circulation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1">
                <label>Supplemental data</label>
                <media xlink:href="nxy014_supp.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>We thank Steeve Larouche, Christiane Landry, and Johanne Marin at the INAF and Sylvain Pouliot at the CRIUCPQ for their technical assistance on this project.</p>
              <p>The authors’ contributions were as follows—BL, PJHJ, AT, EL, and PC: designed the research and obtained the funding; PC: was responsible for the screening and medical supervision of the study participants; D Brassard and MT-G: contributed in the clinical trial coordination; D Brassard, BJA, and MB: performed the CEC measurements; D Bernic and BA: performed the HDL particle analysis; D Brassard performed statistical analyses; DT: provided advice regarding statistical analyses; D Brassard: wrote the first draft of the manuscript; BL: had primary responsibility for final content; and all authors: critically reviewed the manuscript and provided final approval of the submitted manuscript, had full access to all the data in the study, took responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data in the analysis, and affirmed that the article is an honest, accurate, and transparent account of the study being reported and that no important aspects of the study have been omitted.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes id="nt1">
              <title>Notes</title>
              <p>Supported by grants from the National Dairy Council and the Dairy Research Cluster Initiative [Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, Dairy Farmers of Canada (DFC), the Canadian Dairy Network, and the Canadian Dairy Commission]. Funders were not involved in designing the study, conducting of the study, in collection, management, analysis, or interpretation of the data, or in the preparation and review of the manuscript prior to submission.</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplemental Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplemental Tables 1 and 2</xref> are available from the “<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref>” link in the online posting of the article and from the same link in the online table of contents at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/jn/">https://academic.oup.com/jn/</ext-link>.</p>
              <p>Abbreviations used: ABCA1, ATP-binding cassette transporter 1; BUTTER, diet rich in SFAs from butter; CAD, coronary artery disease; CEC, cholesterol efflux capacity; CHEESE, diet rich in SFAs from cheese; CHO, diet in which SFAs were substituted for by carbohydrate (control reference diet); E, energy; MUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by MUFAs; PUFA, diet in which SFAs were replaced by PUFAs; SR-B1, scavenger receptor class B type 1.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heitmann</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bälter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldbourt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallmans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knekt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Major types of dietary fat and risk of coronary heart disease: a pooled analysis of 11 cohort studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1425</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19211817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siri-Tarino</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies evaluating the association of saturated fat with cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20071648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mozaffarian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Micha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects on coronary heart disease of increasing polyunsaturated fat in place of saturated fat: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1000252</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warnakula</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunutsor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forouhi</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Association of dietary, circulating, and supplement fatty acids with coronary risk: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>398</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24723079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maroleanu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cozma</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishibe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uleryk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budylowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schünemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beyene</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Intake of saturated and trans unsaturated fatty acids and risk of all cause mortality, cardiovascular disease, and type 2 diabetes: systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>351</volume>:<fpage>h3978</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26268692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Otto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mozaffarian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kromhout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nettleton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary intake of saturated fat by food source and incident cardiovascular disease: the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22760560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Praagman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beulens</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alssema</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zock</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanders</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sluijs</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Schouw</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between dietary saturated fatty acids and ischemic heart disease depends on the type and source of fatty acid in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition–Netherlands cohort</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26791181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tessier-Grenier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allaire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajendiran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>She</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramprasath</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gigleux</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Comparison of the impact of SFAs from cheese and butter on cardiometabolic risk factors: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28251937</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Goede</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geleijnse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soedamah-Muthu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of cheese consumption on blood lipids: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26011901</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mensink</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zock</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kester</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary fatty acids and carbohydrates on the ratio of serum total to HDL cholesterol and on serum lipids and apolipoproteins: a meta-analysis of 60 controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1146</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12716665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Probstfield</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neaton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castelli</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knoke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bangdiwala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyroler</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-density lipoprotein cholesterol and cardiovascular disease. Four prospective American studies</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source><year>1989</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2642759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voight</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peloso</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orho-Melander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frikke-Schmidt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbalic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hindy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hólm</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Plasma HDL cholesterol and risk of myocardial infarction: a Mendelian randomisation study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>380</volume>:<fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607825</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballantyne</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barter</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brumm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaitman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holme</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kallend</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Effects of dalcetrapib in patients with a recent acute coronary syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>2089</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23126252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Després</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HDL cholesterol is not HDL—don't judge the book by its cover</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cardiol</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22945326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleheen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Javad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Picataggi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lukmanova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mucksavage</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luben</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billheimer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Association of HDL cholesterol efflux capacity with incident coronary heart disease events: a prospective case-control study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26025389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosior</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Didonato</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Paradoxical association of enhanced cholesterol efflux with increased incident cardiovascular risks</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1696</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23520163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zech</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bronzert</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aamodt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of human apolipoproteins A-I and A-II: compartmental models</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source><year>1983</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6403641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiavaroli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidgen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Josse</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adding monounsaturated fatty acids to a dietary portfolio of cholesterol-lowering foods in hypercholesterolemia</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>182</volume>:<fpage>1961</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21041432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct transesterification of all classes of lipids in a one-step reaction</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source><year>1986</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3958609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérusse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Després</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couillard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method for HDL particle sizing by polyacrylamide gradient gel electrophoresis using whole plasma</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asztalos</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roheim</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of ApoA-I-containing HDL subpopulations in patients with coronary heart disease</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2670</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11116070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-density lipoprotein function measurement in human studies: focus on cholesterol efflux capacity</article-title>. <source>Prog Cardiovasc Dis</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25968932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Llera-Moya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drazul-Schrader</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asztalos</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuchel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rader</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rothblat</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ability to promote efflux via ABCA1 determines the capacity of serum specimens with similar high-density lipoprotein cholesterol to remove cholesterol from macrophages</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>796</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20075420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beusekamp</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerstens</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dullaart</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A low-saturated-fat, low-cholesterol diet decreases plasma CETP activity and pre beta-HDL formation but does not affect cellular cholesterol efflux to plasma from type 1 diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Scand J Clin Lab Invest</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</article-title>. <source>Scand J Stat</source><year>1979</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin-Chartier</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tessier-Grenier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Côté</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labonté</surname><given-names>M-È</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desroches</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couture</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review of the association between dairy product consumption and risk of cardiovascular-related clinical outcomes</article-title>. <source>Adv Nutr</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1026</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28140321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huth</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulgoni</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keast</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auestad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major food sources of calories, added sugars, and saturated fat and their contribution to essential nutrient intakes in the U.S. diet: data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (2003–2006)</article-title>. <source>Nutr J</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23927718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin-Chartier</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Côté</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labonté</surname><given-names>M-È</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tessier-Grenier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desroches</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couture</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive review of the impact of dairy foods and dairy fat on cardiometabolic risk</article-title>. <source>Adv Nutr</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1041</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28140322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oram</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HDL apolipoproteins and ABCA1: partners in the removal of excess cellular cholesterol</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxysterols and atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimpin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haskelberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Gobbo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mozaffarian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is butter back? A systematic review and meta-analysis of butter consumption and risk of cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and total mortality</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0158118</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27355649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asztalos</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of HDL particles on cell-cholesterol efflux under various pathological conditions</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28420704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernáez</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castañer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elosua</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pintó</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estruch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salas-Salvadó</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arós</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serra-Majem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Mediterranean diet improves high-density lipoprotein function in high-cardiovascular-risk individuals: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28193797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fruchart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerique</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid saturation of the diet and plasma lipid concentrations, lipoprotein particle concentrations, and cholesterol efflux capacity</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11864853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaisar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wimberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suffredini</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinecke</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory remodeling of the HDL proteome impairs cholesterol efflux capacity</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1519</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Després</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abdominal obesity and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>444</volume>:<fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Goff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Eck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curtiss</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cartland</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>HDL particle size is a critical determinant of ABCA1-mediated macrophage cellular cholesterol export</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>1133</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25589556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Givens</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayers</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neeland</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuhanna</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rader</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Lemos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>HDL cholesterol efflux capacity and incident cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>371</volume>:<fpage>2383</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25404125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khera</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuchel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Llera-Moya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jafri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mucksavage</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilensky</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Cholesterol efflux capacity, high-density lipoprotein function, and atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>364</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21226578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
