<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T02:43:27Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8897753" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8897753</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-03-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8897753</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8897753</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8897753</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35244704</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35244704</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.0951</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi220053</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-only">
                  <subject>Online Only</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area">
                  <subject>Psychiatry</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effect of Combination Treatment With Varenicline and Nicotine Patch on Smoking Cessation Among Smokers Who Drink Heavily</article-title>
                <subtitle>A Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Varenicline and Nicotine Patch for Smoking Cessation Among Smokers Who Drink Heavily</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Varenicline and Nicotine Patch for Smoking Cessation Among Smokers Who Drink Heavily</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>King</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi220053aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vena</surname>
                    <given-names>Ashley</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi220053aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Wit</surname>
                    <given-names>Harriet</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi220053aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Grant</surname>
                    <given-names>Jon E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi220053aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cao</surname>
                    <given-names>Dingcai</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi220053aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="zoi220053aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neuroscience, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois</aff>
              <aff id="zoi220053aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences, University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> January 13, 2022.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> March 4, 2022. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.0951</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2022 King A et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="zoi220053cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Andrea King, PhD, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neuroscience, University of Chicago, 5841 S Maryland Ave, MC-3077, Chicago, IL 60637 (<email xlink:href="aking@bsd.uchicago.edu">aking@bsd.uchicago.edu</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions</bold>: Drs Vena and Cao had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
                <p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> King, Cao.</p>
                <p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> King, Vena, Cao.</p>
                <p><italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> de Wit, Cao.</p>
                <p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> King, Cao.</p>
                <p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> King, Vena, Grant.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervision:</italic> King, Cao.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr King reported receiving grants from Pfizer during the conduct of the study and personal fees from the Respiratory Health Association outside the submitted work. Dr de Wit reported being on the board of directors of PharmAla Biotech; being a scientific advisor to Awakn Life Sciences, Gilgamesh Pharmaceuticals, and Schedule I Therapeutics; and receiving research support from the Beckley Foundation outside the submitted work. Dr Grant reported receiving grants from Biohaven Pharmaceuticals, Otsuka Pharmaceutical Company, and Promentis Pharmaceuticals outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was supported by grant P30 CA14599 from the University of Chicago Medicine Comprehensive Cancer Center and the Global Research Award for Nicotine Dependence from Pfizer and the Women’s Board of the University of Chicago Cancer Research Foundation (Dr King).</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funding organizations had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI220053-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Joel Africk, President and CEO, and staff members of the Respiratory Health Association provided study visit space. Patrick McNamara, BS, of Northwestern University; Meghan Howe, BA, of Rosalind Franklin University; Alyssa Bathery, BS, of University of Illinois; and Nathan Didier, MSc, BMI, of University of Chicago, provided research assistance and support in data management. Biosamples and assays were provided by the University of Chicago Clinical Research Center (Chicago, Illinois), Mayo Clinic Laboratories (Rochester, Minnesota), and Salimetrics Lab (State College, Pennsylvania).</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-03-04T10:00">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>5</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <elocation-id>e220951</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>7</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2022 King A et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951.pdf">jamanetwopen-e220951.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.0951"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-1">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>Is the combination of varenicline tartrate and nicotine patch a more effective treatment than placebo with nicotine patch for smoking cessation in adult cigarette smokers who drink heavily?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-2">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this randomized clinical trial of 122 smokers who drink heavily, combination treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch significantly improved continuous cigarette abstinence during the final 4 weeks of treatment relative to placebo and nicotine patch.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-3">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>This study found that combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch improved smoking cessation outcomes among smokers who drink heavily, a population who have historically experienced worse outcomes with standard approved treatments for tobacco cessation.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-4">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>The concurrent use of both tobacco and alcohol causes substantial disease and early mortality, and smokers who drink heavily tend to be less successful in smoking cessation than smokers who do not. Although varenicline combined with nicotine replacement therapy for smoking cessation has been examined among smokers who do not drink heavily, this combination treatment has not yet been examined among smokers who drink heavily.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-5">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To determine whether combined treatment with varenicline tartrate and nicotine patch improves continuous abstinence from cigarette smoking among smokers who drink heavily.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-6">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>This double-blind, placebo-controlled, superiority randomized clinical trial evaluated combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch compared with placebo and nicotine patch for smoking cessation (primary outcome) and drinking behavior (secondary outcome) among smokers who drink heavily. The clinical trial was conducted at 2 outpatient sites in Chicago, Illinois, with enrollment from March 26, 2018, to February 14, 2020. The 122 participants were recruited from the community via social media and public transit advertisements and equally randomized to the 2 treatment groups, which were stratified by sex and smoking behavior. Eligible participants smoked between 5 and 30 cigarettes per day and drank heavily (&gt;14 drinks per week for men or &gt;7 drinks per week for women and ≥1 heavy drinking day [defined as &gt;5 drinks per occasion for men or &gt;4 drinks per occasion for women] per month for the past year) and had a desire to quit smoking.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-7">
                  <title>Interventions</title>
                  <p>Varenicline tartrate, 1.0 mg, twice daily or matching placebo pills twice daily for 12 weeks. Nicotine patch at manufacturer-recommended doses for 10 weeks and brief individual smoking cessation counseling the week before the quit date and on the quit date.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-8">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>The primary outcome was self-reported continuous cigarette abstinence through weeks 9 to 12; abstinence was biochemically confirmed at the week 12 study visit. Secondary outcomes were the frequency of weekly drinking and weekly heavy drinking during the study period.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-9">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Among 122 participants (mean [SD] age, 44.0 [12.4] years; 67 men [54.9%]), 61 were randomly assigned to receive combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch (varenicline group), and 61 were randomly assigned to receive placebo and nicotine patch (placebo group). A total of 54 participants (44.3%) self-identified as Black, 56 (45.9%) as White, and 12 (9.8%) as other races (including American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, &gt;1 race, and unspecified race). A total of 8 participants (6.6%) self-identified as Hispanic and 114 (93.4%) as non-Hispanic ethnicity. Study retention to 12 weeks was 89%. The intention-to-treat analyses showed higher smoking cessation rates during weeks 9 to 12 in the varenicline group vs the placebo group (27 participants [44.3%] vs 17 participants [27.9%]; odds ratio, 2.20; 95% CI, 1.01-4.80; <italic>P </italic>= .047) and lower likelihood of relapse throughout treatment in the varenicline group relative to the placebo group (hazard ratio, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.40-0.96; <italic>P </italic>= .03). Both treatments were well tolerated; however, compared with participants in the placebo group, those in the varenicline group experienced more adverse effects, with 5 participants in the varenicline group discontinuing medication due to adverse effects.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-10">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>In this study, combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch was more effective than placebo and nicotine patch for smoking cessation among smokers who drink heavily. The combination treatment had no effect on alcohol consumption, with both groups showing significant reductions. Combination treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch may be a viable option for smokers who drink heavily.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi220053-11">
                  <title>Trial Registration</title>
                  <p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02859142" ext-link-type="uri">NCT02859142</ext-link></p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic">
                <p>This randomized clinical trial assesses whether combined treatment with varenicline tartrate and nicotine patch improves continuous abstinence from cigarette smoking among smokers who drink heavily.</p>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-ZOI220053">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Tobacco and alcohol use are among the top 3 leading contributors to preventable disease and injury in the US and cause significant public health and economic burdens.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Moreover, many people concurrently use both substances, resulting in high rates of cancer and pulmonary and cardiovascular disease, with mortality beyond the risks of each substance individually.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Almost 20% of smokers drink heavily compared with 6.5% of nonsmokers; conversely, those who drink heavily are 2 to 3 times more likely to smoke than those who do not.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Notably, smokers who drink heavily are less likely to quit smoking than those who drink lightly or do not drink.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Thus, there is a need to develop efficacious interventions targeting smokers who drink heavily.</p>
              <p>One potential candidate for targeting both alcohol and smoking behaviors is varenicline tartrate, a highly effective pharmacotherapy approved for smoking cessation.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Varenicline may improve smoking cessation rates among smokers who drink heavily because it acts on neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors that play an important role in the reinforcing effects of both alcohol and nicotine.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Although varenicline is not an approved medication for alcohol use disorder (AUD),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> it has been shown to modify acute alcohol responses<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and reduce consumption levels.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> These effects may be important for smokers who drink heavily because they regularly drink to intoxication, which increases smoking urges<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> and smoking lapses.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Thus, varenicline therapy may be effective for smokers who drink heavily because of possible shared neurochemical mechanisms and because alcohol and tobacco facilitate each other.</p>
              <p>For the treatment of smokers who drink heavily, varenicline is more effective than other approved monotherapies, such as bupropion or nicotine replacement therapy, for smoking cessation<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> or cigarette reduction.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> However, even with varenicline, quit rates among smokers who drink heavily lag behind those of smokers who do not<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>; therefore, a combined pharmacotherapeutic approach may provide additional benefit. The combination of varenicline with the opioid antagonist naltrexone was recently shown to be effective in reducing the number of drinks consumed per drinking day among smokers who drink heavily but was inferior to varenicline alone for smoking abstinence.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Another combination therapy approach, varenicline and nicotine patch, has been examined among smokers who do not drink heavily and was shown to be well tolerated.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> This combination treatment produced higher smoking cessation rates than varenicline alone,<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> particularly among heavy smokers,<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> but did not lead to higher quit rates when nicotine patch was delivered for a shorter interval than manufacturer recommendations.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Notably, the combination of varenicline and nicotine replacement therapy has not been studied among smokers who drink heavily because they are often excluded from these types of randomized clinical trials.</p>
              <p>Thus, we conducted a randomized clinical trial to examine the efficacy of combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch over 12 weeks of smoking cessation treatment among smokers who drink heavily. We hypothesized that the combined treatment would improve our primary outcome of smoking cessation rates during weeks 9 to 12 compared with placebo and nicotine patch. In addition, we hypothesized that the combined treatment would also reduce secondary alcohol drinking outcomes as measured by the frequency of weekly drinking and weekly heavy drinking throughout the 12-week treatment period.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-ZOI220053">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="H2-1-ZOI220053">
                <title>Design Overview</title>
                <p>The study was a double-blind, placebo-controlled, superiority randomized clinical trial evaluating the effect of varenicline combined with nicotine patch vs placebo combined with nicotine patch on smoking cessation (primary outcome) and weekly drinking behavior (secondary outcome) among smokers who drink heavily. The study was approved by the University of Chicago Institutional Review Board (<xref rid="note-ZOI220053-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). All participants provided both written and oral informed consent at the screening visit. This study followed the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" ext-link-type="uri">CONSORT</ext-link>) reporting guideline for randomized clinical trials.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p>
                <p>Participants were enrolled between March 26, 2018, and February 14, 2020. Most study visits (88%) took place at the Clinical Addictions Research Laboratory at the University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, and the remainder (12%) took place at the Respiratory Health Association in downtown Chicago. Recruitment was conducted via advertisements on social media and public transit as well as community outreach to local organizations. Study candidates deemed eligible based on a telephone screening interview were invited to attend an in-person screening session.</p>
                <p>Eligible candidates were age 18 to 85 years; had a current desire to quit smoking; had self-reported smoking frequency of 5 to 30 cigarettes per day, which was bioverified by urinary cotinine level (≥3 on immunochromatographic assay test strips [NicAlert; Nymox Pharmaceutical Corporation]); were fluent in English; had an educational level of grade 8 or higher; had stable residence; did not use nicotine patches within the past 3 months or receive varenicline within the past 3 years; and had no history of adverse reactions to varenicline or nicotine patch. Candidates were also required to meet hazardous drinking levels consistent with National Institute on Alcohol and Alcoholism guidelines (&gt;14 drinks per week for men or &gt;7 drinks per week for women and ≥1 heavy drinking day [defined as &gt;5 drinks per occasion for men or &gt;4 drinks per occasion for women] per month for the past year).<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Candidates were not seeking treatment to change their drinking behavior. Individuals with major medical or psychiatric contraindications were deemed ineligible; contraindications included uncontrolled hypertension, history of seizures, liver enzymes outside of the normal range, history of suicide attempt or current suicidal ideation, and history of severe alcohol withdrawal. Among women, current pregnancy, breastfeeding, plans to become pregnant within the next 3 months, or unwillingness to use effective birth control, as applicable, were also reasons for exclusion.</p>
                <p>After providing informed consent at the screening visit, candidates completed surveys on demographic characteristics, medical history, and smoking, mood, and substance use history. They also completed the Fagerström Test for Cigarette Dependence (score range, 0-10 points, with higher scores indicating greater nicotine dependence),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (score range, 0-40 points, with higher scores indicating greater alcohol consumption and alcohol-related problems; potential problematic drinking was defined as a score of ≥8 points),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> the research version of the Structured Clinical Interview for the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (Fifth Edition),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (score range, 0-25 points, with higher scores indicating greater levels of suicidal ideation or behavior),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> and a Timeline Followback<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> interview measuring daily cigarette and alcohol use within the past 28 days. At arrival, candidates were required to have a breath alcohol concentration of 0 g/dL, a score of less than 10 points on the Clinical Institute Withdrawal Assessment for Alcohol (score range, 0-67 points, with higher scores indicating greater severity of withdrawal symptoms),<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> and a negative urine toxicologic screening result for cocaine, amphetamines, benzodiazepines, opiates, and phencyclidine. Individuals deemed eligible were scheduled for 4 study visits over 12 weeks. Randomization occurred during the first study visit, and the target smoking cessation date was scheduled for 1 week later to coincide with the second study visit. The third and fourth visits occurred at 2 weeks and 12 weeks after the target quit date, respectively.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-2-ZOI220053">
                <title>Randomization and Interventions</title>
                <p>Varenicline and matching placebo tablets were provided by Pfizer. Participants were randomly assigned (1:1 via a random number generator) to receive either varenicline and nicotine patch (varenicline group) or placebo and nicotine patch (placebo group), stratified by sex and smoking behavior (light smoking [defined as &lt;10 cigarettes per day] vs heavy smoking [defined as ≥10 cigarettes per day]) (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI220053-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). At the first study visit, all participants in the intention-to-treat sample ingested the first tablet (varenicline or placebo) with a small snack (granola bar) under the observation of an investigator (A.V.).</p>
                <p>The doses of varenicline tartrate were titrated according to the standard approved regimen of 0.5 mg once daily for 3 days, 0.5 mg twice daily for 4 days, and 1.0 mg twice daily starting on the quit date through the remaining 12 weeks of treatment. After week 12, participants in both groups were given the option to receive down-titration dosing. For the varenicline group, this dosing comprised 0.5-mg tablets twice daily for 4 days, then 0.5-mg tablets once daily for 3 days. Participants randomized to the placebo group received tablets that appeared identical to varenicline using the same dosing schedule. The nicotine patch was provided at the first visit, with instructions to initiate use on the morning of their quit day and to continue use for 10 weeks at dosing levels recommended by the manufacturer. Light smokers (&lt;10 cigarettes per day) received 14-mg patches to use daily for the first 6 weeks, then 7-mg patches to use daily for 4 weeks. Heavy smokers (≥10 cigarettes per day) received 21-mg patches to use daily for the first 6 weeks followed by 14-mg patches to use daily for 2 weeks, then 7-mg patches to use daily for 2 weeks. Medication and patch adherence was monitored via tablet and patch counts at each study visit and self-reported log entries. Participants who discontinued medication or had a dose reduction were allowed to complete the trial.</p>
                <p>Each participant received brief behavioral therapy during their first 2 visits. At the first visit, they met for 30 to 45 minutes with a trained counselor supervised by a licensed psychologist (A.K.). The counseling protocol was based on the Courage to Quit program<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> and included preparations for quit day, discussion of medication adherence, and techniques for coping with smoking urges and nicotine withdrawal symptoms. The counseling focused on smoking cessation, and changes in alcohol drinking behavior were mentioned briefly in the motivational context of reducing smoking triggers. Participants attended a second 15-minute counseling session during the second visit (quit day) to reinforce the skills discussed in the first visit. At the fourth study visit (week 12), participants received $60 as compensation for time spent completing study measures.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-3-ZOI220053">
                <title>Assessments</title>
                <p>At each visit, participants received breath tests measuring carbon monoxide and alcohol levels, measurement of vital signs and body weight, and investigator-delivered interviews, including the Clinical Institute Withdrawal Assessment for Alcohol, the Timeline Followback interview for daily cigarette and alcohol use, and the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale to assure safety.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Participants also completed a 15-item assessment of adverse effects (AEs) rated on a 4-point scale (with 1 indicating absent, 2 indicating mild, 3 indicating moderate, and 4 indicating severe AEs) and returned any unused tablets and patches along with a log of their daily tablet and patch use. The primary outcome was smoking cessation rates as defined by continuous cigarette abstinence based on self-report of no smoking (defined as not even 1 puff of a cigarette) during weeks 9 to 12 of treatment; smoking cessation was biochemically confirmed by an exhaled carbon monoxide level of 10 ppm or lower at the fourth study visit (week 12)<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> (details and adjustments made due to the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic are available in eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI220053-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). Secondary outcomes were alcohol drinking measured by weekly drinking frequency and weekly heavy drinking frequency throughout the treatment period.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-4-ZOI220053">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>The sample size of 61 participants per group was determined based on data obtained from the largest study to date of combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch for smoking cessation.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> With this sample size, the clinical trial had at least 80% power to detect a medium effect size (Cohen <italic>d</italic> = 0.52) for the between-group difference on a continuous drinking outcome for a 2-sided test at α = .05. A logistic regression model was used to compare continuous smoking abstinence (not even 1 puff of a cigarette) between groups through weeks 9 to 12. A Cox proportional hazards regression model was conducted to assess continuous smoking status starting on the quit day through week 12 of active treatment. Both analyses adjusted for baseline number of cigarettes per smoking day. An intention-to-treat approach was used for analyses conducted among all randomized participants; because most participants who did not complete the clinical trial (11 of 13 individuals [84.6%]) reported continuation of smoking up to the point of study withdrawal, we determined that those who did not complete the study could be reasonably assumed to have relapsed to smoking.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> For changes in drinking outcomes (weekly drinking days and heavy drinking days), generalized estimating equation models (with normal distributions and identity link functions) were used to analyze the effects of group, time, and their interaction, controlling for baseline drinking behavior.</p>
                <p>All tests were 2-sided with a significance threshold of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. All analyses were conducted using Stata software, version 15.1 (StataCorp LLC).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-ZOI220053">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="H2-5-ZOI220053">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>Among 122 participants, 61 were randomly assigned to receive combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch, and 61 were randomly assigned to receive placebo and nicotine patch (<xref rid="zoi220053f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The mean (SD) age of the total sample was 44.0 (12.4) years; 55 participants (45.1%) were female, and 67 (54.9%) were male (<xref rid="zoi220053t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A total of 54 participants (44.3%) self-identified as Black, 56 (45.9%) self-identified as White, and 12 (9.8%) self-identified as other races (including American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, &gt;1 race, and unspecified race). A total of 8 participants (6.6%) self-identified as Hispanic and 114 (93.4%) as non-Hispanic ethnicity. The mean (SD) smoking duration was 25.2 (13.2) years, with a mean (SD) of 11.8 (6.6) cigarettes smoked per smoking day and a mean (SD) score of 3.9 (2.4) points on the Fagerström Test for Cigarette Dependence, indicating moderate dependence. All participants regularly drank heavily, with a mean (SD) score of 11.9 (5.6) points on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (scores of ≥8 points indicated potential problematic drinking). Mean (SD) alcohol consumption was 24.7 (19.6) drinks per week, with 33% constituting heavy drinking days among all days in the past month. A total of 68 participants (55.7%) met the criteria for AUD. The varenicline vs placebo groups did not differ with regard to demographic characteristics (eg, mean [SD] age, 44.0 [12.9] years vs 44.0 [12.0] years; 35 men [57.4%] vs 32 men [52.5%]), smoking patterns and use (eg, mean [SD] smoking days in past month, 27.8 [0.8] vs 27.4 [1.7]; mean [SD] cigarettes per smoking day, 11.8 [6.3] vs 11.8 [7.1]), and drinking patterns and use (eg, mean [SD] drinking days per week, 4.4 [1.8] vs 4.7 [1.8]; 30% vs 37% heavy drinking days).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi220053f1" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 1. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Study Flow Diagram</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="zoi220053t1">
                  <label>Table 1. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col width="37.62%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="21.51%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="21.51%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="19.36%" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                        <th colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Total (N = 122)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varenicline and nicotine patch (n = 61)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo and nicotine patch (n = 61)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), y</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0 (12.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0 (12.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0 (12.0)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (45.1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (42.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (47.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (54.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (57.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (52.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (44.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (39.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (49.2)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (45.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (45.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (45.9)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other<xref rid="zoi220053t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (9.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (14.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.9)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.3)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (93.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (90.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (96.7)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level, mean (SD), y</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 (2.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5 (2.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 (2.3)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI score, mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 (6.1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (4.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (7.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking patterns and use</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Duration of smoking, mean (SD), y</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2 (13.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5 (13.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9 (12.6)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoking days in past month, mean (SD)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6 (1.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 (0.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4 (1.7)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cigarettes per smoking day, mean (SD)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (6.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (6.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (7.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Menthol cigarette preference</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (54.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (52.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (57.4)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> FTCD score, mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (2.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (2.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (2.4)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Carbon monoxide level, mean (SD), ppm</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1 (10.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 (11.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 (9.7)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking patterns and use</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Drinking days per week, mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (1.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (1.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (1.8)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Drinks per drinking day, mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (4.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (3.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.2)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heavy drinking days within past month, %<xref rid="zoi220053t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AUDIT total score, mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 (5.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 (5.1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 (6.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No. of <italic>DSM-5</italic> AUD symptoms</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi220053t1n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (2.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Symptom category</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None (0-1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (42.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (39.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (45.9)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild (2-3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (27.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.9)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate (4-5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (18.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (14.8)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe (≥6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (10.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (11.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Abbreviations: AUD, alcohol use disorder; AUDIT, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; <italic>DSM-5</italic>, <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (Fifth Edition); FTCD, Fagerström Test for Cigarette Dependence.</p>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n1">
                      <label>
                        <sup>a</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Other category included American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, more than 1 race, and unspecified race.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n2">
                      <label>
                        <sup>b</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Score range, 0-63 points, with higher scores indicating more severe levels of depression.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n3">
                      <label>
                        <sup>c</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Score range, 0-10 points, with higher scores indicating greater nicotine dependence.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n4">
                      <label>
                        <sup>d</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Consumption during the 28 days before enrollment.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n5">
                      <label>
                        <sup>e</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Score range, 0-40 points, with higher scores indicating greater alcohol consumption and alcohol-related problems. Heavy drinking days were defined as more than 5 drinks per occasion for men and more than 4 drinks per occasion for women.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t1n6">
                      <label>
                        <sup>f</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Missing data for 2 participants (1 participant from each group) were imputed based on AUDIT scores and drinking patterns.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-6-ZOI220053">
                <title>Retention and Adherence</title>
                <p>Study retention through 12 weeks of treatment was high, with 109 of 122 participants (89.3%) completing active treatment (4 participants in the varenicline group and 9 participants in the placebo group withdrew from the study). The treatment groups did not differ in the percentage of dispensed tablets reported taken over the 12-week treatment period (median, 85.5% [IQR, 48.6%-97.2%] in the varenicline group vs 86.6% [IQR, 69.8%-97.5%] in the placebo group; <italic>P</italic> = .36) or the percentage of dispensed nicotine patches used (median, 82.9% [IQR, 45.7%-98.6%] in the varenicline group vs 92.9% [IQR, 67.9%-97.9%] in the placebo group; <italic>P</italic> = .30).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-7-ZOI220053">
                <title>Outcomes at End of Treatment</title>
                <p>Smoking cessation rates during weeks 9 to 12 were higher in the varenicline group vs the placebo group (27 participants [44.3%] vs 17 participants [27.9%]; odds ratio, 2.20; 95% CI, 1.01-4.80; <italic>P</italic> = .047) (<xref rid="zoi220053f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A). A Kaplan-Meier survival analysis of continuous cigarette abstinence throughout the 12 weeks of treatment confirmed a lower likelihood of smoking relapse among those in the varenicline group compared with those in the placebo group (hazard ratio, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.40-0.96; <italic>P</italic> = .03) (<xref rid="zoi220053f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>B).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi220053f2" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 2. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Cigarette Smoking Outcomes by Treatment Group</title>
                    <p>Participants in the varenicline group received varenicline tartrate, 1.0 mg, twice daily and nicotine patch. Participants in the placebo group received matching placebo pills twice daily and nicotine patch. A total of 61 participants were in each group. B, Day 0 indicates the smoking cessation day, which corresponded to the first day of the full medication dose and nicotine patch.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Regarding secondary outcomes, significant decreases in the frequency of any alcohol drinking (<xref rid="zoi220053f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A) and heavy drinking (<xref rid="zoi220053f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B) were observed. Among both groups, weekly drinking days decreased by 25% (from 65% at baseline to 49% at 12 weeks; <italic>P</italic> = .003 for main effect of time), and weekly heavy drinking days decreased by 54% (from 33% at baseline to 15% at 12 weeks; <italic>P</italic> = .004 for main effect of time). However, the treatment groups did not differ for either outcome (drinking days: χ<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub>  = 0.06 [<italic>P</italic> = .81 for main effect] and χ<sup>2</sup><sub>12</sub> = 10.41 [<italic>P</italic> = .58 for interaction]) between group and time; heavy drinking days: <italic>P</italic> = .57 for main effect of group and χ<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub>  = 0.32 [<italic>P</italic> = .57 for main effect] and χ<sup>2</sup><sub>12</sub> = 8.40 (<italic>P</italic> = .75 for interaction]).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi220053f3" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 3. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Alcohol Drinking Outcomes by Treatment Group</title>
                    <p>Participants in the varenicline group received varenicline tartrate, 1.0 mg, twice daily and nicotine patch. Participants in the placebo group received matching placebo pills twice daily and nicotine patch. Analysis included 109 of 122 participants (89.3%) who completed active treatment. Baseline refers to the mean of the 4-week period before enrollment, and week 0 was the week before the smoking cessation date during which medication was initiated. For baseline drinks per week, data from 3 participants (with outlier values &gt;3 SD higher than the mean) were normalized to 3 SD of the sample mean before analysis. Generalized estimating equation analyses were based on mean drinking days per week and heavy drinking days per week. Each week was divided by a constant of 7 for ease of presenting percentages of drinking days and heavy drinking days. Heavy drinking days were defined as 5 or more drinks per occasion for men and 4 or more drinks per occasion for women.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-8-ZOI220053">
                <title>Adverse Events</title>
                <p>The rate of AEs among participants who reported symptoms of greater severity compared with baseline are shown in <xref rid="zoi220053t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Participants in the varenicline group vs the placebo group experienced significantly more frequent nausea (34 participants [55.7%] vs 18 participants [29.5%]; <italic>P</italic> = .003), gas (30 participants [49.2%] vs 17 participants [27.9%]; <italic>P</italic> = .009), abnormal dreams (45 participants [73.8%] vs 30 participants [49.2%]; <italic>P</italic> = .007), sleep problems (31 participants [50.8%] vs 15 participants [24.6%]; <italic>P</italic> = .003), and headaches (26 participants [42.6%] vs 14 participants [23.0%]; <italic>P</italic> = .02) (<xref rid="zoi220053t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Among both groups, most of these AEs (190 of 220 reports [86.4%]) were rated as mild or moderate. Two serious AEs occurred in the varenicline group; 1 participant had a brief psychiatric hospitalization for suicidal ideation, and another participant had a brief hospitalization for temporary loss of consciousness. In both cases, varenicline was promptly discontinued, and participants completed the clinical trial. In the varenicline group, 5 participants (8.2%) discontinued medication because of AEs, and another 6 participants (9.8%) requested a 50% dose reduction. There were no serious AEs, discontinued medications, or dose reductions requested among participants in the placebo group.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="zoi220053t2">
                  <label>Table 2. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Adverse Events</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col width="50.02%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="20.85%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="19.03%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="10.1%" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Event<xref rid="zoi220053t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
                        <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Participants, No. (%)</th>
                        <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value<xref rid="zoi220053t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Varenicline and nicotine patch (n = 61)</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo and nicotine patch (n = 61)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (55.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (29.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (14.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gas</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (49.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.009</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constipation</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (36.1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal dreams</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (73.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (49.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.007</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problems</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (50.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (24.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased heart rate</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (16.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.27</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizures</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;.99</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased effects of alcohol (drunkenness)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal thoughts</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.56</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dizziness</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;.99</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (42.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joint pain</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.62</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin irritation (outside of patch site)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (14.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t2n1">
                      <label>
                        <sup>a</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Adverse events reported as new onset or greater severity than baseline at visits 2, 3, and 4.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="zoi220053t2n2">
                      <label>
                        <sup>b</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Significance threshold was χ<sup>2</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-ZOI220053">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this randomized clinical trial, combined treatment with varenicline and nicotine patch was more effective than nicotine patch alone for smoking cessation rates during weeks 9 to 12 of treatment among smokers who drank heavily. The combined treatment had no effect on alcohol consumption. Notably, the findings of this study expanded our knowledge of smoking cessation treatment among smokers who drink heavily in several ways. First, the combination treatment of varenicline and nicotine patch improved on the historically worse smoking cessation outcomes among smokers who drink heavily, with a 44.3% quit rate that was comparable with quit rates (22%-55%) reported among smokers who did not drink heavily receiving the same combination treatment in other studies.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Second, the results demonstrated that smokers who drink heavily can be enrolled and retained in a smoking cessation treatment program and tolerate a comprehensive pharmacotherapy regimen. Third, varenicline and nicotine patch reduced the likelihood of relapse throughout treatment, which suggests that longer-term dosing with varenicline would be necessary for its therapeutic effect to be observed.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Although participants were enrolled irrespective of desire to change alcohol use, we observed a significant decrease in drinking frequency during treatment. This finding was unexpected because drinking modification was not a treatment goal and was not addressed beyond a brief mention of triggers during the first counseling session. Nevertheless, these participants reduced their drinking to a level similar to that observed in a study of individuals with AUD who were motivated to change their drinking behavior.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> This reduction in drinking may have produced a floor effect, obscuring any potential benefit of varenicline therapy for alcohol use. However, the change in drinking behavior occurred in both the varenicline and placebo groups, raising the possibility that the nicotine patch was sufficient to decrease drinking because it was able to reduce subjective intoxication and latency to drink<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> as well as alcohol withdrawal symptoms.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Participants may alternately have changed drinking behavior due to assessment reactivity, demand characteristics, or concerns about medication interactions. Warnings about varenicline from the US Food and Drug Administration suggest that patients “reduce the amount of alcohol they consume until they know whether [the medication] affects them.”<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup><sup>(p1)</sup> Nonetheless, the lack of a direct varenicline benefit for drinking behavior was consistent with results from other studies involving both smokers who drink heavily<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and individuals with AUD.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The combination of varenicline plus nicotine replacement therapy has been examined in clinical trials of smokers who do not drink heavily and was shown to be well tolerated but with mixed efficacy.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi220053r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> The precise neuropharmacological mechanism underlying the efficacy of varenicline and nicotine patch is unclear but may be due to synergistic mechanisms of action at neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Varenicline is more potent than nicotine patch in desensitizing reward-mediating α4β2 neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors, blocking nicotine receptor occupancy,<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> and producing synaptic trapping,<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> but varenicline may not fully saturate α4β2 subunit receptors or provide complete blockage of nicotine reinforcement.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup> Nicotine patch produces greater and more immediate activation of α4β2 subunit receptors and may complement varenicline by reducing ad hoc cravings that are especially important early in a smoking cessation attempt.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> More therapeutic clinical trials and basic translational research are needed to fully understand the interrelationship of neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors and other circuitries underlying nicotine-alcohol interactions<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup> because combination treatments do not always show benefit; for example, varenicline and naltrexone were found to worsen smoking cessation rates among smokers who drink heavily compared with varenicline and placebo.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p>
              <sec id="H2-9-ZOI220053">
                <title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
                <p>This study has strengths. These strengths include enrollment of a racially diverse sample of smokers who drank heavily as well as high retention rates (89% completion at 12 weeks) within a protocol that was consistent with the clinical practice of 2 visits after the smoking cessation date over 12 weeks.</p>
                <p>The study also has limitations. First, the clinical trial met its recruitment goal, but the sample was small, precluding analyses of moderators of varenicline effects, such as sex<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and race.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Second, this superiority clinical trial with 2-group randomization lacked the full 2 × 2 design with placebo conditions for nicotine patch; therefore, assessment of varenicline alone or double placebo–condition effects was not possible. Third, the clinical trial was completed during the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic, and biochemical verification of self-reported smoking cessation rates was not possible for some participants given the unavoidable limitations and quick transition to completing the study using virtual and telephone platforms.<sup><xref rid="zoi220053r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-ZOI220053">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>The findings of this randomized clinical trial indicate that, among smokers who drink heavily, more than 50% of whom had AUD, the combination of varenicline and nicotine patch treatment (vs placebo and nicotine patch) produced higher smoking cessation rates throughout 12 weeks of treatment. The combination pharmacotherapy was also safe and well tolerated. The results support continued investigation of varenicline with nicotine patch as a combination treatment strategy for smokers with hazardous drinking behaviors who have historically experienced worse outcomes with standard approved tobacco cessation treatments. Smokers who drink heavily can be enrolled and retained in smoking cessation clinical trials, and further investigation is warranted to help reduce the health disparities associated with chronic smoking and heavy drinking.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-ZOI220053">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zoi220053r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerberding</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Actual causes of death in the United States, 2000</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>291</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1238</fpage>-<lpage>1245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.291.10.1238</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15010446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15010446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group>. Smoking &amp; tobacco use: fast facts. 2021. Accessed March 31, 2021. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/data_statistics/fact_sheets/fast_facts/index.htm#beginning" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/data_statistics/fact_sheets/fast_facts/index.htm#beginning</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</collab></person-group>. Alcohol facts and statistics. National Institutes of Health; June 2021. Accessed July 16, 2021. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www" ext-link-type="uri">https://www</ext-link><ext-link xlink:href="http://.niaaa.nih.gov/publications/brochures-and-fact-sheets/alcohol-facts-and-statistics" ext-link-type="uri">.niaaa.nih.gov/publications/brochures-and-fact-sheets/alcohol-facts-and-statistics</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tavani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Attributable risk for oral cancer in northern Italy</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 8318870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8318870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wingo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer (1973 through 1998), featuring cancers with recent increasing trends</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>824</fpage>-<lpage>842</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/93.11.824</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11390532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Marrero</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conjeevaram</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lok</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol, tobacco and obesity are synergistic risk factors for hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2004.10.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15664247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15664247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mukamal</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. The effects of smoking and drinking on cardiovascular disease and risk factors. <italic>Alcohol Res Heal</italic>. <year>2006</year>;29(3):199-202.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ebbert</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janney</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cerhan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. The association of alcohol consumption with coronary heart disease mortality and cancer incidence varies by smoking history. <italic>J Gen Intern Med</italic>. <year>2005</year>;20(1):14-20. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1525-1497.2005.40129.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of <italic>DSM-5</italic> alcohol use disorder: results from the National Epidemiologic Survey on Alcohol and Related Conditions III</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>-<lpage>766</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2015.0584</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26039070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Drinking as a risk factor for sustained smoking</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0376-8716(99)00130-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10812284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10812284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Searching for personalized medicine for binge drinking smokers: smoking cessation using varenicline, nicotine patch, or combination nicotine replacement therapy</article-title>. <source>J Stud Alcohol Drugs</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15288/jsad.2020.81.426</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32800078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32800078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jorenby</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Varenicline Phase 3 Study Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of varenicline, an α4β2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor partial agonist, vs placebo or sustained-release bupropion for smoking cessation: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.296.1.56</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16820547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rennard</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nides</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Varenicline Phase 3 Study Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline, an α4β2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor partial agonist, vs sustained-release bupropion and placebo for smoking cessation: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.296.1.47</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16820546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engleman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nicotinic receptor modulation to treat alcohol and drug dependence</article-title>. <source>Front Neurosci</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2014.00426</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25642160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25642160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guildford</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao-Shea</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tapper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nicotinic acetylcholine receptors containing the α4 subunit modulate alcohol reward</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>738</fpage>-<lpage>746</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.09.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23141806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23141806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guildford</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tapper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors: common molecular substrates of nicotine and alcohol dependence</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2013.00029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23641218?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23641218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mansukhani</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karpyak</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneekloth</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolla</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of varenicline on alcohol consumption in subjects with alcohol use disorders: systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>19r12924</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.19r12924</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32097546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32097546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>DJO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline potentiates alcohol-induced negative subjective responses and offsets impaired eye movements</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>906</fpage>-<lpage>914</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2011.01675.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22339626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22339626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>ELR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline reduces alcohol self-administration in heavy-drinking smokers</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.01.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19249750?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19249750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fucito</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An integrated behavioural intervention combined with varenicline for heavy-drinking smokers: a randomized pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Smok Cessat</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/jsc.2020.13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33312238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33312238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline decreases alcohol consumption in heavy-drinking smokers</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>223</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-012-2717-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22547331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22547331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Tobacco chippers show robust increases in smoking urge after alcohol consumption. <italic>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</italic>. <year>2007</year>;190(3):321-329. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-006-0438-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kahler</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metrik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol use and initial smoking lapses among heavy drinkers in smoking cessation treatment</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>-<lpage>785</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntq083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20507898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20507898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kahler</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metrik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acute effects of low and high dose alcohol on smoking lapse behavior in a laboratory analogue task</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>231</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>4649</fpage>-<lpage>4657</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-014-3613-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24858377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24858377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ebbert</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croghan</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline for tobacco-dependence treatment in alcohol-dependent smokers: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2017.11.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29324248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zweben</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fucito</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of varenicline combined with medical management on alcohol use disorder with comorbid cigarette smoking: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.3544</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29261824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29261824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Zawertailo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Foll</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Safety and efficacy of varenicline for smoking cessation in alcohol-dependent smokers in concurrent treatment for alcohol use disorder: a pilot, randomized placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCP.0000000000001172</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32068562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32068562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Efficacy of combining varenicline and naltrexone for smoking cessation and drinking reduction: a randomized clinical trial. <italic>Am J Psychiatry</italic>. <year>2021</year>;178(9):818-828. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2020.20070993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hajek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhanji</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McRobbie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Is a combination of varenicline and nicotine patch more effective in helping smokers quit than varenicline alone? a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-11-140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23718718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23718718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Koegelenberg</surname><given-names>CFN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of varenicline combined with nicotine replacement therapy vs varenicline alone for smoking cessation: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>312</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.7195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25005652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25005652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ramon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morchon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masuet-Aumatell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Combining varenicline and nicotine patches: a randomized controlled trial study in smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-014-0172-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25296623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25296623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>; <collab>CONSORT Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-8-18</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20334633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20334633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><collab>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</collab></person-group>. <source>Helping Patients Who Drink Too Much: A Clinician’s Guide</source>. <publisher-name>National Institutes of Health</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fagerström</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Determinants of tobacco use and renaming the FTND to the Fagerström Test for Cigarette Dependence</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntr137</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22025545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De La Fuente</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <italic>AUDIT: the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test: Guidelines for Use in Primary Health Care</italic>. 2nd ed. World Health Organization; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>First</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JBW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karg</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>User’s Guide for the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 Disorders, Research Version (SCID-5-RV).</source><publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale: initial validity and internal consistency findings from three multisite studies with adolescents and adults</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1266</fpage>-<lpage>1277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2011.10111704</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22193671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22193671</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Sobell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sobell</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title>Timeline follow-back</part-title>. In: <person-group><string-name><surname>Litten</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>Measuring Alcohol Consumption.</source><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4612-0357-5_3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sykora</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneiderman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of alcohol withdrawal: the revised clinical institute withdrawal assessment for alcohol scale (CIWA-Ar)</article-title>. <source>Br J Addict</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1353</fpage>-<lpage>1357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.1989.tb00737.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2597811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2597811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Asvat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Africk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility and effectiveness of a community-based smoking cessation intervention in a racially diverse, urban smoker cohort</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>suppl 4</issue>):<fpage>S620</fpage>-<lpage>S627</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2014.302097</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25100429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25100429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ebbert</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>West</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Effect of varenicline on smoking cessation through smoking reduction: a randomized clinical trial. <italic>JAMA</italic>. <year>2015</year>;313(7):687-694. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Nollen</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahluwalia</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanderson Cox</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of racial differences in pharmacotherapy efficacy for smoking cessation: secondary analysis of the EAGLES randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e2032053</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.32053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33464316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33464316</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keely</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niaura</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ossip-Klein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Measures of abstinence in clinical trials: issues and recommendations</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1462220031000070552</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12745503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12745503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baker TB, Piper ME, Smith SS, Bolt DM, Stein JH, Fiore MC. Effects of combined varenicline with nicotine patch and of extended treatment duration on smoking cessation: a randomized clinical trial. <italic>JAMA</italic>. 2021;326(15):1485–1493. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.15333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Plebani</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></string-name></person-group>, Rennert L, <person-group><string-name><surname>Pettinati</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name></person-group>, O’Brien CP, Kampman KM. Results from a pilot clinical trial of varenicline for the treatment of alcohol dependence. <italic>Drug Alcohol Depend</italic>. <year>2013</year>;133(2):754-758. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.06.019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krishnan-Sarin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Effect of transdermal nicotine replacement on alcohol responses and alcohol self-administration. <italic>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</italic>. <year>2008</year>;196(2):189-200. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-007-0952-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quijano-Carde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Biasi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nicotinic mechanisms modulate ethanol withdrawal and modify time course and symptoms severity of simultaneous withdrawal from alcohol and nicotine</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2327</fpage>-<lpage>2336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2015.80</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25790020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25790020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">US Food and Drug Administration. FDA drug safety communication: FDA updates label for stop smoking drug Chantix (varenicline) to include potential alcohol interaction, rare risk of seizures, and studies of side effects on mood, behavior, or thinking. Updated February 26, 2018. Accessed February 2, 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/fda-drug-safety-communication-fda-updates-label-stop-smoking-drug-chantix-varenicline-include" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/fda-drug-safety-communication-fda-updates-label-stop-smoking-drug-chantix-varenicline-include</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>De Bejczy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lof</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Varenicline for treatment of alcohol dependence: a randomized, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2189</fpage>-<lpage>2199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.12854</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26414337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of varenicline in patients with severe alcohol dependence: a pilot double-blind randomized and controlled study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCP.0000000000001056</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31188242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31188242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r51">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rollema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The contribution of agonist and antagonist activities of α4β2* nAChR ligands to smoking cessation efficacy: a quantitative analysis of literature data</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>235</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2479</fpage>-<lpage>2505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-018-4921-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29980822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29980822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r52">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Govind</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Selective and regulated trapping of nicotinic receptor weak base ligands and relevance to smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>e25651</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.25651</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28718768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28718768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r53">
                <label>53</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ebbert</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Combination pharmacotherapy for stopping smoking: what advantages does it offer?</article-title><source>Drugs</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>643</fpage>-<lpage>650</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11536100-000000000-00000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20394453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20394453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r54">
                <label>54</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Doyon</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostroumov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dani</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Potential substrates for nicotine and alcohol interactions: a focus on the mesocorticolimbic dopamine system</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1181</fpage>-<lpage>1193</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2013.07.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23876345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23876345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi220053r55">
                <label>55</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ashare</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlienz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duerr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Making lemonade from SARS coronavirus–2 lemons: transitioning a smoking cessation trial to a virtual platform</article-title>. <source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<elocation-id>108100</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2020.108100</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32811627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32811627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI220053-1">
              <supplementary-material id="note-ZOI220053-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Trial Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-s001.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>eMethods. </bold>Randomization, Blinding, and Bioverification of Self-reported Smoking Status</p>
                  <p>
eReferences
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-s002.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e220951-s003.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
