<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T02:40:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9884574" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:9884574</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-01-30</datestamp>
        <setSpec>phebmjpg</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjopen</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC9884574</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9884574</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">9884574</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693691</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693691</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2022-065032</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-065032</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Sports and Exercise Medicine</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>1506</subject>
                  <subject>2474</subject>
                  <subject>1736</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <series-title>Protocol</series-title>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effects of a 12-week, seated, virtual, home-based tele-exercise programme compared with a prerecorded video-based exercise programme in people with chronic neurological impairments: protocol for a randomised controlled trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-98489505" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Divecha</surname>
                    <given-names>Ayushi A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-98489506" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bialek</surname>
                    <given-names>Amy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-98489507" contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9305-2982</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kumar</surname>
                    <given-names>Devina S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-98489508" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Garn</surname>
                    <given-names>Rachel M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-98489509" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Currie</surname>
                    <given-names>Lydia E J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-98489510" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Campos</surname>
                    <given-names>Talita</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-87953082" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9538-9228</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Friel</surname>
                    <given-names>Kathleen M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Burke Neurological Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">White Plains</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New York</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">School of Medicine</institution>, <institution>State of New York Upstate Medical University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Syracuse</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">NY</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">School of Nursing</institution>, <institution>Columbia University Irving Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">New York</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">NY</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Brain and Mind Research Institute</institution>, <institution>Weill Cornell Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">New York</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New York</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Kathleen M Friel; <email>kaf3001@med.cornell.edu</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>13</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <elocation-id>e065032</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <ali:free_to_read/>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-01-24">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032.pdf"/>
              <self-uri content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032.reviewer_comments.pdf"/>
              <self-uri content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032.draft_revisions.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>Exercise is vital to staying well and preventing secondary complications in people with chronic neurological impairments (CNI). Appropriate exercise is often inaccessible to this population. The purpose of the study is to investigate the effects of a seated, virtual exercise programme on heart rate, recovery, fatigue, pain, motivation, enjoyment and quality of life in people with CNI.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods and analysis</title>
                  <p>Individuals with CNI will be screened for eligibility, and 60 participants will be randomised 1:1 into either a live or prerecorded group. There is no geographical limitation to where participants reside, since participation is virtual. The study will be coordinated by one site in White Plains, New York, USA. The live group will exercise with an instructor via Zoom while the prerecorded group will exercise at their chosen time using prerecorded videos, 3×/week for 12 weeks. Primary outcome measures: change in heart rate during exercise/recovery. Secondary outcome measures: fatigue, motivation, level of pain and exertion, physical well-being, enjoyment of physical activity, motivation and quality of life. Outcomes will be assessed at baseline, midpoint, end of study and 1-month poststudy. Adverse events, medication changes and physical activity will be tracked throughout. Within-group and between-group comparisons will be performed by using analysis of covariance and regression.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
                  <p>BRANY IRB approval: 22 September 2020, protocol #20-08-388-512. All participants will provide written informed consent. Results will be disseminated through presentations, publications and ClinicalTrials.gov.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration number</title>
                  <p><ext-link xlink:href="NCT04564495" ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov">NCT04564495</ext-link>.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Rehabilitation medicine</kwd>
                <kwd>Neurology</kwd>
                <kwd>Telemedicine</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group id="funding-1">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) of the National Institutes of Health (NIH)</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>UL1 TR 002384</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="funding-2">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100009357</institution-id>
                      <institution>Burke Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>N/A</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="funding-3">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Sabrina Cohen Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>N/A</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>special-feature</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>unlocked</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>access-type</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>free</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float">
              <caption>
                <title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title>
              </caption>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>This study will use a comprehensive set of physiological and behavioural assessments to assess effects of exercise.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The virtual design of the study enables people to participate without commuting to our institute.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>For those participants with limited technological experience, difficulty using blood pressure devices and heart rate monitors will cause missing data values.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The virtual design of the study prohibits hands-on evaluations.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </boxed-text>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Exercise is a vital component to staying well and preventing secondary impairments. Exercise is known to positively influence a range of factors including cardiovascular health, cognition, mental health, bone health, sleep and quality of life, among many others.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1–8</xref> The benefits of exercise are further amplified in the estimated one billion people worldwide with chronic (&gt;6 months) neurological impairments (CNI), as the injuries often lead to sedentary lifestyles and thus higher rates of obesity and cardiovascular disease.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref> Incorporating an exercise regimen is vital to preventing secondary complications such as muscular weakness, fatigue, limited mobility, pain, spasticity, bone loss and increased risk of fractures, falls, diabetes, depression and obesity.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8 12 13</xref> Exercise can be neuroprotective and neuroregenerative by increasing neurotrophic factors, which are involved in neuroprotection, neuroplasticity and maintenance of neuronal health.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 14–18</xref> Exercise can also improve muscle strength and bone integrity in people with CNI.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref></p>
              <p>People with CNI often cannot access community exercise centres, as mobility can be more difficult, insurance payments sparse, centres not welcoming or accessible and assistive exercise equipment too costly for most facilities.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22–35</xref></p>
              <p>Another key barrier to exercise for people with CNI is transportation.<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Although COVID-19 introduced many new barriers to community participation, it also had some silver linings for people with CNI. COVID-19 resulted in the emergence of many new Zoom or online classes tailored to people with CNI, which removed the barrier of transportation.</p>
              <p>Although there has been an explosion of virtual-based exercise opportunities since 2020, much is unknown regarding optimal delivery models to bring exercise to people with CNI. Two general types of virtual exercise delivery models exist. In synchronous exercise, one or more participants join a virtual space via videoconferencing, and interact with the trainer in real time. Synchronous exercise enables the trainer to provide feedback as participants exercise. In contrast, in asynchronous exercise, trainers record instructional videos, which participants complete on their own time, without being in the same virtual space with the trainer at the same time. Asynchronous exercise provides scheduling flexibility to participants but does not allow for real time interaction and feedback from the trainer. There has only been one study directly comparing synchronous versus asynchronous exercise training in people with CNI.</p>
              <p>In a recent study, 40 adults with spinal cord injury were randomised to either synchronous or asynchronous tele-exercise. While there was no significant difference in average daily workload between the interventions, the synchronous tele-exercise found significantly higher values for adherence and successful data recording of the exercise, resulting in greater weekly training loads.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Virtual exercise platforms are part of society even as the pandemic wanes. Thus, it is important to determine optimal delivery models for specific groups of participants.</p>
              <p>This study will examine the cardiovascular benefits, as well as differences in compliance, motivation and feelings of socialisation and exertion between synchronous and asynchronous classes. The classes will be held for 12 weeks, 3 times/week using seated exercise via Zoom. The instructor will remain the same and alternate between boxing, high intensity interval training (HIIT) and power posture classes. We will examine the potential benefits of an accessible form of exercise for a population that is in urgent need. Additionally, by comparing synchronous and asynchronous classes, we will compare user compliance, motivation, enjoyment and socialisation.</p>
              <p>We hypothesise that individuals in the synchronous class will have better attendance, more robust exertion as measured by heart rate (HR) and better enjoyment than people in the asynchronous class, due to the social component of the synchronous classes. We hypothesise that participants in both groups will show improvement in HR recovery, physical wellness, quality of life, enjoyment and motivation/engagement, and that changes will be greater in the synchronous class due to consistent supervision and contact.</p>
              <sec id="s1-1">
                <title>Methods and analysis</title>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-2">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This study is a parallel randomised controlled trial to investigate the effects of a 12-week, 3 times/week, seated tele-exercise programme for adults with CNI (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). All 36 exercise sessions will be completed online via Zoom with the physical exercise instructor (live, synchronous group) or offline using recorded videos (prerecorded, asynchronous group). Participants will be in their own homes as they complete the exercise classes. Participants can continue their medications, physical, occupational, speech therapies and existing exercise routines (two times/week or fewer).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Study flow diagram. BP, blood pressure; HR, heart rate.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032f01" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-3">
                <title>Eligibility criteria and participants</title>
                <p>The eligibility criteria will be kept broad to accommodate all neurological impairments.</p>
                <p>Inclusion criteria:</p>
                <list list-type="order">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Participants diagnosed with chronic (&gt;6 months) neurological impairments.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Ages 18–75 years.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Able to sit for at least 1 hour.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Stable HR and blood pressure (BP)</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Medical clearance to participate in moderate intensity exercises.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Can don and doff a wrist HR monitor with or without assistance.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Can maintain daily exercise and physical activity during the study.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>No other neurological, medical or cognitive impairments.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Able to access the internet and use the cloud-based Zoom conference platform.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Ability to speak and understand English.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Currently exercising 2 days or less per week.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Presence of caregiver or supervisor during exercise, for safety.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
                <p>Exclusion criteria:</p>
                <list list-type="order">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Unstable or uncontrolled medical conditions.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Medical issues preventing safe participation.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Unable to follow simple two-step commands.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-4">
                <title>Number of participants</title>
                <p>We plan to conduct multiple cohorts of participants, each with different participant populations, for example, multiple sclerosis, cerebral palsy, stroke, spinal cord injury.</p>
                <p>For each cohort, with 27 participants in the synchronous and asynchronous groups, we will have 80% power to detect a change in maximum HR during exercise from about 80 bpm to 100 bpm (or greater), from the first session to the last session of the intervention. This calculation assumes a conservative SD of the pre/post differences in HR of 35 bpm. We plan for a 30% drop-out rate, which is an estimate based on our feasibility pilot study (Current status of the study), which means that we will recruit 35 participants per group to achieve 80% power.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-5">
                <title>Recruitment</title>
                <p>Participants will be recruited via the Sabrina Cohen Foundation, which has a network of people with CNI, and by the Burke Neurological Institute (BNI), who has a database of potential participants from prior studies or programmes. We will also post our recruitment flier on our website, social media and will mail it to neurological patient advocacy groups. We will send the study flier to all above mentioned entities, without prioritising any database or group over another. If we cannot recruit appropriate numbers using these methods, we will pursue paid advertising in our community.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-6">
                <title>Randomisation</title>
                <p>A person not affiliated with the study will generate a series of permuted randomised blocks in a computerised spreadsheet with a defined block size of 4. Participants will be allocated to either the live (synchronous) or prerecorded (asynchronous) group, with a 1:1 ratio between groups. Due to the nature of the intervention, it is not possible to conceal allocation from the participants or the study team. However, the two groups will never interact with one another.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-7">
                <title>Blinding and rigour of data</title>
                <p>Due to the nature of the study, blinding of participants and study team members to group allocation will not be possible. All participants will complete the outcome surveys directly online, without input or assistance from the study team. HR data will be collected through a HR monitor that collects quantitative data without input or filtering by the study team.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-8">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p>The exercise intervention will be delivered by a trained professional who specialises in adaptive exercise for individuals with CNI. The instructor will structure each class to ensure standardisation in terms of class structure<underline>,</underline> including warm-up, cool-down, cues for recording HR during class, use of additional equipment and adherence to the general study protocol. The instructor has extensive experience in offering adaptations to exercises in a virtual setting. He offers alternative ways to perform the exercises, such that everyone in class will be able to fully participate safely.</p>
                <p>All participants, regardless of allocation to live or prerecorded groups, will participate in 45 min of aerobic exercise intervention, three times a week, for a period of 12 weeks. The overall exercise session will be up to 1 hour long to include measuring vitals, answering questions before/after sessions and rest breaks (if any). Two additional weeks will be provided for making up missed sessions, if applicable. Each intervention will be preceded by a warm up and followed by a cool-down period. All participants will be asked to document any adverse events and changes in medications before each session. The order of classes will be rotated. Individual aerobic interventions for the first cohort are described below and summarised in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Summary of exercise sessions</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minutes into session</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIIT</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boxing</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Power posture</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Warm up</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Warm up</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Warm up</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Intervals of 30 s high intensity movements, 1–2 min lower intensity</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Intervals of 30 s high intensity boxing movements, 1–2 min lower intensity</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stretching</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Fast paced movements targeting trunk, posture</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Stretching</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cool down</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cool down</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cool down</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">End</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">End</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">End</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T1_FN1">
                      <p>HIIT, high intensity interval training.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <sec id="s1-8-1">
                  <title>High intensity interval training</title>
                  <p>In HIIT sessions, participants will do repetitive bouts of high intensity exercises, with intermittent periods of rest or active recovery. Examples of high intensity movements used in these sessions include fast punching movements, repeatedly rapidly lifting one’s arms overhead (with or without weights, as tolerated by each participant) and abdominal crunches. The duration of each bout of high intensity is about 10–30 s. Since this study will include participants with variable neurological impairments, the upper limit of exercise intensity in HIIT will be dependent on instructor’s judgement, participant feedback, rate of perceived exertion (RPE) and any exercise HR restrictions given by their doctor in the medical screening.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s1-8-2">
                  <title>Boxing</title>
                  <p>In boxing sessions, participants will do a circuit of individual and combinations of various arm strikes and punches. Boxing is a moderate to high intensity aerobic activity by nature. During the session, participants will do bouts of high intensity movements, similar to HIIT, along with periods of lower intensity arm movements such as practising defensive blocks of punches from an imaginary boxing opponent. The exercise intensity for boxing, as in HIIT, will be subjective for participants based on level of perceived exertion as well as exercise HR restrictions, if any.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s1-8-3">
                  <title>Power posture</title>
                  <p>Power posture is a HIIT-style strength and endurance class in which participants will move in ways that train trunk stability and control of sitting with correct posture. In these sessions, there will be a warm up period of 5–10 min, focused on slow, gentle repetitions to prepare the trapezius and other supporting scapular muscles for movement. This workout will target postural form, with fast paced targeted movements for 10–15 min. After the fast-paced movements, a cool-down period will focus on gentle deep neck flexor/extensor chin tuck exercises, range of motion and stretching.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-9">
                <title>Virtual nature of the study</title>
                <p>Each aspect of this study will be performed virtually. Screenings will be performed on the telephone, with a standard list of criteria asked of each person. If deemed eligible, the potential participant will be sent a Zoom link to go through the informed consent on a one-to-one basis. The informed consent will be uploaded to REDCap, a secure web application for building and managing online surveys and databases. REDCap is 21 CFR part 11-ready and HIPAA compliant and is specifically geared to support online and offline data capture for research studies and operations.</p>
                <p>To obtain informed consent directly from participants, a study team member will arrange a Zoom call with each participant. The informed consent will be signed virtually by sharing a virtual remote with the participant during the call. If anyone has difficulty, they can be sent the informed consent from REDCap via email and return it to REDCap just as easily. Each participant will be sent a copy of their signed consent form via the same REDCap email system (see <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental material for a sample consent form</xref>).</p>
                <supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-065032.supp1</object-id>
                  <label>Supplementary data</label>
                  <p>
                    <inline-supplementary-material id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
                  </p>
                </supplementary-material>
                <p>Each participant will be mailed a home exercise kit, which will contain a Polar optical HR monitor (OH1), BP monitor, yellow and green resistance TheraBands and wrist weights.</p>
                <p>After the home kits have been received by the participants and before the intervention begins, we will hold a series or training videoconferencing calls to acquaint participants with the study procedures and the use of all devices.</p>
                <p>Polar OH1 HR monitor: We will train participants in donning/doffing the HR monitor, using the Polar app, using their Polar accounts, syncing the Polar devices with their smartphones and starting/ending their HR tracking during exercise sessions.</p>
                <p>BP monitor: We will send each participant a commercially available automatic BP monitor. We will train each person to use it, and we have embedded an instructional video into the REDCap data entry form on which participants will input their BP.</p>
                <p>Checking compliance: After each session, a study team member will review each participant’s data entry forms and synching of their HR data with the Polar app. For the synchronous group, this will occur before the participant leaves the session. For the asynchronous group, this will occur within 1 day of when the participant completes the session.</p>
                <p>All questionnaires and questions to be answered before and after each class will be sent from and stored on REDCap. All HR data will be transmitted to the Polar website, which can be accessed only by the participant or the researchers. Then, the data will be analysed in MATLAB using custom scripts written by the study team.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-10">
                <title>Study safety</title>
                <p>We will monitor side effects before and after each session by having participants complete surveys on REDCap. If pain or BP are higher than usual, we will ask the participant if they wish to continue. If BP rises near limitations prescribed by a participant’s doctor, we will discontinue the participant. If any injury occurs during or outside of study sessions that may increase the risk of further injury, we will discontinue the participant.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-11">
                <title>Patient and public involvement</title>
                <p>Persons with disabilities were involved in the design of this study, and will be involved in the conduct, reporting and dissemination plans of this research. Our pilot study participants provided constructive feedback on the study, in surveys and in a zoom discussion group after they completed the study. Our class instructor owns and operated an adaptive gym for people with disabilities, and received feedback from his clients when designing the exercise classes. We will continue to involve these people as we complete the study, through regular meetings and surveys.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-12">
                <title>Strategies to improve adherence</title>
                <p>In this study, adherence is defined as the number of sessions a participant completed. The study team will take attendance at each synchronous session and will monitor session completions for the asynchronous group. Completion for the asynchronous group will be monitored via REDCap. Each time a person completes a data entry form before and after the session, it will be automatically saved and time stamped in REDCap.</p>
                <p>If a participant misses a class, we will reach out and inquire about their ability to attend future sessions. We have a priori set a minimum number of 30 of 36 classes that a participant must attend to be included in the main analyses of the study. We will offer 2 weeks of makeup sessions at the end of the 12 weeks. If a participant drops out before completing 30 sessions, we will encourage them to complete the poststudy outcome measures and the satisfaction survey. We will use the number of sessions completed as a covariate in the analyses.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-13">
                <title>Outcome measures</title>
                <p>All outcome measures are summarised in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Outcome measures</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Primary outcome measure</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Measure</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modality assessed</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method of Ascertainment</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time points</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Peak heart rate</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular function</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar OH1/Polar Beat app</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Secondary outcome measures</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Measure</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modality assessed</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method of ascertainment</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time points</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Demographics</td>
                        <td align="char" char="hyphen" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before first session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Attendance</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adherence</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap time stamps</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Baseline heart rate</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular function</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar OH1/Polar Beat app</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart rate at end of session</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular function</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar OH1/Polar Beat app</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart rate recovery</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular function</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar OH1/Polar Beat app</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Blood pressure</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular function</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Automatic BP device</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before and after each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rate of perceived exertion</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiopulmonary fitness</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before and after each session</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Perceived Wellness Survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wellness</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline, weeks 6, 12, 16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enjoyment of exercise</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline, weeks 6, 12, 16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Short Form-36</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical and mental health</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline, weeks 6, 12, 16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Numerical Pain Rating Scale</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline, weeks 6, 12, 16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Reason for Exercise Inventory</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motivation to exercise</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline, weeks 6, 12, 16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Participant Feedback Survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participant satisfaction</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REDCap survey</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">End of study or at dropout</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T2_FN1">
                      <p>BP, blood pressure.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-14">
                <title>Demographics</title>
                <p>We will collect the following demographics by having each participant complete a demographics data entry form on REDCap: age, gender, neurological diagnosis, time of diagnosis and comorbid health issues (eg, diabetes, high BP). We will also document whether a person needs assistance with walking or transfers. In addition, we will require each participant to receive written medical clearance by their doctor to participate in the study, and if any exercise restrictions need to be followed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-15">
                <title>Primary outcome measure: peak HR during exercise</title>
                <p>Continuous HR tracking is the primary outcome measure for the study. All participants will receive the OH1 Polar HR monitor as part of their exercise kit for the study (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>). The Polar OH1 (Polar Electro, Bethpage, New York, USA) is an optical HR sensor on an armband that records HR activity. It has six LED sensors that record at 1 s intervals.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> HR activity is recorded via Bluetooth to a phone compatible with the Polar Flow or Polar Beat app. It has validity in moderate to vigorous intensity exercises and high endurance sports activities.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38–40</xref></p>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Polar OH1 heart rate monitor. (A) Picture of the monitor and charger. (B) Proper placement of the monitor, with the device on the forearm. (C) The polar beat APP on a smart phone streams data in real time from the OH1 monitor via Bluetooth. (D) After a session, data are Retrievable from the polar coach website, where it is exported to a CSV file and processed in Matlab. CSV, comma-separated values.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032f02" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Immediately before each exercise session, participants will turn on their OH1 monitor. Then, the participant will open the Polar Beat app on their smart phone and hit ‘start’ when the exercise session begins. The Polar OH1 continuously records HR at 10 Hz when the device is powered on and the Polar Beat app recording has been started. Participants will record HR through the entire exercise session and for 10 min after completion of the session to capture HR during exercise as well as HR recovery for 10 min after the end of exercise sessions. The live group will be supervised by the research team for each session. The prerecorded groups will have the research team available for assistance and troubleshooting. Data are stored on the Polar Coach website, where study staff can export sessions as CSV files that are then processed in MATLAB (MathWorks). In MATLAB, peak HR (primary measure) will be calculated.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-16">
                <title>Secondary outcome measures</title>
                <sec id="s1-16-1">
                  <title>Measures acquired at each exercise session</title>
                  <p>We will calculate secondary measures of HR in MATLAB using the same Polar comma-separated values (CSV) files mentioned above: baseline HR, HR at end of session, and HR at 30 s intervals for 10 min after the end of the session will be analysed, to measure HR recovery.</p>
                  <p>At each session, participants will complete an online assessment to RPE, BP, HR and adverse events before and after the exercise session. Additionally, as described above, attendance will be taken at each session as a measure of adherence. After the session is over, participants will complete a lab-developed survey to rate their experience on a 10-point scale from 1 (not a good experience) to 10 (very good experience) on questions related to motivation, energy, satisfaction and performance. In addition, participants will provide information on changes related to health, falls or other adverse events.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s1-16-2">
                  <title>Measures acquired at specified times during the intervention</title>
                  <p>A comprehensive set of secondary outcome measures will be completed by participants at baseline, mid-study (6 weeks), end of study (12 weeks) and follow-up after 1 month. All questionnaires will be self-administered or administered by a trained researcher virtually using REDCap.</p>
                  <p>Perceived Wellness Survey (PWS): Participants will quantify their perceived health status by completing the PWS. The PWS is a 36-item instrument used to measure an individual’s perceived health status in physical, psychological, emotional, intellectual, spiritual and social wellness constructs. Items under each construct are scored on a scale of 1 (very strongly disagree) to 6 (very strongly agree). Higher scores indicate better perceived wellness. The PWS has good reliability and validity in healthy and neurological populations.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41–43</xref></p>
                  <p>Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (PACES): The PACES is a self-assessment measure of enjoyment with their current physical activity. It is an 18-item scale with scoring from 1 (I enjoy it) to 7 (I hate it). Scores on the bipolar rating scale are summed with higher scores indicative of more enjoyment. It is reliable and valid in neurological populations.<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44–47</xref></p>
                  <p>Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36): The SF-36 measures physical health and mental health. There are eight scales-Physical Functioning, Physical Role Limitations, Bodily Pain, General Health, Vitality, Social Functioning, Emotional Role Limitations, and Mental Health. It is easy to use with good validity and reliability in neurological populations.<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48–51</xref></p>
                  <p>Numerical Pain Rating (NPR) scale: The NPR is a standardised instrument for pain assessment in clinical and research practice. It is an 11-point scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (the most intense pain) at rest and during movement. It is simple to use with high sensitivity to changes in chronic pain in adult populations.<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52 53</xref> It is reliable and valid for pain assessments of neurological populations.<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></p>
                  <p>Borg’s RPE: The Borg RPE is a widely used standardised measure to evaluate perceived intensity of exertion, effort and fatigue during physical exercise. The scale ranges from 6 (no exertion at all) to 20 (absolute maximum). Higher ratings on the scale indicate greater overall body exertion. It is a reliable and valid measure in neurological populations.<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55–62</xref></p>
                  <p>Reason for exercise inventory (REI): The REI is a 24-item scale to assess the reason that motivates a person to exercise. The modified version has four subscales: Weight/appearance management, fitness/health management, stress/emotion management, and socialisation. A 7-point scale ranges from 1 (not at all important) to 7 (extremely important). Higher scores represent greater motivation to exercise.<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></p>
                  <p>Participant feedback: On study completion, or when withdrawn/dropped out from the study, participants will complete a study feedback form. The feedback will be based on study acceptance, ease of using HR and BP devices and exercise equipment, and support from the research team. Participants who do not complete the study will also provide their final timepoint measure at the end of their final exercise session.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-17">
                <title>Statistical methods</title>
                <p>Descriptive statistics (including mean, SD, median, IQR, frequency and percent) will be calculated for demographic and clinical characteristics of the study participants. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to evaluate the independent effect of synchronous versus asynchronous group status on change in peak HR (first session vs final session), after controlling for baseline HR and any other factors that may remain imbalanced between groups after randomisation. Adjusted mean differences in peak HR (first session vs final session) between the synchronous and asynchronous groups and 95% CIs for these differences will be estimated from the multivariable ANCOVA model. Similar analyses as described above will be performed for other continuous outcomes (primary and secondary), including Borg’s RPE scale, mood, motivation and pain scales, PWS, SF-36v2 score and PACES score. Categorical variables (eg, safety questions, adverse events, medication changes) will be compared between the synchronous and asynchronous groups (at baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks) by the χ<sup>2</sup> test or Fisher’s exact test, as appropriate. Generalised estimating equations modelling will also be explored to evaluate between-group differences over repeated assessments, and to account for potential missing data in some of the outcome variables at one or more of the evaluation time points. All estimates from the multivariable models will serve as preliminary data (ie, hypothesis-generating) for future studies. All p values will be two sided with statistical significance evaluated at the 0.05 alpha level. Ninety-five per cent CIs for all parameters of interest will be calculated to assess the precision of the obtained estimates. All analyses will be performed in R and SPSS v.26 by a person blinded to treatment allocation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-18">
                <title>Data management</title>
                <p>Participant identifying information will be kept confidential by providing a unique identification number (ID number) for the course of the study. To maintain privacy, only authorised research investigators involved in the study will have access to participant information. Password protected laptops, online documents and access to cloud-based servers will prevent leaks in data privacy. All records including informed consent, screening tools, medical records and participant surveys will be completed, and documented on REDCap, a Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA)-compliant online research database.</p>
                <p>Privacy on Zoom platform: Our institutional Zoom account (through Weill Cornell Medicine) is compliant with HIPAA guidelines. Participant profile names will be updated to display their ID. After each session, the recorded video will be uploaded to the password protected WCM cloud-based server. Respective group participants will be given the live Zoom links (synchronous) or passwords to access the asynchronous Zoom sessions.</p>
                <p>Polar OH1 HR monitor (Optical HR sensor): Participants’ profiles using allotted ID’s will be created in the Polar Beat App and the Flow for Coach cloud-based online platform. All information uploaded to the platform will be accessible by the investigators using a secured login ID and password.</p>
                <p>Adverse events, change in medications and protocol deviation will be documented and updated before and after each class on REDCap. The study team will perform weekly self-audits to ensure data quality and completeness.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-19">
                <title>Procedure for handling missing data</title>
                <p>This study is an intention-to-treat trial. If data are missing, we will use a mixed linear regression model that accounts for uneven numbers of data points across participants.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-20">
                <title>Data monitoring and stopping rules</title>
                <p>Since this is a low-risk study, our IRB determined that a data monitoring committee is not necessary. We will audit our data weekly and assess safety data at each session. If we find an increase in pain by 25% or a decrease in quality of life measures by 25% across participants in a cohort, we will pause the trial and evaluate how to improve the safety of the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-21">
                <title>Current status of the study</title>
                <p>We have performed a feasibility cohort, with people with a range of abilities and diagnoses. The first participant was consented on 22 January 2021, for an intervention that began on 24 March 2021 and ended on 28 June 2021. In this feasibility study, we determined that participants could readily complete the online assessments, exercise sessions and could effectively use Zoom, the Polar OH1 sensor and Polar Beat app, and the BP measurement device. Our next step will be to enrol separate cohorts of people with specific neurological diagnoses, such as cerebral palsy, stroke and multiple sclerosis. This will begin in 2023.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-22">
                <title>Resource sharing plan</title>
                <p>We plan to use the concept, methods and analysis as a framework to develop evidence-based protocols for future cohorts and studies. We have made a commitment to publish all relevant scientific information in a timely manner. Unpublished information may be available to interested individuals or organisations by request to the principal investigator.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s1-23">
                <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
                <p>The study was approved by the BRANY Institutional Review Board on 22 September 2020, protocol #20-08-388-512. All study participants will provide written informed consent before participation. All protocol deviations, adverse events and protocol modifications will be reported to the IRB immediately. The results of the study will be disseminated to the academic community via publications and presentations. The deidentified study data will be shared on our laboratory website. The trial is registered at Clinicaltrials.gov, number NCT04564495.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e178">
                <caption>
                  <title>Reviewer comments</title>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032.reviewer_comments.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e179">
                <caption>
                  <title>Author's
manuscript</title>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-065032.draft_revisions.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>We thank the Sabrina Cohen Foundation for funding and for commitment to assist with study development and recruitment. We thank Devon Palermo at DPI Adaptive Fitness who will serve as the adaptive fitness instructor for this study.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> KMF is the principal investigator. KMF, AAD and AB were responsible for ethics applications and reporting. AAD, AB, DSK, RMG, LEJC, TC and KMF drafted the final version of this manuscript. All authors have contributed to the writing and critical review of the manuscript and have approved the final version.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work is supported by funding from the Sabrina Cohen Foundation and the Burke Foundation. This work is supported by grant number UL1 TR 002384 from the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). The Sabrina Cohen Foundation has established the tele-exercise classes we are studying and will assist with recruitment.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> The Sabrina Cohen Foundation and Burke Foundation will have no role in data collection, analyses, interpretation, or publication of the work.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to the Methods section for further details.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec sec-type="ethics-statement">
              <title>Ethics statements</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Patient consent for publication</title>
                <p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not applicable.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gkotzamanis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magriplis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panagiotakos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of physical activity interventions on cognitive function of older adults: a systematic review of clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Psychiatriki</source><year>2022</year>; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22365/jpsych.2022.060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>IGM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van der Kolk</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic exercise alters brain function and structure in Parkinson’s disease: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Annals of Neurology</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.26291</pub-id>
<comment>Available</comment>: <uri xlink:href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/toc/15318249/91/2">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/toc/15318249/91/2</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34951063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Social interaction, lifestyle, and depressive status: mediators in the longitudinal relationship between cognitive function and instrumental activities of daily living disability among older adults</article-title>. <source>IJERPH</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>4235</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19074235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35409918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Minto</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <comment>n.d.</comment><article-title>Impact of cardiovascular risk factors on the relationships of physical activity with mood and cognitive function in a diverse sample</article-title>. <source>Aging, Neuropsychology, and Cognition</source><volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13825585.2022.2071414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rosado</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raimundo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of two 24-week multimodal exercise programs on reaction time, mobility, and Dual-task performance in community-dwelling older adults at risk of falling: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>Suppl 2</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-10448-x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schuch</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vancampfort</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and incident depression: a meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>175</volume>:<fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2018.17111194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29690792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Exercise training improves sleep quality in middle-aged and older adults with sleep problems: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Physiother</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1836-9553(12)70106-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22884182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The roles of exercise in bone remodeling and in prevention and treatment of osteoporosis</article-title>. <source>Prog Biophys Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbiomolbio.2015.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility, acceptability, and fidelity of physical activity routines after stroke (PARAS): a multifaceted behaviour change intervention targeting free-living physical activity and sedentary behaviour in community-dwelling adult stroke survivors</article-title>. <source>Pilot Feasibility Stud</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>197</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40814-022-01139-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36057723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gormley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The risk, burden, and management of non-communicable diseases in cerebral palsy: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>753</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.13737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29572812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zwierzchowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosołek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Forced sedentariness and sports activity as factors differentiating anthropometric characteristics, indices, and body composition in people with disabilities</article-title>. <source>Biology</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>906</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology11060906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35741427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jasińska-Mikołajczyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drews</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domaszewska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of physical activity on neurotrophin concentrations and cognitive control in patients with a depressive episode</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>777394</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.777394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35546921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lampousi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berglind</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forsell</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of changes in cardiorespiratory fitness with health-related quality of life in young adults with mobility disability: secondary analysis of a randomized controlled trial of mobile APP versus supervised training</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<elocation-id>1721</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-09830-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33198702</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dimyan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroplasticity in the context of motor rehabilitation after stroke</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2010.200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21243015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Knaepen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goekint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroplasticity - exercise-induced response of peripheral brain-derived neurotrophic factor: a systematic review of experimental studies in human subjects</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11534530-000000000-00000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20726622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Exercise intervention promotes the growth of synapses and regulates neuroplasticity in rats with ischemic stroke through exosomes</article-title>. <source>Front Neurol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>752595</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2021.752595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34777222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Penna</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramalho</surname><given-names>SHR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of aerobic physical exercise on neuroplasticity after stroke: systematic review</article-title>. <source>Arq Neuropsiquiatr</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>832</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0004-282X-ANP-2020-0551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34669820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Lifestyle modulators of neuroplasticity: how physical activity, mental engagement, and diet promote cognitive health during aging</article-title>. <source>Neural Plast</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<elocation-id>3589271</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/3589271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28695017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Legerlotz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of resistance training on health of children and adolescents with disabilities</article-title>. <source>Am J Lifestyle Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559827618759640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33281519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O’Connell</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coppinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of nutrition and physical activity in frailty: a review</article-title>. <source>Clin Nutr ESPEN</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clnesp.2019.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31987100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>van der Scheer</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin Ginis</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ditor</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exercise on fitness and health of adults with spinal cord injury: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733344</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coote</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Participant experiences of eight weeks of supervised or home-based Pilates among people with multiple sclerosis: a qualitative analysis</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>5549</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09638288.2021.1939446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34151667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Forgea</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and facilitators to engagement in rehabilitation among stroke survivors: an integrative review</article-title>. <source>Rehabil Nurs</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/RNJ.0000000000000340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34149000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casemore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing participation while aging with spinal cord injury: applying behaviour change frameworks to develop intervention recommendations</article-title>. <source>Spinal Cord</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41393-020-00555-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32989252</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hickingbotham</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowling</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and facilitators to physical education, sport, and physical activity program participation among children and adolescents with psychiatric disorders: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Transl Behav Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1739</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/tbm/ibab085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34166515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Karssemeijer</surname><given-names>EGA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Klijn</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bossers</surname><given-names>WJR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Ranking barriers, motivators, and facilitators to promote physical activity participation of persons with dementia: an explorative study</article-title>. <source>J Geriatr Phys Ther</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JPT.0000000000000210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30095552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keramat</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahammed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Disability, physical activity, and health-related quality of life in Australian adults: an investigation using 19 waves of a longitudinal cohort</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<elocation-id>e0268304</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0268304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35552556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haegele</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers, expectancy-value beliefs, and physical activity engagement among adults with visual impairments</article-title>. <source>Adapt Phys Activ Q</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/apaq.2019-0196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33631720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Fishing participation, motivators and barriers among UK anglers with disabilities: opportunities and implications for green social prescribing</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<elocation-id>4730</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19084730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35457597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brick</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and facilitators of physical activity in adolescents with intellectual disabilities: an analysis informed by the COM-B model</article-title>. <source>J Appl Res Intellect Disabil</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jar.12985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35229409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mckenzie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and facilitators of physical activity participation for young people and adults with childhood-onset physical disability: a mixed methods systematic review</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>914</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.14830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33559889</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nightingale</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heneghan</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>SAM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity and health-related quality of life in adults with a neurologically-related mobility disability during the COVID-19 pandemic: an exploratory analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Neurol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>699884</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2021.699884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34512516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>MRL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elmose-Østerlund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Motives and barriers related to physical activity and sport across social backgrounds: implications for health promotion</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<elocation-id>5810</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18115810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34071630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Perceived barriers to exercise in adults with traumatic brain injury vary by age</article-title>. <source>J Funct Morphol Kinesiol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<elocation-id>47</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jfmk3030047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33466976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Porteny</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alegría</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del Cueto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and strategies for implementing community-based interventions with minority elders: positive minds-strong bodies</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci Commun</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<elocation-id>41</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43058-020-00034-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32885198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schootemeijer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der Kolk</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and motivators to engage in exercise for persons with Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source>J Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JPD-202247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32925106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RRG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorneles</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veloso</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <comment>n.d.</comment><article-title>Synchronous and asynchronous tele-exercise during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic: comparisons of implementation and training load in individuals with spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>J Telemed Telecare</source><volume>2021</volume>:<fpage>1357633X2098273</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1357633X20982732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hermand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cassirame</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ennequin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of a photoplethysmographic heart rate monitor: polar OH1</article-title>. <source>Int J Sports Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0875-4033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31189190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hettiarachchi</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nahavandi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of polar OH1 optical heart rate sensor for moderate and high intensity physical activities</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<elocation-id>e0217288</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0217288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31120968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De La Rosa</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The polar ® OH1 optical heart rate sensor is valid during moderate-vigorous exercise</article-title>. <source>Sports Med Int Open</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>E67</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0631-0920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30539120</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hamdani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-stakeholder perspectives on perceived wellness of special olympics athletes</article-title>. <source>Disabil Health J</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dhjo.2019.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kaveh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostovarfar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keshavarzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of perceived wellness survey (PWS) in a sample of Iranian population</article-title>. <source>Malays J Med Sci</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21315/mjms2016.23.4.6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27660544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huggins</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The relationships between perceived wellness, sleep, and acute: chronic training load in national collegiate athletics association division I male soccer players</article-title>. <source>J Strength Cond Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1326</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JSC.0000000000004003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33677462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jekauc</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voelkle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Reliability, validity, and measurement invariance of the German version of the physical activity enjoyment scale</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Psychol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpepsy/jss088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22946084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring enjoyment of physical activity in older adults: invariance of the physical activity enjoyment scale (paces) across groups and time</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>103</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5868-8-103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21951520</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Murrock</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bekhet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zauszniewski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the physical activity enjoyment scale in adults with functional limitations</article-title>. <source>Issues Ment Health Nurs</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01612840.2015.1088904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26980666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teques</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calmeiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validation and adaptation of the physical activity enjoyment scale (PACES) in fitness group exercisers</article-title>. <source>J Sport Health Sci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jshs.2017.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32768128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laubscher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of the short form 36 (SF-36) health survey questionnaire among stroke patients</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1812</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.str.27.10.1812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8841336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validation and calibration of the SF-36 health transition question against an external criterion of clinical change in health status</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-009-9467-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rotstein</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Quality of life in multiple sclerosis: development and validation of the “ rays ” scale and comparison with the SF-36</article-title>. <source>Int J Qual Health Care</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intqhc/12.6.511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11202605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R51">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of the general module of the system of quality of life instruments for chronic diseases and its comparison with SF-36</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2010.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21530153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R52">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LaMoreaux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical importance of changes in chronic pain intensity measured on an 11-point numerical pain rating scale</article-title>. <source>Pain</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3959(01)00349-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11690728</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R53">
                <label>53</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sorkin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Neglected topics in chronic pain treatment outcome studies: determination of success</article-title>. <source>Pain</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3959(93)90049-U</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8316386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R54">
                <label>54</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Troxel</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validity, reliability, and clinical importance of change in a 0-10 numeric rating scale measure of spasticity: a post hoc analysis of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Clin Ther</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>974</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2008.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18555944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R55">
                <label>55</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Abadie</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of viewing the RPE scale on the ability to make ratings of perceived exertion</article-title>. <source>Percept Mot Skills</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/pms.1996.83.1.317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8873207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R56">
                <label>56</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A brief note on the validity and reliability of the rating of perceived exertion scale in monitoring exercise intensity among Chinese older adults in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Percept Mot Skills</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/29.PMS.121c24x8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26595201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R57">
                <label>57</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Compagnat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salle</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandigout</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Rating of perceived exertion with borg scale in stroke over two common activities of the daily living</article-title>. <source>Top Stroke Rehabil</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10749357.2017.1399229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29105582</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R58">
                <label>58</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsubaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between the borg scale rating of perceived exertion and leg-muscle deoxygenation during incremental exercise in healthy adults</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>1269</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-48238-1_15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33966201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R59">
                <label>59</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsubaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nashimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Face scale rating of perceived exertion during cardiopulmonary exercise test</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Sport Exerc Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<elocation-id>e000474</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2018-000474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R60">
                <label>60</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsubaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between the rating of perceived exertion scale and the load intensity of resistance training</article-title>. <source>Strength Cond J</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/SSC.0000000000000373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29674945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R61">
                <label>61</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Penko</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barkley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koop</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Borg scale is valid for ratings of perceived exertion for individuals with Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source>Int J Exerc Sci</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R62">
                <label>62</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hutsler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergsteinová</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The validity and reliability of a rating scale of perceived exertion</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports</source><year>1973</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4721013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R63">
                <label>63</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Novy</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Why do women exercise? factor analysis and further validation of the reasons for exercise inventory</article-title>. <source>Percept Mot Skills</source><year>1994</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/pms.1994.78.2.539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8022678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
