<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T06:44:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4291235" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4291235</identifier>
        <datestamp>2015-02-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jac</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Antimicrob Chemother</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Antimicrob. Chemother</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jac</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jac</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-7453</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2091</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4291235</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4291235</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4291235</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25281400</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dku382</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dku382</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Pharmacokinetics and safety of rifabutin in young HIV-infected children receiving rifabutin and lopinavir/ritonavir</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moultrie</surname>
                    <given-names>Harry</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McIlleron</surname>
                    <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sawry</surname>
                    <given-names>Shobna</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kellermann</surname>
                    <given-names>Tracy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wiesner</surname>
                    <given-names>Lubbe</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kindra</surname>
                    <given-names>Gurpreet</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gous</surname>
                    <given-names>Hermien</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Van Rie</surname>
                    <given-names>Annelies</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Wits Reproductive Health and HIV Institute</addr-line>, <institution>University of the Witwatersrand</institution>, <addr-line>Johannesburg</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff>
                <aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Department of Medicine</addr-line>, <institution>University of Cape Town</institution>, <addr-line>Cape Town</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff>
                <aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Epidemiology</addr-line>, <institution>University of North Carolina</institution>, <addr-line>Chapel Hill, NC</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Tel: +27-823311618; Fax: +27-116460712; E-mail: <email>moultrieh@gmail.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2015</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
              <volume>70</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>543</fpage>
              <lpage>549</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>12</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-request">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the British Society for Antimicrobial Chemotherapy.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="dku382.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>Co-treatment of HIV and TB in young children is complicated by limited treatment options and complex drug–drug interactions. Rifabutin is an alternative to rifampicin for adults receiving a ritonavir-boosted PI. We aimed to evaluate the short-term safety and pharmacokinetics of rifabutin when given with lopinavir/ritonavir in children.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Patients and methods</title>
                  <p>We conducted an open-label study of rifabutin dosed at 5 mg/kg three times a week in HIV-infected children ≤5 years of age receiving lopinavir/ritonavir. Intensive steady-state pharmacokinetic sampling was conducted after six doses. The Division of AIDS 2004, clarification 2009, table for grading severity of adverse events was used to classify drug toxicities. The study was registered with ClinicalTrials.gov, number NCT01259219.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Six children completed the study prior to closure by institutional review boards. The median (range) AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of rifabutin was 6.91 (3.52–8.67) μg · h/mL, the median (range) <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> of rifabutin was 0.39 (0.19–0.46) μg/mL, the median (range) AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin was 5.73 (2.85–9.13) μg · h/mL and the median (range) <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> of 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin was 0.17 (0.08–0.32) μg/mL. The neutrophil count declined in all children; two children experienced grade 4 neutropenia, which resolved rapidly without complications. There was strong correlation between AUC<sub>0–48</sub> measures and neutrophil counts.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Rifabutin dosed at 5 mg/kg three times per week resulted in lower AUC<sub>0–48</sub>, AUC<sub>0–24</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> values for rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin compared with adults receiving 150 mg of rifabutin daily, the current recommended dose. We observed high rates of severe transient neutropenia, possibly due to immaturity of CYP3A4 in young children. It remains unclear whether a safe and effective rifabutin dose exists for treatment of TB in children receiving lopinavir/ritonavir.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>treatment</kwd>
                <kwd>tuberculosis</kwd>
                <kwd>TB</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>TB is the commonest opportunistic infection in HIV-infected children, with almost one in three children in South Africa on TB treatment at the time of initiating combination ART (cART).<sup><xref rid="DKU382C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> While cART should be initiated as soon as TB treatment is tolerated, initiation of cART in young children on TB treatment is complicated by clinically significant drug–drug interactions between rifampicin and antiretroviral drugs, as well as limited paediatric drug formulations for concomitant TB and HIV treatment. In resource-poor countries, most adults with HIV/TB coinfection receive a combination of efavirenz-based cART and rifampicin-based TB treatment. Efavirenz is not recommended in children &lt;3 years of age despite recent FDA approval as there is considerable pharmacokinetic variability and data are limited.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> For children &lt;3 years with TB/HIV coinfection, the 2013 WHO guidelines recommend either a triple NRTI regimen or two NRTIs plus nevirapine in children co-treated with rifampicin-containing TB therapy.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> While no randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of these regimens have been performed in young HIV-infected children with active TB, data from studies in children without active TB suggest that both of these regimens are suboptimal. Two RCTs have demonstrated lower virological suppression rates in young children without TB when treated with nevirapine- compared with lopinavir/ritonavir-based cART.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Furthermore, there are concerns that co-treatment with rifampicin might result in a reduction in nevirapine concentrations in children.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The ARROW trial demonstrated significantly worse long-term viral load suppression rates in those children who were switched to a triple NRTI regimen 36 weeks after commencing a four-drug regimen consisting of nevirapine and three NRTIs.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The induction of hepatic and intestinal cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) and P-glycoprotein results in inadequate lopinavir exposure in children when lopinavir/ritonavir is administered at either standard or double dose together with rifampicin.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In South Africa, the recommended cART regimen for children &lt;3 years who receive concomitant treatment for TB is to add additional ritonavir such that the lopinavir/ritonavir ratio is increased from 4 : 1 to 1 : 1 together with two NRTIs.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> This regimen is also suboptimal as the short shelf life of ritonavir results in frequent stock outs and the palatability of ritonavir is poor.</p>
              <p>Rifabutin is recommended as an alternative to rifampicin to treat TB in combination with PI-containing cART in adults and was added to the WHO essential medicine list in 2009 for treatment of TB in HIV-infected adults treated with ritonavir-boosted PI-containing cART.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> In contrast to rifampicin, rifabutin induces the activity of CYP3A4 and P-glycoprotein to a limited extent and does not have clinically significant effects on the concentrations of concomitantly administered lopinavir/ritonavir.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> However, ritonavir-mediated CYP3A4 inhibition inhibits the metabolism of both rifabutin and its active metabolite, 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin and results in a substantial increase in exposure, necessitating a reduction in the dose of rifabutin.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Because of concerns of inadequate response associated with rifabutin dosed at 150 mg three times a week, the recommended dose of rifabutin in adults receiving concomitant ritonavir-boosted PI-based cART has recently been increased to 150 mg daily or 300 mg three times a week.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Safety data for concomitant administration of rifabutin and lopinavir/ritonavir in HIV-infected individuals in resource-limited settings are scarce. Haematological toxicities, most commonly neutropenia and thrombocytopenia, associated with rifabutin dose and/or coadministration of CYP3A4 inhibitors have been well described, though it remains unknown whether the occurrence of toxicities is associated with specific pharmacokinetic parameters.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="DKU382C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> While resolution is generally rapid after discontinuation of rifabutin, monitoring of haematological parameters is recommended. In addition, monitoring for uveitis is required.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Currently, the major obstacle to the use of rifabutin to treat TB in young HIV/TB-coinfected children receiving concomitant lopinavir/ritonavir is the absence of pharmacokinetic and safety data and no suitable paediatric formulation of rifabutin. We aimed to determine the optimal dosing strategy, pharmacokinetic profile and short-term safety of rifabutin when given concomitantly with a lopinavir/ritonavir-containing cART regimen in HIV-infected children ≤5 years of age in Soweto, South Africa.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>Patients and methods</title>
              <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Study design and treatment</title>
                <p>We conducted an open-label, adaptive study to determine the short-term safety and optimal dose of rifabutin when coadministered with lopinavir/ritonavir in young (age ≤5 years) HIV-infected children residing in a high TB/HIV burden, resource-limited setting. The optimal dose was defined as the dose that resulted in a geometric mean AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of 4.5–6 μg · h/mL, in keeping with the levels reported from studies in adults receiving 150 mg three times a week,<sup><xref rid="DKU382C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="DKU382C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> the recommended adult dose at the time of enrolment into the study.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> The initial rifabutin dose was selected based on the 150 mg used thrice weekly in adults adjusted for children based on their weight using the established scientific framework of an allometric scaling (clearance and volume having allometric exponents of 0.75 and 1, respectively<sup><xref rid="DKU382C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>). Accordingly, a 10 kg child would be expected to have approximately twice the clearance (per kilogram of body weight) of an adult, corresponding to approximately twice the per kilogram dose requirement in children aged 1–5 years. A rifabutin dose of 5 mg/kg three times per week thus was anticipated to correspond to the 150 mg three times a week rifabutin dose for adults when co-treated with lopinavir/ritonavir.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p>
                <p>Participating children received a total of six doses of 5 mg/kg rifabutin (three times a week on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays over a 2 week period). All children took the first dose of rifabutin on a Friday and the final dose on a Wednesday. The rifabutin suspension was compounded by research pharmacists using 150 mg Mycobutin<sup>®</sup> capsules, OraSure<italic><sup>®</sup></italic> and Orasweet<sup>®</sup>.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Since one anticipates minimal change in lopinavir exposures with the addition of rifabutin, lopinavir/ritonavir dosages were dosed twice daily according to the WHO weight bands and not altered during coadministration with rifabutin.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> The first and sixth doses of rifabutin were directly observed. Parents were telephonically contacted after all other rifabutin doses to confirm administration according to schedule. In addition, adherence to rifabutin and antiretroviral agents was assessed using diary cards and weighing of medicine bottles at dispensing and on return. A full medical history and clinical examination were conducted at screening, enrolment, the three consecutive pharmacokinetic sampling days (days 13, 14 and 15) and at the close-out visit, which was conducted between 2 and 4 weeks after the last dose.</p>
                <p>A data and safety monitoring board (DSMB) consisting of two independent South African infectious diseases paediatricians and an independent US-based pharmacologist was constituted and reviewed all serious adverse events and any grade 3 or 4 adverse events according to the NIAID Division of AIDS (DAIDS) 2004, clarification 2009, grading tables.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The study protocol mandated that enrolment would be halted if the DSMB determined that any serious adverse event, grade 3 or 4 adverse event or uveitis was related to rifabutin exposure. In that case, all pharmacokinetic samples already collected would be analysed and a DSMB review of all data would be conducted. In addition, an interim analysis of rifabutin pharmacokinetic parameters was planned after the first 10 children completed pharmacokinetic assessments in order to determine the final sample size.</p>
                <p>The study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committees of the University of the Witwatersrand and University of Cape Town and the Institutional Review Board of the University of North Carolina Chapel Hill. The study was registered with ClinicalTrials.gov, number NCT01259219. Written informed consent was obtained from the parents of all participating children.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2b">
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>HIV-infected children ≤5 years of age who had successfully completed a course of therapy for active TB within the past 2–6 weeks and who were receiving a cART regimen containing lopinavir/ritonavir at the Harriet Shezi Children's Clinic in Soweto were invited to participate. The requirement to have recently successfully completed a course of therapy, defined as completed a course with resolution of symptoms and signs, was instituted to reduce the risk that an HIV-infected child with untreated or undiagnosed active TB would be exposed to rifabutin monotherapy. To reduce potential risk associated with administration of rifabutin in the absence of direct benefit, children were excluded if they had a history of symptomatic clinical hepatitis during TB treatment, ALT &gt;2.5× the upper limit of normal (ULN), bilirubin &gt;1.5× ULN, creatinine &gt;1.1× ULN, haemoglobin &lt;8 g/dL, neutrophil &lt;1000 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>, platelets &lt;125 000 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>, any pre-existing eye condition at screening or required treatment with another drug with potential for interaction with rifabutin.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2c">
                <title>Pharmacokinetic and safety sampling</title>
                <p>Blood for safety parameters was drawn for full blood count, white blood cell differential count, liver function tests, bilirubin, urea, creatinine and electrolytes at screening and full blood count, white blood cell differential count and liver function tests at first scheduled pharmacokinetic visit. Children were screened for symptoms and signs of uveitis at every visit and were referred for slit lamp examination by an ophthalmologist if required. Serial blood samples for pharmacokinetic analysis were collected pre-dose (0 h) and at 2, 4, 9, 24 and 48 h after the observed administration of the sixth rifabutin dose. Samples were centrifuged at 2600 rpm for 10 min and plasma was extracted and stored at −70°C.</p>
                <p>Rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin were analysed with a validated LC/MS/MS assay. The samples were processed with a protein precipitation extraction method using 50 μL of plasma and 300 μL of acetonitrile. Rifaximin was used as an internal standard and was spiked into the precipitation solvent at a concentration of 100 ng/mL. Gradient chromatography was performed on a Phenomenex, Luna 5 μm PFP(2), 100 A, 50 mm×2 mm analytical column, using acetonitrile and 0.1% formic acid as mobile phase, and was delivered at a flow rate of 500 μL/min. An AB Sciex API 3200 mass spectrometer was operated at unit resolution in the multiple reaction monitoring mode, monitoring the transition of the protonated molecular ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 847.4 to the product ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 95.1 for rifabutin, the protonated molecular ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 805.4 to the product ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 95.1 for 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin and the protonated molecular ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 786.3 to the product ions <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 151.1 for the internal standard. The accuracies (%Nom) for rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin were between 99.1% and 109.0% at low, medium and high quality control (QC) levels during interbatch validation. The percentage coefficient of variation (%CV) for rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin during interbatch validation was &lt;9.2% at low, medium and high QC levels. The calibration range for rifabutin was between 3.91 ng/mL and 1000 ng/mL and for 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin the calibration range was between 0.780 ng/mL and 200 ng/mL.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2d">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Age- and sex-adjusted <italic>Z</italic>-scores for weight and height were calculated using WHO 2006 growth references.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Pharmacokinetic data were analysed in Stata 12.2 (StataCorp) using non-compartmental methods and the trapezoid rule to obtain the area under the curve from 0 to 24 h (AUC<sub>0–24</sub>) and from 0 to 48 h (AUC<sub>0–48</sub>), <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>max</sub> and elimination half-life. Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to assess the strength of correlation between the absolute neutrophil count (ANC) and pharmacokinetic parameters.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s3a">
                <title>Participant characteristics</title>
                <p>Between December 2010 and July 2011, informed consent was obtained for seven children; six were enrolled and one died of acute pneumonia prior to the screening visit. The median (range) age and weight of the children were 27 (10–41) months and 10.6 (8.8–12.2) kg, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKU382TB1">1</xref>). Three children had a history of WHO stage IV-defining conditions: two extrapulmonary TB and one confirmed cytomegalovirus infection without ocular involvement. Children had been on lopinavir/ritonavir-based cART for a median of 7 months (range 6–28) and had completed TB treatment a median of 4 weeks (range 3.9–5.7) prior to the first dose of rifabutin. The median CD4% at enrolment was 24.9% (range 15.3%–45.8%). HIV-1 RNA viral load on ART was available for four children; all had ≤400 copies/mL. All six children received daily co-trimoxazole prophylaxis according to South African guidelines.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Adherence to rifabutin as assessed by weighing of medicine containers was excellent with adherence ranging between 98% and 110% in the five children for whom this could be assessed.
<table-wrap id="DKU382TB1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Baseline demographic and clinical characteristics of children</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Child<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight-for-age <italic>Z</italic>-score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height-for-age <italic>Z</italic>-score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior WHO AIDS condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPTB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPTB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4 count (cells/mm<sup>3</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1695</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">982</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral load (copies/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White cell count (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANC (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets (10<sup>12</sup>/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">385</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART drugs in addition to LPV/r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d4T + 3TC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3TC + ABC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3TC + ABC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3TC + ABC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d4T + 3TC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d4T + 3TC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Months on LPV/r-based ART</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time since end of TB treatment (weeks)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><p>PTB, pulmonary TB; EPTB, extrapulmonary TB; CMV, cytomegalovirus; NA, not available; d4T, stavudine; 3TC, lamivudine; ABC, abacavir; LPV/r, lopinavir/ritonavir.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3b">
                <title>Pharmacokinetics of rifabutin</title>
                <p>All children had measurable rifabutin concentrations at all timepoints, but there was substantial interindividual variation despite uniform dosing (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKU382TB2">2</xref>). The median AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of rifabutin was 6.91 μg · h/mL, ranging from 3.52 to 8.67 μg · h/mL. Only one child had a rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub> below the target range of 4.5–6.0 μg · h/mL. The median rifabutin <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 0.385 μg/mL, ranging from 0.19 to 0.46 μg/mL. One of the six children had a <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> &gt;0.45 μg/mL. The rifabutin half-life was 16.0 h (range 10.9–38.6). Time of <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> indicated delayed absorption in child 1.
<table-wrap id="DKU382TB2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin pharmacokinetic parameters from non-compartmental analyses in six HIV-infected children</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>0–24</sub> (µg · h/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>0–48</sub> (µg · h/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Half-life (h)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> (µg/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic><sub>max</sub> (h)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Rifabutin</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> median</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> median</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3c">
                <title>Pharmacokinetics of 25-O-desacetyl rifabutin</title>
                <p>All children had measurable 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin concentrations at all timepoints (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKU382TB2">2</xref>). The median AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin was 5.73 μg · h/mL (range 2.9–9.1). The median 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 0.17 μg/mL. The half-life of 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin was 36.2 h (range 11.9–55.0).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3d">
                <title>Combined rifabutin and 25-O-desacetyl rifabutin pharmacokinetic parameters</title>
                <p>The median AUC<sub>0–48</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> ratios of 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin to rifabutin were 0.80 (range 0.70–1.24) and 0.49 (range 0.38–0.72), respectively. The median combined AUC<sub>0–48</sub> for rifabutin plus 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin was 12.99 μg · h/mL (range 6.36–16.55).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3e">
                <title>Adverse events</title>
                <p>The ANC decreased in all six children. Two children developed grade 4 neutropenia, one grade 2 neutropenia and one grade 1 neutropenia when graded according to the DAIDS 2004, clarification August 2009, table (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKU382TB3">3</xref>).<sup><xref rid="DKU382C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Both of the grade 4 neutropenias resolved to grade 1 without sequelae, 2 and 6 days after cessation of drug exposure. Apart from one child who had an intercurrent infection, no other potential causes for decline in ANC were identified. When neutrophil counts were graded according to the pre-2004 grading table, there were no grade 4 events, one grade 3, one grade 2 and two grade 1 neutropenias (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKU382TB3">3</xref>).<sup><xref rid="DKU382C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>
<table-wrap id="DKU382TB3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Decrease in ANC and DAIDS adverse event gradings</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rifabutin dose (mg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rifabutin dose (mg/kg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline ANC (cells/mm<sup>3</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-rifabutin ANC<sup>a</sup> (cells/mm<sup>3</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAIDS 2004 grading<sup><xref rid="DKU382C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAIDS 1994 grading<sup><xref rid="DKU382C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">770</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1960</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2690</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3270</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN2"><p><sup>a</sup>Taken on first pharmacokinetic day (day 13).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p>The median platelet count decreased from 393 000 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> (range 330 000–627 000) to 260 000 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> (range 130 000–493 000). None of the six children developed elevated liver enzymes, uveitis, myalgia, arthralgia or gastrointestinal symptoms.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3f">
                <title>Correlation between ANC and pharmacokinetic parameters</title>
                <p>When excluding the one outlier (child with an elevated baseline ANC of 8600 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> and who had had an intercurrent illness and whose ANC therefore could be expected to change substantially in the time period of interest independent of rifabutin exposure), there was a strong correlation between pharmacokinetic parameters and ANC measured during rifabutin administration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DKU382F1">1</xref>a–c): <italic>r</italic> = −0.85 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.07) for correlation between rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub> and ANC; <italic>r</italic> = −0.94 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02) for correlation between AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of the metabolite 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin and ANC; and <italic>r</italic> = −0.96 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01) for correlation between the combined AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of rifabutin and its metabolite 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin and ANC. The correlation between <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and ANC was <italic>r</italic> = −0.67 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.21) for rifabutin <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>r</italic> = −0.90 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04) for 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>. There was no correlation between any of these pharmacokinetic parameters and ANC when the outlier was not excluded.
<fig id="DKU382F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Correlation between ANC on day 13 of rifabutin exposure and (a) rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub>, (b) 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub> and (c) combined rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dku38201"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3g">
                <title>Review of study by DSMB, ethics committees and funding agency</title>
                <p>Per protocol DSMB reviews were conducted after the first and sixth children had grade 4 neutropenia. The DSMB classified the first case as unrelated to rifabutin as the child had an intercurrent infection at the time and the second case as potentially related to rifabutin. The DSMB and Human Research Ethics Committees of the University of the Witwatersrand and Cape Town approved an amended protocol with a reduced rifabutin dose (from 5 to 3 mg/kg three times a week), an additional safety visit after the third dose of rifabutin and a switch to the DAIDS 1994 grading tables to address the issue of ethnic neutropenia. The Institutional Review Board of the University of North Carolina determined that the study required approval under 45 CFR 46.407 because of greater than minimal risk without direct benefit. The study was stopped when the funding agency decided not to pursue the 407 process.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this study, we found that rifabutin dosed at 5 mg/kg three times a week together with a lopinavir/ritonavir-containing cART regimen in young (≤5 years) children resulted in generally higher AUC<sub>0–48</sub>, AUC<sub>0–24</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> values for rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin compared with adults receiving 150 mg of rifabutin three times a week,<sup><xref rid="DKU382C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> though lower than the values associated with the more recent recommendations of 150 mg of rifabutin daily.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> High rates of severe neutropenia were observed and values for rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin AUC were strongly correlated with low neutrophil counts during rifabutin administration.</p>
              <p>Despite the dose adjustments made to account for expected differences in clearance between children and adults,<sup><xref rid="DKU382C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> the median rifabutin AUC<sub>0–24</sub>, AUC<sub>0–48</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> parameters observed in these young children were higher than those reported in a study of 10 adults in the USA receiving 150 mg of rifabutin three times a week in combination with lopinavir/ritonavir.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> In these adults, Boulanger <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> observed a median rifabutin <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.23 (0.04–0.32) μg/mL and AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of 4.42 (0.96–7.48) μg · h/mL, lower than the median <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.39 (0.19–0.46) μg/mL and AUC<sub>0–48</sub> of 6.91 (3.52–8.67) μg · h/mL observed in our paediatric study. In contrast, a study of 13 Vietnamese adults receiving 150 mg of rifabutin thrice weekly in combination with lopinavir/ritonavir observed higher median values for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> [0.54 (0.06–0.96) μg/mL] and AUC<sub>0–48</sub> [7.34 (1.43–10.90) μg · h/mL] than those observed in our study.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The rifabutin AUC<sub>0–48</sub> in our study participants receiving rifabutin three times per week were not surprisingly substantially lower than those in both Vietnamese (14.58 μg · h/mL) and South African (9.53 μg · h/mL) adults when dosed at 150 mg of rifabutin daily, the current recommended dose in combination with lopinavir/ritonavir.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="DKU382C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p>
              <p>We also found high AUC<sub>0–48</sub> values for the active metabolite 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin [5.73 (2.85–9.13) μg · h/mL], higher than those observed in US adults [2.70 (1.39–4.23) μg · h/mL] and Vietnamese adults [3.81 (0.87–7.63) µg · h/mL] when dosed at 150 mg three times a week. This is consistent with potent inhibition of CYP3A4 by ritonavir and the immaturity of the CYP3A4 enzyme in young infants.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The decline in ANC in all children soon after administration of rifabutin, with two of six children experiencing severe neutropenia after six doses of rifabutin, is cause for concern, even if the neutropenia resolved rapidly and without sequelae after withdrawal of rifabutin. While neutropenia has been described in adults receiving rifabutin, the rate observed in this group of young children was higher than expected. In the study of Vietnamese adults, only 1 in 12 adults developed a grade 3 neutropenia and no grade 4 neutropenia was observed. Similarly, in the study of US adults, two patients developed grade 2 neutropenia and no grade 3 or 4 neutropenia was observed. The strong correlation between the ANC under rifabutin and high plasma concentration of both rifabutin and its metabolite in our study suggest that the neutropenia observed may be the consequence of immaturity of CYP3A4 in these young children. It is important to note however that when 1994 DAIDS grading tables were applied the grades of neutropenia experienced in our study were less severe, supporting the need for population-specific grading tables for neutrophil counts to accommodate relative ethnic neutropenia.<sup><xref rid="DKU382C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–<xref rid="DKU382C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p>
              <p>In conclusion, the 5 mg/kg dose of rifabutin resulted in lower rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin exposures in young children than those obtained in adults dosed at 150 mg of rifabutin daily, the current recommended dose for co-treatment with a ritonavir-boosted PI. The high interindividual variability in plasma concentrations, the high rates of neutropenia and the strong association between rifabutin and 25-<italic>O</italic>-desacetyl rifabutin plasma concentrations and neutrophil count suggest that it will be difficult to identify a safe and effective dose of rifabutin for young children in need of concomitant treatment with lopinavir/ritonavir.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This work was supported by the <funding-source id="cs1" rid="cn1">National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (<award-id id="cn1" rid="cs1">R01 HD058972-01</award-id>). H. McIlleron is supported in part by the <funding-source id="cs2" rid="cn2">National Research Foundation of South Africa</funding-source> (grant number <award-id id="cn2" rid="cs2">90729</award-id>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s6">
              <title>Transparency declarations</title>
              <p>None to declare.</p>
              <sec id="s6a">
                <title>Author contributions</title>
                <p>H. Moultrie and A. V. R. contributed to the conceptualization, design, acquisition, analysis and interpretation of the data and drafting and revision of the manuscript. H. McIlleron contributed to the design, acquisition, analysis and interpretation of the data and drafting and revision of the manuscript. S. S., G. K. and H. G. contributed to the conduct and safety of the study, acquisition of data and drafting and revision of the manuscript. T. K. and L. W. contributed to the pharmacokinetic data acquisition and analysis and drafting and revision of the manuscript. All authors approved the final manuscript.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>These data were presented at the Nineteenth Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections, Seattle, WA, USA, 2012 (Poster S-177).</p>
              <p>The study team would like to acknowledge the children and their parents for their commitment during the study and the members of the DSMB for their support. The study team is grateful for the support provided by Gary Maartens and Nick Holford in designing the study and the members of the DSMB who provided superb oversight.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="DKU382C1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyers</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yotebieng</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuhn</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Antiretroviral therapy responses among children attending a large public clinic in Soweto, South Africa</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>974</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21734620</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>WHO</collab>
                  <source>Consolidated Guidelines on the Use of Antiretroviral Drugs for Treating and Preventing HIV Infection: Recommendations for a Public Health Approach</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva: WHO</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Violari</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lindsey</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hughes</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nevirapine versus ritonavir-boosted lopinavir for HIV-infected children</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>366</volume>
                  <fpage>2380</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22716976</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Palumbo</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lindsey</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hughes</surname>
                      <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Antiretroviral treatment for children with peripartum nevirapine exposure</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>363</volume>
                  <fpage>1510</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20942667</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oudijk</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIlleron</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mulenga</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of nevirapine in HIV-infected children under 3 years on rifampicin-based antituberculosis treatment</article-title>
                  <source>AIDS</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <fpage>1523</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546991</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kekitiinwa</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <collab>ARROW Trial team</collab>
                  <article-title>Routine versus clinically driven laboratory monitoring and first-line antiretroviral therapy strategies in African children with HIV (ARROW): a 5-year open-label randomised factorial trial</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>381</volume>
                  <fpage>1391</fpage>
                  <lpage>403</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23473847</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuhn</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coovadia</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Monitoring strategies for management of ART in children</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>381</volume>
                  <fpage>1343</fpage>
                  <lpage>4</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23473849</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIlleron</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nuttall</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Lopinavir exposure is insufficient in children given double doses of lopinavir/ritonavir during rifampicin-based treatment for tuberculosis</article-title>
                  <source>Antivir Ther</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
                  <lpage>21</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555825</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nuttall</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egbers</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of rifampicin on lopinavir pharmacokinetics in HIV-infected children with tuberculosis</article-title>
                  <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>566</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18197120</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>CDC</collab>
                  <source>Managing Drug Interactions in the Treatment of HIV-Related Tuberculosis</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <comment>
                    <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/tb/publications/guidelines/tb_hiv_drugs/pdf/tbhiv.pdf">http://www.cdc.gov/tb/publications/guidelines/tb_hiv_drugs/pdf/tbhiv.pdf</uri>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>WHO</collab>
                  <source>The Selection and Use of Essential Medicines: Report of the WHO Expert Committee, March 2009 (Including the 16th WHO Model List of Essential Medicines and the 2nd WHO Model List of Essential Medicines for Children)</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva: WHO</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>Abbott Pharmaceuticals</collab>
                  <source>Kaletra Product Information</source>
                  <comment>
                    <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/000368/WC500039043.pdf">www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/000368/WC500039043.pdf</uri>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other">
                  <collab>Department of Health and Human Services</collab>
                  <article-title>Panel on Antiretroviral Guidelines for Adults and Adolescents. <italic>Guidelines for the Use of Antiretroviral Agents in HIV-1-Infected Adults and Adolescents</italic></article-title>
                  <comment>
                    <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://aidsinfo.nih.gov/ContentFiles/AdultandAdolescentGL.pdf">http://aidsinfo.nih.gov/ContentFiles/AdultandAdolescentGL.pdf</uri>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burman</surname>
                      <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gallicano</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peloquin</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparative pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of the rifamycin antibacterials</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432536</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffith</surname>
                      <given-names>DE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brown</surname>
                      <given-names>BA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wallace</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                      <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Varying dosages of rifabutin affect white blood cell and platelet counts in human immunodeficiency virus—negative patients who are receiving multidrug regimens for pulmonary <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex disease</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>1321</fpage>
                  <lpage>2</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953085</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cerri</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richeldi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rifabutin for treating pulmonary tuberculosis</article-title>
                  <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>CD005159</fpage>
                  <comment>issue</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943842</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ford</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>YC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lou</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharmacokinetic interaction between fosamprenavir-ritonavir and rifabutin in healthy subjects</article-title>
                  <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <fpage>534</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18056271</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boulanger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hollender</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farrell</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharmacokinetic evaluation of rifabutin in combination with lopinavir-ritonavir in patients with HIV infection and active tuberculosis</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <fpage>1305</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19807276</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naiker</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conolly</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weisner</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pharmacokinetic evaluation of different rifabutin dosing strategies in African TB patients on lopinavir/ritonavir-based ART</article-title>
                  <publisher-loc>Alexandra, VA, USA</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Foundation for Retrovirology and Human Health</publisher-name>
                  <comment><italic>Abstracts of the Eighteenth Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections, Boston, MA, 2011</italic> Abstract 650</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>del Rio</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Updated guidelines for the use of rifamycins in HIV/TB-coinfected patients</article-title>
                  <source>AIDS Clin Care</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15526395</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anderson</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holford</surname>
                      <given-names>NH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mechanism-based concepts of size and maturity in pharmacokinetics</article-title>
                  <source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914927</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haslam</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Egodage</surname>
                      <given-names>KL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Stability of rifabutin in two extemporaneously compounded oral liquids</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10690216</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>WHO</collab>
                  <source>Antiretroviral Therapy for HIV Infection in Infants and Children: Towards Universal Access—2010 Revision</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva: WHO</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other">
                  <collab>NIH</collab>
                  <comment><italic>Division of AIDS Table for Grading the Severity of Adult and Pediatric Adverse Events, Version 1.0, December, 2004; Clarification August 2009</italic>. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rsc.tech-res.com/Document/safetyandpharmacovigilance/Table_for_Grading_Severity_of_Adult_Pediatric_Adverse_Events.pdf">http://rsc.tech-res.com/Document/safetyandpharmacovigilance/Table_for_Grading_Severity_of_Adult_Pediatric_Adverse_Events.pdf</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>WHO Multicentre Growth Reference Study Group</collab>
                  <source>WHO Child Growth Standards: Length/Height-for-Age, Weight-for-Age, Weight-for-Length, Weight-for-Height and Body Mass Index-for-Age: Methods and Development</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>Department of Health</collab>
                  <source>Guidelines for the Management of HIV in Children, 2010</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Pretoria: South African National Department of Health</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other">
                  <collab>NIAID</collab>
                  <comment><italic>Division of AIDS (DAIDS) Table for Grading Severity of Pediatric (&gt;3 Months of Age) Adverse Experiences, April 1994</italic>. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://rsc.tech-res.com/Document/safetyandpharmacovigilance/Table_for_Grading_Severity_of_Pediatric_AEs_Over3MonthsAge_v03.pdf">http://rsc.tech-res.com/Document/safetyandpharmacovigilance/Table_for_Grading_Severity_of_Pediatric_AEs_Over3MonthsAge_v03.pdf</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lan</surname>
                      <given-names>NT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thu</surname>
                      <given-names>NT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barrail-Tran</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Randomised pharmacokinetic trial of rifabutin with lopinavir/ritonavir-antiretroviral therapy in patients with HIV-associated tuberculosis in Vietnam</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>e84866</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465443</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anderson</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holford</surname>
                      <given-names>NH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Understanding dosing: children are small adults, neonates are immature children</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>98</volume>
                  <fpage>737</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23832061</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wells</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shetty</surname>
                      <given-names>AK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stranix</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Range of normal neutrophil counts in healthy Zimbabwean infants: implications for monitoring antiretroviral drug toxicity</article-title>
                  <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>460</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16810112</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kourtis</surname>
                      <given-names>AP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bramson</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Horst</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Low absolute neutrophil counts in African infants</article-title>
                  <source>J Int Assoc Physicians AIDS Care (Chic)</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16867975</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="DKU382C32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haddy</surname>
                      <given-names>TB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rana</surname>
                      <given-names>SR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Benign ethnic neutropenia: what is a normal absolute neutrophil count?</article-title>
                  <source>J Lab Clin Med</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>133</volume>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10385477</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
