<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:38:02Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10578518" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10578518</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-10-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>lwwopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">qai</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes (1999)</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1525-4135</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1944-7884</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>JAIDS Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10578518</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10578518</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10578518</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37643392</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37643392</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">QAIV23119</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000003279</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00008</article-id>
              <article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Implementation Science</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Phone-Delivered Intervention to Improve HIV Care for Young People Living With HIV: Trial to Inform Implementation and Utility</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0912-5112</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kalichman</surname>
                    <given-names>Seth C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kalichman</surname>
                    <given-names>Moira O.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSW</degrees>
                  <email>moirakalichman@gmail.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Eaton</surname>
                    <given-names>Lisa A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <email>lisa.eaton@uconn.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <aff>Institute for Collaboration on Health Intervention and Policy, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp>Correspondence to: Seth C. Kalichman, InCHIP, 2006 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT 06269 (e-mail <email>seth.k@uconn.edu</email>).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>13</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>94</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>227</fpage>
              <lpage>234</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>06</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2023 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="qai-94-227.pdf"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="toc">
                <p>Supplemental Digital Content is Available in the Text.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>Phone-delivered counseling has demonstrated improved health outcomes for people living with HIV. However, counseling is hampered by a lack of guidance on the frequency and duration of intervention in relation to clinical benefits. The added benefits of bidirectional (ie, interactive) vs. unidirectional (ie, passive) text messages to augment counseling are also unknown. We conducted a clinical trial of adaptive phone counseling along with either bidirectional or unidirectional text messaging for people living with HIV.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>A community sample of 425 young people (aged 16–36 years) living with HIV in Georgia, USA, received weekly phone counseling sessions with the number of sessions determined by the participant and their counselor. Participants were subsequently randomized to either (1) weekly bidirectional text messages with their counselor or (2) weekly automated unidirectional text message reminders. Participants were followed for 16 months to assess 3 primary outcomes: antiretroviral therapy (ART) adherence, HIV care engagement, and HIV suppression.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>Participants demonstrated improved clinical outcomes over the follow-up period, with 74% of those who were not taking ART initiating treatment, 65% of those on ART improving adherence, and 47% who had detectable viral loads at baseline attaining viral suppression. The number of sessions completed predicted improved ART adherence, greater care engagement, and HIV suppression over follow-ups. Bidirectional text messages impacted care engagement by moderating the effects of counseling sessions on HIV suppression.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions:</title>
                  <p>Phone counseling augmented by bidirectional text messages has the potential to improve HIV care for young adults living with HIV.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Key Words:</title>
                <kwd>HIV treatment engagement</kwd>
                <kwd>ART adherence</kwd>
                <kwd>behavioral intervention: implementation science</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="award1">
                  <funding-source xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.13039/501100010232">National Institute of Development Administration</funding-source>
                  <award-id>R01-DA033067</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>SDC</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>T</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Antiretroviral therapy (ART) has revolutionized the treatment of HIV infection, transforming what was once a life-threating disease into a manageable health condition. Unfortunately, not all people living with HIV are experiencing the full benefits of ART due to poor retention in care and treatment nonadherence. Adolescents and young adults living with HIV are particularly disadvantaged in HIV care, with poorer health outcomes relative to all other age groups.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Among the factors that undermine HIV treatment are structural barriers (eg, food insecurity, unstable housing, and lack of transportation), mental health concerns (eg, depression and HIV stigma), and substance use.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> These challenges often go unaddressed when patients who are marginally engaged in health care are required to attend additional clinic-based services.</p>
              <p>Access to telephone-delivered interventions offers a viable option to addressing barriers to care without the added burdens posed by in-person services. Clinical trials have shown that phone-delivered interventions can increase engagement in care, improve adherence,<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and increase HIV suppression,<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> including when targeted to young adults.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Text messaging, for example, can offer sustained support by reminding patients of care appointments and prompting medication taking.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> However, different models of text messaging may have different outcomes. For example, unidirectional text message reminders of care appointments have yielded mixed results,<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> whereas bidirectional text messaging with a counselor offers opportunities to sustain clinical outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Questions remain regarding the implementation of phone-delivered interventions for young adults living with HIV. For example, phone counseling has often taken a one-size-fits all approach, typically prescribing 4 or 5 counseling sessions without consideration of where individuals fall along the HIV continuum of care.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In clinical trials that have tested phone counseling, as many as half of participants have not achieved optimal ART adherence and HIV suppression,<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> begging the question as to whether results may be improved by allowing patients and their counselors to determine the number of counseling sessions. We are not aware of research that has examined the number of phone counseling sessions received in relation to clinical outcomes.</p>
              <p>The aim of this trial was to answer fundamental questions about phone counseling to inform its implementation with young adults living with HIV. We conducted a trial to test an adaptive approach to phone counseling that meets participants where they fall along the HIV continuum of care. In addition, participants and their counselors determined the number of counseling sessions received. We tested the association between the number of phone counseling sessions received and retention in HIV care, ART adherence, and HIV detection. In addition, we conducted a head-to-head comparison of bidirectional vs. unidirectional text messages to augment counseling. We hypothesized that receiving a greater number of phone counseling sessions would predict improved ART adherence, attending more care appointments, and reduced HIV viral load. We also hypothesized that participants receiving bidirectional text messages would demonstrate more positive outcomes over the 16-month follow-up compared with participants receiving unidirectional text messages.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>METHODS</title>
              <sec id="s2-1">
                <title>Participants and Setting</title>
                <p>Young adults (aged 16–36 years) living with HIV in Atlanta and Macon, Georgia, were recruited between September 2017 and December 2019 through multiple channels: for example, 42% from social media outlets (Facebook and Jack'd), 41% from past participant referrals, and 17% from community/clinical services.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-2">
                <title>Study Design Overview and Procedures</title>
                <p>Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the overall trial design and flow of participants. Individuals were screened over the phone and those who were HIV positive and between the ages of 16 and 36 years were scheduled for an enrollment appointment. Enrollment commenced with individuals presenting clinical documentation of their HIV status, (eg, positive test result, viral load test result, and ART bottle) and a photograph ID with their age. Persons who were confirmed eligible for the run-in were provided informed consent and completed an office visit to conduct a computerized interview and collect urine and blood specimens. The run-in also included 2 phone-based unannounced pill counts approximately 30 days apart to determine ART adherence.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>FIGURE 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Study design and flow of participants through the clinical trial.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="qai-94-227-g001" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>On completion of the run-in, we determined whether participants met eligibility criteria for the trial: (1) not engaged in care, or (2) &lt;85% ART adherent, or (3) HIV-1 viral load &gt; 831 copies/mL, or (4) positive urine screening for substance use. We included active substance use among the entry criteria because of its close association with risk for poor HIV treatment outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Participants meeting trial entry criteria received weekly phone counseling sessions with the number of sessions determined by participants with their counselor (see below). Furthermore, after counseling was completed, participants were randomized to receive either bidirectional (interactive) or unidirectional (passive) text messages for their remaining time in the trial. No additional office visits were required after the run-in, with follow-up measures completed remotely on mobile devices. For follow-up blood samples, participants were sent collection supplies and return courier envelopes (see below). Participants also completed brief monthly phone interviews that included pill counts over 16 months. All participants were enrolled before the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic, with all postenrollment procedures conducted remotely. Participants were reimbursed for completing measures and were not compensated for intervention activities. Privacy was protected through a federal certificate of confidentiality. The University of Connecticut Institutional Review Board approved all procedures (registered <ext-link xlink:href="http://NCT03665532.gov" ext-link-type="uri">NCT03665532.gov</ext-link>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-3">
                <title>Phone-Delivered Counseling</title>
                <p>The intervention was grounded in behavioral self-regulation theory,<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> motivational interviewing, and social–cognitive theories of decision-making.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> The counseling centered on weighing options to overcome challenges and developing strategies for care retention and ART adherence. The counseling had 5 major elements: (1) increasing motivation to commit to HIV care, (2) developing strategies for managing stigma experiences, (3) addressing substance use, (4) practicing decision-making skills to effectively manage barriers to care, and (5) developing realistic plans for acting on health decisions (see electronic supplemental material for the intervention manual, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/QAI/C105" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/QAI/C105</ext-link>).</p>
                <p>Participants received a maximum of 16 weekly phone counseling sessions delivered by one of 3 bachelor-level counselors. The first session was designed to determine where participants were along the HIV continuum of care, specifically whether they had a care provider (linked), had seen their provider in the past 6 months (engaged), and whether they were receiving and were adherent to ART. The intervention sessions directly addressed substance use and the impact of stigma experiences as impediments to HIV care. Counseling also directly addressed an array of structural and mental health barriers to care and made referrals to local services. Counseling ended by participants either initiating a discussion with their counselor about termination or participants not scheduling or not attending scheduled counseling sessions.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-4">
                <title>Text Message Support</title>
                <p>On completion of the final counseling session, participants were randomly assigned to one of the 2 text message conditions. Allocation was accomplished using condition codes randomly generated by the project manager through an automated system. Randomization was not breached throughout the trial. Text messages commenced either (1) the day after the final counseling session or (2) 2 weeks of being unable to contact participants who did not return for counseling. Counselors were not aware of the participants' text message condition during the counseling and all other research staff remained blinded to condition.</p>
                <sec id="s2-4-1">
                  <title>Bidirectional Text Messages</title>
                  <p>Participants randomized to this condition received weekly contacts initiated by their counselor that started after phone counseling ended and continued over the remainder of this study. This condition afforded opportunities for problem solving with the counselor as needed.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2-4-2">
                  <title>Unidirectional Text Messages</title>
                  <p>This condition received weekly computer-generated text message reminders without the option to reply.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> The message content was constrained to 10 words or less and was generated by participants as a reminder for them to stay in care and remain adherent.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>MEASURES</title>
              <sec id="s3-1">
                <title>Participant Characteristics and Predictors of Counseling Sessions Completed</title>
                <sec id="s3-1-1">
                  <title>Demographic and health characteristics</title>
                  <p>Participants were asked their age, ethnicity, sex, education, income, and related demographic information. Participants provided the date they tested HIV positive, the date they first saw an HIV care provider, and the date they initiated ART. We also assessed key structural barriers including food security,<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> housing stability, and access to transportation.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-1-2">
                  <title>Depression and Stigma</title>
                  <p>The 20-item Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale assessed symptoms of depression,<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> α =0.90<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> The HIV Stigma Mechanisms Scale<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> assessed internalized (6 items), enacted (24 items), and anticipated (24 items) stigma within a 4-month timeframe to cover the follow-up periods, α′s between 0.90 and 0.94. In addition, for each endorsed stigma item, participants rated the amount of distress they experienced, using a 12-point scale, 0 = not at all distressed to 11 = extremely distressed, averaged across experiences to obtain an index of stigma distress.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-1-3">
                  <title>Substance Use</title>
                  <p>Participants completed the 3-item consumption subscale of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT-C<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>) α = 0.72. We also conducted a multipanel urine test to detect metabolites to 12 drugs (ie, cocaine, amphetamines, THC, and opioids) used in the previous 72 to 96 hours (Redwood Toxicology Labs) and a urine test for ethyl glucuronide for detecting alcohol use within 24 hours.<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-1-4">
                  <title>HIV Treatment Self-Efficacy and Medication Beliefs</title>
                  <p>Based on theories of health behavior change,<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> we used a measure of self-efficacy that allowed participants to judge how confident they were that they could keep care appointments and take medications in varied circumstances,<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> α = 0.88. Medication beliefs were assessed using the 10-item Beliefs About Medicines Questionnaire,<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> including necessity and concerns beliefs about taking ART, α′s = 0.77 and 0.75, respectively.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-2">
                <title>Primary Outcomes</title>
                <sec id="s3-2-1">
                  <title>ART Adherence</title>
                  <p>Participants completed monthly unannounced phone-based pill counts throughout this study, with the first 2 calls in the run-in period used to determine trial eligibility and constituting the baseline. Unannounced pill counts are reliable and valid in assessing medication adherence when conducted in the home<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and on the phone.<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> All antiretroviral medications were included in the pill counts and in calculating adherence. The first pill count established the number of pills in possession with subsequent pill counts used to calculate adherence, defined as the ratio of pills counted relative to pills prescribed, taking into account the number of pills previously counted and the number dispensed. For outcome analyses, ART adherence was averaged across months within assessment intervals, specifically 4-month follow-up (mean of months 2, 3, and 4), 8-month (mean of months 5, 6, 7, and 8), 12-month (mean of months 9, 10, 11, and 12) and 16-month follow-up (mean of months 13, 14, 15, and 16).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-2-2">
                  <title>Engagement in Care</title>
                  <p>Missed care appointments are among the most immediately actionable health care behaviors that are associated with poor clinical outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> We used an adapted measure of appointment keeping to assess engagement in care.<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> In monthly phone interviews, participants were asked to report whether they had scheduled HIV care appointments the previous month and whether they attended or did not attend the appointments. The number of kept appointments was adjusted for months of follow-up by taking the ratio of appointments kept/total appointments scheduled aggregated over the follow-up.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-2-3">
                  <title>HIV Detection</title>
                  <p>To determine HIV RNA concentrations (viral load), participants provided 80 µL of fingerstick blood for dried blood collected in Hemaspot HF devices at baseline and at 4-, 8-, 12-, and 16-month follow-ups. HIV-1 viral load testing was conducted using reverse transcription PCR,<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> and the limit of detection is 831 copies/mL (log 2.92).</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-3">
                <title>Sample Size</title>
                <p>Sample size was determined with effect sizes observed for counseling and text message interventions derived from pilot testing,<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> previous research,<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and meta-analyses.<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> We assumed 80% retention and estimated 212 participants in each of the 2 text messaging conditions to achieve 90% chance of detecting differences.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-4">
                <title>Data Analyses</title>
                <p>Before conducting the main outcome analyses, we performed integrity tests of our randomization procedures. We also examined potential counselor effects and interactions among counselors for sessions completed and compared the text message conditions on all baseline measures.</p>
                <sec id="s3-4-1">
                  <title>Predictors of Counseling Sessions Completed</title>
                  <p>We conducted bivariate Poisson regression models to predict number of sessions completed from participant characteristics. We report the resulting regression coefficients (B) and their associated standard errors (SE).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-4-2">
                  <title>Threshold Analysis of Counseling Sessions Completed</title>
                  <p>We examined the associations between number of counseling sessions completed and ART adherence. Linear regressions tested the association between number of sessions completed in relation to 4-month ART adherence, controlling for baseline adherence. We report the standardized (Beta) and unstandardized (B) regression coefficients, SE, and changes in variance accounted for (R<sup>2</sup>) over and above baseline adherence.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3-4-3">
                  <title>Phone Counseling Effects on Primary Outcomes</title>
                  <p>We tested the effects of the number of counseling sessions completed and the moderating effects of the text message conditions on ART adherence and HIV detection using a moderated mediation framework performed in the SPSS PROCESS module.<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> Conceptually, counseling is aimed to affect ART adherence, which is considered the causal agent (mediator) for HIV detection.<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> The models tested direct effects of counseling sessions completed on ART adherence and HIV detection, as well as controlling for the direct effects of ART adherence on HIV detection. The models also tested the indirect effects of number of counseling sessions completed on HIV detection through the mediator, ART adherence. The indirect effects of counseling sessions on HIV detection through ART adherence were also examined for the 2 text message conditions (moderated mediation). Models were tested with all available data at the 4-, 8-, 12-, and 16-month follow-ups. All of the outcome analyses include baseline ART adherence and baseline HIV viral load as covariates.</p>
                  <p>The same moderated mediation approach to testing the number of counseling sessions in relation to health outcomes was undertaken with the cumulative number of care appointments kept included as the behavioral outcome (mediator). In this model, we aggregated HIV viral loads across the number of available follow-ups, adjusting for attrition. Specifically, each of the follow-up viral load tests was coded as detectable = 1 or undetectable = 0, with the ratio of viral load results taken over the number of completed assessments. Baseline HIV viral load was included as a covariate. All analyses defined statistical significance as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s4">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The sample consisted of 425 people living with HIV; 89% assigned male sex at birth, 89% Black/African American, and 39% had 12 years or less education. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the participant characteristics and their association with the number of counseling sessions completed (see below). There were no differences between the 2 text message conditions for any participant characteristics, and there were no serious adverse events in this trial.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>TABLE 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Participant Characteristics and Their Association to the Number of Phone Counseling Sessions Completed</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristic</td>
                      <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Participants N = 425</td>
                      <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Association Between Participant Characteristic and Number of Intervention Sessions Completed<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth sex male</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.033</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth sex female</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transgender identity</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">African American</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education less than 12 years</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Ref)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education 12 years</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.091</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education more than 12 years</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual income &lt;$30,000</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.114<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has no health insurance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.057</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has limited transportation</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.464</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficulty getting to care appointments</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiences housing instability</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food insecurity</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive drug test other than cannabis</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.053</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis (THC) positive</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.035</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol (EtG) positive</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.137<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taking ART at baseline</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.008</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral load undetectable</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.055</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years since testing HIV positive</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUDIT-C</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-efficacy for care appointments</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-efficacy for ART adherence</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internalized stigma</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.006</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enacted stigma</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stigma-distress</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.011<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticipated stigma</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.015</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CES-depression</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication necessity beliefs</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication concern beliefs</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.029<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline ART adherence</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Poisson models.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn2">
                    <label>†</label>
                    <p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Changes that occurred along the HIV continuum of care showed that for the 34 participants who were not taking ART when enrolled in the trial, 74% had initiated ART by 16 months of follow-up. Among those 391 who were taking ART at enrollment, 54% demonstrated higher adherence at the follow-ups, with 65% having greater than baseline adherence at 16 months of follow-up. Overall, 77% of care appointments were kept and among the 107 participants who had detectable viral loads at baseline, 47% had attained an undetectable viral load at 16 months of follow-up.</p>
              <sec id="s4-1">
                <title>Predictors of Counseling Sessions Completed</title>
                <p>Ten participants (&lt;2%) declined counseling beyond the first session, with all remaining participants completing between 2 and 13 sessions. The mean and median number of sessions completed was 6, and the sessions lasted a mean of 25.3 minutes. (SD = 7.0). Over the course of this study, 2445 counseling sessions were delivered, with 73 focused on linkage to care, 80 focused on engagement in care, 1548 focused on ART adherence, and 744 focused on retention in care.</p>
                <p>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the results of Poisson regression models for participant characteristics (pooled across text message conditions) as predictors of the number of intervention sessions completed. Low income, testing positive for alcohol use, experiencing greater stigma distress, and holding greater medication concern beliefs, all predicted receiving fewer counseling sessions. By contrast, greater medication adherence self-efficacy and greater baseline ART adherence were significant predictors of completing more counseling sessions.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4-2">
                <title>Threshold Analysis for Number of Counseling Sessions Completed</title>
                <p>Analyses controlling for baseline adherence indicated that completing 5 or fewer counseling sessions, as was the case 182 participants (43%), was not associated with improved ART adherence, whereas for the remaining 243 participants (57%) receiving 6 to 13 sessions was associated with improved ART adherence (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>TABLE 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Threshold Analysis for Number of Completed Phone Counseling Sessions as a Predictor of 4 Months ART Adherence</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Number of Counseling Sessions Completed</td>
                        <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Participants Completing Number of Sessions</td>
                        <td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Predicting ART Adherence at 4 Months Follow-Up<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup> Change<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.028</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.010</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">‖</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn3">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p>All models control for baseline ART adherence.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn4">
                      <label>†</label>
                      <p>Change in R<sup>2</sup> over and above baseline adherence.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn5">
                      <label>‡</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn6">
                      <label>§</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn7">
                      <label>‖</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.06.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4-3">
                <title>Counseling and Text Message Effects on ART Adherence and Viral Load</title>
                <p>The results demonstrated significant direct effects of receiving a greater number of counseling sessions on ART adherence and direct effects of ART adherence on HIV detection at all follow-ups (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The nonconditional indirect effect of counseling sessions on HIV detection through ART adherence was significant at the 4-, 8-, and 12-month follow-ups; greater number of counseling sessions predicted lower viral load through increased ART adherence. Moderator analyses only demonstrated a significant effect of the text message conditions at the 16-month follow-up, where the indirect effect of counseling sessions on HIV detection through ART adherence was significant for the unidirectional text message condition, but not for the bidirectional text message condition.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>TABLE 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Models Testing Counseling Sessions Completed on HIV Detection Mediated by Health Behaviors (ART Adherence and Care Appointments) Over Follow-Ups and Moderated by Text Message Conditions</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ART Adherence</td>
                        <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4 Months</td>
                        <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8 Months</td>
                        <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">12 Months</td>
                        <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">16 Months</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counseling sessions → ART adherence (a path)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0369<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0150</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0313<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0145</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0312<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0155</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0380<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0165</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Texting condition → ART adherence (moderator)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1223</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0694</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0448</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0679</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0755</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0727</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1532<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0774</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Texting condition X counseling sessions interaction</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0118</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0894</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0083</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0092</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0094</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0097</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0192</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0103</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART adherence → viral load (b path)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.5265<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5603</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1048</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5147</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.677<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5083</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1977<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5182</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counseling sessions → viral load (c path)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0915</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0562</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0803</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0493</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0127</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0476</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0472</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="9" rowspan="1">Indirect effects: counseling sessions → art adherence → viral load</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nonconditional</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0526<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0193</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0583<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0172</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0494<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0164</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0293</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0189</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Conditional unidirectional Text Messages</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0635<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0716<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0240</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0584<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0217</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0602<xref rid="tblfn8" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0271</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Conditional bidirectional text messages</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0337</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0206</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0460</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0255</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0333</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0222</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012</td>
                        <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0270</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn fn-type="other">
                      <p>All models control for baseline ART adherence and viral load.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn8">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4-4">
                <title>Counseling and Text Message Effects on Care Appointments and Viral Load</title>
                <p>The moderated mediation model for the number of counseling sessions predicting care appointments and HIV detection over 16 months indicated significant direct effects of counseling sessions completed on care appointments, B = 0.0221, SE = 0.0110, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and HIV load, B = −0.0131, SE = 0.0051, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. In addition, there was a significant direct effect of care appointments kept on HIV load, B= −0.3019, SE = 0.0740, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, with a greater number of care appointments kept predicting a greater number of undetectable viral loads. The indirect effect of counseling sessions on viral load through care appointments was significant, and this effect was moderated by text message conditions, interaction = −0.0163, SE = 0.0068, 95% CI −0.0298 to −0.0028. There was also a significant moderator effect of text message conditions; participants receiving bidirectional text messages kept a greater number of care appointments, B = 0.0105, SE = 0.0047, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. The effects of counseling sessions on HIV detection through care appointments was significant for participants in the bidirectional text message condition, B = 0.0032, SE = 0.0015, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and not for participants in the unidirectional text message condition, B = − 0.0018, SE = 0.0016, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The results showed that modest improvements in ART adherence and HIV detection were associated with receiving a greater number of counseling sessions. Participants who elected to receive more counseling sessions had higher incomes, were less likely to have recently drank alcohol, had greater self-efficacy for remaining ART adherent, experienced less stigma-related distress, had fewer ART-related medication concerns, and greater baseline ART adherence.</p>
              <p>The main outcome analyses indicated significant effects of phone counseling on ART adherence, attending care appointments, and HIV detection that were sustained over the follow-up. These results suggest that previous trials testing phone counseling limited to 4 or 5 sessions may have provided too little intervention for as many as half of participants who may have otherwise benefitted. Similar effects of the number of completed counseling sessions were observed for retention in HIV care. However, there was evidence that bidirectional text messaging moderated the effects of counseling sessions completed on HIV detection through care appointments. Challenges such as not having transportation to care appointments may be readily identified as amenable to problem solving assistance offered by a counselor. Thus, the optimal intervention tested in this trial was receiving 6 or more counseling sessions augmented by ongoing bidirectional text messages.</p>
              <p>We found that young people with HIV attended phone-delivered counseling sessions, with the potential to reduce barriers to care including transportation and other costs. In addition, transportation, substance use, and stigma pose challenges to accessing care that can be avoided by bringing services to participants. Receiving phone counseling sessions augmented by bidirectional text messaging can result in increased care appointment attendance and sustained ART adherence for young adults living with HIV. As experienced with interrupted clinical services during COVID-19 lockdowns, phone counseling can be sustained when facility-based services are disrupted. We therefore conclude that the scale of phone-delivered counselling to improve HIV outcomes should be augmented by bidirectional text messaging.</p>
              <p>The results of this study should be interpreted in light of its strengths and limitations. A strength of this study was the sample coming from multiple recruitment sources, rather than a single clinic. Nevertheless, our sample was one of convenience and cannot be considered representative of young adults living with HIV. In addition, the trial was geographically constrained to only 1 US state. This study included self-report measures of structural barriers, depression, and indicators of treatment motivation, all of which may have been influenced by socially desirable responding. In addition, although we set forth to examine the number of counseling sessions completed in relation to clinical outcomes, the trial was not designed to explicitly test the titration (eg, dose) of counseling on outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Although we controlled for baseline ART adherence and viral load, we could not control for underlying self-selection biases. Finally, we are unable to know whether participants habituated to the weekly unidirectional and bidirectional text messages. Given the modest gains observed in this important patient population, there remains an urgent need to enhance evidence-based interventions targeted to young persons who are not engaged in HIV care or are not adherent to ART.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <fig id="s001" position="anchor">
                <media xlink:href="qai-94-227-s001.pdf"/>
              </fig>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="supported-by">
                <p>Supported by National Institute on Drug Abuse Grant R01-DA033067.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p>Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's Web site (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.jaids.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.jaids.com</ext-link>).</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapogiannis</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The HIV continuum of care for adolescents and young adults attending 13 Urban US HIV care centers of the NICHD-ATN-CDC-HRSA SMILE collaborative</article-title>. <source>JAIDS J Acq Imm Defic Syn</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadland</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Milloy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Young age predicts poor antiretroviral adherence and viral load suppression among injection drug users</article-title>. <source>AIDS Patient Care STDS</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labisi</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Podany</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadul</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> . <article-title>Factors associated with viral suppression among cisgender women living with human immunodeficiency virus in the United States: an integrative review</article-title>. <source>Womens Health (Lond).</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>174550572210922</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Merly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of food, housing, and transportation insecurity on ART adherence: a hierarchical resources approach</article-title>. <source>AIDS Care</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27846730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez Martorell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Safran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review on promoting adherence to antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected patients using mobile phone technology</article-title>. <source>Appl Clin Inform</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>09</volume>:<fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Free</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis in the effectiveness of mobile phone interventions used to improve adherence to antiretroviral therapy in HIV infection</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>915</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31288772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haubrick</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A review of interventions to enhance HIV medication adherence</article-title>. <source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34152554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saragih</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonapa</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Osingada</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of telehealth-assisted interventions among people living with HIV/AIDS: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled studies</article-title>. <source>J Telemed Telecare</source>. <year>2021</year>:<fpage>1357633X211070726</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarra</surname><given-names>AMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwadz</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health technology-enabled interventions for adherence support and retention in care among US HIV-infected adolescents and young adults: an integrative review</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>3154</fpage>–<lpage>3171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28776275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>e Costa</surname><given-names>DAG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Results of a randomized controlled trial to assess the effects of a mobile SMS-based intervention on treatment adherence in HIV/AIDS-infected Brazilian women and impressions and satisfaction with respect to incoming messages</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22296762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finitsis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellowski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Text message intervention designs to promote adherence to antiretroviral therapy (ART): a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e88166</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505411</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pop-Eleches</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirumurthy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Habyarimana</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mobile phone technologies improve adherence to antiretroviral treatment in a resource-limited setting: a randomized controlled trial of text message reminders</article-title>. <source>AIDS</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21252632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibeneme</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndukwu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Myezwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of mobile text reminder in improving adherence to medication, physical exercise, and quality of life in patients living with HIV: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34425789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunje</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallstrom</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerene</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of mobile phone text message reminder interventions to improve adherence to antiretroviral therapy among adolescents living with HIV: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0254890</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34293033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ybarra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Promising outcomes from a cognitive behavioral therapy text-messaging intervention targeting drug use, antiretroviral therapy adherence, and HIV risk behaviors among adults living with HIV and substance use disorders</article-title>. <source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>231</volume>:<fpage>109229</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34979421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reback</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisler</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Text messaging improves HIV care continuum outcomes among young adult trans women living with HIV: text me, girl</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>3011</fpage>–<lpage>3023</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34164763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of a mobile phone short message service on antiretroviral treatment adherence in Kenya (WelTel Kenya1): a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>376</volume>:<fpage>1838</fpage>–<lpage>1845</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21071074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> .<article-title>Randomized factorial trial of phone-delivered support counseling and daily text message reminders for HIV treatment adherence</article-title>. <source>JAIDS J Acq Imm Defic Syn</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Katner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative effects of telephone versus in-office behavioral counseling to improve HIV treatment outcomes among people living with HIV in a rural setting</article-title>. <source>Transl Behav Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>862</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>When is enough, enough? How the absence of dose-determination trials impedes implementation of HIV behavioral interventions</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>2219</fpage>–<lpage>2225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31440859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of alcohol consumption on adherence to and toxicity of antiretroviral therapy and survival</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Res Health</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23584069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Self-efficacy: The Exercise of Control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freeman</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janis</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Decision-making: A Psychological Analysis of Conflict, Choice, and Commitment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>; <year>1977</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influencing medication taking behaviors using automated two-way digital communication: a narrative synthesis systematic review informed by the Behavior Change Wheel</article-title>. <source>Br J Health Psychol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>890</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35080811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mobile phone interventions to promote adherence to HIV treatment: mitigating the challenges</article-title>. <source>Nurs Stand</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A brief indicator of household energy security: associations with food security, child health, and child development in US infants and toddlers</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>e867</fpage>–<lpage>e875</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The CES-D Scale: a self-report depression scale for research in the general population</article-title>. <source>Appl Psychol Meas</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudoir</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>From conceptualizing to measuring HIV stigma: a review of HIV stigma mechanism measures</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1160</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19636699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudoir</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>HIV stigma mechanisms and well-being among PLWH: a test of the HIV stigma framework</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23456594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aasland</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT): WHO collaborative project on early detection of persons with harmful alcohol consumption II</article-title>. <source>Addiction</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>791</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8329970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maisto</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Conigliaro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An empirical investigation of the factor structure of the AUDIT</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assess</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11021159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andresen-Streichert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Glahn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol biomarkers in clinical and forensic contexts</article-title>. <source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29807559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing medication adherence self-efficacy among low-literacy patients: development of a pictographic visual analogue scale</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15253999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding patients' adherence-related beliefs about medicines prescribed for long-term conditions: a meta-analytic review of the Necessity-Concerns Framework</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e80633</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24312488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bangsberg</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlebois</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparing objective measures of adherence to HIV antiretroviral therapy: electronic medication monitors and unannounced pill counts</article-title>. <source>AIDS Behav</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monitoring medication adherence by unannounced pill counts conducted by telephone: reliability and criterion-related validity</article-title>. <source>HIV Clin Trials</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18977718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stearns</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to antiretroviral therapy assessed by unannounced pill counts conducted by telephone</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1006</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17390095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mugavero</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Westfall</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beyond core indicators of retention in HIV care: missed clinic visits are independently associated with all-cause mortality</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1471</fpage>–<lpage>1479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25091306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mugavero</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>From access to engagement: measuring retention in outpatient HIV clinical care</article-title>. <source>AIDS patient care and STDs</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20858055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molecular</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RealTime HIV-1 Assay. Abbott Park</article-title>, <source>IL: Abbott Laboratories</source>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.molecular.abbott/us/en/products/infectious-disease/realtime-hiv-1-viral-load" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.molecular.abbott/us/en/products/infectious-disease/realtime-hiv-1-viral-load</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed January 10, 2023</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalichman</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brief behavioral self-regulation counseling for HIV treatment adherence delivered by cell phone: an initial test of concept trial</article-title>. <source>AIDS Patient Care and STDs</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Telephone support to improve antiretroviral medication adherence: a multisite, randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAIDS J Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivet Amico</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of antiretroviral therapy adherence interventions: a research synthesis of trials, 1996 to 2004</article-title>. <source>JAIDS J Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hospers</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Standard care quality determines treatment outcomes in control groups of HAART-adherence intervention studies: implications for the interpretation and comparison of intervention effects</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19916634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Model Templates for PROCESS for SPSS and SAS</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Process analysis: estimating mediation in treatment evaluations</article-title>. <source>Eval Rev</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voils</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Crandell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Informing the dosing of interventions in randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1225</fpage>–<lpage>1230</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22841930</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
