<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:57:13Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10125117" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10125117</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-04-25</datestamp>
        <setSpec>lwwopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transplantation</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transplantation</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TPA</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Transplantation</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0041-1337</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1534-6080</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10125117</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10125117</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10125117</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36279020</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36279020</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00027</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000004373</article-id>
              <article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Clinical Science—General</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Sitagliptin Versus Placebo to Reduce the Incidence and Severity of Posttransplant Diabetes Mellitus After Kidney Transplantation—A Single-center, Randomized, Double-blind Controlled Trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Delos Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Rowena B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hagopian</surname>
                    <given-names>Jennifer C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PharmD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Ling</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
                    <given-names>Madhuri</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wijeweera</surname>
                    <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>CNP</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Klein</surname>
                    <given-names>Christina L.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brennan</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniel C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology, Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO.</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Pharmacy, Barnes-Jewish Hospital, St. Louis, MO.</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Division of Biostatistics, Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO.</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology, University of Kansas, Kansas City, KS.</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label> Piedmont Transplant Institute, Atlanta, GA.</aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label> Nephrology Division and Comprehensive Transplant Center, Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions, Baltimore, MD.</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Rowena B. Delos Santos, MD, Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology, Washington University in St. Louis, MSC 8126-005-0603A, 4523 Clayton Ave, St. Louis, MO 63110. (<email xlink:href="delossantos@wustl.edu">delossantos@wustl.edu</email>).</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>107</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>1180</fpage>
              <lpage>1187</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2022 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="tpa-107-1180.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Background.</title>
                <p>Postkidney transplant diabetes mellitus (PTDM) affects cardiovascular, allograft, and recipient health. We tested whether early intervention with sitagliptin for hyperglycemia (blood glucose &gt;200 mg/dL) within the first week of transplant and discontinued at 3 mo could prevent development of PTDM in patients without preexisting diabetes.</p>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods.</title>
                  <p>The primary efficacy objective was to improve 2-h oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) by <italic toggle="yes">&gt;</italic>20 mg/dL at 3 mo posttransplant. The secondary efficacy objective was to prevent new onset PTDM, defined as a normal OGTT at 3 mo.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results.</title>
                  <p>Sixty-one patients consented, and 50 patients were analyzed. The 3-mo 2-h OGTT (end of treatment) was 141.00 ± 62.44 mg/dL in the sitagliptin arm and 165.22 ± 72.03 mg/dL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.218) in the placebo arm. The 6-mo 2-h OGTT (end of follow-up) was 174.38 ± 77.93 mg/dL in the sitagliptin arm and 171.86 ± 83.69 ng/dL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.918) in the placebo arm. Mean intrapatient difference between 3- and 6-mo 2-h OGTT in the 3-mo period off study drug was 27.56 <italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 52.74 mg/dL in the sitagliptin arm and −0.14 <italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 45.80 mg/dL in the placebo arm (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0692). At 3 mo, 61.54% of sitagliptin and 43.48% of placebo patients had a normal 2-h OGTT (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.2062), with the absolute risk reduction 18.06%. There were no differences in HbA1c at 3 or 6 mo between sitagliptin and placebo groups. Participants tolerated sitagliptin well.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions.</title>
                  <p>Although this study did not show a significant difference between groups, it can inform future studies in the use of sitagliptin in the very early posttransplant period.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>Kidney transplantation improves the quality of life and expectancy of transplant recipients compared with those who remain on dialysis. Although the benefits of transplantation are numerous, risks and complications also accompany this life-changing therapy. One complication that occurs after kidney transplantation is posttransplant diabetes mellitus (PTDM). Diabetes mellitus carries risk of future development of infectious complications, cardiovascular disease, decreased allograft survival, and increased patient mortality.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Historically, new diagnoses of diabetes mellitus affect up to 15% to 50% of posttransplant patients.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Known risk factors for PTDM include family history of diabetes, age, obesity, genetic predisposition, impaired insulin release, impaired insulin uptake by muscle and adipose tissues, and impaired suppression of glucagon release. Transplant-specific factors associated with development of PTDM include hepatitis C and cytomegalovirus infections, polycystic kidney disease history, and use of immunosuppressant medications such as corticosteroids and calcineurin inhibitors.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Corticosteroids lead to increased gluconeogenesis and decreased glycogen synthesis by the liver, increase lipolysis and triglyceride release from adipose tissue, increase central and visceral adiposity, and decrease glucose uptake by muscles. Calcineurin inhibitors lead to impaired glucose tolerance and diabetes through decreased insulin gene expression and induction of islet cell apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The majority of patients who are not previously diabetic may develop new PTDM in the first 3 mo after a transplant.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Conversion from hyperglycemia to PTDM is not fully predictable, and prevention of new PTDM is paramount in a population that faces other health concerns.</p>
              <p>The stresses of surgery, along with high-initial doses of corticosteroids to promote graft acceptance and higher calcineurin inhibitor doses to help avoid early rejection, are contributing factors. Patients documented to have impaired glucose tolerance by the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) pretransplant are at greater risk of developing new PTDM posttransplant.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Performing this test routinely is not done because of logistics and costs because candidates can spend years on the kidney transplant waiting list. Hyperglycemia in the very early postkidney transplant period is very common, with a reported rate of 90%. Nondiabetics with significant hyperglycemia (blood glucose &gt;200 mg/dL) during the first week posttransplant have higher rates of newly diagnosed PTDM.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Although labs are monitored frequently in the early posttransplant period and recognition of hyperglycemia is apparent, there are limited strategies to prevent the development of new PTDM. Rapid tapering of corticosteroids and lowering calcineurin inhibitor levels may not occur early posttransplant because of the concern for acute rejection.</p>
              <p>Previous investigators have used various medications to treat posttransplant diabetes mellitus, including metformin, insulin, and dipeptidyl-peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> One notable study has attempted to prevent PTDM through isophane insulin use within the first 12 mo posttransplant.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Although effective at preventing PTDM compared with standard-of-care at 12 mo, there were incidences of asymptomatic hypoglycemia in the insulin-treated group.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> There have been no studies to our knowledge using DPP-2 inhibitors starting the first week of transplant to prevent PTDM in previously nondiabetic transplant recipients. Sitagliptin, an orally active antidiabetic agent, is part of the family of DPP-4 inhibitors. Normally, endogenous incretin hormones, glucagon-like peptide (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) are rapidly inactivated by DPP-4. DPP-4 inhibitors work by inhibiting plasma DPP-4 function, thus allowing increased levels of incretin hormones GLP-1 and GIP in the postprandial setting. This potentiates glucose stimulated insulin production and release and slows glucagon release without causing hypoglycemia.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In diabetic animal models, it has led to improvement in beta cell function and neogenesis.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> The lack of hypoglycemia and other manifestations of gastrointestinal side effects makes DPP-4 inhibitors generally well tolerated among patients. A prospective study has shown that treatment of PTDM with sitagliptin was effective in lowering hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) in kidney transplant patients with new onset diabetes after transplant and importantly did not alter calcineurin inhibitor levels.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> To our knowledge, the use of sitagliptin for prevention of new PTDM has not been described in the literature. Given its mechanism of action and safety profile, we hypothesized that sitagliptin is an ideal pharmacologic agent to prevent new PTDM in the first 3 mo of transplant.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study Design and Subjects</title>
                <p>This was a single-center, randomized, double-blind, and placebo-controlled trial in kidney transplant recipients to evaluate the role of sitagliptin in the prevention of PTDM. Participants in the trial provided written informed consent. The trial adhered to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. The study was approved by the Washington University in Saint Louis institutional review board (IRB ID no. 201306111 and registered NCT number NCT01928199).</p>
                <p>All adults aged 18 y or older who received a living or deceased kidney allograft after July 25, 2013, were evaluated for inclusion. Those without a history of diabetes were screened for postoperative hyperglycemia (random blood glucose &gt;200 mg/dL) within the first 72 h following transplantation. In June 2015, the inclusion time point was expanded to 120 h posttransplant based on the finding that there were patients who screened positive outside the initial 72 h. Exclusion criteria included a history of diabetes including diet-controlled diabetes; history of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agent use before transplant; inclusion of the patient being placed on medication then taken off as a result of improved glycemic control; HbA1c ≥6.5% immediately before transplant; recipient of simultaneous kidney-pancreas, kidney-liver, kidney-heart, or kidney-lung transplant; or history of prior nonrenal transplant.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Study Procedures</title>
                <p>Those that screened positive for postoperative hyperglycemia were approached to participate in the study. Once consented, patients were randomized by the research pharmacist by block randomization to receive sitagliptin or placebo, and they kept record of patient allocation, whereas the rest of the study team and participants remained blinded. Placebo tablets were provided that looked identical in shape, color, and size to a 25-mg sitagliptin tablet. Randomization was based upon a stratification of pretransplant HbA1c (&lt;5.7% or 5.7%–6.4%). The target enrollment was 50 patients but was later extended to 61 patients to account for drop out and loss to follow-up. After randomization, patients continued on the study drug, adjusted for renal function for 3 mo. At 3 mo’ time, the study drug was discontinued, and patients were followed for an additional 3 mo off the study drug.</p>
                <p>Participants had outpatient study visits at 1 mo, 3 mo, and 6 mo after discharge. Patients were instructed to monitor their blood glucose at least 1 time per day via finger stick glucometer; however, monitoring of fasting blood glucose and 2 h after the largest meal of the day was requested. At the 1-mo and 3-mo visit, an investigator reviewed the blood glucose logs and assessed for adverse effects. Additionally, at the 3-mo study visit, HbA1c, 2-h OGTT blood glucose, and fasting C-peptide level were obtained. Following discontinuation of the study medication at the 3-mo study visit, participants had a 6-mo study visit where repeat HbA1c, 2-h OGTT blood glucose, and fasting C-peptide level were obtained.</p>
                <p>In addition to the monitoring for the study described above, patients obtained routine posttransplant laboratory monitoring including a complete blood count, renal panel, and tacrolimus trough level. Labs were assessed per center protocol twice weekly for 2 wks, weekly between 2 through 12 wks, and every 2 wks for the duration of the study.</p>
                <p>Elevated blood glucose readings were assessed by the study investigators. Diagnosis and treatment of diabetes was in accordance with published guidelines with the exception that add-on therapy to the study medication could not include use of a DPP-4 inhibitor because the investigators were blinded to the randomized arm.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Primary and Secondary Endpoints</title>
                <p>The primary efficacy objective was to assess the efficacy of sitagliptin to improve 2-h OGTT by &gt;20 mg/dL at 3 mo posttransplant in patients without preexisting diabetes undergoing living-donor or deceased-donor kidney transplant compared with placebo. The secondary efficacy objective was to assess the efficacy of sitagliptin to prevent new onset posttransplant diabetes mellitus as determined by a normal OGTT at 3 mo posttransplant in patients without preexisting diabetes undergoing living-donor or deceased-donor kidney transplant compared with placebo. The primary efficacy endpoint was a difference in 2-h OGTT blood glucose of ≥20 mg/dL assessed at the 3-mo study visit. For reference, a normal fasting glucose is &lt;100 mg/dL; at 2 h, the expected normal value of glucose for an OGTT is &lt;140 mg/dL; 140 mg/dL to 199 mg/dL indicates impaired glucose tolerance; and a value &gt;200 mg/dL is diagnostic of diabetes mellitus. These levels were compared with the values at the 6-mo study visit. The secondary endpoint assessed in this study was the attainment of a normal 2-h OGTT blood glucose at 3 mo in the study group compared with placebo. Other outcomes included the improvement of HbA1c by ≥0.5% between groups, differences between fasting OGTT blood glucose, fasting blood glucose, postprandial blood glucose, fasting C-peptide, and fasting insulin within the groups from the end of treatment compared with the end of the observation period. Assessments of graft function and immunosuppression serum levels were also assessed between study groups.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Maintenance Immunosuppression</title>
                <p>Maintenance immunosuppression was standardized and included administration of methylprednisolone 7 mg/kg on the day of transplant followed by oral prednisone 1 mg/kg (maximum 80 mg) on postoperative days (PODs) 1 and 2 followed by 20 mg daily for 10 d, 15 mg daily for 7 d, 10 mg daily for 7 d, and then 5 mg daily thereafter. Tacrolimus was initiated on POD 1 and adjusted to a target tacrolimus trough level of 7 to 10 ng/mL for 1 mo, then 3 to 7 ng/mL for the remainder of the study period. Mycophenolate sodium was initiated at 720 mg BID and reduced to 360 mg BID once the target tacrolimus trough level was achieved.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>Demographic and admission variables were compared between groups using the 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test or Mann-Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test for continuous variables as appropriate. Categorical variables were tested using the chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test as appropriate. Analysis was based on the intention-to-treat principle. Efficacy outcomes were defined as change from month 3 to month 6. Mean change of outcomes was compared between groups using the 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. All statistical tests were 2-sided at significance level 0.05, and analyses were performed with SAS, version 9.4 (SAS Inc, Cary, NC).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Sample Size Calculation</title>
                <p>Based on a sample size of 25 patients per group, this study has 80.7% power to detect a mean difference of 20 mg/dL in 2-h OGTT based on the 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test at significance level 0.05. The calculation assumes a SD of 25 mg/dL or less between groups.<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>In total, 61 patients consented to be in the study, 32 in the sitagliptin arm and 29 in the placebo arm. CONSORT flow diagram Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> indicates enrollment and follow-up for the study. By the end of study, 27 patients in the sitagliptin arm and 23 patients in the placebo arm completed at least the 3- or 6-mo visit for inclusion in the efficacy analyses. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows baseline characteristics between the 2 groups. There were no differences in sex, race, cause of end-stage renal disease, type of transplant, or comorbidities between the groups. The mean baseline HbA1c in the sitagliptin and placebo arms was 5.27% (+0.46%) and 5.13% (+0.41%) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.23), respectively. The mean participant body mass index at study entry was 28.82 kg/m<sup>2</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 4.58 in the sitagliptin group and 29.40 kg/m<sup>2</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 4.27 in the placebo group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.6133). The time of day for the qualifying blood glucose &gt;200 mg/dL was divided between midnight to 8:00 AM, 8:01 to 4:00 PM, and 4:01 PM through midnight. Nineteen patients (31.15%) qualified during the midnight to 8:00 AM time period, another 15 patients (24.59%) qualified during the 8:01 AM to 4:00 PM time point, and 27 patients (44.26%) had qualifying blood glucoses levels during the 4:01 PM through midnight time period. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the time points where patients qualified separated between study groups.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>TABLE 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Baseline patient demographics and characteristics</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographic or characteristic</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo (N = 29)</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitagliptin (N = 32)</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at transplant (y)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.81 ± 16.54</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.71 ± 12.63</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7718</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HgbA1c at admit (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13 ± 0.41</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27 ± 0.46</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2307</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6661</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Male</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (58.6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (53.1)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (41.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (46.9)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3111</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (79.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (68.8)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (17.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (25.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cause of ESRD, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2148</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.8)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (31.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IgA</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PKD</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.1)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> FSGS</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other GN</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lupus</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.8)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of transplant, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8279</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Living related</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (15.6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Living unrelated</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (18.8)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Deceased donor</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (69.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (65.6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMV status donor/recipient, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3489</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Donor+/recipient–</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (17.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (28.1)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Donor±/recipient+</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (62)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (62.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Donor–/recipient–</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of DM, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8491</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (79.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (81.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(20.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (18.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI at time of transplant (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.40 ± 4.27</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.82 ± 4.58</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6133</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of day plasma glucose &gt;200 mg/dL to qualify for study, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3849</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 00:01–08:00</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (31.03)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (31.25)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 08:01–16:00</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (17.24)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (31.25)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 16:01–00:00</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (51.72)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (37.50)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn fn-type="other">
                    <p>Mean ± SD for continuous variables and no. (%) for categorical variables.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn fn-type="other">
                    <p>BMI, body mass index; CMV, cytomegalovirus; DM, diabetes mellitus; ESRD, end stage renal disease; FSGS, focal segmental glomerulosclerosis; GN, glomerulonephritis; PKD, polycystic kidney disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig position="float" id="F1">
                <label>FIGURE 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>CONSORT diagram of the patient participation in the study.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="tpa-107-1180-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <sec>
                <title>Primary and Secondary Efficacy Analysis</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Primary Efficacy Analysis</title>
                  <p>The 3-mo 2-h OGTT at the end of study drug treatment duration was 141.00 ± 62.44 mg/dL in the sitagliptin arm and 165.22 ± 72.03 mg/dL in the placebo arm, with a difference of 24.22 mg/dL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.218). This was not statistically significant. The sitagliptin arm mean 2-h OGTT was just above the normal cutoff of 139 mg/dL for a normal OGTT. The 6-mo 2-h OGTT was 174.38 ± 77.93 mg/dL in the sitagliptin arm and 171.86 ± 83.69 ng/dL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.918) in the placebo arm. Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> depicts the 2-h OGTT for months 3 and 6 for placebo and sitagliptin groups. The mean intrapatient difference between months 3 and 6, 2-h OGTT (6-mo OGTT–3-mo OGTT) was 27.56 <italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 52.74 in the sitagliptin arm and −0.14 <italic toggle="yes">+</italic> 45.80 in the placebo arm (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0692). Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the findings of the primary efficacy analysis.</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                    <label>TABLE 2.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Primary and secondary efficacy outcome data</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo (N = 23)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitagliptin (N = 27)</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-h OGTT 3 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.22 ± 72.03</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.00 ± 62.44</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2180</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-h OGTT 6 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171.86 ± 83.69</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.38 ± 77.93</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9177</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference between 3-mo and 6-mo 2-h OGTT (mg/dL)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14 ± 45.80</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.57 ± 52.74</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0692</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with normal 2-h OGTT at 3-mo %</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.48</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.54</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2678</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with normal 2-h OGTT at 6-mon %</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.62</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.67</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9000</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c 3 mo (%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78 ± 0.85</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52 ± 0.58</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2333</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c 6 mo (%)</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79 ± 0.69</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91 ± 0.84</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5998</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolute mean difference in HbA1c 3 and 6 mo</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01%</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0568</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn fn-type="other">
                        <p>Mean ± SD for continuous variables and no. (%) for categorical variables.</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn fn-type="other">
                        <p>OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <fig position="float" id="F2">
                    <label>FIGURE 2.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>It shows the 2-h OGTT for months 3 and 6 for placebo (solid line) and sitagliptin (dash line) groups. OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="tpa-107-1180-g002" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Secondary Efficacy Analysis</title>
                  <p>The percentage of patients in the sitagliptin and placebo arms at 3 mo with a normal 2-h OGTT was 61.54% and 43.48% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.2678) with the absolute risk reduction 18.06%. At 6 mo, when both groups had a 3-mo washout period without the study drug, the percentage of patients in the sitagliptin and placebo arms with a normal 2-h OGTT was 41.67% and 47.62%, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.900).</p>
                  <p>No difference was seen in HbA1c between treatment groups at the end of the treatment period or at the end of the follow-up period. Comparing sitagliptin versus placebo, at 3 mo, the HbA1c was 5.52% ± 0.58% versus 5.78% ± 0.85% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.2333), and at 6 mo, the HbA1c was 5.91% ± 0.84% versus 5.79% ± 0.69% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.5998). The absolute mean difference in HbA1c between 3 and 6 mo (6 mo–3 mo) was 0.39% and 0.01% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0568) in the sitagliptin and placebo groups, respectively. Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> illustrates the change in HbA1c between 3 and 6 mo for placebo and sitagliptin groups.</p>
                  <fig position="float" id="F3">
                    <label>FIGURE 3.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>It illustrates the change in HbA1c between 3 and 6 mo for placebo (solid line) and sitagliptin (dash line) groups.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="tpa-107-1180-g003" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Glycemic Outcomes</title>
                <p>Fasting OGTT, average fasting blood glucose, average postprandial blood glucose, and fasting insulin and fasting C-peptide values at the 3- and 6-mo time points, as well as OGTT results divided between normal, impaired glucose tolerance and diabetes, are shown in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. There were no significant mean or proportion differences in these outcomes. Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> illustrates the fasting OGTT change from months 3 to 6 for placebo and sitagliptin groups.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>TABLE 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Glucose and metabolic outcome data</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo (N = 23)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitagliptin (N = 27)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting OGTT 3 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.35 ± 17.76</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.92 ± 18.91</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6268</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting OGTT 6 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.67 ± 18.56</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.33 ± 20.12</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9533</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference between 3 and 6 mo fasting OGTT (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 ± 14.01</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 ± 19.78</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7125</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 mo C-peptide (ng/mL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08 ± 1.52</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 ± 1.48</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8922</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 mo C-peptide (ng/mL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01 ± 1.65</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04 ± 1.35</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9435</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 mo fasting insulin (µIU/mL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.78 ± 7.81</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.37 ± 7.01</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8446</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 mo fasting insulin (µIU/mL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.11 ± 7.42</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.72 ± 6.54</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8490</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average BS fasting 3-mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.43 ± 35.21</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.30 ± 12.86</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3711</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average BS fasting 6-mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.75 ± 23.12</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.18 ± 26.88</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2560</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average BS 2-h postprandial 3-mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.13 ± 51.93</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.00 ± 24.34</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4451</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average BS 2-h postprandial 6-mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.88 ± 22.86</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.67 ± 20.50</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4354</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OGTT results 3 mo, n (%)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2678</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (43.48)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (61.54)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Impaired</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (34.78)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15.38)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.74)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (23.08)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OGTT results 6 mo, n (%)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8998</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (47.62)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (41.67)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Impaired</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (28.57)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (29.17)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (23.81)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (29.17)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn fn-type="other">
                      <p>Mean ± SD for continuous variables and no. (%) for categorical variables.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn fn-type="other">
                      <p>BS, blood sugar; OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig position="float" id="F4">
                  <label>FIGURE 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>It illustrates the fasting OGTT for months 3 and 6 for placebo (solid line) and sitagliptin (dash line) groups. OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="tpa-107-1180-g004" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>One month into study participation, 2 patients in the sitagliptin arm and 3 patients in the placebo arm became diabetic and required additional medication to treat hyperglycemia. By the 3-mo follow-up, a total of 3 patients in the sitagliptin arm and 5 patients in the placebo arm were already identified as diabetic, requiring additional medication to treat hyperglycemia. Additional patients were identified at the time of the 3 mo follow-up OGTT. At the final 6-mo follow-up, a total of 5 in the sitagliptin group and 6 in the placebo group were diabetic and required additional medication to treat hyperglycemia, with additional patients identified at the time of the 6-mo OGTT. Medications used to treat these patients for diabetes included metformin, sulfonylureas, and insulin.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Safety Outcomes</title>
                <p>Overall, the study medication was well tolerated. Both groups had similar renal function and tacrolimus levels through the follow-up period (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). No patients experienced acute cellular or antibody mediated rejection or allograft failure during the follow-up. Three patients had serious adverse events by month 3 in both the sitagliptin arm and the placebo arm (11.54% versus 13.04%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.8729). Events included a urine leak with need for surgical intervention, volume overload, and right arm weakness in the sitagliptin group. In the placebo group, 1 patient had a hernia repair, another had shortness of breath, and another underwent elective bilateral native nephrectomies. There were 2 additional patients with serious adverse events by month 6 in the sitagliptin arm and one in the placebo arm (7.41% versus 5%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.7414). This included admission for nausea and vomiting and a ureteral stricture, respectively. However, no patients discontinued study medication in either group because of adverse effects. Events were unlikely to be related to side effects from the study drug.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                  <label>TABLE 4.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Mean creatinine and tacrolimus levels at 1, 3, and 6 mo and hemoglobin at baseline, 3, and 6 mo</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo (n = 23)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitagliptin (n = 27)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean creatinine 1 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 ± 0.44</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 ± 0.55</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8081</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean creatinine 3 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 ± 0.27</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 ± 0.42</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4029</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean creatinine 6 mo (mg/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 ± 0.31</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 ± 0.46</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2433</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean tacrolimus level 1 mo (µg/L)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38 ± 4.27</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21 ± 3.81</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3080</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean tacrolimus level 3 mo (µg/L)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.87 ± 2.45</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.63 ± 3.39</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7846</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean tacrolimus level 6 mo (µg/L)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73 ± 2.52</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.12 ± 2.37</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5951</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Hgb at baseline (g/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.81 ± 1.54</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.21 ± 1.63</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3307</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Hgb 3 mo (g/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.27 ± 1.88</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.21 ± 1.24</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9013</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Hgb 6 mo (g/dL)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.86 ± 1.62</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.48 ± 1.30</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3910</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study to evaluate the use of sitagliptin initiated at the time of transplant to prevent the development of PTDM in kidney transplant recipients without preexisting diabetes but who had early posttransplant hyperglycemia. We used a medication class that would be beneficial in this population given its mechanism of action, lack of interaction with immunosuppressants, and low risk of hypoglycemia or other adverse effects. Posttransplant use of DPP-4 inhibitors has been examined in prior studies. A study conducted by Lane et al evaluated sitagliptin in 15 patients who were on average 4.7 years out from transplant but developed diabetes posttransplant.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> They showed that sitagliptin was effective in lowering the HbA1c without affecting immunosuppression levels for tacrolimus or sirolimus. Werzowa et al explored the use of vildagliptin or pioglitazone in comparison to placebo over a 3-mo period in 48 renal transplant patients at least 6 months posttransplant.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Vildagliptin, pioglitazone, or placebo were initiated in patients who were found to have impaired glucose tolerance with OGTT (2-h OGTT result 140 mg/dL to 199 mg/dL), and given treatment for 3 mo. The investigators found that vildagliptin and pioglitazone improved 2-h OGTT in patients with impaired glucose tolerance at least 6 mo out from transplant, although the difference in change in 2-h OGTT was not statistically significant. In a follow-up randomized controlled trial, Haidinger et al compared vildagliptin to placebo in stable posttransplant patients at least 6 mo posttransplant who were newly diagnosed with PTDM through routine OGTT testing (2-h OGTT <italic toggle="yes">&gt;</italic>200 mg/dL). They found that vildagliptin improved 2-h OGTT results and HgbA1c levels compared with placebo.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Our trial used sitagliptin within the first week posttransplant to improve glycemic control when blood glucose levels were elevated because of the physical stress of transplant surgery and medications that increase blood glucose.</p>
              <p>There is only 1 other study to our knowledge that sought to treat early hyperglycemia posttransplantation with the intention of reducing PTDM. This randomized trial compared early postoperative intermediate acting (isophane) insulin (treatment group) with treatment using short-acting insulin and oral sulfonylurea (control/standard-of-care group) according to consensus treatment guidelines, with the primary endpoint being the difference in HbA1c at 3 mo.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Medications were titrated up or down based on blood glucose levels recorded the evening prior. Although the HbA1c increased from a baseline obtained at the time of transplant for both groups, the investigators found that, at 3 mo, there was a lower mean difference in HbA1c of 0.52% in the treatment isophane insulin group compared with standard-of-care (control). Five patients experienced asymptomatic hypoglycemia, defined in the study as blood glucose 41 to 60 mg/d, in the treatment group compared with 1 patient as the control group. Although the strategy of early tight blood glucose control early after transplant seemed to help prevent long-term PTDM, hypoglycemia remains a significant concern in newly transplanted patients when medications are changing regularly, particularly in patients new to insulin who may not be fully aware of the symptoms associated with hypoglycemia. An advantage of our study design was to use a DDP-4 inhibitor with a low risk of hypoglycemia. We did not observe any incidence of hypoglycemia in our study.</p>
              <p>The kidney transplant population is a unique group of patients because their risk of newly diagnosed diabetes mellitus posttransplant is greatest at the beginning of transplant. Perhaps the most well-known diabetes prevention study in the general population is the Diabetes Prevention Program, which studied standard lifestyle recommendations plus placebo, standard lifestyle recommendations plus metformin, or intensive lifestyle modification over the course of 2.8 y.<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The incidence of diabetes was reduced by 58% in the intensive lifestyle modification and 31% in the metformin group compared with placebo.<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> These methods have limitations, preventing implementation in the early posttransplant period because of fluctuating and oftentimes elevated Cr in the first several weeks after transplant and thus the inability to prescribe metformin early on, and patients are unable to tolerate moderately intensive exercise in the early part of their transplant because of recent surgery.</p>
              <p>The primary objective of our study was to assess sitagliptin ability to improve 2-h OGTT by ≥20 mg/dL at 3 mo posttransplant. We observed a lower 2-h OGTT in the sitagliptin group (141.00 ± 62.44) than in the placebo group (165.22 ± 72.03); although this was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.218), it may be clinically significant and paralleled the reported average blood sugar 2-h postprandial at 3 mo (sitagliptin 140.00 ± 24.34 and placebo 162.13 ± 51.93, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.4451). After discontinuation of the study drug at 3 mo, there was no difference between sitagliptin or placebo arms in 2-h OGTT at 6 mo posttransplant (sitagliptin 174.38 mg/dL ± 77.93 versus placebo 171.86 mg/dL ± 83.69), with a mean increase in HbA1c between 3 and 6 mo of 0.39% in the sitagliptin arm compared with 0.01% in the placebo arm (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0568). The secondary objective of this study was to assess sitagliptin ability to prevent new onset PTDM at 3 mo versus placebo. We found that 61.54% of the sitagliptin arm has a normal 2-h OGTT at 3 mo (2-h BS &lt;−140 mg/dL) compared with 43.48% of the placebo arm, not reaching statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.2062). Notably, more patients in the sitagliptin arm required treatment for diabetes by the 6 mo OGTT, suggesting that they may have derived some benefit to blood glucose lowering with the sitagliptin. Given the lack of meeting statistical significance for both the primary and secondary objectives of this study, our findings were ultimately negative.</p>
              <p>Our study was limited by sample size, and findings can be useful to power a future study. Although the HbA1c test can be affected by anemia and renal function, which can fluctuate within the first several months after transplant, we evaluated the baseline and 3- and 6-mo Hgb levels and serum creatinine and mean tacrolimus levels and found no significant difference between the sitagliptin and placebo groups (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The use of OGTT as the primary test for patients in this study was used because both anemia and renal functions affect HbA1c, and our goal was to use a test that was not affected by labs that may be fluctuating as we performed our study procedures. However, patients in the study did have their first OGTT on the last day of taking their study drug, and thus, those on the sitagliptin would be expected to have a lower OGTT.</p>
              <p>There is evidence from prior studies that poor glycemic control early posttransplant is associated with increased risk of perioperative infections.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Although this current study did not specifically evaluate for a difference in early posttransplant infections related to hyperglycemia, no significant infections were reported. It is not clear whether continuing patients on the study drug through the first 6 mo would provide benefit in prevention of new onset PTDM or impaired glucose tolerance. Withdrawal of sitagliptin at the 3-mo follow-up led to an increase in the 2-h OGTT and HbA1c for the intervention patients, indicating a potential benefit of extending sitagliptin. The advantage of sitagliptin is the lack of hypoglycemic episodes, ease of use and tolerability by patients with minimal side effects, decreased morbidity with respect to infectious complications, and lack of potential interaction with immunosuppression. We believe our study, although not showing statistical significance, can better inform future studies that evaluate the management of posttransplant hyperglycemia in patients with no preexisting diabetes.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
                <p>This study was funded by a grant from Merck, who provided study medication and placebo for the study, and supported by Washington University Diabetes Research Center National Institutes of Health grant P30 DK020579, Clinical and Translational Science Award grant UL1 TR002345, and Siteman Comprehensive Cancer Center and National Cancer Institute/Cancer Center Support grant P30 CA091842. These supporters had no role in study design, data collection, or analysis.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Clinical Trial Notation: Clinical Trials.gov (NCT01928199).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>
                  <italic toggle="yes">R.D.S. has received grant funding to Washington University from Merck, Novartis, Veloxis, and CareDx; has received honoraria from Veloxis and Alexion and royalties from UpToDate; and has equity in Pfizer. J.C.H. has received honoraria from Veloxis. C.L.K. has received honoraria from Veloxis, Sanofi, and Nephrosant and royalties from UpToDate. D.C.B. has received grant funding to Johns Hopkins from Amplyx, Allovir, CareDx, and Natera and consulting fees or honoraria from CareDx, Medeor, Sanofi, and Veloxis and is on the editorial board for Transplantation and UpToDate. L.C., M.R., and H.W. declare no conflict of interest.</italic>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="equal">
                <p>R.D.S. participated in the research design, writing of the article, performance of the research, and data analysis. J.C.H. participated in writing of the article, performance of the research, and data analysis. L.C. participated in writing of the article and data analysis. M.R. participated in performance of the research. H.W. participated in the performance of the research, writing of the article, and data analysis. C.L.K. participated in research design, writing of the article, and performance of the research. D.C.B. participated in research design and writing of the article.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasiske</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbertson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes mellitus after kidney transplantation in the United States.</article-title><source>Am J Transplant</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wauters</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosio</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez Fernandez</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular consequences of new-onset hyperglycemia after kidney transplantation.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valderhaug</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjelmesæth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The association of early post-transplant glucose levels with long-term mortality.</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1341</fpage>–<lpage>1349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21409415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Iqbal A, Zhou K, Kashyap SR, Lansang MC. Early post-renal transplant hyperglycemia. <italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic>. 2022;107:549–562.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnitzler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and cost of new onset diabetes mellitus among U.S. wait-listed and transplanted renal allograft recipients.</article-title><source>Am J Transplant</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>590</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12752315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakkera</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Devarapalli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between inpatient hyperglycemia and insulin treatment after kidney transplantation and future new onset diabetes mellitus.</article-title><source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1669</fpage>–<lpage>1675</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20558559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenssen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Post-transplant diabetes mellitus in patients with solid organ transplants.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30622369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourlanos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjelmesaeth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New-onset diabetes after kidney transplantation-changes and challenges.</article-title><source>Am J Transplant</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>–<lpage>828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22123607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David-Neto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadel</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The dynamics of glucose metabolism under calcineurin inhibitors in the first year after renal transplantation in nonobese patients.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17627237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porrini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Osuna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prediabetes in patients receiving tacrolimus in the first year after kidney transplantation: a prospective and multicenter study.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1133</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18431233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caillard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eprinchard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and risk factors of glucose metabolism disorders in kidney transplant recipients: role of systematic screening by oral glucose tolerance test.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>764</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21336240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hecking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haidinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Döller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early basal insulin therapy decreases new-onset diabetes after renal transplantation.</article-title><source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22343119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haidinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Werzowa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of vildagliptin in new-onset diabetes after kidney transplantation–a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial.</article-title><source>Am J Transplant</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alnasrallah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transplantation and diabetes (Transdiab): a pilot randomised controlled trial of metformin in impaired glucose tolerance after kidney transplantation.</article-title><source>BMC Nephrol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31035960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of sitagliptin, an inhibitor of dipeptidyl peptidase IV, in healthy subjects: results from two randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies with single oral doses.</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16338283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of single oral doses of sitagliptin, a dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitor, on incretin and plasma glucose levels after an oral glucose tolerance test in patients with type 2 diabetes.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>4612</fpage>–<lpage>4619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirakawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohminami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitor against increased β cell apoptosis induced by dietary sucrose and linoleic acid in mice with diabetes.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>286</volume>:<fpage>25467</fpage>–<lpage>25476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21613229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Odegaard</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haire</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sitagliptin therapy in kidney transplant recipients with new-onset diabetes after transplantation.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>e56</fpage>–<lpage>e57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22067216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic evaluation of oral glucose tolerance tests in nondiabetic subjects after various levels of carbohydrate intake.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1960</year>;<volume>262</volume>:<fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13844739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Odegaard</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haire</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sitagliptin therapy in kidney transplant recipients with new-onset diabetes after transplantation.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>e56</fpage>–<lpage>e57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22067216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werzowa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haidinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vildagliptin and pioglitazone in patients with impaired glucose tolerance after kidney transplantation: a randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23380864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Knowler WC, Barrett-Connor E, Flowler SE, et al. <article-title>Reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes with lifestyle intervention or metformin.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832527</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourfarziani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early hyperglycemia after allogenic kidney transplantation: does it induce infections.</article-title><source>Ann Transplant</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344934</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early peri-operative glycaemic control and allograft rejection in patients with diabetes mellitus: a pilot study.</article-title><source>Transplantation</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>1324</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11602863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
