<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T07:44:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3645973" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3645973</identifier>
        <datestamp>2013-05-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcgeri</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Geriatr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Geriatr</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Geriatrics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2318</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3645973</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3645973</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3645973</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23635086</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2318-13-38</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23635086</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2318-13-38</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Laxative use and incident falls, fractures and change in bone mineral density in postmenopausal women: results from the Women’s Health Initiative</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Haring</surname>
                    <given-names>Bernhard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                  <email>Haring_B@medizin.uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pettinger</surname>
                    <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
                  <email>mpettinger@whi.org</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bea</surname>
                    <given-names>Jennifer W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
                  <email>jbea@azcc.arizona.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wactawski-Wende</surname>
                    <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
                  <email>jww@buffalo.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Carnahan</surname>
                    <given-names>Ryan M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
                  <email>ryan-carnahan@uiowa.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ockene</surname>
                    <given-names>Judith K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref>
                  <email>Judith.Ockene@umassmed.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wyler von Ballmoos</surname>
                    <given-names>Moritz</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref>
                  <email>mcwvb@post.harvard.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wallace</surname>
                    <given-names>Robert B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref>
                  <email>robert-wallace@uiowa.edu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wassertheil-Smoller</surname>
                    <given-names>Sylvia</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref>
                  <email>Sylvia.Smoller@einstein.yu.edu</email>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine I, Comprehensive Heart Failure Center, University of Würzburg, Oberdürrbacher Strasse 6, Würzburg, 97080, Germany</aff>
              <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Arizona Cancer Center, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, University at Buffalo, SUNY School of Public Health and Health Professions, Buffalo, NY, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Department of Epidemiology, University of Iowa College of Public Health, Iowa City, Iowa, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Division of Preventive and Behavioral Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Department of Surgery &amp; Division of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Froedtert Memorial Hospital &amp; Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
              <aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Department of Epidemiology and Population Health, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York, USA</aff>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>13</volume>
              <fpage>38</fpage>
              <lpage>38</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Haring et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Haring et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2318/13/38"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>Laxatives are among the most widely used over-the-counter medications in the United States but studies examining their potential hazardous side effects are sparse. Associations between laxative use and risk for fractures and change in bone mineral density [BMD] have not previously been investigated.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>This prospective analysis included 161,808 postmenopausal women (8907 users and 151,497 nonusers of laxatives) enrolled in the WHI Observational Study and Clinical Trials. Women were recruited from October 1, 1993, to December 31, 1998, at 40 clinical centers in the United States and were eligible if they were 50 to 79 years old and were postmenopausal at the time of enrollment. Medication inventories were obtained during in-person interviews at baseline and at the 3-year follow-up visit on everyone. Data on self-reported falls (≥2), fractures (hip and total fractures) were used. BMD was determined at baseline and year 3 at 3 of the 40 clinical centers of the WHI.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Age-adjusted rates of hip fractures and total fractures, but not for falls were similar between laxative users and non-users regardless of duration of laxative use. The multivariate-adjusted hazard ratios for any laxative use were 1.06 (95% confidence interval [CI], 1.03-1.10) for falls, 1.02 (95% CI, 0.85-1.22) for hip fractures and 1.01 (95% CI, 0.96-1.07) for total fractures. The BMD levels did not statistically differ between laxative users and nonusers at any skeletal site after 3-years intake.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>These findings support a modest association between laxative use and increase in the risk of falls but not for fractures. Its use did not decrease bone mineral density levels in postmenopausal women. Maintaining physical functioning, and providing adequate treatment of comorbidities that predispose individuals for falls should be considered as first measures to avoid potential negative consequences associated with laxative use.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Laxative use</kwd>
                <kwd>Falls</kwd>
                <kwd>Fractures</kwd>
                <kwd>Bone mineral density</kwd>
                <kwd>Aging</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec>
              <title>Background</title>
              <p>Laxatives belong to one of the most frequently sold over-the-counter pharmacy sales categories in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. In 2011, consumers spent approximately $875 million on laxative drug products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. This easy availability can facilitate use without indication, long-term use, inappropriate dosing and even abuse of these medicines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Electrolyte and fluid imbalances have been reported as potential negative consequences and side-effects of laxative use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. These medical conditions are known causes of muscle weakness, lassitude, cardiac arrhythmias, and osteoporosis that may increase the risk for falls and fractures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In fact, use of a wide range of prescription drugs such as loop diuretics or antiepileptics have already been shown to be associated with falls, fractures and even changes in bone mineral density as these drugs may alter fluid and electrolyte metabolism (e.g. hyponatremia, hypocalemia) and even vitamin D absorption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p>
              <p>To this point, prior epidemiological studies suggest that laxative use increases the risk for falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. However, these studies were limited by small numbers of falls, lack of data on important potential confounders and short follow-up period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Additionally, although electrolyte and fluid imbalances, vitamin malabsorption as well as a history of falls are important risk factors for changes in bone mineral density and fractures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], the effect of laxative use on these bone outcomes remains to be determined.</p>
              <p>Based on current literature laxative users may be characterized by several different groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. The first and by far largest group is made up of individuals who are generally middle aged or older who begin using laxatives when constipated. The second group consists of individuals suffering from an eating disorder such as anorexia or bulimia nervosa. Third, individuals engaged in certain types of sports training may be inclined to be users. The fourth group includes surreptitious laxative abusers who use the drugs to cause factitious diarrhea. As constipation occurs more frequently in the female population and it becomes more prevalent with increasing age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], the role of laxative use in postmenopausal women is of particular interest.</p>
              <p>Our aim is to evaluate a possible association of laxative intake with the incidence of falls, total fractures, hip fractures and change in bone mineral density in postmenopausal women. Such information may provide insight into the safety profile and potential hazards of a widely used medication class and thereby be of high public health relevance.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>The study population consisted of 161,808 women enrolled in the Women’s Health Initiative (WHI) Observational Study (OS) (n=93,676) and Clinical Trials (CTs) (n=68,132). Details of the study population have been described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. For this analysis, 160,404 women with no prior hip fracture (OS: n=92,789/CT: n=67,615) were included. Women were recruited from October 1, 1993, to December 31, 1998, at 40 clinical centers in the United States and were eligible if they were 50 to 79 years old and were postmenopausal at the time of enrollment. In addition to age and menopausal status, eligibility criteria for the clinical trial (CT) and observational study (OS) included ability and willingness to provide written informed consent and an agreement to reside in the area for at least 3 years after enrollment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Participants were subsequently followed up through March 31, 2005, for an average of 7.8 years (OS: 7.6 years /CT: 8 years). Among 160,404 women, 7421 (4.6%) were lost to follow-up (OS: n=4451/ CT: n=2970), whereas 9709 (6.1%) deceased (OS: n=6146 /CT: n= 3563). OS participants were scheduled for two clinic visits at baseline and year 3 of follow-up compared to CT participants who were scheduled for clinic visits at years 1, 3, 6 and 9. To update selected exposures and ascertain medical outcomes participants in the OS were mailed annual questionnaires whereas women in the CTs were sent semiannual forms to ensure the timely update of medical histories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. All protocols were approved by institutional review boards at participating institutions.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Exposure assessment</title>
                <p>Current medication use was assessed by asking the participants to present all containers for medications taken for 2 weeks prior to clinic visit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Clinic interviewers then entered each medication into the WHI database, which assigned drug codes using Medispan software (First DataBank, Inc., San Bruno, California). For this analysis, we used baseline information on current laxative use including label product name, label generic name, dosage form, strength and duration (WHI Form 44: Current Medications). Duration of use was examined in three categories (&lt;1 year, 1 to 3 years, or &gt;3years). Since the medication class of laxatives is a heterogeneous entity with various different kinds of pharmacologically active substances and with many commercially available laxative products consisting of two or more active pharmacological compounds, we investigated the effect of ‘any (compound containing) laxative’ on our outcomes of interest. We additionally stratified laxatives by the underlying containing substances into five categories [‘oral stimulant containing’, ‘fiber containing’, ‘osmotic containing’, ‘stool softener containing’ and ‘lubricant containing’ laxative] to potentially gain information on the distribution of these categories being used and the effects on our outcomes of interest. However, as we are lacking information on the exact composition and pharmacological impact of each compound of the various commercially available mixture products, for analyses these categories were not mutually exclusive.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Outcome assessment and other covariates</title>
                <p>As primary outcome measures, we assessed the incidence of falls and fractures (total and hip fractures) and change in bone mineral density. Incident falls and fractures were ascertained prospectively using annual (OS) or semiannual (CT) self-report questionnaires. Fall history was obtained by asking about the number of times the participant fell or landed on the ground (excluding falls owing to sports) in the interval since the last medical history update (WHI Form 33: Medical History). A participant was identified as having a history of falls if she reported 2 or more falls per year as previously defined in epidemiologic studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. In WHI CTs, all fracture outcomes were verified by central review of radiology reports whereas in the WHI OS, only hip fractures were centrally adjudicated for all women.</p>
                <p>Bone mineral density (BMD) at the total hip, posterior-anterior spine, and total body was measured at baseline at 3 of the 40 clinical centers of the WHI (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; Birmingham, Alabama; and Phoenix and Tucson, Arizona) among 10,833 women with dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry using a Hologic QDR densitometer (Hologic Inc, Waltham, Massachusetts). We determined change in BMD by laxative use at these sites from baseline to year 3. Information on all covariates was assessed via self-report, clinic interview or by physical measure at baseline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The characteristics of women using laxatives at baseline were compared with nonusers [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>]. Differences between laxative users and nonusers were compared using χ<sup>2</sup> statistics for categorical variables and <italic>t-</italic>test or ANOVA, as appropriate, for continuous variables. Clinical outcomes were summarized according to laxative use and its various subgroups [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>]. Age-adjusted incidence rates of falls, total and hip fractures per 1000 person-years were calculated according to duration of laxative use by direct-adjustment based on the 5-year age distribution of the total CTs+OS sample (n=161,808) [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1]. Hazard ratios (HRs) for the risk of falls (≥2) and total or hip fractures associated with laxative use at baseline as compared with no laxative use were obtained by adjusted Cox proportional hazards analyses using time from enrollment to the first occurrence of the event as 'time' in the models [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>]. Two models were formed for each outcome to examine the effect of potential confounding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. Model 1 was stratified by 10-year age intervals and OS vs. CT cohorts, and adjusted for linear age, race/ethnicity, and randomization assignment for WHI-CTs. Model 2A additionally adjusted for BMI, smoking, physical activity, self-reported health, treated diabetes mellitus, history of fracture at age ≥55 years, corticosteroid use, physical function score, number of chronic medical conditions (including treated diabetes mellitus, stroke, any cancer, CVD, arthritis, hypertension, and emphysema), number of psychoactive medications (including anxiolytics, hypnotics, antidepressants, antipsychotics, and antiepileptic agents), use of HT and bisphosphonates. Model 2B also included history of falls (≥2). Similarly, we constructed adjusted hazards ratio of falls and bone outcomes using time-dependent laxative use from all medication inventories collected during follow-up time [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2]. Data on laxative use were updated at year 3 in the OS, and at years 1, 3, 6 and 9 in the CT. Follow-up time was censored three years after last medication collection. Multivariate linear regression methods were constructed to assess the association of baseline BMD for total hip, total spine and total body levels with any laxative use, as well as 3-year changes in BMD [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>]. For evaluating the relation of the duration of laxative intake to the incidence of falls and fractures, we used proportional hazards models to examine the association of different duration of laxative use (&lt;1 year, 1–3 years, or &gt;3years) with the outcomes of interest [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>]. We also conducted selected subgroup analyses for associations of laxative use on the outcomes by age group, current hormone replacement therapy use, current psychoactive therapy, BMI and history of fracture [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S3]. Finally, to further explore laxative intake under randomized trial conditions we conducted subgroup analyses relating any laxative use to incidence of fracture and falls in the WHI Hormone Therapy Trial [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S4]. All analyses were conducted using SAS statistical software (version 9.2; SAS Institute Inc, Cary, North Carolina).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Baseline differences between users and non-users of laxatives</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"> </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Laxative user (N=8907)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Nonuser of laxatives (N=151,497)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>P-value</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Age<hr/></td>
                        <td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt; 60<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">51188 (33.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;= 60<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6745 (75.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">100309 (66.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Race/ethnicity<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  White<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7859 (88.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">124468 (82.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Black<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">630 (7.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">13899 (9.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Other<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">418 (4.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">13130 (8.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">BMI (kg/m2)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt;25<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3334 (37.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">52350 (34.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  25 - &lt;30<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3079 (34.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">52168 (34.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;=30<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2433 (27.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">45624 (30.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Smoking<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Never<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">4353 (49.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">76367 (51.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Past<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3995 (45.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">62554 (41.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Current<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">451 (5.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">10581 (7.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">&gt; 7 Alcoholic drinks/week<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Nondrinker<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3885 (43.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">63883 (42.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0252<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3972 (44.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">69542 (46.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1026 (11.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">17568 (11.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Coffee intake<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  0 cups a day<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3977 (45.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">61373 (40.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt;= 1 cup a day<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1428 (16.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">23379 (15.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  1-3 cups a day<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2567 (29.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">47787 (31.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt; 4 cups a day<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">848 (9.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">17359 (11.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Diabetes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8482 (95.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">144679 (95.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2068<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">418 (4.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6680 (4.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical activity (METs) h/wk<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  0, Inactive<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1259 (14.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">22956 (15.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt; 5<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1712 (19.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">30445 (21.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  5-12<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2083 (24.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">34366 (23.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;=12<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3584 (41.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">56535 (39.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Last medical visit within one year<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">997 (11.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">26958 (18.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7683 (88.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">119360 (81.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Fair or poor self-reported health<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7738 (87.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">137171 (91.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1119 (12.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">13339 (8.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Osteoporosis<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7881 (89.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">138322 (92.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">932 (10.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">10972 (7.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical functioning &gt; 90<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6190 (70.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">92769 (62.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2567 (29.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">55808 (37.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Number of chronic conditions<sup>a</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  0<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1771 (19.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">43185 (28.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  1<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3016 (33.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">53641 (35.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  2<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2393 (26.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">34652 (22.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  3<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1226 (13.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">14609 (9.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;= 4<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">501 (5.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">5410 (3.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">History of falls<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7702 (86.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">133542 (88.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1205 (13.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">17955 (11.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Fracture on or after age 55<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">5818 (81.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">96946 (84.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1290 (18.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">17991 (15.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Hormone therapy use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Never used<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3233 (36.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">66953 (44.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Past user<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1692 (19.0%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">24005 (15.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Current user<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3977 (44.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">60405 (39.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Bisphosphonates use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8679 (97.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">148671 (98.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">228 (2.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2824 (1.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Corticosteroid use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8813 (98.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">150222 (99.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0319<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">94 (1.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1273 (0.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Calcitonin use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8861 (99.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">151077 (99.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">46 (0.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">418 (0.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Psychoactive drug use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7123 (80.0%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">136454 (90.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1748 (20.0%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">15043 (9.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Total baseline calcium intake (mg/d)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt;400<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">458 (5.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">11502 (7.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  400 - &lt;800<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1850 (21.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">38580 (26.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  800 - &lt;1200<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2145 (24.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">36436 (24.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;= 1200<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">4202 (48.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">60392 (41.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Calcium supplement use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2974 (33.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">68257 (45.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">5933 (66.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">83238 (54.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom">Total baseline Vitamin D intake (IU/d)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &lt;200<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2557 (29.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">56042 (38.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  200 - &lt;400<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1457 (16.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">27342 (18.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  400 - &lt;600<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2440 (28.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">35784 (24.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  &gt;= 600<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2201 (25.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">27742 (18.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Vitamin D supplement use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3647 (40.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">80042 (52.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">5260 (59.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">71453 (47.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline total body bone density<sup>b</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.017<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.014<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5236<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline total body bone density adjusted<sup>c</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.027<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.012<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0017<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline lumbar spine bone density<sup>b</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.990<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.979<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1551<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline lumbar spine bone density adjusted<sup>c</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.998<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.978<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0065<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline total hip bone density<sup>b</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.837<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.853<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0123<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline total hip bone density adjusted<sup>c</sup><hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.850<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.850<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.9395<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Hormone therapy trial<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7694 (86.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">125585 (82.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1213 (13.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">25912 (17.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Dietary modification trial<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6652 (74.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">105272 (69.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2255 (25.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">46225 (30.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Calcium Vitamin D trial<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7435 (83.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">116920 (77.2%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  Yes<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1472 (16.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">34577 (22.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Observational study<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">  No<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3168 (35.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">64447 (42.5%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt; 0.0001<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">  Yes</td>
                        <td align="right">5739 (64.4%)</td>
                        <td align="right">87050 (57.5%)</td>
                        <td align="right"> </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p><sup>a</sup> Includes treated diabetes mellitus, stroke, any cancer, CVD, arthritis, hypertension, 2 or more falls, emphysema.</p>
                    <p><sup>b</sup> From subset.</p>
                    <p><sup>c</sup> Adjusted for age, ethnicity, and BMI.</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Clinical outcomes according to laxative use and drug class</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Clinical outcome</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>No Laxative use (N=151497)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Laxative use (N=8907)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Oral stimulant containing laxative (N=1603)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Fiber containing laxative (N=5372)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Osmotic containing laxative (N=281)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Stool softener containing laxative (N=2525)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Lubricant containing laxative (N=33)</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>Falls (&gt; 2)</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">50175 (33.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">3484 (40.0%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">588 (37.7%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2040 (38.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">106 (39.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1067 (43.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">15 (46.9%)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">p-yrs<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">959,729<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">53,592<hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">Follow-up yrs (SD) / person<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6.4 (2.7)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6.1 (2.7)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>Hip fracture</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1706 (1.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">142 (1.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">33 (2.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">73 (1.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">4 (1.4%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">52 (2.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0 (0.0%)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">p-yrs<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1,171,740<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">67,909<hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">Follow-up yrs (SD) / person<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7.8 (1.6)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">7.6 (1.7)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>Total fracture</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">21642 (14.3%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1476 (16.6%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">255 (15.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">852 (15.9%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">48 (17.1%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">449 (17.8%)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">6 (18.2%)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">p-yrs<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1,053,650<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">61,029<hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right"> </td>
                        <td rowspan="2" align="right"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="right">Follow-up yrs (SD) / person</td>
                        <td align="right">7.2 (2.2)</td>
                        <td align="right">7.1 (2.2)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Adjusted hazards ratio of fractures and falls by laxative use at baseline</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <th colspan="2" align="left"> </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 1 HR (95% CI)*</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 1 p-value*</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 2A HR (95% CI)**</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 2A p-value**</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 2B HR (95% CI)**</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Model 2B p-value**</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Falls (≥ 2)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Any laxative use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.21 (1.17, 1.25)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt;.0001<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (1.03, 1.10)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0006<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (1.03, 1.10)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0008<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Oral stimulant containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.15 (1.06, 1.25)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0009<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.98 (0.90, 1.07)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.6162<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.97 (0.89, 1.05)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4450<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Fiber containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.15 (1.10, 1.20)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt;.0001<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (1.01, 1.11)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0147<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.05 (1.01, 1.10)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0272<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Osmotic containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.20 (0.99, 1.46)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0577<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.10 (0.90, 1.34)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3493<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.10 (0.90, 1.34)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3510<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Stool softener containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.35 (1.27, 1.44)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">&lt;.0001<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.08 (1.02, 1.15)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0145<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.10 (1.03, 1.17)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0036<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Lubricant containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.51 (0.91, 2.50)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1113<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.10 (0.63, 1.94)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.7390<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (0.60, 1.87)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8377<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Hip fracture<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Any laxative use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.11 (0.94, 1.32)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2200<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.02 (0.85, 1.22)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8509<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.02 (0.85, 1.22)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8426<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Oral stimulant containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.62 (1.15, 2.28)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0062<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.31 (0.90, 1.91)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1556<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.32 (0.91, 1.93)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1444<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Fiber containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.92 (0.73, 1.16)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4907<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.86 (0.67, 1.11)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2514<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.87 (0.67, 1.11)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2552<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Osmotic containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (0.40, 2.82)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.9118<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.98 (0.37, 2.61)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.9625<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.00 (0.38, 2.68)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.9942<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Stool softener containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.46 (1.11, 1.93)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0070<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.26 (0.94, 1.69)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1203<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.26 (0.94, 1.69)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1273<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Lubricant containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">NA***<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Total fracture<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Any laxative use<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.07 (1.01, 1.13)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0137<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.01 (0.96, 1.07)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.6237<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.02 (0.96, 1.07)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5511<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Oral stimulant containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.13 (0.99, 1.27)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0606<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.04 (0.92, 1.18)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5391<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.04 (0.91, 1.18)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5725<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Fiber containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.99 (0.92, 1.06)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.6831<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.97 (0.90, 1.04)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4089<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.97 (0.90, 1.04)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4004<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Osmotic containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.15 (0.87, 1.53)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3263<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.10 (0.82, 1.47)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5285<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.12 (0.84, 1.49)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4517<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Stool softener containing laxative<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.20 (1.09, 1.31)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0002<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.05 (0.95, 1.16)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3285<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (0.96, 1.17)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2331<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left"> </td>
                        <td align="left">Lubricant containing laxative</td>
                        <td align="right">1.29 (0.58, 2.88)</td>
                        <td align="right">0.5267</td>
                        <td align="right">1.29 (0.58, 2.87)</td>
                        <td align="right">0.5322</td>
                        <td align="right">1.26 (0.57, 2.81)</td>
                        <td align="right">0.5665</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>* Adjusted for age, ethnicity, and WHI clinical trial indicators.</p>
                    <p>** Adjusted for age, ethnicity, BMI, WHI clinical trial indicators, smoking status, physical activity, self-reported health, treated diabetes, history of fracture after age 55, corticosteroid use, physical function score, number of chronic medical conditions (including treated diabetes mellitus, stroke, any cancer, CVD, arthritis, hypertension, and emphysema), number of psychoactive drugs (including antipsychotic, antiepileptic, anxiolytic, hypnotic and antidepressant drug use), use of HRT, and bisphosphonate use, and in Model 2B history of falls (≥2).</p>
                    <p>*** No hip fractures occurred in this group.</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Three-year changes in mean bone mineral density (BMD) according to laxative use</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="right"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="right"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th>
                        <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>Laxative Use</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                        <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>No Laxative Use</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"> </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>N</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Mean (SE) *</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>N</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Mean (SE) *</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>P-value *</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>P-value **</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>P-value ***</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Total hip<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">509<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.842 (0.006)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">10791<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.847 (0.001)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4170<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8376<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8624<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Year 3<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">424<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.847 (0.006)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8916<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.854 (0.001)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2767<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3282<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3409<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Absolute change<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">422<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.004 (0.002)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8810<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.006 (0.000)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3866<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3734<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3714<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Percent change<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">422<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.596 (0.201)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8810<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.730 (0.047)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.5108<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4856<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4791<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Total spine<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">487<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.991 (0.007)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">10456<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.975 (0.002)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0339<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1307<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1325<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Year 3<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">401<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.010 (0.009)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8653<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.995 (0.002)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0836<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.4034<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.3974<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Absolute change<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">400<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.017 (0.002)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8579<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.021 (0.001)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.2075<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1396<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1573<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Percent change<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">400<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.840 (0.257)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8579<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">2.198 (0.060)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1711<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1324<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1505<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Total body<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Baseline<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">512<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.023 (0.004)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">10794<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.011 (0.001)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0090<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0209<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0234<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Year 3<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">424<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.033 (0.005)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8891<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.023 (0.001)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.0692<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1754<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.1854<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Absolute change<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">423<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.012 (0.002)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">8796<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.011 (0.000)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.6686<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.9132<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.8580<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">Percent change</td>
                        <td align="right">423</td>
                        <td align="right">1.236 (0.181)</td>
                        <td align="right">8796</td>
                        <td align="right">1.150 (0.043)</td>
                        <td align="right">0.6422</td>
                        <td align="right">0.8545</td>
                        <td align="right">0.7946</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>* Adjusted for age, ethnicity, and WHI clinical trial indicators.</p>
                    <p>** Adjusted for age, ethnicity, BMI, WHI clinical trial indicators, smoking status, physical activity, self-reported health, treated diabetes, history of fracture after age 55, corticosteroid use, physical function score, number of chronic medical conditions (including treated diabetes mellitus, stroke, any cancer, CVD, arthritis, hypertension, and emphysema), number of psychoactive drugs (including antipsychotic, antiepileptic, anxiolytic, hypnotic and antidepressant drug use), use of HRT, and bisphosphonate use.</p>
                    <p>*** Adjusted as in (**) with the addition of history of falls (≥ 2).</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T5">
                  <label>Table 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Adjusted hazards ratio of fractures and falls by any laxative use duration</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="left"/>
                      <col align="center"/>
                      <col align="right"/>
                      <col align="right"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>Any laxative use</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>N</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                        <th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom">
                          <bold>HR (95% CI)**</bold>
                          <hr/>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left"> </th>
                        <th align="left"> </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Falls (&gt;2)</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Hip fracture</bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="right">
                          <bold>Total fracture</bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">Nonuser<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">151,497<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> &lt; 1 year<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">1924<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.11 (1.04, 1.74)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.17 (0.89, 1.55)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.06 (0.97, 1.16)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 1-3 years<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">3091<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.07 (0.99, 1.15)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.02 (0.69, 1.50)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.03 (0.92, 1.15)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom"> &gt; 3 years<hr/></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom">3892<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">1.00 (0.95, 1.06)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.90 (0.68, 1.19)<hr/></td>
                        <td align="right" valign="bottom">0.97 (0.89, 1.05)<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">p-value for linear trend</td>
                        <td align="left"> </td>
                        <td align="right">0.0458</td>
                        <td align="right">0.9553</td>
                        <td align="right">0.9996</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>** Adjusted for age, ethnicity, BMI, WHI clinical trial indicators, smoking status, physical activity, self-reported health, treated diabetes, history of fracture after age 55, corticosteroid use, physical function score, number of chronic medical conditions (including treated diabetes mellitus, stroke, any cancer, CVD, arthritis, hypertension, 2 or more falls and emphysema), number of psychoactive drugs (including antipsychotic, antiepileptic, anxiolytic, hypnotic and antidepressant drug use), use of HRT, and bisphosphonate use.</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Among the 161,808 women in the WHI OS and CTs, 160,404 had no prior hip fracture at baseline and were included in this study; 8907 (5.6%) of study participants were currently using laxatives at baseline [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>]. Of those, 1603 persons used an oral stimulant containing laxative, 5372 a fiber containing laxative, 281 an osmotic containing laxative, 2525 a stool softener containing laxative and 33 a lubricant containing laxative [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>]. Nearly 4000 women (43.7%) had used laxative medication for more than 3 years, 3091 (34.7%) for 1 to 3 years, and 1924 (21.6%) for less than 1 year [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>]. Those using laxatives at baseline were of older age, had lower BMI, more likely to have a lower physical functioning or a history of fractures, more likely to report low or fair health or osteoporosis, and to be included in the observational study (WHI-OS) [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>]. Concurrent use of psychoactive medications and hormone replacement therapy was more common among laxative users. Calcium and Vitamin D supplementation as well as bisphosphonates and calcitonin were more often used by laxative users. After adjustment for age, ethnicity and BMI laxative users tended to have a higher lumbar spine and total BMD. Other baseline characteristics were similar.</p>
              <p>During 6.4 follow-up years/person in the laxative non-user group (n=151,497) as compared to 6.1 follow-up years/person in the user group (n=8907), 50,175 falls were reported in the non-user and 3484 falls in the user-group [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>]. The age-adjusted rates of falls were 52.84/1000 person-years for non-users and 63.35/1000 person-years for laxative users. Similarly, the rates of hip fractures were 1.54/1000 and 1.75/1000 and the rates of total fractures were 20.89/1000 and 23.07/1000 for laxative non-users and users [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1].</p>
              <p>In minimally adjusted models a significant association was found between ‘any laxative use’ and falls (HR, 1.21; 95% CI, 1.17-1.25), and total fractures (HR, 1.07; 95% CI, 1.01-1.13) at baseline, while the association with hip fractures was not statistically significant (HR, 1.11; 95% CI, 0.94-1.32) [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>].When stratifying these associations by the various laxative subgroups, we noted ‘oral stimulant’, ‘fiber’ and ‘stool softener containing laxatives’ to be significantly associated with the risk of falls. After full adjustment ‘any laxative use’ (Model 2A: HR, 1.06; 95% CI, 1.03-1.10), ‘fiber containing laxatives’ (Model 2A: HR, 1.06; 95% CI, 1.01-1.11) and ‘stool softener containing laxatives’ (Model 2A: HR, 1.08; 95% CI, 1.02-1.15) remained statistically significantly associated with falls. These results did only marginally change after additional adjustment for history of falls. No significant relationship between laxative use and the risk for fractures was found after fully accounting for confounding factors. To investigate the effects of laxative use over time, we additionally constructed time-dependent models [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2]. There we continued to find a significant association between the risk for falls and ‘any laxative use’ (HR, 1.06; 95% CI, 1.02-1.10) and ‘stool softener containing laxatives’ (HR 1.13; 95% CI, 1.06-1.21). In contrast to baseline analyses, ‘oral stimulant containing laxatives’ (HR, 2.04; 95% CI, 1.36-3.07) and ‘stool softener containing laxatives’ (HR, 1.50; 95% CI, 1.09-2.05) remained significantly associated with the risk for hip fractures even after full adjustment. No relationship between the risk for total fractures and any laxative subgroup except for ‘stool softener containing laxatives’ (HR, 1.12; 95% CI, 1.00-1.25) could be established in time-dependent analyses.</p>
              <p>At baseline, women using laxatives had similar BMD at the hip level (adjusted mean, 0.85 vs. 0.84 g/cm<sup>2</sup>) compared with nonusers. Total body BMD and total spine BMD differed significantly in users compared with nonusers (adjusted mean, 1.02 vs. 1.01 g/cm<sup>2</sup> and 0.99 vs. 0.98 g/cm<sup>2</sup>) [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>]. Examining the 3-year BMD change from baseline, we found small statistically non-significant increases in BMD in all areas of interest, which may stem from the fact that a high proportion of women in both groups were part of the active treatment arms in the WHI-CT involving calcium and vitamin D supplementation and/or hormone trial (HT).</p>
              <p>Any laxative use tended to be associated with an increased hazard for falls in stratified analysis by exposure duration while no clear trend could be observed for the risk for hip fractures or total fractures [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>]. Because laxative use may have different effects on various subpopulations, we additional undertook several subgroup analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. Laxative use was associated with an increased hazard for total fractures by age in women older than 65 years (HR, 1.06; 95% CI, 0.99-1.14, interaction p-value = 0.05), although no significant interaction by age was found for falls and hip fractures. Psychoactive therapy was associated with a lower risk for total fractures (HR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.81-1.03, interaction p-value = 0.05), whereas no significant influence on falls or hip fractures was noted [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S3]. Finally, we found no significant difference in the prevalence of laxative intake between women receiving hormone therapy or placebo under WHI Hormone Therapy Trial settings [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S4]. Interaction tests for women stratified by trial randomization did not result in significant differences in risk of falls and fractures between laxative users and non-users.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this large prospective study of postmenopausal women with no prior hip fracture, we found a statistically significant association of laxative use with the occurrence of falls (≥2). Laxative use was not associated with an increased risk for total fractures and hip fractures after fully adjustment for confounding factors. Among laxative users at baseline, the HR for falls was 1.06, for hip fractures 1.02 and for total fractures 1.01. The CIs indicate that the true HR for falls may be as low as 1.03 or as high as 1.10, for hip fractures 0.85 and 1.22 and for total fractures 0.96 and 1.07 respectively. Using time-dependent analyses laxative use remained statistically significantly associated with an increased risk for falls. These results were most likely driven by a higher number of women starting to take laxatives during follow-up; thus we achieved a higher power to detect differences between users and non-users. Nonetheless, we cannot rule out residual confounding by indication as having partly influenced our results. Longer duration of laxative use did not show a statistically significant association with the risk for hip fractures or total fractures, while a positive relationship for falls could be observed.</p>
              <p>Several intrinsic and extrinsic effects of laxatives have been associated with their use providing potential mechanisms for an altered risk for falls and bone outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Extrinsically, laxatives can increase the urgency to void with resulting higher risk of falling. Intrinsically, laxatives can lead to diarrhoea with associated electrolyte and fluid imbalances. Potassium is the main electrolyte being lost followed by reductions in sodium and chloride. Generalized muscle weakness, lassitude and cardiac arrhythmias may be a direct consequence of electrolyte disturbances resulting in an increased risk for falls and bone outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Most recent reports have linked electrolyte imbalances such as mild hyponatremia to osteoporosis and fracture risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Additionally, laxatives have also been described to irritate bowel functioning and bowel disturbances in the colon and small bowl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Fat-soluble vitamin malabsorption secondary to these types of laxative induced side effects of small intestine damage may further predispose for falls, fractures and BMD loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Indeed, prior epidemiological studies have shown that laxative use is associated with an increased risk for falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. One of the first was the St. Louis OASIS study in which laxative use was found to be an important risk factor for multiple falls in elderly people living in the community (OR, 2.14; 95% CI, 1.02-4.49) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. Other cross-sectionally designed studies confirmed this positive association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Observational studies examining medications and chronic diseases with one year follow-up period reported risks for falling between OR 1.09 (95% CI, 0.86-1.38) and 2.51 (95% CI, 1.50-4.22) with laxative use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. A recent meta-analysis summarizing the risks for falls related to laxatives elderly individuals resulted in an OR 2.03 (95% CI, 1.52-2.72) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Nevertheless, external validity of many included studies may be limited as the mean age of the study population was above 80 years old [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] with a small number of participants, events and short follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Last, data on fracture risk or change in BMD were not assessed even though a history of falls is an independent risk factor for fractures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p>
              <p>In contrast to previously published findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>], our results indicate a modest association between laxative use and the occurrence of falls, whereas we found no relationship between laxative use and fractures. Furthermore, although baseline total body bone density and total lumbar spine density varied between laxative users or non-users, three-year changes in BMD did not show any significant differences between both groups for all BMD areas. In particular, we did not observe differences in total hip bone density between laxative users or not users. These findings are surprising given the different baseline characteristics of laxative users and non-users suggesting that laxative users have a higher number of chronic conditions, lower physical functioning and are of older age, factors known to influence the risk for falls, fractures and changes in BMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. It may be explained by various levels of calcium and vitamin D intake between the two groups. Nevertheless, given our hypothesis that laxative intake may potentially cause electrolyte imbalances, vitamin D malabsorption or even small intestine mucosal damage, we expected a strong relationship between falls and laxative use and an increased risk for fractures and BMD reductions. To further investigate the association of laxative use with the incidence of falls and fractures when used concomitantly with certain medications (psychoactive drugs, hormone therapy), in certain age groups, with different BMI levels or history of fracture, we conducted a subgroup analysis. We found a slightly higher risk for falls in laxative users being of older age (&gt;65 y), while current psychoactive therapy, BMI, history of fracture had no negative effect. Moreover, we noted a higher risk for falls in laxative users under current hormone treatment in the total study population (WHI OS and CTs) which we and others did not continue to observe in a hormone trial setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. On the other hand, older women using laxatives showed a significant risk for total fractures despite similar BMD levels. Finally, concomitant use of psychoactive agents did not increase the risk for hip and total fractures in our study population.</p>
              <p>The strengths of our analysis include the sample size of our study population, the large number of complete follow-up and the structured availability of several confounding factors. Nonetheless, our study also exhibits several limitations. Among those, first the relative low prevalence of long time laxative use and the missing data on dosing may limit the validity of this study. Also, since many commercially available laxatives are mixture products consisting of two or more pharmacologically active substances, our analyses on the various categories of laxatives are limited due to missing information on the exact composition of these products. Second, laxative intake as well as incident falls and fractures were ascertained via self-report. Hence, we cannot exclude information bias. However, since laxative intake is likely to be assumed to be underreported, the actual effects may be underestimated. Third, even though a wide range of confounding factors was considered in the analysis, residual confounding cannot be excluded. Our results may be partly confounded by indication for which we controlled by measures of restriction, stratification and extensive multivariate adjustment. Additionally, even though this study was designed prospectively, reverse causation may have influenced our results. Last, as our study population consisted of postmenopausal women, generalizability may be limited and further research in other study populations is warranted.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Laxative users are characterized by older age, lower physical functioning, more comorbidities and higher concurrent use of psychoactive medications and hormone replacement therapy. Our findings support an association between any laxative use and increased risk for falls but not with total fracture risk or hip fracture risk. A relationship of laxative use with changes in BMD over time was not demonstrated, but calcium and vitamin D were more often supplemented by laxative users. Bisphosphonate and calcitonin use was more likely in this group as well. Thus, questions remain regarding the influence on bone health and potential risks associated with long-term laxative use. Given the low cost, widespread use and over-the-counter availability it appears prudent to periodically reevaluate laxative use. Maintaining physical functioning, and providing adequate treatment of comorbidities that predispose individuals for falls should be considered as first measures to avoid potential negative consequences associated with laxative use.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p>Dr. Carnahan's work was supported by the University of Iowa Institute for Clinical and Translational Science, and an Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality Centers for Education and Research on Therapeutics cooperative agreement #5 U18 HS016094 (the Iowa Older Adults CERT). In the past 5 years he received research funding from Boehringer Ingelheim, Forest Laboratories, Wyeth, and Ortho-McNeil. None of the other authors reported disclosures.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>MP and BH had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Study concept and design: BH, SWW Acquisition of data: BP, MP, SWW Analysis and interpretation of data: MP, BH, WvB, JWB, JWW, RMC, RBW Drafting of the manuscript: BH, JWB, JWW, JO, RBW Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content: JWB, RCM, JO, RCM, RBW, SWW, WvB Statistical analysis: MP Obtained funding: SWW Administrative, technical, or material support: SWW Study supervision: SWW. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Pre-publication history</title>
              <p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p>
              <p>
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2318/13/38/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2318/13/38/prepub</ext-link>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
                <caption>
                  <title>Additional file 1: Table S1</title>
                  <p>Age adjusted rates for any laxative use at baseline. <bold>Table S2</bold> Adjusted hazards ratio of fractures and falls by laxative use using time-dependent laxative use from all medication inventories collected during follow-up. <bold>Table S3</bold> Adjusted hazard ratios relating any laxative use to incidence of fracture and falls - subgroup analyses and interaction tests. <bold>Table S4</bold> Adjusted hazard ratios relating any laxative use to incidence of fracture and falls in the WHI Hormone Therapy trial – subgroup analyses and interaction tests.</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="1471-2318-13-38-S1.doc">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for file</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <sec>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>WHI Short List of Investigators: Program Office: (National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, Bethesda, Maryland) Jacques Rossouw, Shari Ludlam, Dale Burwen, Joan McGowan, Leslie Ford, and Nancy Geller Clinical Coordinating Center: Clinical Coordinating Center: (Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA) Garnet Anderson, Ross Prentice, Andrea LaCroix, and Charles Kooperberg. Investigators and Academic Centers: (Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA) JoAnn E. Manson; (MedStar Health Research Institute/Howard University, Washington, DC) Barbara V. Howard; (Stanford Prevention Research Center, Stanford, CA) Marcia L. Stefanick; (The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH) Rebecca Jackson; (University of Arizona, Tucson/Phoenix, AZ) Cynthia A. Thomson; (University at Buffalo, Buffalo, NY) Jean Wactawski-Wende; (University of Florida, Gainesville/Jacksonville, FL) Marian Limacher; (University of Iowa, Iowa City/Davenport, IA) Robert Wallace; (University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA) Lewis Kuller; (Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, NC) Sally Shumaker. Women’s Health Initiative Memory Study: (Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, NC) Sally Shumaker.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Funding/support</title>
              <p>The WHI program is funded by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services through contracts HHSN268201100046C, HHSN268201100001C, HHSN268201100002C, HHSN268201100003C, HHSN268201100004C, and HHSN271201100004C.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <ref id="B1">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
                  <collab>Consumer Health Care Association</collab>
                  <source>OTC Sales by Category</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <comment>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chpa-info.org/pressroom/Sales_Category.aspx">http://www.chpa-info.org/pressroom/Sales_Category.aspx</ext-link>] (Last accessed 03-25-2013</comment>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                    <given-names>EH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sandle</surname>
                    <given-names>GI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Complications of laxative abuse</article-title>
                  <source>Annu Rev Med</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <lpage>134</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.med.47.1.127</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8712767?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8712767</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moriarty</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silk</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Laxative abuse</article-title>
                  <source>Dig Dis</source>
                  <year>1988</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>29</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000171181</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 3280173?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3280173</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Roerig</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Steffen</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zunker</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Laxative abuse: epidemiology, diagnosis and management</article-title>
                  <source>Drugs</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1487</fpage>
                  <lpage>1503</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11898640-000000000-00000</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20687617?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20687617</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fleischer</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brown</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                    <given-names>DY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Delena</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Chronic laxative-induced hyperaldosteronism and hypokalemia simulating Bartter's syndrome</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <year>1969</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>791</fpage>
                  <lpage>798</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-70-4-791</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 4306128?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4306128</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sankar</surname>
                    <given-names>NS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Donaldson</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Lessons to be learned: a case study approach diuretic therapy and a laxative causing electrolyte and water imbalance, loss of attention, a fall and subsequent fractures of the tibia and fibula in an elderly lady</article-title>
                  <source>J R Soc Promot Health</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>118</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <lpage>240</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/146642409811800410</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10076675?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10076675</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yakabowich</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Prescribe with care. The role of laxatives in the treatment of constipation</article-title>
                  <source>J Gerontol Nurs</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2229958?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2370432</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Decaux</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Is asymptomatic hyponatremia really asymptomatic?</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Med</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <issue>7 Suppl 1</issue>
                  <fpage>S79</fpage>
                  <lpage>82</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16949392?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16843090</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gankam Kengne</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Andres</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sattar</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Melot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Decaux</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Mild hyponatremia and risk of fracture in the ambulatory elderly</article-title>
                  <source>QJM</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>101</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
                  <lpage>588</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcn061</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18477645?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477645</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kinsella</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moran</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                    <given-names>MO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Molloy</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Eustace</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Hyponatremia independent of osteoporosis is associated with fracture occurrence</article-title>
                  <source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <lpage>280</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2215/CJN.06120809</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20056759?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20056759</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sajadieh</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Binici</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mouridsen</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nielsen</surname>
                    <given-names>OW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hansen</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Haugaard</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Mild hyponatremia carries a poor prognosis in community subjects</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Med</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>122</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>679</fpage>
                  <lpage>686</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2008.11.033</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19559171?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19559171</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cranney</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Weiler</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>O'Donnell</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Puil</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Summary of evidence-based review on vitamin D efficacy and safety in relation to bone health</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>513S</fpage>
                  <lpage>519S</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18689393?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18689393</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Janssen</surname>
                    <given-names>HC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Samson</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Verhaar</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Vitamin D deficiency, muscle function, and falls in elderly people</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>611</fpage>
                  <lpage>615</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11916748?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916748</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McCarroll</surname>
                    <given-names>KG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Coughlan</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Healy</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kenny</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cunningham</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Vitamin D and orthostatic hypotension</article-title>
                  <source>Age Ageing</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>810</fpage>
                  <lpage>813</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afs088</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22789765?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22789765</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Carbone</surname>
                    <given-names>LD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bush</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robbins</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Loop diuretic use and fracture in postmenopausal women: findings from the Women's Health Initiative</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>169</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <lpage>140</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinternmed.2008.526</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19171809?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171809</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Carbone</surname>
                    <given-names>LD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robbins</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Curb</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Watson</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gass</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lacroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Antiepileptic drug use, falls, fractures, and BMD in postmenopausal women: findings from the women's health initiative (WHI)</article-title>
                  <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>873</fpage>
                  <lpage>881</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19839772?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19839772</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hix</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silver</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sterns</surname>
                    <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Diuretic-associated hyponatremia</article-title>
                  <source>Semin Nephrol</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
                  <lpage>566</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semnephrol.2011.09.010</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22099512?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22099512</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rastogi</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pelter</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Deamer</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Evaluations of hospitalizations associated with thiazide-associated hyponatremia</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <lpage>164</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-7176.2011.00575.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22372775</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sonnenblick</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Friedlander</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rosin</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Diuretic-induced severe hyponatremia. Review and analysis of 129 reported patients</article-title>
                  <source>Chest</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>103</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>601</fpage>
                  <lpage>606</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.103.2.601</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8432162?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432162</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kallin</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gustafson</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sandman</surname>
                    <given-names>PO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Karlsson</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Drugs and falls in older people in geriatric care settings</article-title>
                  <source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>270</fpage>
                  <lpage>276</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15575120?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15575120</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kallin</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gustafson</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sandman</surname>
                    <given-names>PO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Karlsson</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Factors associated with falls among older, cognitively impaired people in geriatric care settings: a population-based study</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
                  <lpage>509</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15956270?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15956270</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lundin-Olsson</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jensen</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nyberg</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gustafson</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Predicting falls in residential care by a risk assessment tool, staff judgement, and history of falls</article-title>
                  <source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <lpage>59</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12841419?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12841419</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Luukinen</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Koski</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Laippala</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kivela</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Predictors for recurrent falls among the home-dwelling elderly</article-title>
                  <source>Scand J Prim Health Care</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <lpage>299</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/02813439508996778</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8693215?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8693215</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Luukinen</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Koski</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Laippala</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kivela</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Risk factors for recurrent falls in the elderly in long-term institutional care</article-title>
                  <source>Public Health</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <volume>109</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <lpage>65</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0033-3506(95)80076-X</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 7871147?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7871147</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ryynanen</surname>
                    <given-names>OP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kivela</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Honkanen</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Laippala</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Saano</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Medications and chronic diseases as risk factors for falling injuries in the elderly</article-title>
                  <source>Scand J Soc Med</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <lpage>271</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8310279?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8310279</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Spector</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shaffer</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Potter</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Correa-de-Araujo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rhona Limcangco</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Risk factors associated with the occurrence of fractures in U.S. nursing homes: resident and facility characteristics and prescription medications</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <lpage>333</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2007.01081.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17341233?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17341233</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Svensson</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rundgren</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Landahl</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Falls in 84- to 85-year-old people living at home</article-title>
                  <source>Accid Anal Prev</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>527</fpage>
                  <lpage>537</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-4575(92)90061-M</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1520435?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1520435</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bloch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Thibaud</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dugue</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Breque</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rigaud</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kemoun</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Laxatives as a risk factor for iatrogenic falls in elderly subjects: myth or reality?</article-title>
                  <source>Drugs Aging</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>895</fpage>
                  <lpage>901</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11584280-000000000-00000</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20964463?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20964463</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>von Heideken</surname>
                    <given-names>WP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gustafson</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kallin</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jensen</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lundin-Olsson</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Falls in very old people: the population-based Umea 85+ study in Sweden</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
                  <lpage>396</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archger.2008.12.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19144414?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19144414</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McPherson</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dunsmuir</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Hyponatraemia in hip fracture patients</article-title>
                  <source>Scott Med J</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <lpage>116</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12469566?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12469566</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ayus</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moritz</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Bone disease as a new complication of hyponatremia: moving beyond brain injury</article-title>
                  <source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <lpage>168</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2215/CJN.09281209</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20089487?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089487</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bischoff-Ferrari</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dawson-Hughes</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Willett</surname>
                    <given-names>WC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Staehelin</surname>
                    <given-names>HB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bazemore</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zee</surname>
                    <given-names>RY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Effect of Vitamin D on falls: a meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>291</volume>
                  <issue>16</issue>
                  <fpage>1999</fpage>
                  <lpage>2006</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.291.16.1999</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15113819?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113819</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Boonen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bischoff-Ferrari</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cooper</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lips</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ljunggren</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Meunier</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Reginster</surname>
                    <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Addressing the musculoskeletal components of fracture risk with calcium and vitamin D: a review of the evidence</article-title>
                  <source>Calcif Tissue Int</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <lpage>270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00223-005-0009-8</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16622587?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16622587</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Broe</surname>
                    <given-names>KE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Weinberg</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bischoff-Ferrari</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Holick</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kiel</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>A higher dose of vitamin d reduces the risk of falls in nursing home residents: a randomized, multiple-dose study</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <lpage>239</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2007.01048.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17302660?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17302660</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gennari</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Calcium and vitamin D nutrition and bone disease of the elderly</article-title>
                  <source>Public Health Nutr</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>2B</issue>
                  <fpage>547</fpage>
                  <lpage>559</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11683549?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11683549</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lips</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bouillon</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>van Schoor</surname>
                    <given-names>NM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vanderschueren</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Verschueren</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kuchuk</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Milisen</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Boonen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Reducing fracture risk with calcium and vitamin D</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <lpage>285</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03701.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20796001</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Malabanan</surname>
                    <given-names>AO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Holick</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Vitamin D and bone health in postmenopausal women</article-title>
                  <source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <lpage>156</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/154099903321576547</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12737713</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rodriguez-Martinez</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Garcia-Cohen</surname>
                    <given-names>EC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Role of Ca(2+) and vitamin D in the prevention and treatment of osteoporosis</article-title>
                  <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <lpage>49</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0163-7258(02)00164-X</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11916540?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916540</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Edwards</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jameson</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Denison</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Harvey</surname>
                    <given-names>NC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sayer</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dennison</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cooper</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Clinical risk factors, bone density and fall history in the prediction of incident fracture among men and women</article-title>
                  <source>Bone</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>541</fpage>
                  <lpage>547</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bone.2012.11.006</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23159464?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23159464</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pryor</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wiederman</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>McGilley</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Laxative abuse among women with eating disorders: an indication of psychopathology?</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Eat Disord</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-108X(199607)20:1&lt;13::AID-EAT2&gt;3.0.CO;2-7</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8807348?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8807348</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vanin</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Saylor</surname>
                    <given-names>KE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Laxative abuse: a hazardous habit for weight control</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Coll Health</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <lpage>230</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07448481.1989.9939064</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2649529?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2649529</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Campbell</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Busby</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Horwath</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Factors associated with constipation in a community based sample of people aged 70 years and over</article-title>
                  <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.47.1.23</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8382251?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8382251</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B43">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Everhart</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Go</surname>
                    <given-names>VL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Johannes</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fitzsimmons</surname>
                    <given-names>SC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Roth</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>A longitudinal survey of self-reported bowel habits in the United States</article-title>
                  <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>1153</fpage>
                  <lpage>1162</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01537261</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 2787735?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2787735</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B44">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Koch</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hudson</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Older people and laxative use: literature review and pilot study report</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Nurs</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>516</fpage>
                  <lpage>525</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2702.2000.00357.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11261131?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11261131</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B45">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McCrea</surname>
                    <given-names>GL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Miaskowski</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stotts</surname>
                    <given-names>NA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Macera</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Paul</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Varma</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Gender differences in self-reported constipation characteristics, symptoms, and bowel and dietary habits among patients attending a specialty clinic for constipation</article-title>
                  <source>Gend Med</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <lpage>271</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genm.2009.04.007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19467522?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467522</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B46">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <collab>Design of the Women's Health Initiative clinical trial and observational study</collab>
                  <article-title>The Women's Health Initiative Study Group</article-title>
                  <source>Control Clin Trials</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <lpage>109</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9492970?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9492970</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B47">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jackson</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gass</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wallace</surname>
                    <given-names>RB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robbins</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bassford</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Beresford</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Black</surname>
                    <given-names>HR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Blanchette</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Calcium plus vitamin D supplementation and the risk of fractures</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>354</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>669</fpage>
                  <lpage>683</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa055218</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16481635?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16481635</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B48">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Langer</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kotchen</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hendrix</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Trevisan</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>The Women's Health Initiative Observational Study: baseline characteristics of participants and reliability of baseline measures</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>9 Suppl</issue>
                  <fpage>S107</fpage>
                  <lpage>121</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 14575943?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14575943</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B49">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Prentice</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Caan</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chlebowski</surname>
                    <given-names>RT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Patterson</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kuller</surname>
                    <given-names>LH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ockene</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Margolis</surname>
                    <given-names>KL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Limacher</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Manson</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Parker</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Low-fat dietary pattern and risk of invasive breast cancer: the Women's Health Initiative Randomized Controlled Dietary Modification Trial</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>295</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
                  <lpage>642</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.295.6.629</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 16467232?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467232</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B50">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rossouw</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>GL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Prentice</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kooperberg</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stefanick</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jackson</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Beresford</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Howard</surname>
                    <given-names>BV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Risks and benefits of estrogen plus progestin in healthy postmenopausal women: principal results From the Women's Health Initiative randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>288</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <lpage>333</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.288.3.321</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12117397?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117397</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B51">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hays</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hunt</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hubbell</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>GL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Limacher</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Allen</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rossouw</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>The Women's Health Initiative recruitment methods and results</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>9 Suppl</issue>
                  <fpage>S18</fpage>
                  <lpage>77</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 14575939?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14575939</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B52">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Masud</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Morris</surname>
                    <given-names>RO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Epidemiology of falls</article-title>
                  <source>Age Ageing</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>Suppl 4</issue>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/30.suppl_4.3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 11769786?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11769786</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B53">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stalenhoef</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Diederiks</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Knottnerus</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kester</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Crebolder</surname>
                    <given-names>HF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>A risk model for the prediction of recurrent falls in community-dwelling elderly: a prospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <fpage>1088</fpage>
                  <lpage>1094</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0895-4356(02)00502-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12507672?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507672</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B54">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ainsworth</surname>
                    <given-names>BE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Haskell</surname>
                    <given-names>WL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leon</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Montoye</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sallis</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Paffenbarger</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Compendium of physical activities: classification of energy costs of human physical activities</article-title>
                  <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <lpage>80</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/00005768-199301000-00011</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 8292105?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8292105</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B55">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kristal</surname>
                    <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Feng</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Coates</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Oberman</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>George</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Associations of race/ethnicity, education, and dietary intervention with the validity and reliability of a food frequency questionnaire: the Women's Health Trial Feasibility Study in Minority Populations</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>146</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>856</fpage>
                  <lpage>869</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a009203</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9384206?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9384206</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B56">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ware</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sherbourne</surname>
                    <given-names>CD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. Conceptual framework and item selection</article-title>
                  <source>Med Care</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>473</fpage>
                  <lpage>483</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199206000-00002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1593914?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1593914</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B57">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gray</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robbins</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cauley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Manson</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Proton pump inhibitor use, hip fracture, and change in bone mineral density in postmenopausal women: results from the Women's Health Initiative</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>170</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>765</fpage>
                  <lpage>771</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20458083?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20458083</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B58">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cauley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pettinger</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hsia</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bauer</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>McGowan</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>McNeeley</surname>
                    <given-names>SG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Passaro</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Statin use, clinical fracture, and bone density in postmenopausal women: results from the Women's Health Initiative Observational Study</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>139</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>104</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-139-2-200307150-00009</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12859159?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12859159</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B59">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cumming</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kelsey</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davis</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Arfken</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Birge</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Peck</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Medications and multiple falls in elderly people: the St Louis OASIS study</article-title>
                  <source>Age Ageing</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <lpage>461</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/20.6.455</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1776597?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1776597</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B60">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lavsa</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fabian</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Saul</surname>
                    <given-names>MI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Corman</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Coley</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Influence of medications and diagnoses on fall risk in psychiatric inpatients</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>67</volume>
                  <issue>15</issue>
                  <fpage>1274</fpage>
                  <lpage>1280</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2146/ajhp090611</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20651318?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20651318</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B61">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sandhu</surname>
                    <given-names>HS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gilles</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>DeVita</surname>
                    <given-names>MV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Panagopoulos</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Michelis</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Hyponatremia associated with large-bone fracture in elderly patients</article-title>
                  <source>Int Urol Nephrol</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>733</fpage>
                  <lpage>737</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11255-009-9585-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19472069?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19472069</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B62">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gross</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Treatment of hyponatremia</article-title>
                  <source>Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>885</fpage>
                  <lpage>891</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.47.0918</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18480571?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18480571</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B63">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Renneboog</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Musch</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vandemergel</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Manto</surname>
                    <given-names>MU</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Decaux</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Mild chronic hyponatremia is associated with falls, unsteadiness, and attention deficits</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Med</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>71 e71</fpage>
                  <lpage>78</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16431193</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B64">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shumway-Cook</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ciol</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dudgeon</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yorkston</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chan</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Falls in the Medicare population: incidence, associated factors, and impact on health care</article-title>
                  <source>Phys Ther</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>89</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>324</fpage>
                  <lpage>332</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2522/ptj.20070107</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19228831?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228831</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B65">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Robbins</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Aragaki</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kooperberg</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Watts</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wactawski-Wende</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jackson</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LeBoff</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stefanick</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Factors associated with 5-year risk of hip fracture in postmenopausal women</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>298</volume>
                  <issue>20</issue>
                  <fpage>2389</fpage>
                  <lpage>2398</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.298.20.2389</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18042916?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042916</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B66">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bea</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cauley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>LaCroix</surname>
                    <given-names>AZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bassford</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jackson</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tylavsky</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <article-title>Effect of hormone therapy on lean body mass, falls, and fractures: 6-year results from the Women's Health Initiative hormone trials</article-title>
                  <source>Menopause</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <lpage>52</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/gme.0b013e3181e3aab1</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20689466?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689466</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
