<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:55:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10539987" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10539987</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-09-30</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10539987</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10539987</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10539987</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37768666</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37768666</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33846</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230978</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-only">
                  <subject>Online Only</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area">
                  <subject>Psychiatry</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Reattribution to Mind-Brain Processes and Recovery From Chronic Back Pain</article-title>
                <subtitle>A Secondary Analysis of a Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Reattribution to Mind-Brain Processes and Recovery From Chronic Back Pain</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Reattribution to Mind-Brain Processes and Recovery From Chronic Back Pain</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ashar</surname>
                    <given-names>Yoni K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lumley</surname>
                    <given-names>Mark A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Perlis</surname>
                    <given-names>Roy H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Liston</surname>
                    <given-names>Conor</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gunning</surname>
                    <given-names>Faith M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wager</surname>
                    <given-names>Tor D.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi230978aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="zoi230978aff1"><label>1</label>Division of Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230978aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Psychology, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230978aff3"><label>3</label>Center for Quantitative Health, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230978aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, New York</aff>
              <aff id="zoi230978aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Dartmouth College, Hanover, New Hampshire</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> August 8, 2023.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> September 28, 2023. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33846</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2023 Ashar YK et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="zoi230978cor1"><bold>Corresponding Authors:</bold> Yoni K. Ashar, PhD, Division of Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, 13001 E 17th St, Aurora, CO 80445 (<email xlink:href="yoni.ashar@cuanschutz.edu">yoni.ashar@cuanschutz.edu</email>); Tor D. Wager, PhD, Department of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Dartmouth College, Hanover, NH 03755 (<email xlink:href="tor.d.wager@dartmouth.edu">tor.d.wager@dartmouth.edu</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Ashar had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
                <p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Ashar, Wager.</p>
                <p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p>
                <p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Ashar, Lumley, Perlis, Liston, Gunning.</p>
                <p><italic>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Ashar, Perlis, Liston, Gunning, Wager.</p>
                <p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Ashar, Liston.</p>
                <p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Ashar, Wager.</p>
                <p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Gunning, Wager.</p>
                <p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Perlis, Liston, Wager.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Ashar reported receiving consulting fees from Lin Health, personal fees for clinical training from Pain Reprocessing Therapy Center and Mental Health Partners of Boulder County during the conduct of the study. Dr Lumley reported personal fees from Cognifisense, Inc outside the submitted work. Dr Perlis reported personal fees from Psy Therapeutics, Genomind, Burrage Capital, Circular Genomics, and Vault Health outside the submitted work. Dr Liston reported receiving consulting fees from Compass Pathways PLC, Delix Therapeutics, and Brainify.AI outside the submitted work. Dr Wager service on the advisory board for Curable Health Scientific and personal fees from Flomenhaft Law Firm outside the submitted work.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was funded by National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (Nos. TL1-TR-002386 [Dr Ashar], 1P30AG064198-01 [Dr Ashar], and 5P30AG022845-19 [Dr Ashar]), National Institute for Mental Health (No. R01 MH076136 [Dr Wager]), National Institute on Drug Abuse (No. R01DA035484 [Dr Wager]), the Foundation for the Science of Therapeutic Encounter, the Psychophysiologic Disorders Association, and community donations.</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> Drs Perlis and Gunning are associate editors of <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>; neither were involved in any of the decisions regarding review of the manuscript or its acceptance.</p>
                <p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> We thank Daniel Kusko, BS (University of Alabama Birmingham), Jordan Kelley, DPT (Tufts Medical Center), and Ethan Low, BS (Baylor College of Medicine) for help with coding. Messrs Kusko and Kelley received compensation for their contributions.</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-09-28T10:00">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>6</volume>
              <issue>9</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2333846</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>8</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Ashar YK et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2333846.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33846"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-1">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>In primary chronic back pain (CBP), the belief that pain indicates tissue damage is both inaccurate and unhelpful. Reattributing pain to mind or brain processes may support recovery.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-2">
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>To test whether the reattribution of pain to mind or brain processes was associated with pain relief in pain reprocessing therapy (PRT) and to validate natural language–based tools for measuring patients’ symptom attributions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-3">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>This secondary analysis of clinical trial data analyzed natural language data from patients with primary CBP randomized to PRT, placebo injection control, or usual care control groups and treated in a US university research setting. Eligible participants were adults aged 21 to 70 years with CBP recruited from the community. Enrollment extended from 2017 to 2018, with the current analyses conducted from 2020 to 2022.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-4">
                  <title>Interventions</title>
                  <p>PRT included cognitive, behavioral, and somatic techniques to support reattributing pain to nondangerous, reversible mind or brain causes. Subcutaneous placebo injection and usual care were hypothesized not to affect pain attributions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-5">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>At pretreatment and posttreatment, participants listed their top 3 perceived causes of pain in their own words (eg, football injury, bad posture, stress); pain intensity was measured as last-week average pain (0 to 10 rating, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating greatest pain). The number of attributions categorized by masked coders as reflecting mind or brain processes were summed to yield mind-brain attribution scores (range, 0-3). An automated scoring algorithm was developed and benchmarked against human coder–derived scores. A data-driven natural language processing (NLP) algorithm identified the dimensional structure of pain attributions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-6">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>We enrolled 151 adults (81 female [54%], 134 White [89%], mean [SD] age, 41.1 [15.6] years) reporting moderate severity CBP (mean [SD] intensity, 4.10 [1.26]; mean [SD] duration, 10.0 [8.9] years). At pretreatment, 41 attributions (10%) were categorized as mind- or brain-related across intervention conditions. PRT led to significant increases in mind- or brain-related attributions, with 71 posttreatment attributions (51%) in the PRT condition categorized as mind- or brain-related, as compared with 22 (8%) in control conditions (mind-brain attribution scores: PRT vs placebo, <italic>g</italic> = 1.95 [95% CI, 1.45-2.47]; PRT vs usual care, <italic>g</italic> = 2.06 [95% CI, 1.57-2.60]). Consistent with hypothesized PRT mechanisms, increases in mind-brain attribution score were associated with reductions in pain intensity at posttreatment (standardized β = −0.25; <italic>t</italic><sub>127</sub> = −2.06; <italic>P</italic> = .04) and mediated the effects of PRT vs control on 1-year follow-up pain intensity (β = −0.35 [95% CI, −0.07 to −0.63]; <italic>P</italic> = .05). The automated word-counting algorithm and human coder-derived scores achieved moderate and substantial agreement at pretreatment and posttreatment (Cohen κ = 0.42 and 0.68, respectively). The data-driven NLP algorithm identified a principal dimension of mind and brain vs biomechanical attributions, converging with hypothesis-driven analyses.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-7">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>In this secondary analysis of a randomized trial, PRT increased attribution of primary CBP to mind- or brain-related causes. Increased mind-brain attribution was associated with reductions in pain intensity.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-8">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>Does pain reprocessing therapy, a promising psychological treatment, help patients view primary chronic pain as caused by mind or brain processes?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-9">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this secondary analysis of clinical trial data, natural language methods were applied to understand patients’ beliefs about the underlying causes of their primary chronic back pain. Pain reprocessing therapy led to significant increases in mind- or brain-related attributed causes of pain and increases in mind-brain attributions were associated with reduced pain.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi230978-10">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>These results suggest that patients’ pain attributions are often inaccurate, and that promoting mind- or brain-related attributions may support the effective treatment of primary chronic pain; helping patients to consider pain as “in the brain” may help relieve it.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic">
                <p>This secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial examines whether patient reattribution of primary chronic back pain to brain- or mind-related causes is associated with pain relief in pain reprocessing therapy.</p>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-ZOI230978">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Beliefs that pain is due to peripheral pathophysiology (eg, a bulging disc, osteoarthritis) are common. Yet, peripheral findings are often incidental in nature and not the predominant cause of symptoms. For patients with primary or nociplastic chronic pain—including the majority of cases of chronic back pain, tension headache, and many other pain conditions—pain is driven predominantly by central upregulation and threat learning processes.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> For these patients, the inaccurate belief that pain signifies tissue damage may promote fear, avoidance, disuse, and the persistence of pain.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
              <p>We recently developed pain reprocessing therapy (PRT), a novel psychological treatment aiming to help patients reframe primary chronic pain as caused by nondangerous, reversible brain pathways. PRT presents primary pain as what could be described as a “false alarm” of tissue damage that can be reversed. PRT demonstrated promising efficacy in a 2022 clinical trial<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> of 151 adults with low-moderate severity chronic back pain: 66% of participants randomized to PRT were pain-free or nearly so at posttreatment, as compared with fewer than 20% of placebo and usual care controls. Better understanding the psychological mechanisms of PRT is critical.</p>
              <p>In medically unexplained symptom disorders, the misattribution of symptoms to bodily damage or disease is recognized as a central factor driving dysfunction.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Patients’ symptom attributions have rarely been investigated in chronic pain, although extant work suggests that attributions center on peripheral tissue pathology.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> This is understandable: imaging studies often reveal incidental findings (eg, small disc bulges) that can be easily misinterpreted as causal of pain, and pain is naturally associated with injury, rendering other attributions unintuitive.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> We hypothesized that the reattribution of pain to mind- or brain-related processes: (1) occurs in PRT, and (2) is associated with pain reduction.</p>
              <p>We measured pain attributions before and after treatment using open-ended, free-text responses asking participants to describe the perceived causes of pain in their own words. Natural language approaches complement other valuable measurement tools. Relative to multiple choice–format questions, they provide a minimally constrained approach to studying how patients spontaneously think, capturing a broader set of concepts and beliefs than otherwise possible. Relative to qualitative analyses, they are quantitative and scalable (easily applied to large text data sets, eg, social media, electronic health record data). Natural language methods have been valuable in several psychiatric applications, including dimensional phenotyping<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and prediction of treatment response,<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> but we are not aware of previous applications to symptom attributions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-ZOI230978">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>The pain attribution data presented here were collected as part of a preregistered clinical trial (<ext-link xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/study/NCT03294148?term=NCT03294148&amp;rank=1" ext-link-type="uri">NCT03294148</ext-link>) conducted from 2017 to 2019, with the current analyses conducted from 2020 to 2022. Primary outcomes have been previously reported,<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> but not the attribution data. We provide a brief overview of the trial design here, with full details available in the prior publication and online.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> This manuscript follows the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" ext-link-type="uri">CONSORT</ext-link>) reporting guideline.</p>
              <sec id="H2-1-ZOI230978">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>Participants aged 21 to 70 years with back pain for at least half the days of the last 6 months and 1-week pain intensity averaging 4 or higher on the 10-point Brief Pain Inventory were recruited from the Boulder, Colorado, area via printed and digital advertisements. We targeted primary (nociplastic) chronic back pain (CBP), excluding patients with leg pain worse than back pain, a history of metastasizing cancer, pain-related compensation or litigation, or severe mental illness. Participants provided written informed consent as approved by the University of Colorado institutional review board. Race (including American Indian or Alaskan Native, Asian and Pacific Islander, Black, White, and other or unknown), ethnicity, and gender were self-reported by participants; sex assigned at birth was not collected. Participants were randomized to PRT, placebo, or usual care, with equal probability using an imbalance minimization algorithm. No major changes to study protocol occurred after trial commencement, and sample size was determined by power analyses (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-2-ZOI230978">
                <title>Interventions</title>
                <p>In the PRT group, participants completed a 1-hour telehealth session with a physician followed by 8 individual 1-hour sessions with a therapist twice weekly for 4 weeks. Treatment assessed centralized vs peripheral contributions to pain and provided education on mind and brain generators of chronic pain, substantiated by personalized supporting evidence (eg, spatial spread of symptoms, history of multiple somatic symptoms).<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Treatment aimed to shift pain attributions using guided somatically focused reappraisal exercises and by promoting insight into links between emotional or psychological states and pain. A further description of PRT is provided in the eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p>
                <p>Participants in the open-label placebo group watched 2 videos<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> describing how placebos can powerfully relieve pain even when known to be inert and received a subcutaneous injection openly described as saline into the back during an empathic, validating clinical encounter in an orthopedic medical center. This intervention did not directly target pain attributions. Participants in the usual care group agreed to continue current care as usual and not start new treatments during study participation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-3-ZOI230978">
                <title>Measures</title>
                <p>Participants completed self-report measures at baseline (prerandomization) and posttreatment using an electronic database (REDCap) and masked research assistants. Attributions were collected using an adapted form of the final item of the Illness Perceptions Questionnaire,<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> instructing participants to “please list in rank-order the 3 most important factors that you believe caused your pain” in a short-answer format. Pain intensity was measured as last-week average pain (0 to 10 numerical rating, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating greatest pain), using the first item of the Brief Pain Inventory Short Form.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Questionnaire measures of pain beliefs included: (1) the Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK-11),<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> which has a 2-factor structure measuring activity avoidance and harm beliefs<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>; (2) the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS),<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> assessing pain-related amplification, rumination, and helplessness; and (3) the Survey of Pain Attitudes (SOPA) 2-item Emotions subscale,<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> assessing perceived influences of stress and emotion on pain.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="H2-4-ZOI230978">
                <title>Analyses</title>
                <p>We conducted 4 sets of analyses of the free-text pain attributions: (1) categorization of the attributions by human coders, with the total number of attributions assigned to a category reflecting mind or brain processes quantified as mind-brain attribution scores; (2) computing the frequencies of specific words used in attributions; (3) application of a data-driven (unsupervised) text scaling algorithm identifying the principle semantic dimensions underlying the attributions data; and (4) developing a scalable, automated algorithm scoring attributions for mind- and brain-related concepts.</p>
                <sec id="H3-1-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Human Coder–Derived Categorization</title>
                  <p>The authors reviewed the free-text attributions while masked to treatment condition and time point and developed conceptually coherent categories of attributions based on this review of the data. Two masked authors then assigned each participant-generated attribution to a category, with disagreement resolved by discussion. Three categories were considered by the authors as mind- or brain-related. We tallied how many of the 3 attributions provided by each participant were assigned to one of these categories, yielding a mind-brain attribution score for each participant at each time point ranging from 0 (no mind- or brain-related attributions) to 3 (all attributions mind- or brain-related).</p>
                  <p>Using these mind-brain attribution scores, we tested for (1) their association with questionnaire measures of pain beliefs (TSK-11, PCS, SOPA-emotions) and demographic attributes at baseline, (2) effects of PRT vs control conditions to measure target engagement, and (3) for associations with changes in pain intensity, harm beliefs, or activity avoidance in PRT, investigating whether reattribution might be a psychological mechanism of PRT. We additionally investigated longer-term effects of reattribution, examining associations between changes in mind-brain attribution scores and pain intensity at 1-year follow-up. Finally, we conducted a longitudinal mediation analysis testing whether the effects of PRT vs combined controls on 1-year follow-up pain intensity was mediated by pre-to-posttreatment changes in mind-brain attribution scores. Statistical model details are provided in the eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-2-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Word Frequency Changes</title>
                  <p>We identified the specific words with the largest pre-to-posttreatment changes in frequency within the PRT condition. The word counts reflect how often participants used particular words in their attributions. This complemented the human coder–derived categorizations in 2 ways: it provided an objective outcome (not based on human coder decisions), and it provided a finer-grained outcome relative to the coarser categories.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-3-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Text Scaling</title>
                  <p>Text-scaling algorithms characterize the semantic structure of collections of documents, identifying principal dimensions based on patterns of word cooccurrence. We used an algorithm including regularization methods that provides enhanced reliability for short documents.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Text scaling is commonly used to identify ideological dimensions underlying political texts (eg, political left vs right); we hypothesized that a text-scaling algorithm might identify a mind-brain vs structural-biomechanical dimension underlying pain attributions and that post-PRT participants would be further toward the mind-brain end of such a dimension (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-4-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Automated Attribution Scoring Algorithm</title>
                  <p>We sought to develop an automated, scalable method for scoring whether attributions were mind- or brain-related. Five expert clinicians who had not seen the participant-provided attributions generated words that they would consider mind- or brain-related, which we preprocessed using standard methods (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). A word-counting algorithm computed whether each attribution contained words from the expert-derived list (yes-no scoring), yielding an algorithmically derived mind-brain attribution score ranging from 0 (no attributions contained expert-derived mind or brain words) to 3 (all 3 attributions contained expert-derived mind or brain words). We benchmarked the performance of the automated word-counting algorithm relative to the human coder–derived mind-brain attribution scores using Cohen κ (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). In contrast to text scaling, the automated algorithm was trained independently of the data and provided scores on the same scale as the manual coding approach, enabling direct comparison and validation.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-ZOI230978">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>A total of 151 participants were randomized and provided pain attributions at pretreatment, and 135 (89.4%) completed their assigned treatment condition and provided attributions at posttreatment (mean [SD] age, 41.1 [15.6] years; 81 female [54%]; 134 White [89%]) (<xref rid="zoi230978f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). No adverse events were reported. The sample had moderate pain intensity (mean [SD] score, 4.10 [1.26]) and disability (mean [SD] Oswestry Disability Index, 23.34 [10.17]) at pretreatment, with mean (SD) CBP duration of 10.0 (8.9) years. Preexisting spinal imaging was available in 20 patients in the PRT condition, all of whom had at least 1 spinal anomaly, with a median of 4 anomalies per participant.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Full sample demographics are available in Ashar et al.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <fig position="float" id="zoi230978f1" fig-type="figure">
                <label>Figure 1. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Study Flow Diagram</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>All participants provided 3 substantive or meaningful pain attributions, except for 1 participant (who wrote “???”). Attributions ranged in length from 1 to 39 words, with a mean (SD) of 3.11 (3.26) words. Of 891 attributions coded, only 38 (4%) were categorized discrepantly between coders.</p>
              <sec id="H2-5-ZOI230978">
                <title>Human Coder–Derived Categorization</title>
                <p>Participants’ pain attributions varied widely (word cloud presented in eFigure in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). We grouped them into 11 conceptually coherent categories (<xref rid="zoi230978t1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>, <xref rid="zoi230978f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The most prevalent attribution categories at pretreatment were activity (111 attributions [25%]), injury (85 attributions [19%]), and physiological (71 attributions [16%]). Three categories were considered by the authors as mind- or brain-related: stress (30 [7%]), psychological (10 [2%]), and brain (1 [0.2%]), all of which were low prevalence at pretreatment.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230978t1">
                  <label>Table. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Categories of Patient Attributions Regarding Perceived Causes of Pain</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col width="20.96%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="43.02%" span="1"/>
                    <col width="36.02%" span="1"/>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category<xref rid="zoi230978t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
                        <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Example attributions</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spinal condition</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spinal injury or anatomical issue</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Degenerative processes”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Scoliosis”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Overworking my back muscles to cause spinal disc to bulge”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physiological</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral soft tissue, potential for behavioral remediation</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Lack of flexibility”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Weak core and abdominal muscles”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Bad posture”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injury</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference to a specific past injury event</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Sports injury”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Falling—ice skating as a child”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Pushing a car out of the snow 40 years ago”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activity</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General engagement in an activity (no reference to a specific injury event)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Gymnastics”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Rowing”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Playing three sports in high school”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neglect</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Failure to engage in care or treatment</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Lack of treatment early in life”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Inadequate self-care”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Too busy to take care of my body properly”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedentariness</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inactivity, sedentary lifestyle, prolonged sitting</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Sedentary work/lifestyle”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Inactive lifestyle—I sit a lot in front of a computer or in a car”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Sitting for 8-14 h/day”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attribution focuses on “stress,” with little elaboration</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Stress”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Stressful job”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychological</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A psychological attribution besides stress. Generally related to negative affect.</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Personality”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Outlook on life”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Guilt”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Putting everyone else’s needs before my own”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurobiological or pain-processing related attribution</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Neural pathways”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Brain pathways that developed and stayed even after healing”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Overactive pain response”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hereditary or congenital</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hereditary or congenital attribution</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Genetics”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Birth defect”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Hereditary”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aging-related attribution</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Age”</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>“Aging”</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="zoi230978t1n1">
                      <label>
                        <sup>a</sup>
                      </label>
                      <p>Categories were derived from discussion among authors masked to treatment condition and time point analyses. Prevalence rates for each category are shown in <xref rid="zoi230978f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> and eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230978f2" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 2. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Pain Attribution Category Prevalence</title>
                    <p>Pain attributions were assigned to categories by coders masked to treatment condition and time point. Attribution category prevalence rates for each condition at each time point are shown, with each participant contributing 3 attributions. Substantial increases in psychological and brain attributions (psychological, brain, and stress categories) were observed in the PRT condition, with relatively little attribution changes in placebo or usual care. Numeric values for attribution counts are shown in eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>. Definitions and exemplars for each category are presented in the <xref rid="zoi230978t1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-g002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Each participant’s mind-brain attribution score was computed as the number of attributions assigned by the human coders to a mind- or brain-related category (stress, psychological, and brain). Mind-brain attribution scores ranged from 0 to 3 and were low at baseline (mean, 0.27; median, 0), which indicated predominantly non–mind or brain attributions (<xref rid="zoi230978f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>At baseline, mind and brain attribution scores were positively correlated with a stronger perceived influence of stress and emotion on pain (SOPA Emotion subscale) (<italic>r</italic><sub>149</sub> = 0.22; <italic>P</italic> = .007), were positively correlated with pain intensity (<italic>r</italic><sub>149</sub> = 0.17; <italic>P</italic> = .03), and were marginally higher for women than men (<italic>d</italic> = 0.28; <italic>P</italic> = .07). Baseline mind-brain attribution scores were not correlated with harm beliefs or activity avoidance (TSK-11), pain catastrophizing (PCS), age, or duration of back pain.</p>
                <p>PRT led to substantial increases in mind-brain attributions (<xref rid="zoi230978f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A). Mind-brain attribution scores increased for PRT vs placebo (β = 1.57, <italic>t</italic><sub>130</sub> = 10.83; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) corresponding to <italic>g</italic> = 1.95 (95% CI, 1.45-2.47), and for PRT vs usual care (β = 1.64, <italic>t</italic><sub>130</sub> = 11.65; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) corresponding to <italic>g</italic> = 2.06 (95% CI, 1.57-2.60).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi230978f3" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 3. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Effects of Pain Reprocessing Therapy (PRT) on Patients’ Attributions Regarding the Underlying Causes of Chronic Back Pain </title>
                    <p>Mind-brain attribution scores were computed by counting how many of the 3 attributions provided by participants were categorized as psychological, stress, or brain by coders masked to treatment condition and time point (range: 0-3, with higher scores indicating more mind or brain attributions). A, PRT produced large pre-to-posttreatment increases in mind-brain attribution scores relative to placebo and usual care. B, Within the PRT condition, pre-to-posttreatment increases in mind and brain attributions were significantly associated with decreases in pain intensity.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Increases in mind-brain attribution scores were associated with decreases in pain intensity at posttreatment in the PRT condition (standardized β = −0.25, <italic>t</italic><sub>127</sub> = −2.06; <italic>P</italic> = .04), consistent with hypotheses (<xref rid="zoi230978f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B); interactions for condition × change in mind-brain attribution score on pain intensity were not significant. Examining simple correlations, pre-to-posttreatment changes in mind-brain attribution scores and pain intensity were <italic>r</italic><sub>133</sub> = −0.52 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) across the full sample and <italic>r</italic><sub>42</sub> = −0.28 (<italic>P</italic> = .06) within the PRT condition, corresponding to roughly 9% of variance explained by changes in mind-brain attribution scores within the PRT condition. These effects were largely maintained when examining pain intensity at 1-year follow-up, with standardized β = −0.33 (<italic>t</italic><sub>108</sub> = −2.42; <italic>P</italic> = .02) and simple correlations of <italic>r</italic><sub>114</sub> = −0.44 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) across the full sample and <italic>r</italic><sub>34</sub> = −0.25 (<italic>P</italic> &gt; .99) within the PRT condition. Changes in mind-brain attribution scores partially mediated the effects of PRT vs control on pain intensity at 1-year follow-up (standardized β = −0.35 [95% CI, −0.07 to −0.63]; <italic>P</italic> = .05).</p>
                <p>Increases in mind-brain attribution scores were associated with decreased harm beliefs and activity avoidance (TSK-11) at posttreatment in the PRT condition, standardized β = −0.27 (<italic>t</italic><sub>127</sub> = −2.41; <italic>P</italic> = .02), consistent with hypotheses; interactions for condition × change in mind-brain attribution scores interactions were not significant. Pre-to-posttreatment changes in mind-brain attribution scores and pre-to-post changes in harm beliefs or activity avoidance were correlated <italic>r</italic><sub>133</sub> = −0.57 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) in the full sample and <italic>r</italic><sub>42</sub> = −0.37 (<italic>P</italic> = .01) within the PRT condition. Increases in mind-brain attribution scores were similarly associated with decreased catastrophizing (eResults in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                <sec id="H3-5-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Word Frequency Changes</title>
                  <p>The word with the largest increase in prevalence in the PRT condition was <italic>anxiety</italic>. Several emotion-related words (eg, <italic>fear</italic>, <italic>feelings</italic>, <italic>emotion</italic>, <italic>people</italic>) and neurobiological words (<italic>neural</italic>, <italic>pathways</italic>) were absent at baseline but present in PRT participant attributions at posttreatment, reflecting the introduction of a novel vocabulary. PRT participants decreased their use of words reflecting biomedical attributions, including <italic>activity</italic>, <italic>weight</italic>, <italic>disc</italic>, and <italic>sport</italic> (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-6-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Text Scaling</title>
                  <p>The first principal component identified by the data-driven text scaling algorithm ranged from predominantly structural or mechanical words to predominantly mind and brain words (eg, from <italic>car</italic> and <italic>scoliosis</italic> to <italic>anxiety</italic> and <italic>stress</italic>) (<xref rid="zoi230978f4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). Posttreatment locations in this semantic dimension exhibited large group differences (PRT vs placebo: <italic>Z</italic> = 4.55; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001; <italic>g</italic> = 1.03 [95% CI, 0.59-1.48]; PRT vs usual care: <italic>Z</italic> = 4.57; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001; <italic>g</italic> = 1.02 [95% CI, 0.59-1.46]). Within the PRT condition, posttreatment semantic location further toward the mind and brain direction was significantly associated with decreases in pain intensity (standardized β = −0.32, t<sub>127</sub> = −2.35; <italic>P</italic> = .02), consistent with hypotheses.</p>
                  <fig position="float" id="zoi230978f4" fig-type="figure">
                    <label>Figure 4. </label>
                    <caption>
                      <title>Scaling Analysis of Posttreatment Attributions Identifying Semantic Connections Underlying Free-Text Attributions </title>
                      <p>The first dimension ranged from primarily biomechanical words to primarily mind- or brain-related words. The location of each participant’s posttreatment attributions in the first dimension is shown, with 95% CIs around each condition’s mean location (top). Participants randomized to PRT vs placebo and usual care were significantly further toward the mind and brain end of the first dimension, and scores further toward the mind and brain end of the first dimension were associated with greater pain reduction.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-g004" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
                <sec id="H3-7-ZOI230978">
                  <title>Automated Attribution Scoring Algorithm</title>
                  <p>Agreement between the automated word-counting algorithm and the human coder–derived scores was substantial at posttreatment (Cohen κ = 0.68 [95% CI, 0.52-0.84]; <italic>Z</italic> = 8.38; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and moderate at pretreatment (Cohen κ = 0.42 [95% CI, 0.17-0.67]; <italic>Z</italic> = 3.27, <italic>P</italic> = .001). Examination of confusion matrices revealed that disagreement was driven primarily by the automated algorithm considering attributions as mind- or brain-related when human coders did not. For example, <italic>childhood injury</italic> was miscategorized as mind and brain–related by the automated algorithm due to the presence of the word <italic>childhood</italic> in the expert-derived list.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-ZOI230978">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>We investigated how participants think about the underlying causes of their chronic back pain in their own words, and we tested how changes in pain attributions support pain reductions in pain reprocessing therapy (PRT). At baseline, few attributions pertained to mind or brain processes, even though many to most cases of chronic pain have a centralized component.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Relative to control conditions, PRT led to large increases in mind- and brain-related attributions, demonstrating target engagement. Increases in mind and brain attributions were associated with reductions in pain intensity at posttreatment and mediated the effects of PRT on 1-year follow-up pain intensity, consistent with hypothesized mechanisms of PRT.</p>
              <p>Reattribution of pain from body to brain may be a valuable therapeutic target that is not a focus in leading psychological treatments (eg, cognitive behavioral therapy, acceptance and commitment therapy). These treatments typically present the causes of pain as complex or unknowable and describe the brain as providing “gate control,” a metaphor suggesting modulation of afferent nociceptive input. In contrast, PRT and related treatments (eg, Emotional Awareness and Expression Therapy, Explain Pain, and others<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>) provide the explicit affirmation that primary (nociplastic) pain is generated primarily by mind or brain processes.</p>
              <p>A theoretical focus on attributions is consistent with active inference and predictive processing models of brain function. In these models, the brain integrates prior beliefs and incoming sensory data to update generative models of the sources of sensations.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> A shift in the generative model—such that pain is attributed to central neuroplasticity, not peripheral injury—can change how the brain prioritizes, categorizes, and constructs the sensation of pain, directly changing the pain experience.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></p>
              <p>An emphasis of reattribution in PRT is that mind- or brain-generated pain is nondangerous. This emphasis is supported by our finding that increased mind and brain attribution was associated with reduced harm beliefs and activity avoidance. (Although, surprisingly, greater mind-brain attributions were associated with greater pain intensity at pretreatment—see eAppendix in <xref rid="note-ZOI230978-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.) At the biological level, fear reduction engages both prefrontal and amygdala pathways, 2 structures known to regulate pain in part by projections to the brainstem and spinal cord.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Prior functional magnetic resonance imaging analyses from this trial found that PRT vs control altered prefrontal and somatosensory function.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> A likely function of some prefrontal-somatosensory pathways includes inferring (modeling) the causes of sensory input, and the neurobiological changes we observed may reflect the attribution changes described here.</p>
              <p>Attribution words related to emotions (eg, <italic>anxiety</italic>, <italic>fear</italic>, <italic>feelings</italic>) increased in the PRT condition. Reattribution is not just a so-called “cold” cognitive process but may be integrated with other emotion-focused changes happening in PRT.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Attributing pain to emotions may also motivate patients to address long-standing emotional issues or difficult relationships, as in other treatment approaches.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Natural language methods complement traditional self-reported rating scales.<sup><xref rid="zoi230978r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230978r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> These methods provide an open-ended format less constrained by researchers’ hypotheses and perhaps more closely capturing patients’ spontaneous beliefs, which may more closely govern spontaneous behavior. These methods also provide quantitative outputs and can be scaled. For example, the automated mind-brain scoring algorithm developed here may have fruitful applications to existing large text corpuses (eg, electronic health record data, online patient discussion forums), allowing automated measurement of symptom attributions across a range of contexts. Automated or scalable methods could facilitate the study of how attributions differ across pain conditions or across cultures in large samples, although further algorithm validation (eg, by comparison with human coder categorization) will be needed.</p>
              <sec id="H2-6-ZOI230978">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>This study had several limitations, including the modest amount of variance in pain reduction explained by pain reattribution (approximately 9%). As some participants had large attribution changes with no change in pain (<xref rid="zoi230978f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B), reattribution alone is not sufficient for pain relief. The automated algorithm score agreement at pretreatment was only moderate, suggesting that further refinement is needed especially in untreated populations. Additionally, our sample was predominantly White, well-educated, and recruited from a single metropolitan area; future studies must sample more diverse populations.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-ZOI230978">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>In this secondary analysis of a randomized trial of PRT, the reattribution of primary CBP to mind- or brain-related causes was associated with reductions in pain intensity, with modest effect sizes. While the influence of several pain beliefs on chronic pain is well recognized (eg, pain catastrophizing, pain acceptance), patients’ causal symptom attributions have been understudied. Pain attributions will guide major treatment decisions (eg, surgery vs psychotherapy) and are central in emerging neuroscientific models of brain function. Patients’ attributions of chronic pain to tissue damage are often inaccurate, and therapeutic reattribution to brain processes can support recovery from chronic pain.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-ZOI230978">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zoi230978r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Perrot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The IASP classification of chronic pain for ICD-11: chronic secondary musculoskeletal pain</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fitzcharles</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clauw</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Littlejohn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Häuser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nociplastic pain: towards an understanding of prevalent pain conditions</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>397</volume>(<issue>10289</issue>):<fpage>2098</fpage>-<lpage>2110</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00392-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34062144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34062144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kosek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Do we need a third mechanistic descriptor for chronic pain states?</article-title><source>Pain</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1382</fpage>-<lpage>1386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000507</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26835783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26835783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Vlaeyen</surname><given-names>JWS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crombez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral conceptualization and treatment of chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Clin Psychol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-050718-095744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31821023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Meulders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fear in the context of pain: lessons learned from 100 years of fear conditioning research</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Ther</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<elocation-id>103635</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2020.103635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32417719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ashar</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schubiner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of pain reprocessing therapy vs placebo and usual care for patients with chronic back pain: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2021.2669</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34586357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34586357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Van den Bergh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witthöft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptoms and the body: taking the inferential leap</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>Pt A</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28108416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28108416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rief</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Explaining medically unexplained symptoms—models and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>821</fpage>-<lpage>841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2007.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17716793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17716793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological mechanisms of medically unexplained symptoms: an integrative conceptual model</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>793</fpage>-<lpage>812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.130.5.793</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15367081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Barsky</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyshak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypochondriasis and somatosensory amplification</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>404</fpage>-<lpage>409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.157.3.404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2245272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Douzenis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seretis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Descriptive and predictive validity of somatic attributions in patients with somatoform disorders: a systematic review of quantitative research</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2013.05.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23972408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23972408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cebulla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leibbrand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Röers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilges</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Causal symptom attributions in somatoform disorder and chronic pain</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2009.06.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20004296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20004296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rajasekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dilip Chand Raja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pushpa</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ananda</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ajoy Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The catastrophization effects of an MRI report on the patient and surgeon and the benefits of ‘clinical reporting’: results from an RCT and blinded trials</article-title>. <source>Eur Spine J</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2069</fpage>-<lpage>2081</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-021-06809-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33748882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33748882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Stevans</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delitto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoja</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with transition from acute to chronic low back pain in US patients seeking primary care</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>e2037371</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.37371</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33591367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33591367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>TH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High throughput phenotyping for dimensional psychopathology in electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>997</fpage>-<lpage>1004</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2018.01.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29496195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29496195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vachon-Presseau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apkarian</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative language features identify placebo responders in chronic back pain</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>162</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1692</fpage>-<lpage>1704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000002175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33433145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ashar</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perlis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Ashar_2023_CBP_reattribution. GitHub. Accessed April 20, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/yonestar/Ashar_2023_CBP_reattribution" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/yonestar/Ashar_2023_CBP_reattribution</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schubiner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological therapy for centralized pain: an integrative assessment and treatment model</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0000000000000654</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30461545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30461545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kaptchuk</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Placebos without deception: a randomized controlled trial in irritable bowel syndrome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>e15591</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015591</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21203519?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Weinman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moss-Morris</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The illness perception questionnaire: a new method for assessing the cognitive representation of illness</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08870449608400270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name><surname>Cleeland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Brief pain inventory (short form). Pain Research Group. Published online <year>1991</year>. Accessed April 20, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.npcrc.org/files/news/briefpain_short.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.npcrc.org/files/news/briefpain_short.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Woby</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Urmston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the TSK-11: a shortened version of the Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2005.05.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16055269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tkachuk</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia-11 (TSK-11)</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>970</fpage>-<lpage>977</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2012.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23031396?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23031396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Goubert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crombez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vlaeyen</surname><given-names>JWS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bijttebier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Confirmatory factor analysis of the Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia: invariant two-factor model across low back pain patients and fibromyalgia patients</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002508-200403000-00007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14770050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14770050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MJL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pivik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Pain Catastrophizing Scale: development and validation</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assess</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>524</fpage>-<lpage>532</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1040-3590.7.4.524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>One- and two-item measures of pain beliefs and coping strategies</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>469</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3959(03)00076-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12927618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12927618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Text scaling for open-ended survey responses and social media posts</article-title>. <source>SSRN</source>. Preprint posted September 30, <year>2017</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3044864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Parrot toolbox. Github repository. Last updated January <year>2020</year>. Accessed April 20, 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/wilryh/parrot" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/wilryh/parrot</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fifteen years of explaining pain: the past, present, and future</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>-<lpage>813</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2015.05.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26051220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26051220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bagg</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cashin</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of graded sensorimotor retraining on pain intensity in patients with chronic low back pain</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>328</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>430</fpage>-<lpage>439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.9930</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 35916848?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35916848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Vibe Fersum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skouen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kvåle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of classification-based cognitive functional therapy in patients with non-specific chronic low back pain: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>916</fpage>-<lpage>928</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1532-2149.2012.00252.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23208945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23208945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schubiner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emotional awareness and expression therapy, cognitive behavioral therapy, and education for fibromyalgia: a cluster-randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2354</fpage>-<lpage>2363</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001036</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28796118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28796118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Petzschner</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garfinkel</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khalsa</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Computational models of interoception and body regulation</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2020.09.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33378658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Sennesh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Theriault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van de Meent</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Interoception as modeling, allostasis as control</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<elocation-id>108242</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2021.108242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34942287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Interoceptive predictions in the brain</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3950</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26016744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26016744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Khalsa</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adolphs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Interoception Summit 2016 participants</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Interoception and mental health: a roadmap</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry Cogn Neurosci Neuroimaging</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>501</fpage>-<lpage>513</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpsc.2017.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29884281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The theory of constructed emotion: an active inference account of interoception and categorization</article-title>. <source>Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsx060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27798257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27798257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dual and opposing functions of the central amygdala in the modulation of pain</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>332</fpage>-<lpage>346.e5</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.09.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31597095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31597095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An inhibitory circuit from central amygdala to zona incerta drives pain-related behaviors in mice</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>. <year>2022</year>:<elocation-id>e68760</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.68760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36269044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Scaling up cortical control inhibits pain</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1301</fpage>-<lpage>1313</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.03.139</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29719246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29719246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tinnermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geuter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprenger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finsterbusch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Interactions between brain and spinal cord mediate value effects in nocebo hyperalgesia</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2017</year>:<volume>358</volume>(<issue>6359</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aan1221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28983051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tankha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>“I don’t have chronic back pain anymore”: patient experiences in pain reprocessing therapy for chronic back pain</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. Published online April 23, <year>2023</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2023.04.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 37094744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37094744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tesarz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerhardt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of eye movement desensitization and reprocessing (EMDR) treatment in chronic pain patients: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pme.12303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24308821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24308821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wegener</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Emotion regulation as a transdiagnostic factor underlying co-occurring chronic pain and problematic opioid use</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>796</fpage>-<lpage>810</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/amp0000678</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32915024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32915024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Froud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-synthesis of the impact of low back pain on people’s lives</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-15-50</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24559519?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24559519</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi230978r46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of literacy-adapted psychosocial treatments on biomedical and biopsychosocial pain conceptualization</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1396</fpage>-<lpage>1407</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2021.04.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34004347?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34004347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230978-1">
              <supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230978-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Trial Protocol
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-s001.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
eMethods.
</p>
                  <p>
eResults.
</p>
                  <p><bold>eAppendix.</bold> Supplemental Discussion</p>
                  <p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> Number of Attributions in Each Category for Each Group at Each Timepoint</p>
                  <p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Words With Largest Pre-to-Posttreatment Changes in Frequency Among Participants Randomized to PRT, Derived From Participants’ Attributions Regarding Causes of Pain</p>
                  <p><bold>eFigure.</bold> Word Clouds Showing Common Words Used in Participants’ Pain Attributions</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-s002.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333846-s003.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
