<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T06:18:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2828653" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2828653</identifier>
        <datestamp>2011-03-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>diabetes</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diabetes</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">diabetes</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Diabetes</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2828653</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2828653</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2828653</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20028945</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1239</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db09-1239</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Obesity Studies</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Metabolic Changes Following a 1-Year Diet and Exercise Intervention in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Albu</surname>
                    <given-names>Jeanine B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Heilbronn</surname>
                    <given-names>Leonie K.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kelley</surname>
                    <given-names>David E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>Steven R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Azuma</surname>
                    <given-names>Koichiro</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Berk</surname>
                    <given-names>Evan S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pi-Sunyer</surname>
                    <given-names>F. Xavier</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ravussin</surname>
                    <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <collab>the Look AHEAD Adipose Research Group</collab>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Medicine, St. Luke's–Roosevelt Hospital Center, Columbia University, New York, New York; </aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Garvan Institute, Sydney, Australia; </aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; </aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Pennington Biomedical Research Center, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana.</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Jeanine B. Albu, <email>jba1@columbia.edu</email>.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2010</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2009</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>59</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>627</fpage>
              <lpage>633</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2009</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2010 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons">
                  <license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zdb00310000627.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>OBJECTIVE</title>
                  <p>To characterize the relationships among long-term improvements in peripheral insulin sensitivity (glucose disposal rate [GDR]), fasting glucose, and free fatty acids (FFAs) and concomitant changes in weight and adipose tissue mass and distribution induced by lifestyle intervention in obese individuals with type 2 diabetes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title>
                  <p>We measured GDR, fasting glucose, and FFAs during a euglycemic clamp and adipose tissue mass and distribution, organ fat, and adipocyte size by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry, CT scan, and adipose tissue biopsy in 26 men and 32 women in the Look-AHEAD trial before and after 1 year of diet and exercise aimed at weight loss.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTS</title>
                  <p>Weight and fasting glucose decreased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and significantly more in men than in women (−12 vs. −8% and −16 vs. −7%, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), while FFAs during hyperinsulinemia decreased and GDR increased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) and similarly in both sexes (−53 vs. −41% and 63 vs. 43%; <italic>P</italic> = NS). Men achieved a more favorable fat distribution by losing more from upper compared with lower and from deeper compared with superficial adipose tissue depots (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Decreases in weight and adipose tissue mass predicted improvements in GDR but not in fasting glucose or fasting FFAs; however, decreases in FFAs during hyperinsulinemia significantly determined GDR improvements. Hepatic fat was the only regional fat measure whose change contributed independently to changes in metabolic variables.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
                  <p>Patients with type 2 diabetes undergoing a 1-year lifestyle intervention had significant improvements in GDR, fasting glucose, FFAs and adipose tissue distribution. However, changes in overall weight (adipose tissue mass) and hepatic fat were the most important determinants of metabolic improvements.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>Most obese patients with type 2 diabetes have an unfavorable adipose tissue distribution compared with that of similarly obese men and women without type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). We have shown that they manifest proportionally less metabolically protective adipose tissue (gluteo-femoral) and more metabolically adverse fat depots such as abdominal adipose tissue or hepatic fat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Such patterns correlate with increased fasting glucose and decreased insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) in cross-sectional studies. From the perspective of intervention, in type 2 diabetes, both caloric restriction and relatively modest weight reduction result in fasting glucose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) as well as hepatic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) and peripheral insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) improvements. However, not all studies reporting significant weight loss or favorable fat distribution changes have observed a concomitant improvement in peripheral insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Furthermore, there is a surprising paucity of data regarding the relationship between sustained lifestyle intervention–induced changes in fat mass and regional adipose tissue distribution and parallel metabolic improvements.</p>
            <p>In several weight loss studies conducted for up to 6 months, in type 2 diabetes favorable changes in fat distribution and organ fat did not correlate with improved peripheral insulin sensitivity independent of the changes in body weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Even fewer studies reported on longer-term (of up to 1 year) effects of weight loss on fat distribution and metabolic variables in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). In one study, while parallel 1-year improvements were observed both in the fat distribution (measured by the waist-to-hip ratio) and in fasting glucose and fasting insulin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), the metabolic improvements did not relate to the waist-to-hip ratio change but rather to the overall amount of weight loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). One interpretation is that loss of adipose tissue, regardless of depot, is the predominant factor related to the metabolic improvement in obese patients with type 2 diabetes, challenging the tenet, built mostly from cross-sectional studies, that adipose tissue distribution is a crucial and interactive determinant of the improvement. Yet, it is not clear from these studies whether the variability of the weight loss, the sometime limited number of subjects, or incomplete adipose tissue distribution measurements permitted robust evaluation of the role of specific fat depots in the improvements in metabolic control. In addition, changes in other adipose tissue characteristics, such as fat cell sizes or circulating free fatty acids (FFAs), have not been accounted for in previous studies. Larger subcutaneous abdominal fat cells predict insulin resistance and the development of type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), while increased circulating FFAs play an important role in the etiology of insulin resistance and hyperglycemia in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Whether regional fat loss contributes to improvements in FFAs during weight loss in type 2 diabetes has not previously been reported.</p>
            <p>The current study was therefore undertaken to examine the importance of changes in adipose tissue distribution and other closely related characteristics as determinants of the improvements in metabolic fitness in response to weight loss in type 2 diabetes. We tested the hypothesis that simple measures of weight loss rather than various relative changes and permutations of adipose tissue distribution are the predominant determinant of metabolic improvement induced by a 1-year lifestyle intervention in obese patients with type 2 diabetes. Multiple aspects of adipose tissue mass and its distribution were assessed, including upper and lower adipose tissue mass (using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry [DEXA]), adipose tissue subdivisions in the abdomen and lower extremity (using computed tomography [CT] imaging), and estimations of fat content in liver and muscle (using CT imaging). This was performed along with an adipose tissue biopsy in order to measure mean fat cell size within the abdominal subcutaneous depot both at baseline and following the 1 year of lifestyle intervention.</p>
            <sec>
              <title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title>
              <p>This was an ancillary study of the Look AHEAD (Action For Health in Diabetes) trial at 3 of the 16 participating sites (Pennington Biomedical Research Center, Baton Rouge, LA; the University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA; and St. Luke's–Roosevelt Hospital Center, New York, NY). The primary goal of the Look AHEAD trial is to investigate the effects of a lifestyle intervention of weight loss and physical activity (intensive lifestyle intervention [ILI]) versus those of diabetes support and education on cardiovascular morbidity and mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). One-year results from the Look AHEAD trial and other results of this ancillary study have previously been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Research volunteers.</title>
                <p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for Look AHEAD, which include a confirmed diagnosis of type 2 diabetes, have previously been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). This ancillary study included only participants randomized to the ILI arm of the study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). To simplify the potential impact of changes in antidiabetes medications during intervention, those with fasting plasma glucose ≥180 mg/dl and those on insulin or thiazolidinedione treatment were excluded from the substudy. Fifty-eight volunteers with type 2 diabetes (43 non-Hispanic whites, 12 African Americans, and 3 Hispanics) were studied at baseline (preintervention) and after 1 year of ILI. Twenty-six men (mean ± SD age 61.6 ± 1.5 years) and 32 women (58.9 ± 1.3 years) completed baseline and 1-year measurements. The sex distribution of volunteers at the three sites was as follows: 12 female and 13 male participants at Pittsburgh, 13 female and 5 male participants at St Luke's–Roosevelt, and 7 female and 8 male at Pennington. At baseline, 6 women were pre- or perimenopausal and 26 were postmenopausal (8 on hormone-replacement therapy). All participants signed informed consent, and the project was approved by the institutional review board of each institution and by the Look-AHEAD Steering Committee.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Lifestyle intervention and study protocol.</title>
                <p>As described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), ILI was designed to achieve weight loss through decreased caloric intake (∼500 kcal/day) and increased physical activity (≥175 min/week), with an expected 1-year weight loss of ≥7% of initial value. Before and after 1 year of ILI, our participants were admitted to clinical research facilities on the afternoon preceding the metabolic studies and underwent DEXA and CT imaging. After a standardized dinner (50% carbohydrate, 30% fat, and 20% protein), participants were fasted overnight. The next morning, a metabolic weight and a percutaneous adipose tissue biopsy were obtained; 1 h later, a hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp was performed.</p>
                <p>Addition or discontinuation of antihyperglycemic medications at the 1-year testing compared with baseline was noted. Medications added were thiazolidinedione and metformin (one man each). Medications discontinued were α-glucosidase inhibitors (one woman), meglitinides and repaglinides (two men and two women), and sulfonylureas (11 men and three women). Metformin was reintroduced for a week prior to the 1-year testing at the same dose as before the study if the patients were on it at baseline and were discontinued during the intervention (six men and two women).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Body composition.</title>
                <p>Fat mass and fat-free mass (FFM) (including all nonfat tissue, i.e., lean body mass and bone mineral content) were measured using DEXA (Hologic QDR 4500A) according to the Manual of Procedures of the Look AHEAD trial. All DEXA scans were analyzed using QDR for Windows, version 11.1, software. Fat mass and FFM, gluteo-femoral fat, and trunk and arms fat mass (upper-body fat) were measured by the standard default analysis, in which the commercial computer-based algorithm separates the mass of gluteo-femoral and upper-body fat by two oblique lines that pass through the femoral neck (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). The coefficients of variation (CVs) for repeated measures (<italic>n</italic> = 38; unpublished data) of FFM, fat mass, and percentage of body fat were 0.6, 1.1, and 1.1%, respectively. Three cross-sectional CT scans, 1 cm in width, centered, respectively, on the T<sub>12</sub>–L<sub>1</sub> and the L<sub>4</sub>–L<sub>5</sub> disc space and at the mid-thigh, were obtained to assess hepatic fat as well as abdominal and thigh adipose tissue composition. All CT images were analyzed at the University of Pittsburgh using image analysis software (SliceOmatic; Tomovision, Montreal, Canada). To assess hepatic fat, CT liver and spleen attenuations (Hounsfield units) were determined, and to assess adipose tissue composition, the abdominal and thigh areas for bone, adipose tissue, and skeletal muscle were measured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). To determine visceral adipose tissue (VAT) and abdominal subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT) areas, a separation line was drawn manually on the abdominal CT images along abdominal wall musculature in continuity with the fascia of the paraspinal muscles. Abdominal SAT was further divided into superficial and deep SAT by manually tracing the circumferential superficial fascia as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). On thigh CT images, fascia lata was used to subdivide mid-thigh adipose tissue into SAT and subfascial adipose tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Abdominal subcutaneous adipose tissue biopsy and adipocyte size.</title>
                <p>A percutaneous biopsy of superficial abdominal SAT (∼500 mg) was performed ∼10 cm lateral to the umbilicus using a Bergstrom needle with suction. Adipocyte size and number were determined at the Pennington Biomedical Research Center using a Coulter Counter (Multisizer-3; Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA) as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Cell size is presented as the geometric mean.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp.</title>
                <p>A primed continuous infusion of insulin (80 mU/m<sup>2</sup> per min) was used for at least 3 h, with the stipulation that insulin be infused for at least 1 h after reaching a plasma glucose concentration of 100 mg/dl, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). The mean rate of exogenous glucose infusion during steady-state insulin infusion (last 30 min), glucose disposal rate (GDR), was used to assess peripheral insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Oxygen consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> production were measured using metabolic carts (Sensor Medics Corporation, Anaheim CA) over the 40 min just preceding and during the last 40 min of the insulin infusion; fuel oxidation (carbohydrate and fat) was calculated for the last 30 min of each period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Glucose storage was the difference between total GDR and glucose oxidation. Glucose utilization rates were expressed per kilogram of FFM.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Blood analyses.</title>
                <p>Blood samples were immediately centrifuged, aliquoted, and frozen at −70°C. Plasma glucose was analyzed using a glucose oxygen electrode (Synchron CX7 Delta Systems; Beckman, Brea, CA). Plasma insulin was measured by chemiluminescent immunoassays on the Immulite 2000 analyzer (Diagnostic Product, Los Angeles, CA). The intra- and interassay CVs for insulin (at 50 μU/ml) were 1.75 and 3.6%, respectively. Plasma FFA concentrations were measured on a Beckman Synchron CX5 analyzer using a WAKO NEFA C kit (Denver, CO). All samples were analyzed in the Clinical Chemistry Laboratory at the Pennington Biomedical Research Center.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analyses.</title>
                <p>Data were expressed and shown as means ± SEM unless otherwise indicated. For each variable, data were presented for completed, valid measurements both at baseline and after 1 year. Data were missing for men (out of 26) for liver, spleen, and muscle attenuations (1 man each) and for adipose tissue cell size (2 men) and for women (out of 32) for abdominal adipose tissue measurements (1 woman); thigh adipose tissue, liver, spleen, and muscle attenuations (3 women each); and for adipose tissue cell size (1 woman). Variables with significant deviation from normal distribution were log transformed before analyses (insulin, FFAs, and their changes). ANOVA with repeated measures was used to assess significant changes over the 1 year of the intervention; interactions by sex were tested for significance. General linear models were built according to a priori hypotheses. Specifically, we tested the following: <italic>1</italic>) whether changes in any of the regional fat measures were predictors of the 1-year changes in metabolic variables independent of the change in overall weight or fat mass; <italic>2</italic>) whether the change in clamp FFAs was a predictor of the changes in GDR or fasting glucose, independent of changes in weight, fat mass, or any of the regional fat measures; and <italic>3</italic>) whether the change in GDR was a predictor of the change in fasting glucose, independent of changes in weight, fat mass, or any of the regional fat measures. <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. Statistica, version 6.0 (Statsoft, Tulsa, OK), was used for analyses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>One-year changes in weight.</title>
                <p>Weight decreased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) in both men and women (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), but there was a wide range of weight change (between −26.5 and 3.5 kg in men and −27.3 and 0.9 kg in women). Men lost a higher percentage of their initial weight than women (−12.1 ± 1.2 vs. −8.1 ± 1.1%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Higher 1-year weight loss was predicted by higher weight at baseline in both sexes (β = −0.41; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) but was not related to baseline adipose tissue mass or distribution or to fat cell size or metabolic variables.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Weight, adipose tissue mass and distribution, organ fat, and abdominal subcutaneous fat cell size before and after 1-year lifestyle intervention</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Men (<italic>n</italic> = 26)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-1">*</xref><hr/></th>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Women (<italic>n</italic> = 32)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref><hr/></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.2 ± 1.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.8 ± 1.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.4 ± 1.7</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.9 ± 1.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4 ± 0.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4 ± 0.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8 ± 0.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0 ± 0.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFM (kg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9 ± 1.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9 ± 1.0</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2 ± 1.0</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1 ± 0.9</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat mass (Kg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3 ± 1.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 ± 1.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1 ± 1.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8 ± 1.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent fat mass (of weight)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4 ± 0.7</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5 ± 0.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper-body fat (kg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7 ± 0.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gluteo-femoral fat (kg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 ± 0.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 0.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 ± 0.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 ± 0.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311.7 ± 18.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.5 ± 18.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.5 ± 16.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213.3 ± 16.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deep abdominal SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.9 ± 11.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.4 ± 10.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.2 ± 10.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.6 ± 9.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial abdominal SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.9 ± 11.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0 ± 10.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237.1 ± 10.6</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.8 ± 9.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subfascial thigh AT (cm<sup>2</sup>)(one leg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1 ± 1.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 ± 1.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7 ± 1.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1 ± 1.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial thigh SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>) (one leg)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7 ± 7.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8 ± 7.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.5 ± 7.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.4 ± 7.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver attenuation (HU)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.2 ± 2.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.7 ± 1.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 ± 1.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6 ± 1.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen attenuation (HU)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8 ± 0.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/S attenuation ratio<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 ± 0.04</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 ± 0.04</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 ± 0.04</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 ± 0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle area (cm<sup>2</sup>) (both legs)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311.5 ± 6.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292.7 ± 6.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.4 ± 6.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.2 ± 6.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle attenuation (HU)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8 ± 0.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0 ± 0.8</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1 ± 0.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat cell size<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.05</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 ± 0.04</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 ± 0.04</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 ± 0.03</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat cell number<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,756 ± 271</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,897 ± 370</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,982 ± 239</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,345 ± 325</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>Data are unadjusted means ± SE. FFM, FM, upper body fat, and gluteo-femoral fat measured by DEXA; VAT, SAT, abdominal and thigh SAT subcompartments, and organ (liver, spleen, muscle) attenuation measured by CT scan.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF1-1">
                      <p>*Missing data for men (out of 26) for organ attenuations (1 man each) and fat cell size (2 men).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF1-2">
                      <p>†Missing data for women (out of 32) for abdominal adipose tissue measurements (1 woman), thigh adipose tissue and organ attenuations (3 women each), and fat cell size (1 woman).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF1-3">
                      <p>‡Significant change in both men and women (<italic>P</italic> range &lt;0.05 to 0.00001), with significant interaction by sex (<italic>P</italic> range &lt;0.05 to 0.001 for the interaction term).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF1-4">
                      <p>§Significant change in both men and women (<italic>P</italic> range &lt;0.05 to 0.00001), with no significant interaction by sex.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>One-year changes in adipose tissue mass and distribution, organ fat infiltration, and mean abdominal subcutaneous fat cell size.</title>
                <p>Fat mass and FFM decreased significantly by 27.7 ± 2.6 and 5.5 ± 0.8% and by 14.0 ± 2.1 and 3.8 ± 0.7%, in men and women, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The change in fat mass ranged from −20.4 to 0.2 and from −19.5 to 0.8 kg, while the change in FFM ranged from −9.9 to 3.3 and from −7.8 to 2.8 kg, in men and women, respectively, resulting in a significant decrease in body fat percentage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). There were a number of significant changes in various regional adipose tissue depots (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Upper body fat, VAT, and deep abdominal SAT decreased significantly (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) and significantly more in men than in women, independent of baseline values (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). There were also significant decreases in superficial abdominal SAT and gluteo-femoral fat and in the lower extremity of the thigh, measured cross-sectionally for both the subfascial and the superficial adipose tissue depots, but without sex effect (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                <p>Because of the differential of greater loss from the upper compared with the lower body, the fat distribution as measured by DEXA changed significantly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>) in both sexes. In men, VAT decreased more than the superficial abdominal SAT; this resulted in a significant change within abdominal adipose tissue distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>). There was a similar trend evident in women, although to a lesser extent than in men (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>). A similar pattern was noted in the lower extremity: in men, the subfascial thigh adipose tissue decreased more than the superficial thigh SAT, resulting in a significant change in the thigh adipose tissue distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>C</italic>); a similar trend was observed in women (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>C</italic>).</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float">
                  <label>FIG. 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Absolute amounts in kg (<italic>A</italic>) or cm<sup>2</sup> (<italic>B–C</italic>) on the <italic>y</italic>-axis and the relative distribution as percent of total fat (<italic>A</italic>) or percent of total area (<italic>B–C</italic>) shown as means ± SEM of upper-body (UB-Fat) and lower-body (gluteo-femoral [GF-Fat]) fat by DEXA (<italic>A</italic>); VAT and deep (Deep SAT) and superficial (Superficial SAT) abdominal adipose tissue (AT) areas measured at L<sub>4</sub>–L<sub>5</sub> by CT (<italic>B</italic>); and subfascial and superficial subcutaneous adipose tissue areas measured at mid-thigh (one leg) by CT (<italic>C</italic>) before and after 1 year of intervention; <italic>P</italic> values are shown for differences in the relative distribution.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="zdb0031060450001"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The ratio of the liver-to-spleen attenuation increased, indicating a significant decrease in hepatic fat (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) in both men (−18 ± 5%) and women (−18 ± 4%). The thigh muscle attenuation, a surrogate for intramuscular fat, did not change significantly (<italic>P</italic> = 0.36) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The thigh muscle area decreased on average by 4.6%; this decrease was similar in magnitude to the average decrease in FFM (4.6%).</p>
                <p>Mean size of abdominal subcutaneous fat cells decreased in both men and women (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Lipid content per unit of adipose tissue together with the mean fat cell size was used to estimate the number of fat cells per unit of adipose tissue (see <sc>research design and methods</sc>). The calculated number of fat cells per unit of abdominal SAT increased in both sexes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), despite an average decrease in the overall size of the depot by ∼17%.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>One-year changes in fasting glucose, FFAs, and GDR.</title>
                <p>Fasting glucose decreased significantly in both men and women (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) and significantly more in men than in women (−16.2 ± 2.8 vs. −6.8 ± 3.5%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The clamped glucose levels were not different after than before the intervention (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Fasting insulin decreased significantly and equally in both sexes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), while insulin levels at steady state during the clamp were lower after intervention in women only (interaction term <italic>P</italic> = 0.05). Fasting FFAs were significantly decreased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) and were suppressed by insulin to a significantly greater extent (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) after (by 98 ± 0.5 and 97 ± 0.5% in men and women, respectively) than before (by 95 ± 1 and 94 ± 1%) the weight loss. Therefore, FFA levels at steady state of the clamp were significantly decreased after weight loss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) similarly in men and women (−54.9 ± 8.5 vs. −41.2 ± 15.7%). GDR increased significantly (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) similarly in men and women (63.3 ± 8.1 vs. 43.1 ± 8.6%), with improvement of both glucose oxidation and storage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Metabolic parameters during the euglycemic-hyperinsulinemic clamp before and after 1-year lifestyle intervention</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Men (<italic>n</italic> = 26)<hr/></th>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Women (<italic>n</italic> = 32)<hr/></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Postabsorptive state</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Glucose (μmol/l)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 ± 0.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 ± 0.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 ± 0.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Insulin (pmol/l)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.1 ± 7.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5 ± 8.9</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5 ± 6.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0 ± 8.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    FFAs (mmol/l)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 ± 0.02</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 ± 0.03</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 ± 0.03</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.02</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Steady state during clamp</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Glucose (μmol/l)</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 0.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 0.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 0.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 0.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Insulin (pmol/l)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-2">†</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">834.3 ± 49.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">820.1 ± 39.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">982.9 ± 44.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">859.5 ± 35.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    FFAs (mmol/l)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 ± 0.01</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 ± 0.00</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 ± 0.06</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 ± 0.003</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    GDR (mg · kg FFM<sup>−1</sup> · min<sup>−1</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 ± 0.5</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 ± 0.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Glucose oxidation (mg · kg FFM<sup>−1</sup> · min<sup>−1</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 ± 0.1</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 ± 0.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 ± 0.2</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 ± 0.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Glucose storage (mg · kg FFM<sup>−1</sup> · min<sup>−1</sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-3">‡</xref></td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 ± 0.3</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 ± 0.4</td>
                        <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 ± 0.5</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>Values are unadjusted means ± SE.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF2-1">
                      <p>*Significant change in both men and women (<italic>P</italic> range &lt;0.05 to 0.00001), with no significant interaction by sex.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF2-2">
                      <p>†Significant change in women only (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="TF2-3">
                      <p>‡Men, <italic>n</italic> = 26; women, <italic>n</italic> = 30.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Determinants of 1-year changes in metabolic variables (GDR, fasting glucose, and clamp FFAs).</title>
                <p>The 1-year improvement in insulin sensitivity (ΔGDR or as a percentage of baseline value [%ΔGDR]) did not relate to any baseline variables but was significantly related to the decrease in weight (%Δweight; <italic>r</italic> = −0.65; <italic>P</italic> = 0.000002 [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>]) and fat mass (%ΔFM; <italic>r</italic> = −0.71; <italic>P</italic> = 0.00004). It was also significantly related to the decreases in all regional fat depots (<italic>r</italic> range −0.65 to −0.50; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 for all) and in mean abdominal fat cell size (<italic>r</italic> = −0.27; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) as well as to the increase in the relative proportion of the superficial abdominal SAT (<italic>r</italic> = 0.34; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). However, none of these relationships were independent of the changes in weight or fat mass. In multiple regression analyses, the best predictive model for ΔGDR included %Δfat mass and %Δclamp FFA (overall <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.48; <italic>P</italic> = 0.000049) and for %ΔGDR included independent contributions from the %Δweight, %ΔL/S ratio (ratio of the CT attenuation value of the liver to that of the spleen), and %Δclamp FFA (overall <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.52; <italic>P</italic> = 0.000027).</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float">
                  <label>FIG. 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p><italic>A</italic>: The relationships between the change in weight and the change in GDR (mg · kg<sup>−1</sup> · FFM<sup>−1</sup>), both expressed as a percent of the baseline values (<italic>r</italic> = −0.50; <italic>P</italic> = 0.0006). <italic>B</italic>: The change in GDR (mg · kg FFM<sup>−1</sup> · min<sup>−1</sup>) and the change in fasting glucose, both expressed as percent of the baseline values (<italic>r</italic> = −0.37; <italic>P</italic> = 0.005). <italic>C</italic>: The change in the liver-to-spleen attenuation ratio measured by CT and the change in plasma FFAs at steady state during the clamp (clamp FFAs [logged values]) (<italic>r</italic> = −0.33; <italic>P</italic> = 0.014); correlation coefficients and <italic>P</italic> values shown are from models where sex and site were added as factors. ▴, men; ○, women.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="zdb0031060450002"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Similar analyses were performed for the 1-year improvement in fasting glucose and decreases in clamp FFAs. Neither was related to the changes in weight or fat mass. Among regional fat measures, Δfasting glucose was only significantly related to the ΔL/S ratio (<italic>r</italic> = −0.37; <italic>P</italic> = 0.006) and %Δfasting glucose to the %ΔVAT (<italic>r</italic> = 0.31; <italic>P</italic> = 0.03). While Δfasting glucose was also related to the decrease in clamp FFAs (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), in multiple regression analysis the best predictive model for Δfasting glucose included independent contributions from the ΔL/S ratio and ΔGDR (overall <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.32; <italic>P</italic> = 0.009) and for %Δfasting glucose included independent contributions from the %ΔGDR (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.31; <italic>P</italic> = 0.005) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>). The 1-year decrease in clamp FFA was only related to ΔL/S ratio or %ΔL/S ratio (<italic>r</italic> = −0.33, <italic>P</italic> = 0.014, or <italic>r</italic> = −0.39, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>), independently of changes in weight or fat mass.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>After 1 year of Look AHEAD ILI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), participants with type 2 diabetes had greatly improved levels of peripheral insulin sensitivity, fasting glucose, and FFAs in parallel to significant weight and fat loss, improvement in adipose tissue distribution, and decrease in hepatic fat. The changes in the peripheral insulin sensitivity were best predicted by the overall change in weight and fat mass; the only regional fat measure independently predicting metabolic improvements was the decrease in hepatic fat.</p>
              <p>Several studies have examined the effect of weight loss on adipose tissue distribution and organ fat infiltration in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). These studies varied in duration from a few weeks to up to 6 months and reported variable changes in adipose tissue distribution and organ fat depending on the measurements done and the nature of the intervention leading to the weight loss. Our study is unique in that we have studied the subjects after a 1-year intervention, have measured all aspects of adipose tissue distribution and organ fat infiltration, and enrolled a number of subjects sufficient for reporting results separately for both men and women. In general, significant loss of visceral and hepatic fat has consistently been reported, whereas a decrease in muscle fat has not been consistently observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). In our study, muscle fat infiltration did not change; this could have been due to the CT measurement technique, which is less sensitive than intramyocellular lipid measurement by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy (magnetic resonance spectroscopy [MRS]), as well as to the duration and nature of the intervention. Previous studies have suggested that exercise may prevent the loss of intramyocellular lipid during weight loss induced by caloric restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Thus, the exercise component of our intervention could have had a similar effect over the 1-year period.</p>
              <p>We also found that men in our study, and to a lesser degree women, had favorable changes in adipose tissue distribution from the upper to the lower and from the deeper to the more superficial depots. Such changes have not previously been reported during weight loss by dieting in type 2 diabetes; the exercise component of the ILI could have played a role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Changes in adipose tissue distribution could accompany significant improvements in the components of the metabolic syndrome in individuals with type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>); however, we did not find that the relationships specifically between improvements in the adipose tissue distribution and improvements in the peripheral insulin sensitivity were independent of the change in overall weight and adipose tissue mass. We therefore confirmed our original hypothesis that, with the exception of the decrease in hepatic fat, weight loss and overall adipose tissue mass reduction better predicted the improvement in peripheral insulin sensitivity than improvements in adipose tissue distribution. This finding is also in agreement with previous reports, of shorter duration, with smaller sample sizes and more homogenous weight loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p>
              <p>The decrease in insulin-suppressed FFA levels and the decrease in hepatic fat were also independent determinants of improved peripheral insulin sensitivity. The latter finding is new for type 2 diabetes to the best of our knowledge, although cross-sectional independent associations between hepatic fat and insulin sensitivity have previously been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). The causative direction and the underlying pathophysiology of this association could not be determined from the present study. Changes in insulin, glucose, and FFA levels could all be potential mediators. The association between the decrease in the insulin-suppressed FFA levels and the improvement in peripheral insulin sensitivity has previously been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), and the role of FFAs in the etiology of insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes has been stressed in both cross-sectional (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) and weight loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) studies. Both glucose phosphorylation and glucose transport in skeletal muscle are known to be affected by circulating FFA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and, in turn, improve with weight loss in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). We also found that the change in peripheral insulin sensitivity was related to the relative improvement in superficial adipose tissue distribution and the decrease in this depot's mean fat cell size. These relationships were not independent of the change in body weight but are significant in that they point to the importance of the subcutaneous fat characteristics in the etiology of insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p>
              <p>With regard to fasting glucose, our results are similar to those previously published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) in that the best predictor for the improvement in fasting glucose was the improvement in insulin sensitivity (GDR). The changes in VAT and hepatic fat were associated with the improvement in fasting glucose independent of changes in overall adipose tissue mass, but only the change in hepatic fat was related to the change in fasting glucose, independent of the change in GDR. We also report for the first time that the changes in insulin-suppressed FFAs were related to the change in hepatic fat. The importance of hepatic fat as a determinant of metabolic parameters in type 2 diabetes has been underscored by cross-sectional associations with hepatic insulin resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and by associations with insulin requirements during insulin therapy in type 2 diabetes, independent of measured insulin action and FFA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). In our study, a decrease in hepatic fat was associated with improvements in all three key metabolic variables studied. The exact mechanism is not known; among other possibilities is improved insulin clearance after weight loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), which in addition to the improved β-cell function, could result in a more physiologic insulin pattern and lower both plasma glucose and FFAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Thus, we conclude that changes in hepatic fat play a key role in the improvement of metabolic parameters with weight loss in type 2 diabetes.</p>
              <p>The changes in the oral hypoglycemic agents that occurred over the 1-year intervention are a potential limitation for our study. We performed separate analyses excluding the two subjects who were on insulin-sensitizing agents at the 1-year testing and not at baseline and adding discontinuation of any oral agents at 1 year compared with baseline (yes or no) as a factor. Results were essentially unchanged with a notable exception: the sex differences in the overall weight or fat loss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) were not significant anymore once the discontinuation of the oral agents was accounted for. The peripheral insulin sensitivity changes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) and the adipose tissue distribution changes presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> were not affected. Therefore, we speculate that, since more men discontinued oral agents than women, this may have accounted for the sex differences in the overall weight and fat loss. The baseline menopausal status of our women and its change over time could also have potentially influenced our results. Four women changed menopausal status over the course of the study; none changed hormone-replacement therapy. Although we did not find interactions by menopausal status in our analyses (results not shown), the number of women in the different categories is too small to exclude a possible influence of baseline menopausal status on adipose tissue distribution changes over the 1 year of the study.</p>
              <p>Finally, the Look-AHEAD trial participants had measurements of fitness at baseline and then yearly throughout the ILI, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). In our cohort, fitness improved by 40 ± 8 and by 31 ± 7% in men and women, respectively (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The difference in magnitude compared with the fitness improvement of the entire ILI arm (25 and 18% in men and women, respectively) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>) could be due to the special selection criteria of our study. Just for the entire ILI group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), in our study the fitness improvement was significantly correlated with the degree of weight loss; in addition, it was significantly correlated with changes in FM, percent body fat, and GDR but not with changes in fasting glucose or FFA. The fitness improvement, however, did not predict changes in GDR independent of the overall weight or fat loss, which is consistent with results from other studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>).</p>
              <p>In conclusion, patients with type 2 diabetes undergoing a 1-year lifestyle intervention of diet and exercise had significant improvements in adipose tissue distribution, insulin sensitivity, fasting glucose, and circulating FFAs. Changes in overall weight, adipose mass, and hepatic fat were the most important associates of metabolic improvements.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p>Clinical trial reg. no. NCT00017953, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
                <p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked “advertisement” in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
              <p>This study was funded by DK60412 (to E.R.), with additional support from U01 DK056990 (to D.E.K.), the University of Pittsburgh Obesity &amp; Nutrition Research Center (P30 DK46204), the University of Pittsburgh General Clinical Research Center (MO1 RR000056), Pennington Biomedical Research Center Clinical Nutrition Research Unit (P30 DK072476), the Columbia University Diabetes and Endocrinology Research Center (P30 DK63608), the New York Obesity Research Center (P30 DK26687), and Columbia University Clinical Translational Service Award (UL1 RR024156).</p>
              <p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p>
            </ack>
            <app-group>
              <app id="app1">
                <title>APPENDIX</title>
                <sec>
                  <title/>
                  <sec>
                    <title>Writing group.</title>
                    <p>Jeanine Albu, Leonie K. Heilbronn, David E. Kelley, Steven R. Smith, Evan Berk, Koichiro Azuma, F. Xavier Pi-Sunyer, and Eric Ravussin. We acknowledge the other members of the Look AHEAD adipose research group, not included in the writing group. We are grateful to the participants of the primary Look AHEAD trial for their enthusiastic willingness to participate in this ancillary study and to the nursing and nutritional staffs of the three investigational sites.</p>
                  </sec>
                  <sec>
                    <title>Clinical sites.</title>
                    <sec>
                      <title>Pennington Biomedical Research Center.</title>
                      <p>George A. Bray, MD; Donna H. Ryan, MD; Donald Williamson, PhD; Frank L. Greenway, MD; Allison Strate, RN; Elizabeth Tucker; Kristi Rau; Brandi Armand, LPN; Mandy Shipp, RD; Kim Landry; and Jennifer Perault. The Pennington Biomedical Research Center is also the Coordinating Center. <bold><italic>St. Luke's–Roosevelt Hospital Center</italic></bold>. Jennifer Patricio, MS; Jennifer Mayer, MS; Stanley Heshka, PhD; Carmen Pal, MD; Mary Anne Holowaty, MS, CN; Diane Hirsch, RNC, MS, CDE; Linda Haselman, RN, MS, CDE; and Julia Johnson, PhD. <bold><italic>University of Pittsburgh.</italic></bold> Carol A. Kelley, RN; Jacqueline Wesche-Thobaben, RN, BSN, CDE; Rebecca Danchenko, BS; and Jowand Green, BS.</p>
                    </sec>
                  </sec>
                </sec>
              </app>
            </app-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinicor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>The continuing epidemic of obesity and diabetes in the United States</article-title>. 
<source>J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2001</year>;
<volume>286</volume>:
<fpage>1195</fpage>–
<lpage>1200</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbronn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Albu</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<collab>the Look AHEAD Adipose Research Group</collab><article-title>Adipose tissue distribution in relation to insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2007</year>;
<volume>293</volume>:
<fpage>435</fpage>–
<lpage>442</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Thigh adipose tissue distribution is associated with insulin resistance in obesity and in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>71</volume>:
<fpage>885</fpage>–
<lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>McKolanis</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Plasma fatty acids, adiposity, and variance of skeletal muscle insulin resistance in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2001</year>;
<volume>86</volume>:
<fpage>5412</fpage>–
<lpage>5419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701715</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>McKolanis</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegazi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuller</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalhan</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Fatty liver in type 2 diabetes mellitus: relation to regional adiposity, fatty acids, and insulin resistance</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2003</year>;
<volume>285</volume>:
<fpage>E906</fpage>–
<lpage>E916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12959938</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwynne</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Switzer</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of caloric restriction and weight loss on glycemic control, insulin release and resistance, and atherosclerotic risk in obese patients with type II diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Med</source><year>1984</year>;
<volume>77</volume>:
<fpage>7</fpage>–
<lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6377892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olefsky</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of weight loss on mechanisms of hyperglycemia in obese non–insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>1986</year>;
<volume>35</volume>:
<fpage>990</fpage>–
<lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3527829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brechtel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Griver</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Secretion and hepatic extraction of insulin after weight loss in obese noninsulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1988</year>;
<volume>66</volume>:
<fpage>979</fpage>–
<lpage>986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3283164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Buonocore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Relative effects of calorie restriction and weight loss in noninsulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title>. 
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1993</year>;
<volume>77</volume>:
<fpage>1287</fpage>–
<lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8077323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bononi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Caloric restriction per se is a significant factor in improvements in glycemic control and insulin sensitivity during weight loss in obese NIDDM patients</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes Care</source><year>1994</year>;
<volume>17</volume>:
<fpage>30</fpage>–
<lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8112186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Befroy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendler</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Reversal of nonalcoholic hepatic steatosis, hepatic insulin resistance, and hyperglycemia by moderate weight reduction in patients with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2005</year>;
<volume>54</volume>:
<fpage>603</fpage>–
<lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuller</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>McKolanis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of moderate weight loss and orlistat on insulin resistance, regional adiposity, and fatty acids in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2004</year>;
<volume>27</volume>:
<fpage>33</fpage>–
<lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14693963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>FGS</given-names></name><name><surname>Menshikova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritov</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Radikova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLany</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of physical activity and weight loss on skeletal muscle mitochondria and relationship with glucose control in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2007</year>;
<volume>56</volume>:
<fpage>2142</fpage>–
<lpage>2147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17536063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Watada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumashiro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyogoku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maehara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of diet and exercise on muscle and liver intracellular lipid content and insulin sensitivity in type 2 diabetic patients</article-title>. 
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2005</year>;
<volume>90</volume>:
<fpage>3191</fpage>–
<lpage>3196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascale</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guare</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>The effect of weight loss on change in waist-to-hip ratio in patients with type II diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>In J Obesity</source><year>1992</year>;
<volume>16</volume>:
<fpage>59</fpage>–
<lpage>65</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koeske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowalk</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Long-term effects of modest weight loss in type II diabetic patients</article-title>. 
<source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>1987</year>;
<volume>147</volume>:
<fpage>1749</fpage>–
<lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3310940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogardus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tataranni</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Enlarged subcutaneous abdominal adipocyte size, but not obesity itself, predicts type II diabetes independent of insulin resistance</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetologia</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>43</volume>:
<fpage>1498</fpage>–
<lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11151758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamendola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Reaven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Enhanced proportion of small adipose cells in insulin-resistant vs. insulin-sensitive individuals implicates impaired adipogenesis</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetologia</source><year>2007</year>;
<volume>50</volume>:
<fpage>1707</fpage>–
<lpage>1715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17549449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindmark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Renstrom</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Fat cell enlargement is an independent marker of insulin resistance and ‘hyperleptinaemia.’</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2007</year>;
<volume>50</volume>:
<fpage>625</fpage>–
<lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Metabolic consequences of weight loss on glucose metabolism and insulin action in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes Obes and Metab</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>2</volume>:
<fpage>121</fpage>–
<lpage>129</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Role of fatty acids in the pathogenesis of insulin resistance and NIDDM</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>1997</year>;
<volume>46</volume>:
<fpage>3</fpage>–
<lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8971073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Espeland</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovski</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Look AHEAD (Action for Health in Diabetes): design and methods for a clinical trial of weight loss for the prevention of cardiovascular disease in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Control Clin Trials</source><year>2003</year>;
<volume>24</volume>:
<fpage>610</fpage>–
<lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500058</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>LOOK AHEAD Research Group</collab>: 
<article-title>The Look AHEAD study: a description of the lifestyle intervention and the evidence supporting it</article-title>. 
<source>Obesity</source><year>2006</year>;
<volume>14</volume>:
<fpage>737</fpage>–
<lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wadden</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Neiberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Foreyt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Trence</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitolins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<collab>the Look AHEAD Research Group</collab><article-title>One-year weight losses in the Look AHEAD study: factors associated with success</article-title>. 
<source>Obesity</source><year>2009</year>;
<volume>17</volume>:
<fpage>713</fpage>–
<lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19180071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakicic</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanyam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Regensteiner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribisl</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effect of a lifestyle intervention on change in cardiorespiratory fitness in adults with type 2 diabetes: results from the Look AHEAD study</article-title>. 
<source>Int J Obes</source><year>2009</year>;
<volume>33</volume>;
<fpage>305</fpage>–
<lpage>316</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbronn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Albu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<collab>the Look AHEAD Research Group</collab>: 
<article-title>Adipose decreased expression of adipogenic genes in obese subjects with type 2 Diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Obesity</source><year>2006</year>;
<volume>14</volume>:
<fpage>1543</fpage>–
<lpage>1552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galgani</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbronn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Albu</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi-Sunyer</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<collab>the Look AHEAD Adipose Research Group</collab><article-title>Metabolic flexibility in response to glucose is not impaired in people with type 2 diabetes after controlling for glucose disposal rate</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2008</year>;
<volume>57</volume>:
<fpage>841</fpage>–
<lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18285553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pasarica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchoukalova</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbronn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Albu</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<collab>the look AHEAD Adipose Research Group</collab><article-title>Differential effect of weight loss on adipocyte size subfractions in patients with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Obesity</source><year>2009</year>;
<volume>17</volume>:
<fpage>1976</fpage>–
<lpage>1978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19629054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Subcutaneous abdominal fat and thigh muscle composition predict insulin sensitivity independently of visceral fat</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>1997</year>;
<volume>46</volume>:
<fpage>1579</fpage>–
<lpage>1585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9313753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Troost</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huwe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Subdivisions of subcutaneous abdominal adipose tissue and insulin resistance</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>278</volume>:
<fpage>E941</fpage>–
<lpage>E948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10780952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFronzo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Glucose clamp technique: a method for quantifying insulin secretion and resistance</article-title>. 
<source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1979</year>;
<volume>237</volume>:
<fpage>E214</fpage>–
<lpage>E223</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jequier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Acheson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schutz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Assesment of energy expenditure and fuel utilization in man</article-title>. 
<source>Annu Rev Nutr</source><year>1987</year>;
<volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>187</fpage>–
<lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3300732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lara-Castro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Newcomer</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaughnessy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiflett</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigsby</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohning</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchthal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garvey</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effects of short-term very low-calorie diet on intramyocellular lipid and insulin sensitivity in nondiabetic and type 2 diabetic subjects</article-title>. 
<source>Metabolism</source><year>2008</year>;
<volume>57</volume>:
<fpage>1</fpage>–
<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18078853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larson-Meyer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbronn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Newcomer</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisard</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Effect of calorie restriction with or without exercise on insulin sensitivity, β-cell function, fat cell size, and ectopic lipid in overweight subjects</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2006</year>;
<volume>29</volume>:
<fpage>1337</fpage>–
<lpage>1344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16732018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vokac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinas</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Loss of abdominal fat and improvement of the cardiovascular risk profile by regular moderate exercise training in patients with NIDDM</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetologia</source><year>1995</year>;
<volume>38</volume>:
<fpage>1313</fpage>–
<lpage>1319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8582541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mourier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>De Kerviler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigard</surname><given-names>AX</given-names></name><name><surname>Villette</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvallet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guezennec</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cathelineau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Mobilization of visceral adipose tissue related to the improvement in insulin sensitivity in response to physical training in NIDDM</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes Care</source><year>1997</year>;
<volume>3</volume>:
<fpage>385</fpage>–
<lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9051392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabbrini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Magkos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abumrad</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Okunade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Intrahepatic fat, not visceral fat, is linked with metabolic complications of obesity</article-title>. 
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year>;
<volume>106</volume>:
<fpage>15430</fpage>–
<lpage>15435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felber</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Golay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Pathways from obesity to diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Int J Obes</source><year>2002</year>;
<volume>26</volume>(
<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>):
<fpage>S39</fpage>–
<lpage>S45</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoldo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinahan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Weight loss-induced plasticity of glucose transport and phosphorylation in the insulin resistance of obesity and type 2 diabetes</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2003</year>;
<volume>52</volume>:
<fpage>1619</fpage>–
<lpage>1626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryysy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakkinen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vehkavaara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerbacka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Halavaara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yki-Jarvinen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Hepatic fat content and insulin action on free fatty acids and glucose metabolism rather than insulin absorption are associated with insulin requirements during insulin therapy in type 2 diabetic patients</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>49</volume>:
<fpage>749</fpage>–
<lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10905483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utzschneider</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barsness</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Diet-induced weight loss is associated with an improvement in beta-cell function in older men</article-title>. 
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2004</year>;
<volume>89</volume>:
<fpage>2704</fpage>–
<lpage>2710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15181045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsiaras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: 
<article-title>Enhanced fat oxidation through physical activity is associated with improvements in insulin sensitivity in obesity</article-title>. 
<source>Diabetes</source><year>2003</year>;
<volume>52</volume>:
<fpage>2191</fpage>–
<lpage>2197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
