<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T02:38:34Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7927888" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7927888</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-05</datestamp>
        <setSpec>haematol</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Haematologica</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Haematologica</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HAEMA</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Haematologica</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0390-6078</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1592-8721</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Fondazione Ferrata Storti</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7927888</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7927888</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7927888</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32107337</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32107337</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3324/haematol.2019.243386</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Response-adapted therapy with infusional EPOCH chemotherapy plus rituximab in human immunodeficiency virus-associated, B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sparano</surname>
                    <given-names>Joseph A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>Jeannette Y.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kaplan</surname>
                    <given-names>Lawrence D.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ramos</surname>
                    <given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ambinder</surname>
                    <given-names>Richard F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wachsman</surname>
                    <given-names>William</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff007">
                    <sup>7</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Aboulafia</surname>
                    <given-names>David</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff008">
                    <sup>8</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Noy</surname>
                    <given-names>Ariela</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff009">
                    <sup>9</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0010">
                    <sup>10</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Henry</surname>
                    <given-names>David H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0011">
                    <sup>11</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ratner</surname>
                    <given-names>Lee</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0012">
                    <sup>12</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cesarman</surname>
                    <given-names>Ethel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0010">
                    <sup>10</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chadburn</surname>
                    <given-names>Amy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0010">
                    <sup>10</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mitsuyasu</surname>
                    <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0013">
                    <sup>13</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>Montefiore-Einstein Cancer Center, <institution>Montefiore Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Bronx, NY</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><institution>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Little Rock, AR</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><institution>University of California San Francisco</institution>, <addr-line>San Francisco, CA</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><institution>University of Miami</institution>, <addr-line>Miami, FL</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff005"><label>5</label><institution>Sidney Kimmel Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</institution>, <addr-line>Baltimore, MD</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff006"><label>6</label><institution>Moores Cancer Center University of California San Diego</institution>, <addr-line>La Jolla, CA</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff007"><label>7</label><institution>Veterans Affairs San Diego Healthcare System</institution>, <addr-line>San Diego, CA</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff008"><label>8</label><institution>Virginia Mason Cancer Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle, WA</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff009"><label>9</label><institution>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line>New York, NY</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff0010"><label>10</label><institution>Weill Cornell Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>New York, NY</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff0011"><label>11</label><institution>Pennsylvania Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Philadelphia, PA</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff0012"><label>12</label><institution>Washington University, St. Louis</institution>, <addr-line>MO</addr-line></aff>
              <aff id="aff0013"><label>13</label><institution>University of California Los Angeles Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Los Angeles, CA, USA</addr-line>. All the institutes are part of the AIDS Malignancy Consortium</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">JOSEPH A. SPARANO <email>jsparano@montefiore.org</email></corresp>
                <fn>
                  <p>
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Disclosures</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>No conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn>
                  <p>
                    <bold>
                      <italic>Contributions</italic>
                    </bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>The manuscript was written by JAS and was approved by all co-authors. The clinical protocol was written by JAS, JYL, and LDK. The data and statistical analyses were performed by JYL and administrative support and oversight were provided by RM. Pathological review of tumor specimens was performed by EC and AC. Individuals who contributed subjects to the trial included JAS, LDK, JCR, RFA, DA, AN, DHH, LR, EC, WW, and AC.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <day>01</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>106</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>730</fpage>
              <lpage>735</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright© 2021 Ferrata Storti Foundation</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">by-nc 4.0</uri>) which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Four cycles of rituximab plus CHOP (cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone) chemotherapy is as effective as six cycles in low-risk diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL). Here we report a post-hoc analysis of a prospective clinical trial in patients with human immunodeficiency virus-associated DLBCL and high-grade lymphoma treated with four to six cycles of EPOCH plus rituximab based on a response-adapted treatment strategy. One hundred and six evaluable patients with human immunodeficiency virus-associated DLBCL or highgrade CD20<sup>+</sup> non-Hodgkin lymphoma were randomized to receive rituximab (375 mg/m2) given either concurrently prior to each infusional EPOCH cycle, or sequentially (weekly for 6 weeks) following completion of EPOCH. EPOCH consisted of a 96-hour intravenous infusion of etoposide, doxorubicin, and vincristine plus oral prednisone followed by an intravenous bolus of cyclophosphamide every 21 days for four to six cycles. Patients received two additional cycles of therapy after documentation of a complete response by computed tomography after cycles 2 and 4. Sixty-four of 106 evaluable patients (60%; 95% confidence interval [95% CI]: 50%-70%) in both treatment arms had a complete response. The 2-year event-free survival rates were similar in the 24 patients with complete response who received four or fewer cycles of EPOCH (78%; 95% CI: 55%-90%) due to having achieved a complete response after two cycles, compared with those who received five or six cycles of EPOCH (85%; 95% CI: 70%-93%) because a complete response was first documented after cycle 4. A response-adapted strategy may permit a shorter treatment duration without compromising therapeutic efficacy in patients with human immunodeficiency virus-associated lymphoma treated with EPOCH plus rituximab, which merits further evaluation in additional prospective trials. <italic>Clinical Trials.gov identifier NCT00049036.</italic></p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <funding-statement><bold><italic>Funding</italic></bold>: <italic>This study was supported in part by Public Health Service grant n. UM1CA121947, the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, and the Department of Health and Human Services.</italic></funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="2"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="35"/>
                <page-count count="6"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1-1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Six cycles of the anti-CD20 antibody rituximab (R) plus cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone (CHOP) or CHOP-like chemotherapy are recommended by the European Society of Medical Oncology (ESMO) and National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) practice guidelines for the treatment of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL),<sup><xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> a recommendation supported by population-based data demonstrating similar outcomes after six or eight cycles of therapy.<sup><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Poeschel <italic>et al.</italic> reported the non-inferiority of four cycles of R-CHOP (followed by 2 additional doses of rituximab) compared with six cycles of R-CHOP in a randomized, phase III trial that included 588 immunocompetent patients with stage I-II DLBCL aged 18-60 years and an age-adjusted International Prognostic Index score of 0, indicating that de-escalation of treatment duration may be safely achieved without compromising curability in an appropriately selected patient population.<sup><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> This provides a foundation for evaluation of therapeutic de-escalation in other settings using other strategies.</p>
              <p>Infusional administration of cytotoxic therapy has been explored as a potential strategy in patients with poor-risk lymphoma,<sup><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5-8</xref></sup> including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-associated lymphoma.<sup><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9-13</xref></sup> Based upon these considerations, the AIDS Malignancy Consortium conducted a randomized, phase II trial of rituximab (375 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) given either concurrently prior to each infusional EPOCH chemotherapy cycle, or sequentially (weekly for 6 weeks) following completion of all chemotherapy in patients with HIV-associated DLBCL and high-grade lymphoma.<sup><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> EPOCH consisted of a 96-hour intravenous infusion of etoposide, doxorubicin, and vincristine together with oral prednisone followed by an intravenous bolus of cyclophosphamide given every 21 days for four to six cycles, with cyclophosphamide dose adjusted based on pretreatment CD4 lymphocyte count, and subsequently escalated or reduced based on the absence or presence of treatment-associated cytopenias. The prespecified primary efficacy complete response endpoint of 75% was met in the concurrently treated arm (73%, 95% confidence interval [95% CI]: 58%-85%), but not in the arm treated sequentially (55%, 95% CI: 41%-68%).<sup><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Patients were assessed by computed tomography (CT) of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis after every two cycles of EPOCH chemotherapy, and were treated for two cycles beyond achieving a complete response for a minimum of four and a maximum of six cycles of EPOCH. Two-year time to progression rates were similar in the concurrently treated arm (75%, 95% CI: 63%-88%) and the sequentially treated arm (71%, 95% CI: 59%-84%). Inspired by the successful de-escalation of R-CHOP therapy to four cycles documented in a low-risk population with DLBCL,<sup><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> here we report a post-hoc analysis of the outcomes of patients with HIV-associated DLBCL and highgrade lymphoma with higher risk features who achieved a complete response when treated with four or fewer cycles of therapy, based on having achieved a complete response after two cycles of EPOCH.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec1-2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Eligibility criteria and study conduct</title>
                <p>Details regarding eligibility criteria, treatment, and clinical outcomes up to 2 years were previously reported.<sup><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Briefly, eligibility criteria included: (i) CD20<sup>+</sup> B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma, including DLBCL, Burkitt/Burkitt-like lymphoma, or other aggressive lymphomas; (ii) HIV infection; (iii) stage II-IV disease (or stage I disease with an elevated serum lactate dehydrogenase concentration); (iv) Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 0-2; (v) age 18 years or older;<sup><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> and (vi) adequate organ function, similarly to prior trials by the AIDS Malignancy Consortium.<sup><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> The study was reviewed and approved by the Cancer Evaluation Therapy Program of the National Cancer Institute, and by the institutional review board at each participating institution. All patients provided written informed consent to their inclusion in the analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Response assessment and duration of therapy</title>
                <p>Response was defined by the 1999 International Response Criteria for Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma (which utilizes anatomical but not functional imaging).<sup><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Response was evaluated after every two cycles of EPOCH therapy with CT of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis, and continued for two cycles beyond the achievement of a complete response for a minimum of four and a maximum of six cycles, including after completion of R-EPOCH in the concurrently treated arm, and after completion of EPOCH alone and following rituximab alone in the sequentially treated arm. All patients had a bone marrow evaluation and lumbar puncture for cerebrospinal fluid cytological examination at baseline. A repeat bone marrow evaluation for confirmation of complete response was required after completion of therapy if the baseline study demonstrated lymphomatous marrow involvement. 2-Deoxy-2- [fluorine-18]fluoro-D-glucose (FDG) positron emission tomography (PET) scans were not required or consistently performed, and when done were usually performed at the completion of therapy. Event-free survival, time to progression, and overall survival were estimated using the method of Kaplan and Meier. Event-free survival was defined as the time between registration and either relapse or progression of lymphoma or death from any cause (thus corresponding to progression-free survival in other reports<sup><xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>). Time to progression was defined as time to progression or relapse of lymphoma, with deaths from other causes censored. Patients were followed for survival and recurrence up to 5 years after registration. We performed a post-hoc analysis to evaluate the outcomes for patients who received only four cycles of therapy due to achieving a complete response, as determined by CT scan, after two cycles of therapy, compared with those who required five or six cycles of therapy who achieved a complete response after four cycles of therapy.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec1-3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>Patients and response to therapy</title>
                <p>A total of 106 evaluable patients were enrolled and initiated treatment at 20 sites of the AIDS Malignancy Consortium between December 2002 and April 2006 and are included in this analysis, as in the original, previously described analysis.<sup><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The disposition and outcomes of all patients enrolled are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig001">Figure 1</xref>. A complete response was achieved by 64 of the 106 patients (60%, 95% CI: 50%-70%) who received any protocol therapy. The null hypothesis of a complete response rate of 50% was rejected in favor of the alternative of 75% for the concurrently treated arm (<italic>P</italic>=0.005), but not for the sequentially treated arm (<italic>P</italic>=0.394). Of the 64 patients who had a complete response, 24 received four or fewer cycles of REPOCH: 14/35 (40%) in the concurrently treated arm and 10/29 (34%) in the sequentially treated arm.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>Characteristics of patients treated with four or fewer <italic>versus</italic> five or six cycles of EPOCH therapy</title>
                <p>Of 64 patients who achieved a complete response, 24 (38%, 95% CI: 26%-51%) received four or fewer cycles of EPOCH based on their having achieved early complete response after two cycles of therapy, whereas the remaining 40 (63%, 95% CI: 50%-74%) received five or six cycles of therapy. The characteristics of the entire study population, and patients who received four or fewer <italic>versus</italic> five or six cycles are shown in <xref rid="table001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The characteristics of the two groups were generally comparable to each other, and to those of the entire study population, with respect to gender, median age, baseline CD4 count, concurrent antiretroviral therapy, histology, and bone marrow involvement at baseline.</p>
                <p>Information regarding histological subtype (germinal center B-cell [GCB] subtype <italic>vs</italic>. non-GCB subtype) was available for only 21 of the 64 patients who had a complete response, with no significant difference in number with non-GCB subtype for those who received four or fewer cycles compared with those who received five or six cycles (3/8 <italic>vs</italic>. 5/13 patients, <italic>P</italic>=1.000 Fisher exact test).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5">
                <title>Treatment administered</title>
                <p>A total of 322 cycles of EPOCH therapy were given to all 64 patients who achieved a complete response. Among the 24 who received four or fewer cycles, five received fewer than four cycles. The reasons for this were disease progression after achieving a complete response (n=1), physician’s decision (n=1), or other reasons (n=3). Among the 40 who received five or six cycles of EPOCH, 36 received six cycles and four received five cycles due to physicians’ decision (n=3) or unknown reasons (n=1).</p>
                <fig id="fig001" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
                  <label>Figure 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Consort diagram.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="106730.fig1"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="table001" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Characteristics of the entire population and complete responders stratified by number of EPOCH treatment cycles.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="106730.tab1"/>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap id="table002" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Clinical outcomes for entire population and complete responders stratified by number of EPOCH treatment cycles.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="106730.tab2"/>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-6">
                <title>Clinical outcomes by number of EPOCH treatment cycles in complete responders</title>
                <p>Outcome data for the 106 patients in the entire study population, and the 64 patients who achieved complete response are shown in <xref rid="table002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and Figure 2A-C. After a median follow-up of 30 months (range, 0-67 months) for all treated patients, 36 (34%, 95% CI: 25%-44%) died, with relapsed lymphoma being the cause of death in eight (8%, 95% CI: 3%-14%). After a median follow-up of 38.5 months (range, 1-66 months) in the 64 patients who achieved a complete response, 11 (17%, 95% CI: 9%- 29%) died, five (8%, 95% CI: 3%-18%) with relapsed lymphoma as the cause of death. Outcomes were similar for those treated with four or fewer cycles compared with those given five or six cycles with respect to rates of 2- year event-free survival (78% <italic>vs</italic>. 85%), time to progression (91% <italic>vs</italic>. 87%), and overall survival (78% <italic>vs</italic>. 90%).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec1-4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In the absence of prospective comparative data in HIVassociated lymphoma, six cycles of rituximab plus infusional EPOCH is considered a preferred regimen for firstline treatment of HIV-associated DLBCL, HHV8-positive DLBCL, primary effusion lymphoma, and is also among the preferred regimens for HIV-associated Burkitt lymphoma in the 2019 NCCN guidelines.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> These recommendations were driven by the effectiveness of REPOCH in individual phase II trials in HIV-associated DLBCL and high-grade lymphoma,<sup><xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and results from a large meta-analysis that demonstrated greater efficacy for R-EPOCH as compared to R-CHOP in HIV-associated lymphoma.<sup><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> On the other hand, a phase III trial comparing R-CHOP with R-EPOCH in immunocompetent patients with DLBCL found no difference in efficacy.<sup><xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Retrospective analysis showed that a high proliferation rate was associated with better prognosis in HIV-associated lymphomas when treated with infusional R- EPOCH but not with R-CHOP, suggesting that tumors with high proliferation rates, such as high-grade lymphoma and a subset of DLBCL may be those most likely to benefit from infusional EPOCH chemotherapy.<sup><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The findings from our study suggest that patients with HIV-associated lymphoma who achieve a complete response after two cycles of EPOCH plus rituximab have excellent outcomes when therapy is limited to four cycles, thereby sparing toxicity associated with longer treatment durations.</p>
              <p>Dunleavy <italic>et al.</italic> reported a phase II study including 33 patients with HIV-associated DLBCL who received three to six cycles of dose-dense rituximab (SC-EPOCH-RR), of whom 79% received three cycles of therapy based on a risk-adapted approach of treating for one cycle beyond a negative interim PET-CT after cycle 2.<sup><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> At the median follow- up of 5 years, the progression-free survival rate was 84%, although outcomes were excellent only for those with GCB subtype lymphoma (95% for GCB <italic>vs</italic>. 44% for non-GCB subtype).<sup><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Only about one-third of patients in our trial had information regarding GCB or non-GCB subtype, and outcomes were similar irrespective of subtype. Future studies evaluating risk-adapted therapy may need to integrate histological subtyping, be limited to the GCB lymphoma subtype and consider other molecular characteristics that have prognostic relevance.<sup><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p>
              <fig id="fig002" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>Kaplan-Meier estimates of outcomes in patients achieving complete response to response-adapted EPOCH chemotherapy, stratified by number of treatment cycles</bold>. (A-C) Patients are stratified into two groups: a group that received four or fewer cycles of EPOCH chemotherapy and a group that received five or six cycles. Estimates are shown for event-free survival (A), time to progression (B) and overall survival (C).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="106730.fig2"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Interim restaging is recommended to identify patients whose disease has not responded well to, or has progressed, on induction therapy after two to four cycles of therapy.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Staging is recommended using FDG-PET integrated with CT (FDG-PET/CT) at diagnosis, after two to four cycles of therapy, and at the end of treatment.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> A negative PET scan after two to four cycles of induction therapy has been associated with significantly higher event-free survival and overall survival rates in some studies,<sup><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25-28</xref></sup> but not others.<sup><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29-32</xref></sup> Although several studies failed to show improvement in clinical outcomes when therapy was tailored to FDG-PET/CT response,<sup><xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> these studies were designed to evaluate more aggressive therapy in patients with persistent FDG-avid lesions, not deescalation of therapy in patients who had an early FDG response. Differentiation of reactive adenopathy from active lymphoma may be challenging in patients with HIV-associated lymphoma, although this may be less problematic in patients with well-controlled viremia.<sup><xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> Although preliminary results reported by Dunleavy <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> regarding use of interim FDG-PET/CT as a pharmacodynamic biomarker for tailoring de-escalation appears promising in HIV-associated lymphoma, further study is required in multicenter prospective clinical trials.</p>
              <p>Our analysis has several strengths and limitations. The strengths include the prospective nature of the trial, and the protocol-specified guidelines for treatment duration based on radiographic response. The limitations include the post-hoc analysis examining response durability based on rapidity of response and number of treatment cycles, and the fact that the observations were not based on an adequately powered comparison between the standard approach of six treatment cycles compared with a risk-adapted approach. Nevertheless, given recent evidence that four cycles of R-CHOP constitute adequate therapy for a low-risk population,<sup><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> the findings of our study indicating the feasibility of a response-adapted deescalation strategy in a higher-risk population with HIVassociated lymphoma, and the clinical utility of interim FDG/PET, there is now a compelling rationale to prospectively evaluate the use of interim FDG-PET/CT after two cycles of therapy, rather than CT as used in our trial, in order to assess response to guide treatment duration in patients with HIV-associated lymphoma.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec1">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
                <label>Disclosures and Contributions</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
                    <media xlink:href="2019_243386-Disclosures_Contributions.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d39e633" position="anchor"/>
                  </p>
                </caption>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>This study was coordinated by the AIDS Malignancy Consortium (Ronald Mitsuyasu, MD, Chair).</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes da Silva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitolo</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL): ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>Suppl 5</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelenetz</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Advani</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: non-Hodgkin's lymphomas</article-title>. <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>288</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasterlid</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Biccler</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Six cycles of R-CHOP-21 are not inferior to eight cycles for treatment of diffuse large Bcell lymphoma: a Nordic Lymphoma Group population-based study</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>29</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1882</fpage>-<lpage>1883</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poeschel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziepert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Excellent outcome of young patients (18-60 years) with favourable-prognosis diffuse large B-cell lymphoma treated with 4 cycles CHOP plus 6 applications of rituximab: results of the 592 patients of the FLYER trial of the DSHNHL/GLA</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>132</volume> (<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazeer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase 2 trial of infusional cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide in patients with poor-prognosis, intermediate-grade non- Hodgkin lymphoma: an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group trial (E3493)</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1634</fpage>-<lpage>1640</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiernik</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Leaf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutcher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Infusional cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide in relapsed and resistant non- Hodgkin's lymphoma: evidence for a schedule- dependent effect favoring infusional administration of chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1071</fpage>-<lpage>1079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8501493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EPOCH chemotherapy: toxicity and efficacy in relapsed and refractory non-Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1573</fpage>-<lpage>1582</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7687667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossbard</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittaluga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dose-adjusted EPOCH chemotherapy for untreated large B-cell lymphomas: a pharmacodynamic approach with high efficacy</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2685</fpage>-<lpage>2693</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittaluga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Highly effective treatment of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related lymphoma with dose-adjusted EPOCH: impact of antiretroviral therapy suspension and tumor biology</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>4653</fpage>-<lpage>4659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609827</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiernik</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pilot trial of infusional cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide plus didanosine and filgrastim in patients with human immunodeficiency virus-associated non-Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3026</fpage>-<lpage>3035</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8918501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase II trial of infusional cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide in patients with HIVassociated non-Hodgkin's lymphoma: an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group trial (E1494)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1491</fpage>-<lpage>1500</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rituximab plus infusional cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide in HIV-associated non-Hodgkin lymphoma: pooled results from 3 phase 2 trials</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1891</fpage>-<lpage>1897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15550484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>HIV-associated lymphoma: the evidence for treating aggressively but with caution</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Oncol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17762571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rituximab plus concurrent infusional EPOCH chemotherapy is highly effective in HIV-associated B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>3008</fpage>-<lpage>3016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20023215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambinder</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rituximab does not improve clinical outcome in a randomized phase 3 trial of CHOP with or without rituximab in patients with HIV-associated non-Hodgkin lymphoma: AIDS-Malignancies Consortium Trial 010</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1538</fpage>-<lpage>1543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Horning</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coiffier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Report of an international workshop to standardize response criteria for non-Hodgkin's lymphomas. NCI Sponsored International Working Group</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <year>1244</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mounier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Central nervous system involvement in AIDS-related lymphomas</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>857</fpage>-<lpage>866</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27062389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngongondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Umbleja</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early progression and immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome during treatment of mild-to-moderate Kaposi sarcoma in low-resource settings: incidence, longterm outcomes and effects of early chemotherapy</article-title>. <publisher-name>17th International Conference on HIV AIDS</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD, USA</publisher-loc>. October 21-22, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunleavy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittaluga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shovlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Low-intensity therapy in adults with Burkitt's lymphoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>369</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>1915</fpage>-<lpage>1925</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24224624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunleavy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Noy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk-adapted therapy in adults with Burkitt lymphoma: preliminary report of a multicenter prospective phase II study of DAEPOCH- R</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment factors affecting outcomes in HIV- associated non-Hodgkin lymphomas: a pooled analysis of 1546 patients</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>122</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>3251</fpage>-<lpage>3262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24014242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chadburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunophenotypic analysis of AIDS- related diffuse large B-cell lymphoma and clinical implications in patients from AIDS Malignancies Consortium clinical trials 010 and 034</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>5039</fpage>-<lpage>5048</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19752343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunleavy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittaluga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of tumor histogenesis, FDG-PET, and short-course EPOCH with dose-dense rituximab (SC-EPOCH-RR) in HIV-associated diffuse large B-cell lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>3017</fpage>-<lpage>3024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetics and pathogenesis of diffuse large Bcell lymphoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>378</volume>(<issue>15</issue>): <fpage>1396</fpage>-<lpage>1407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29641966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikhaeel</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Timothy</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Doherty</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maisey</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>18-FDG-PET as a prognostic indicator in the treatment of aggressive non-Hodgkin's lymphoma -comparison with CT</article-title>. <source>Leuk Lymphoma</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5-6</issue>):<fpage>543</fpage>-<lpage>553</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11342337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroobants</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early restaging positron emission tomography with (18)F-fluorodeoxyglucose predicts outcome in patients with aggressive non- Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1356</fpage>-<lpage>1363</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haioun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Itti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>[18F]fluoro- 2-deoxy-D-glucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) in aggressive lymphoma: an early prognostic tool for predicting patient outcome</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1376</fpage>-<lpage>1381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15860666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Itti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Response assessment after an inductive CHOP or CHOP-like regimen with or without rituximab in 103 patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: integrating 18fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography to the International Workshop Criteria</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>-<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective international cohort study demonstrates inability of interim PET to predict treatment failure in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1936</fpage>-<lpage>1944</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dabaja</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderplas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosby-Thompson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Radiation for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma in the rituximab era: analysis of the National Comprehensive Cancer Network lymphoma outcomes project</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1032</fpage>-<lpage>1039</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25492236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mamot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingbiel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Final results of a prospective evaluation of the predictive value of interim positron emission tomography in patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma treated with RCHOP- 14 (SAKK 38/07)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2523</fpage>-<lpage>2529</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swinnen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Responseadapted therapy for aggressive non- Hodgkin's lymphomas based on early [18F] FDG-PET scanning: ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group study (E3404)</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>170</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25823885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duhrsen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertenstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Positron Emission Tomography-Guided Therapy of Aggressive Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas (PETAL): a multicenter, randomized phase III trial</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2024</fpage>-<lpage>2034</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29750632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casasnovas</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ysebaert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thieblemont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>FDG-PET-driven consolidation strategy in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: final results of a randomized phase 2 study</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1315</fpage>-<lpage>1326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28701367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlanga</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differentiation of HIV-associated lymphoma from HIV-associated reactive adenopathy using quantitative FDG PET and symmetry</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Mol Imaging</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>596</fpage>-<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
