<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T01:46:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10660907" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10660907</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-11-19</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmjo</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjopen</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10660907</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10660907</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10660907</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37984940</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37984940</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2023-078713</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078713</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Anaesthesia</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>1506</subject>
                  <subject>1682</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <series-title>Protocol</series-title>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Angiotensin II in liver transplantation (AngLT-1): protocol of a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-109923189" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1387-9547</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bokoch</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302777" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tran</surname>
                    <given-names>Amy T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302778" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brinson</surname>
                    <given-names>Erika L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302779" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Marcus</surname>
                    <given-names>Sivan G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302780" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Reddy</surname>
                    <given-names>Meghana</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302781" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sun</surname>
                    <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302782" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Roll</surname>
                    <given-names>Garrett R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302783" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pardo</surname>
                    <given-names>Manuel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302784" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fields</surname>
                    <given-names>Scott</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302785" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Adelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>Dieter</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-110302786" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kothari</surname>
                    <given-names>Rishi P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-100548066" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Legrand</surname>
                    <given-names>Matthieu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Anesthesia and Perioperative Care</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_8785">University of California San Francisco</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Division of Transplant Surgery</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_8785">University of California San Francisco</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Investigational Drug Pharmacy</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_8785">University of California San Francisco</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_6559">Thomas Jefferson University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Philadelphia</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Pennsylvania</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Michael P Bokoch; <email>Michael.Bokoch@ucsf.edu</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>13</volume>
              <issue>11</issue>
              <elocation-id>e078713</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <ali:free_to_read/>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-11-19">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713.pdf"/>
              <self-uri content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713.reviewer_comments.pdf"/>
              <self-uri content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713.draft_revisions.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>Catecholamine vasopressors such as norepinephrine are the standard drugs used to maintain mean arterial pressure during liver transplantation. At high doses, catecholamines may impair organ perfusion. Angiotensin II is a peptide vasoconstrictor that may improve renal perfusion pressure and glomerular filtration rate, a haemodynamic profile that could reduce acute kidney injury. Angiotensin II is approved for vasodilatory shock but has not been rigorously evaluated for treatment of hypotension during liver transplantation. The objective is to assess the efficacy of angiotensin II as a second-line vasopressor infusion during liver transplantation. This trial will establish the efficacy of angiotensin II in decreasing the dose of norepinephrine to maintain adequate blood pressure. Completion of this study will allow design of a follow-up, multicentre trial powered to detect a reduction of organ injury in liver transplantation.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods and analysis</title>
                  <p>This is a double-blind, randomised clinical trial. Eligible subjects are adults with a Model for End-Stage Liver Disease Sodium Score ≥25 undergoing deceased donor liver transplantation. Subjects are randomised 1:1 to receive angiotensin II or saline placebo as the second-line vasopressor infusion. The study drug infusion is initiated on reaching a norepinephrine dose of 0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> and titrated per protocol. The primary outcome is the dose of norepinephrine required to maintain a mean arterial pressure ≥65 mm Hg. Secondary outcomes include vasopressin or epinephrine requirement and duration of hypotension. Safety outcomes include incidence of thromboembolism within 48 hours of the end of surgery and severe hypertension. An intention-to-treat analysis will be performed for all randomised subjects receiving the study drug. The total dose of norepinephrine will be compared between the two arms by a one-tailed Mann-Whitney U test.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
                  <p>The trial protocol was approved by the local Institutional Review Board (#20–30948). Results will be posted on ClinicalTrials.gov and published in a peer-reviewed journal.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration number</title>
                  <p>
                    <ext-link xlink:href="ClinicalTrials.govNCT04901169" ext-link-type="uri">ClinicalTrials.govNCT04901169</ext-link>
                  </p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Angiotensin II</kwd>
                <kwd>Liver Transplantation</kwd>
                <kwd>Vasoconstrictor agents</kwd>
                <kwd>End Stage Liver Disease</kwd>
                <kwd>Liver Cirrhosis</kwd>
                <kwd>Blood Pressure</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group id="funding-1">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>University of California, San Francisco Liver Center</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>NIH P30 DK026743</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>special-feature</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>unlocked</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float">
              <caption>
                <title>Strengths and limitations of this study</title>
              </caption>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Double-blind, randomised controlled trial design.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Precise titration protocol.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Exclusion criteria designed to maximise safety and minimise risk of adverse drug effects.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Results may not be generalisable to patients undergoing liver transplantation with Model for End-Stage Liver Disease Sodium Score &lt;25 or those with acute liver failure.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Results may not be generalisable to patients undergoing living-donor liver transplantation or simultaneous liver and kidney transplantation.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </boxed-text>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Vasoplegia is low systemic vascular resistance with normal or high cardiac output despite the use of high doses of vasopressors.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1 2</xref> This syndrome frequently arises during liver transplantation (LT), particularly in patients with high Model for End-Stage Liver Disease Sodium (MELD-Na) scores and those requiring preoperative renal replacement therapy (RRT).<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> High doses of the catecholamines norepinephrine (NE) and epinephrine are typically infused to maintain adequate mean arterial pressure (MAP) and organ perfusion.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 5</xref> However, extreme doses of catecholamines may impair microvascular perfusion to the kidneys and other organs<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6 7</xref> or trigger arrhythmias.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Rescue therapies for vasoplegia are limited to the off-label use of methylene blue or hydroxocobalamin.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> New haemodynamic therapies are needed to reduce the high rate of acute kidney injury (AKI) after liver transplant, seen in 50%–80% of cases. Acute kidney injury after LT significantly reduces patient and graft survival.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref> Reducing catecholamine dose by adding a vasopressor with a different mechanism may help improve renal perfusion pressure and reduce postoperative AKI after LT.</p>
              <p>The peptide vasopressor angiotensin II (AngII) was approved by the US Food and Drug Administration in 2017 for use in vasodilatory shock. Angiotensin II causes vasoconstriction by activating the angiotensin II type 1 G protein-coupled receptor in arterial smooth muscle, which is distinct from the catecholamine receptors. Angiotensin II selectively constricts efferent arterioles in the kidney to maintain or improve glomerular filtration rate.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> In ATHOS-3, a large, multicentre, international, randomised clinical trial (RCT) of patients with vasodilatory shock (mostly due to sepsis), AngII infusion increased the blood pressure of patients already receiving doses of NE greater than 0.2 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Posthoc analyses of the ATHOS-3 trial found improved 28-day survival, greater blood pressure response and earlier liberation from RRT in patients receiving AngII who required RRT at the time of drug initiation<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> or who had serum renin levels above the median.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> These results suggest that AngII may reduce the required dose of traditional vasopressors and improve microcirculatory flow to organs, especially the kidneys.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Successful use of AngII infusion for vasoplegia during LT has been reported.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> However, no RCTs of AngII have been completed in this setting.</p>
              <p>Angiotensin II therapy is of particular interest for patients undergoing LT not only due to the frequency of vasoplegia observed during LT but also because of the mechanism of action of AngII. The renin-angiotensin system is known to be altered in cirrhosis and contributes to the pathophysiology of end-stage liver disease. The renin-angiotensin system contributes to progression of hepatic fibrosis, portal hypertension and derangements in sodium and volume regulation.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17 18</xref> Elevated plasma renin is observed after cardiopulmonary bypass and provides specific rationale for administering AngII in cardiac surgery.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref> A similar rationale may hold for LT. We report the protocol for a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of AngII as the second-line vasopressor during LT in patients with MELD-Na Score ≥25.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2">
              <title>Objectives</title>
              <p>The primary objective of the AngLT-1 Trial is to assess the efficacy and safety of AngII infusion during LT. Efficacy is assessed by the intraoperative dose of NE required to maintain a MAP ≥65 mm Hg. Safety is assessed by predefined adverse events. The secondary objective is to measure secondary outcomes such as the incidence of AKI and liver graft dysfunction. These data will allow for the design and initiation of a subsequent multicentre RCT powered to detect improvement in postoperative outcomes.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s3">
              <title>Methods and analysis</title>
              <sec id="s3-1">
                <title>Eligibility criteria</title>
                <p>Inclusion criteria are shown in <xref rid="B1" ref-type="boxed-text">box 1</xref>. Eligible subjects are adults (aged ≥18 years) undergoing LT from a deceased donor with a calculated MELD-Na Score ≥25 at the time of transplant (MELD 3.0 was released after this trial was initiated and therefore eligibility is determined by MELD-Na). Subjects also require NE infusion at a dose &gt;0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> during LT before study drug is initiated. At the University of California, San Francisco, over 80% of patients meeting the inclusion criteria receive norepinephrine infusions above the threshold of 0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> during LT. The exclusion criteria are intended to minimise variability in procedural complexity, expected surgery length and intraoperative vasopressor requirements (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="boxed-text">box 1</xref>). Patients with cardiac conditions that could theoretically be harmed by intense vasoconstriction from AngII are excluded. Finally, because the US Food and Drug Administration label for AngII includes a warning about increased risk of venous and arterial thromboembolism, patients with a history of thrombosis, inherited hypercoagulable disorder or conditions increasing the risk of hepatic artery thrombosis (eg, coeliac stenosis) are excluded.</p>
                <boxed-text id="B1" position="float">
                  <label>Box 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Eligibility criteria.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Inclusion criteria</bold>
                  </p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Age ≥18 years</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Undergoing LT from a deceased donor</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Calculated MELD-Na Score ≥25 at the time of transplant</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Require norepinephrine infusion at a dose &gt;0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> during LT before study drug is initiated</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Exclusion criteria</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Type of liver transplantation</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Living-donor liver transplantation</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Donation after cardiac death without normothermic machine perfusion</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Acute liver failure</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Listed for or receiving simultaneous liver-kidney transplantation</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Liver re-transplantation</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Split liver transplantation (isolated right or left lobe)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Cardiac conditions</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Portopulmonary hypertension (defined as mean pulmonary artery pressure &gt;20 mm Hg, pulmonary vascular resistance ≥3 Woods Units, and pulmonary artery wedge pressure ≤15 mm Hg in the setting of portal hypertension without another known cause).</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Left ventricular systolic dysfunction (defined as ejection fraction &lt;45%)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Thromboembolic risk</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>History of thrombotic or embolic disease, inherited hypercoagulability disorder or therapeutic anticoagulation</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Portal vein thrombosis</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Coeliac stenosis</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>History of Raynaud’s disease</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Other</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Preoperative treatment with an angiotensin II receptor blocker or angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor (within 48 hours before LT)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Active bronchospasm at the time of LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>End-stage renal disease (chronic estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt;15 mL min<sup>-1</sup> 1.73 m<sup>-2</sup> or chronic renal replacement therapy)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Known history of allergy to synthetic human angiotensin II</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Subject intubated and/or mechanically ventilated prior to entering the operating room for LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>LT, liver transplantation; MELD-Na, Model for End-Stage Liver Disease Sodium.</p>
                </boxed-text>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-2">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p>Except for the study drug and vasopressor management protocol, perioperative care is provided in accordance with local protocols. Invasive monitoring of radial artery and central venous pressures is performed. Pulmonary artery catheters are not routinely used at our centre. Non-invasive cardiac output monitoring (LiDCO, Masimo, Irvine, CA, USA) is used when available. Norepinephrine is initiated as the first-line vasopressor for all subjects. Once the NE infusion dose exceeds 0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>, the study drug infusion is initiated at a rate equivalent to 5 ng kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> of AngII. The study drug is delivered through a dedicated port of a central venous catheter that is routinely placed as part of standard anaesthesia care. The study drug infusion is connected in a y-configuration to a 0.9% saline carrier running at 50 mL h<sup>-1</sup> throughout surgery to ensure rapid delivery of any dose changes.</p>
                <p>The study drug infusion is titrated no more frequently than every 10 min between 1.25 ng kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> and 40 ng kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup> according to the protocol (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). In between study drug titrations, the anaesthesiologist continuously titrates NE as frequently as needed to maintain a MAP ≥65 mm Hg. If the MAP is persistently &gt;80 mm Hg, the anaesthesiologist will downtitrate NE first and then downtitrate the study drug. If at any time the subject’s blood pressure rises to an unsafe level (systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;100 mmHg), the anaesthesiologist immediately stops the study drug infusion and resumes at a lower rate when safe.</p>
                <fig position="float" id="F1">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Study drug initiation and titration protocol. NE, norepinephrine; MAP, mean arterial pressure; NE, norepinephrine; AngII, angiotensin II; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713f01" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <p>The titration protocol guides the anaesthesiologist to use only NE and study drug infusions until the NE infusion dose reaches 0.3 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>. Once the NE dose exceeds this threshold, the anaesthesiologist may initiate a third-line vasopressor infusion (typically vasopressin). The relatively high threshold of NE recommended before adding a third-line vasopressor was chosen to maximise the observable effect of the study drug on the primary outcome. If the third-line drug is not effective in maintaining a MAP ≥65 mm Hg, a fourth-line vasopressor infusion may also be initiated (typically epinephrine). If at any time the anaesthesiologist decides an additional vasopressor or inotrope is clinically required, for example in the case of bradycardia or myocardial dysfunction, the protocol can be overridden and the third- or fourth-line drug initiated even if the NE infusion dose is &lt;0.3 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>. Usage of third- and fourth-line vasopressors and the reason for initiation are recorded on the case report form. The anaesthesiologist may use their discretion to make other deviations to the vasopressor management protocol in the best interest of clinical care.</p>
                <p>The study drug is discontinued before the end of the procedure. When the surgeon begins to close the abdomen at the end of LT, the anaesthesiologist begins to decrease the study drug dose rapidly until it is discontinued. If necessary, the NE infusion dose is increased as needed to maintain a MAP ≥65 mm Hg. In this trial, the study drug infusion is not continued in the intensive care unit after LT.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-3">
                <title>Primary endpoint and sample size calculation</title>
                <p>The primary endpoint is the total dose of NE, averaged over case duration and total body weight, used during LT to maintain a MAP ≥65 mm Hg (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="boxed-text">box 2</xref>). Preliminary data from our centre indicate that patients undergoing LT with MELD-Na Score ≥25 have higher vasopressor requirements (median NE equivalent dosage 0.11, Q1-Q3 0.05–0.18 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>) during LT than those with scores &lt;25 (median 0.05, Q1-Q3 0.02–0.10 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>). To attain 80% power to detect a 50% reduction in NE dose by AngII infusion as compared with placebo at α=0.05 (one-tailed), an estimated sample size of 44 total subjects (22 in each treatment arm) is required. The target enrolment is 50 subjects to account for drop-out.</p>
                <boxed-text id="B2" position="float">
                  <label>Box 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Primary and secondary endpoints.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Primary Endpoint</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Total dose of norepinephrine (NE), averaged over case duration and total body weight, used during LT to maintain a MAP ≥65 mm Hg.</p>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Secondary Endpoints</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Third- and fourth-line vasopressors</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vasopressin</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Proportion of subjects requiring vasopressin infusion during LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Dose of vasopressin (units or NE equivalents) administered during LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration of vasopressin infusion (minutes)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Epinephrine</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Proportion of subjects requiring epinephrine infusion during LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Dose of epinephrine (µg or NE equivalents) administered during LT, excluding boluses within the 5 minutes immediately following portal reperfusion</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration of epinephrine infusion (minutes)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Haemodynamics and biomarkers</bold>
                  </p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration (minutes) with MAP &lt;65 mm Hg</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Change in direct renin (pg mL<sup>-1</sup>), from the start of surgery until 2 hours after portal reperfusion</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Clinical outcomes</bold>
                  </p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Incidence of severe (stage 2 or 3) acute kidney injury within 48 hours after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Major adverse kidney events at 30 days after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Incidence of early allograft dysfunction</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Model for early allograft function score</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration of renal replacement therapy after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration of intensive care unit stay after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Duration of hospital stay after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Subject and graft survival at 30 days after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Subject and graft survival at 1 year after LT</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                  <p>NE, norepinephrine; LT, liver transplantation; MAP, mean arterial pressure.</p>
                </boxed-text>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-4">
                <title>Outcomes and statistical analysis</title>
                <p>For the primary endpoint, all eligible subjects who are randomised and receive the study drug are included in the intention-to-treat analysis. Subjects that complete the study without protocol violation are included in the per-protocol analysis.</p>
                <p>Doses of NE administered by bolus or infusion are summed and the total NE dose is divided by total body weight and case duration, expressed as µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>. The case duration is defined as the start of surgery (skin incision) until the end of surgery (abdominal closure) and does not include time for anaesthesia induction, line placement or patient transport. Norepinephrine dose in each arm is summarised as median and IQR. The total dose of NE is compared between the two arms by a Mann-Whitney U test and significance declared if p&lt;0.05 (one-tailed). A one-tailed test is justified given that assignment to AngII (a vasopressor drug) cannot plausibly increase the required NE dose.</p>
                <p>The secondary endpoints for the trial are summarised in <xref rid="B2" ref-type="boxed-text">box 2</xref>.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22–26</xref> Vasopressors are reported as raw doses or norepinephrine equivalent dosage.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Categorical variables are summarised by frequency and percentage and continuous variables as median and IQR by arm. Categorical variables are compared between the two arms by either chi-square or Fisher’s exact test as appropriate. Continuous variables are compared between the two arms by two-sample t-tests or Mann-Whitney U tests if the normality assumption does not hold. Time-to-event data is described by the Kaplan-Meier method and compared between the arms by log-rank tests. All statistical analyses are performed in Stata, GraphPad Prism and R software.</p>
                <p>Adverse events within 28 days of LT are tabulated by treatment group and include the number of subjects that experienced the event, the rate of occurrence, severity and relationship to study drug (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="boxed-text">box 3</xref>). Serious adverse events are reviewed by an independent Data and Safety Monitoring Board that may make recommendations to adjust the trial protocol. Predefined safety outcomes are also collected for descriptive purposes (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="boxed-text">box 3</xref>). Given the incidence of early thromboembolism after LT is less than 10%,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> this trial lacks the power to detect a true difference in this complication and data will be purely descriptive.</p>
                <boxed-text id="B3" position="float">
                  <label>Box 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Safety assessments and predefined adverse events.</title>
                  </caption>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Safety assessments</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Methylene blue or hydroxocobalamin administered during LT for vasoplegia</p>
                  <p>Vasopressor infusion required at the time of leaving the operating room (after study drug discontinuation)</p>
                  <p>Name and dose (in native units and norepinephrine equivalents) of vasopressor required at the time of leaving the operating room (after study drug discontinuation)</p>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Adverse events during administration of study drug</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Severe hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mm Hg for &gt;5 min)</p>
                  <p>Cardiac arrhythmias, requiring treatment (excludes bradycardia typically seen with portal vein reperfusion)</p>
                  <p>Bronchospasm, requiring treatment</p>
                  <p>Congestive heart failure, cardiogenic shock or cardiogenic pulmonary oedema</p>
                  <p>
                    <bold>Adverse events within 48 hours of the end of liver transplantation</bold>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thromboembolism (venous or arterial)</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Includes venous thromboembolism, portal vein thrombosis, inferior vena cava thrombosis, catheter-associated thrombosis or superficial thrombophlebitis</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Includes myocardial infarction, ischaemic stroke, transient ischaemic attack, peripheral arterial thrombosis or hepatic artery thrombosis</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Excludes disseminated intravascular coagulation because features of this condition (thrombocytopenia, low fibrinogen and elevated prothrombin time) are highly prevalent during and after LT (liver transplantation)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </boxed-text>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-5">
                <title>Recruitment and consent</title>
                <p>The schedule of study procedures is shown in the SPIRIT figure (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>). Subjects are recruited from a high-volume liver transplant centre (average of 160 deceased donor transplants annually, 2021–2023). Enrolment began in May 2021 and is ongoing. Written consent (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental file 1</xref>) is obtained by a physician along with trained study personnel. The information is presented orally and in written form in the subject’s primary language. Consent forms are available in English, Spanish and Chinese. If the subject lacks capacity to provide consent, written consent is obtained from a legally authorised representative. When possible, subjects consented through a legally authorised representative are re-consented for use of data and specimens for research after regaining capacity.</p>
                <supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078713.supp1</object-id>
                  <label>Supplementary data</label>
                  <p>
                    <inline-supplementary-material id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
                  </p>
                </supplementary-material>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Study schedule of enrolment, interventions and assessments. AngII, angiotensin II; NE, norepinephrine.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713f02" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-6">
                <title>Randomisation and blinding</title>
                <p>At the time of entry into the operating room for LT, subjects are randomised to the experimental treatment (AngII infusion) or placebo (0.9% saline infusion) in a 1:1 ratio using a stratified block randomisation scheme with block size of four. The randomisation is stratified according to the presence or absence of preoperative RRT immediately prior to LT and the use of normothermic machine perfusion of the liver graft. The randomisation scheme is maintained by Randomize.net and accessed through a secure web portal.</p>
                <p>After randomisation, the group assignment is visible only to the research pharmacist. Investigators, research staff, subjects and clinicians (anaesthesiologists, surgeons and nurses) are blinded to the study drug assignment. Infusion bags are prepared by pharmacy staff with identical packaging and labelling for either AngII or saline placebo. The bags are then transported directly to the anaesthesia team in the operating room for administration. Drug infusion pumps are identically programmed as angiotensin II, 2.5 mg in 500 mL (5000 ng mL<sup>-1</sup>), using the subject’s total body weight, units of ng kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>, regardless of the actual study drug assignment.</p>
                <p>During clinical care, anaesthesiologists may sometimes be able to identify the study drug based on the subject’s blood pressure response to the infusion. To quantify inadvertent unblinding, the attending anaesthesiologist is asked to record their best guess of the study drug identity (AngII or saline placebo) on the case report form at the end of each case.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-7">
                <title>Data collection</title>
                <p>Preoperative variables including subject demographics, medical history, medications, laboratory values and vital signs are extracted from the electronic medical record (EMR) and recorded in a secure REDCap database. Intraoperative variables including operative and ischaemia times, caval clamping technique, fluid totals, transfusions, arterial blood gases and laboratory values (haemograms and coagulation tests) are also recorded. Haemodynamics are automatically recorded every 1 min in the EMR. Drug doses, infusion titrations and fluid administrations are recorded in real time by the anaesthesiologist. Paper source documents identified by the study identification code are maintained to record all observations and other pertinent data for each subject. No protected health information is recorded on the source documents.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-8">
                <title>Biospecimen collection</title>
                <p>Research involving human specimens is carried out in accordance with all relevant guidelines and regulations. Blood is collected from the subject’s arterial line and urine from the bladder catheter at two timepoints, baseline (surgical incision) and 2 hours after portal vein reperfusion. Study personnel prepare ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid plasma and serum samples by centrifugation. Samples are frozen for biomarker analysis. Direct renin concentration is measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (DRG, International, Inc., Springfield, NJ, USA).<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The change in direct renin between time points is calculated as a biomarker of the neurohormonal response to study drug.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-9">
                <title>Withdrawals and protocol deviations</title>
                <p>Subjects who wish to withdraw from the trial have their data excluded from analysis. While rare, if the threshold dose of NE required for study drug initiation (0.05 µg kg<sup>-1</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>) is not met during LT, the subject is withdrawn before entering the trial and is not included in the intention-to-treat analysis. Protocol deviations such as early discontinuation of the study drug or failure to follow the titration protocol are recorded. Subjects experiencing a protocol deviation are included in the intention-to-treat analysis but excluded from the per-protocol analysis. Adverse events are documented and followed until resolution.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-10">
                <title>Patient and public involvement</title>
                <p>A community member was part of the Institutional Review Board committee that reviewed and approved the study protocol. Otherwise, there is no patient or public involvement.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
              <sec id="s4-1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p>The study protocol was approved by the University of California, San Francisco Institutional Review Board (#20–30948). A waiver of Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act authorisation was granted for purposes of screening and recruitment. Written informed consent is obtained from all subjects as described under <italic toggle="yes">Recruitment and Consent</italic>. The consent form includes specific permission for use of human specimens (blood and urine) for research.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4-2">
                <title>Experiments involving human specimens</title>
                <p>Biomarker measurements on human blood and urine specimens are conducted in accordance with all relevant guidelines and regulations. These experiments were approved by the University of California, San Francisco Institutional Review Board and the Institutional Biosafety Committee (#BU175175).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s4-3">
                <title>Dissemination plans</title>
                <p>This protocol was presented in oral format at the Society for the Advancement of Transplant Anesthesia spring 2023 meeting and in poster format at the International Anesthesia Research Society 2023 meeting. On completion of enrolment and data analysis, the results will be submitted for written publication to a peer-reviewed journal focused on anaesthesiology or transplantation research.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e226">
                <caption>
                  <title>Reviewer comments</title>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713.reviewer_comments.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e227">
                <caption>
                  <title>Author's
manuscript</title>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-078713.draft_revisions.pdf"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>The authors acknowledge mentorship and guidance from Dr Claus Niemann in designing the trial, and valuable feedback on the manuscript from Liam St. Hilaire.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> MB obtained funding for the trial and oversees the project. MB, ELB, DA, RK and ML designed the trial. MB and ATT wrote the manuscript. MR helped revise the manuscript. SGM assists with data collection. ATT, MR and ES assist with patient consent and data collection and entry. GRR provided surgical advice and helped develop exclusion criteria. MP helped design the titration protocol. SF oversees research pharmacy procedures.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by the University of California, San Francisco Liver Center grant number NIH P30 DK026743.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> MB discloses that support was provided by La Jolla Pharmaceutical Company (now Innoviva, Waltham, MA, USA) for this trial as part of an investigator-initiated research proposal. This support consisted of study drug (AngII) at no cost for trial patients only, and $14 231 USD (direct plus indirect costs) to support an assistant research coordinator. La Jolla Pharmaceutical Company reviewed the protocol before trial initiation but suggested no changes. The authors have sole responsibility (independent of La Jolla Pharmaceutical/Innoviva) for conduct of the trial, analysis and interpretation of data, assignment of adverse events and dissemination of results. ML has received consulting fees from La Jolla Pharmaceutical Company, Alexion Pharmaceuticals and SphingoTec GmbH. All other authors have no competing interests to disclose.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to the Methods and analysis section for further details.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec sec-type="ethics-statement">
              <title>Ethics statements</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Patient consent for publication</title>
                <p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">No individual data is reported.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shaefi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mittel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Vasoplegia after cardiovascular procedures-pathophysiology and targeted therapy</article-title>. <source>J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jvca.2017.10.032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29223724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abuelkasem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sankova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Reversal of vasodilatory shock</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000004343</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boettcher</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woehlck</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Makker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Hydroxocobalamin for treatment of catecholamine-resistant vasoplegia during liver transplantation: a single-center series of 20 cases</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg Case Rep</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>107488</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2022.107488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35981485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Adelmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronish</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Anesthesia for liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiol Clin</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anclin.2017.04.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28784222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bezinover</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Hemodynamic instability during liver transplantation in patients with end-stage liver disease: a consensus document from ILTS, LICAGE, and SATA</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>2184</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000003642</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33534523</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tumlin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes in patients with vasodilatory shock and renal replacement therapy treated with intravenous angiotensin II</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000003092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29509568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive management of blood pressure in patients with septic AKI</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>1018</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12031018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36769666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhazzani</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Association of vasopressin plus catecholamine vasopressors vs catecholamines alone with atrial fibrillation in patients with distributive shock: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>319</volume>:<fpage>1889</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.4528</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29801010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>An</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freundlich</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Case report of high-dose hydroxocobalamin in the treatment of vasoplegic syndrome during liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Transplant</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1552</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajt.14736</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29573551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Karapanagiotou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimitriadis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of RIFLE and AKIN criteria in the evaluation of the frequency of acute kidney injury in post-liver transplantation patients</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>3222</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transproceed.2014.09.161</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25420865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hilmi</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Damian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Khafaji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Acute kidney injury following orthotopic liver transplantation: incidence, risk factors, and effects on patient and graft outcomes</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aeu556</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25673576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The association between vena cava implantation technique and acute kidney injury after liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>e308</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000003331</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32467477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin II for the treatment of vasodilatory shock</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>377</volume>:<elocation-id>2604</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1714511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29281568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Renin and survival in patients given angiotensin II for catecholamine-resistant vasodilatory shock. A clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>202</volume>:<fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201911-2172OC</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32609011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lankadeva</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Urinary oxygenation as a surrogate measure of medullary oxygenation during angiotensin II therapy in septic acute kidney injury</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>e41</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000002797</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29077618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Running</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trudo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Intraoperative use of angiotensin II for severe vasodilatory shock during liver transplantation: a case report</article-title>. <source>A&amp;A Practice</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<elocation-id>e01402</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/XAA.0000000000001402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33577171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Role of the renin-angiotensin system in hepatic fibrosis and portal hypertension</article-title>. <source>Korean J Intern Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3904/kjim.2017.317</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29462546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schierwagen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Activation of the alternate renin-angiotensin system correlates with the clinical status in human cirrhosis and corrects post liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>419</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm8040419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30934723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Küllmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saadat-Gilani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Kinetic changes of plasma renin concentrations predict acute kidney injury in cardiac surgery patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>203</volume>:<fpage>1119</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202005-2050OC</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33320784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Yin and Yang of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system in acute kidney injury</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>203</volume>:<fpage>1053</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202012-4419ED</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33357099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serpa Neto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A double-blind randomised feasibility trial of angiotensin-2 in cardiac surgery</article-title>. <source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1009</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.15802</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35915923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kellum</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lameire</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aspelin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Kidney disease: improving global outcomes (KDIGO) acute kidney injury work group. KDIGO clinical practice guideline for acute kidney injury</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int Suppl</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/kisup.2012.1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Angeli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gines</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of acute kidney injury in patients with cirrhosis: revised consensus recommendations of the International club of Ascites</article-title>. <source>Gut</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2014-308874</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25631669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kellum</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarbock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nadim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>What endpoints should be used for clinical studies in acute kidney injury?</article-title><source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-017-4732-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28255614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Olthoff</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kulik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of a current definition of early allograft dysfunction in liver transplant recipients and analysis of risk factors</article-title>. <source>Liver Transpl</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lt.22091</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20677285</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pareja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hervás</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A score model for the continuous grading of early allograft dysfunction severity</article-title>. <source>Liver Transpl</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lt.23990</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25204890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nguyen-Buckley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agopian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Major thromboembolic complications in liver transplantation: the role of rotational thromboelastometry and cryoprecipitate transfusion</article-title>. <source>Transplantation</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1771</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000003427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32852404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
