<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T02:49:08Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5685932" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5685932</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-01-05</datestamp>
        <setSpec>abm</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Behav Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Behav Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abm</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Annals of Behavioral Medicine: A Publication of the Society of Behavioral Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0883-6612</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1532-4796</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5685932</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5685932</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5685932</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28508330</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28508330</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12160-017-9917-x</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">s12160-017-9917-x</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Mediators of Weight Loss Maintenance in the Keep It Off Trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Crain</surname>
                    <given-names>A L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <!--lauren.a.crain@healthpartners.com-->
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sherwood</surname>
                    <given-names>N E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Martinson</surname>
                    <given-names>B C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jeffery</surname>
                    <given-names>R W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>HealthPartners Institute, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Minneapolis Veterans Affairs, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">A.L. Crain<email>lauren.a.crain@healthpartners.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date iso-8601-date="2017-12-12" pub-type="epub">
                <day>12</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2017</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>12</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2017</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>52</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>9</fpage>
              <lpage>18</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Society of Behavioral Medicine 2017</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="abm_52_1_9.pdf"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <p>Weight loss maintenance intervention participants were more likely to weigh themselves daily and regained less weight over 2 years than non-participants</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="s1">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>An important step toward enhancing the efficacy of weight loss maintenance interventions is identifying the pathways through which successful interventions such as the Keep It Off trial have worked.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2">
                  <title>Purpose</title>
                  <p>This study aimed to assess the viability of mediated relationships between the Keep It Off Guided intervention, conceptually and empirically grounded potential mediators, and weight. Repeated measurement of mediators and weight enabled documentation of the temporal ordering of intervention delivery and changes in mediators and in weight among participants randomized to the Guided intervention or Self-Directed comparison group.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Total, direct, and indirect effects of the Guided intervention on weight change were calculated and tested for significance. Indirect effects were comprised of the influence of the intervention on three change scores for each mediator and the relationship between mediator changes and weight changes 6 months later.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s4">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Guided intervention participants regained about 2% less weight over 24 months than Self-Directed participants. Starting daily self-weighing accounted for the largest share of this difference, followed by not stopping self-weighing.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Daily self-weighing mediated 24-month weight loss maintenance.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s6">
                  <title>Trial Registration Number</title>
                  <p>The trial is registered with<ext-link xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov" ext-link-type="uri">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> (Identifier: NCT00702455<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00702455" ext-link-type="uri">www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00702455</ext-link>).</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Weight loss maintenance</kwd>
                <kwd>Behavioral</kwd>
                <kwd>intervention</kwd>
                <kwd>Maintenance</kwd>
                <kwd>Physical activity</kwd>
                <kwd>Self-monitoring</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>National Cancer Institute</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000054</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                    <!-- oupReleaseDelayRemoved from OA Article (12|0) -->
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>R01CA128211</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>NIH</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                    <!-- oupReleaseDelayRemoved from OA Article (12|0) -->
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Department of Health and Human Services</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000016</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                    <!-- oupReleaseDelayRemoved from OA Article (12|0) -->
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="10"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s7">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Long-term weight loss maintenance remains a challenge for obesity treatment [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Strategies to improve outcomes have included increasing treatment duration [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref>] and incorporating lessons learned (e.g., high physical activity levels) from the National Weight Control Registry [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Additionally, recent studies have focused on the optimal ways to engage people during the weight loss maintenance phase [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], including the development and evaluation of behavioral interventions exclusively for the maintenance phase [9–11].</p>
              <p>Three randomized controlled trials evaluating maintenance-specific interventions showed a similar pattern of results. The Weight Loss Maintenance multi-site trial [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] randomized overweight or obese adults who had lost at least 4 kg during a 6-month weight loss program to one of three 30-month weight loss maintenance conditions: monthly personal contact, unlimited access to an interactive technology-based intervention, or a self-directed control condition. Participants in the personal contact group regained less weight than those in the self-directed group, but weight regain did not differ between the interactive technology-based and self-directed groups [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The STOP Regain trial tested the efficacy of a face-to-face program and an Internet-based program, compared with a newsletter control group, in preventing 18-month weight regain among participants who had lost a of 10% of their body weight and showed that the face-to-face group was the most promising [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The Keep It Off randomized trial also recruited participants after they had lost at least 10% of their body weight and showed that participants in the Guided phone- and mail-based intervention regained significantly less weight over 24 months compared to a brief, Self-Directed maintenance intervention [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Results of these trials were strikingly similar and suggest clinically meaningful but modest effects for maintenance interventions that include sustained intervention support.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s8">
              <title>Weight Loss Maintenance Mediators</title>
              <p>An important step toward enhancing the efficacy of weight loss maintenance interventions is identifying the pathways through which successful interventions have worked. Although many studies have examined factors that are associated with weight change, such as intervention adherence [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and secondary outcomes of interventions including psychological factors such as depression, body image, and disinhibition [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], few have conducted formal mediation analyses. Mediation analyses can inform intervention development and refinement in several ways including confirming that an intervention is having the intended effect on hypothesized mediators of change and in turn the outcome of interest. Mediation analyses can also elucidate areas of improvement for interventions [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p>
              <p>Mediation analyses have been conducted to better understand behavior change mechanisms in the context of multiple types of health behavior change interventions, including physical activity [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17–21</xref>], dietary intake [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and weight loss [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], with some research focused on mediators of weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For example, Teixeira and colleagues [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] evaluated whether self-regulation constructs were mediators of weight loss and 2-year weight loss maintenance in a large sample of overweight women. Results showed that lowering emotional eating and adopting a flexible dietary restraint pattern were critical for sustained weight loss. They also reported that exercise, intrinsic motivation, and self-efficacy were important mediators of long-term weight loss maintenance.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s9">
              <title>Keep It Off Mediators</title>
              <p>The Keep It Off behavioral intervention was designed to help people who had recently lost at least 10% of their body weight maintain their weight loss over a 2-year period. The conceptual framework for the intervention was informed by several theoretical models including Rothman’s Decision Criteria Maintenance Model [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], the Relapse Prevention Model [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], and state-of-the art weight-related behavioral interventions which promote self-regulation behaviors, such as self-monitoring, stimulus control, and problem solving. The following key strategies were promoted during the Keep It Off study: (1) taking part in 60 to 90 min of moderate-intensity physical activity each day; (2) regularly writing down weight, physical activity, and eating, preferably daily; (3) eating a diet moderate in calories; (4) eating breakfast every day; (5) enlisting social support; (6) not letting “lapses” turn into full “relapses”; and (7) appreciating progress made.</p>
              <p>The goal of this manuscript is to identify factors that explain why Keep It Off Guided participants were more successful in maintaining their weight loss over the 2-year study period relative to Self-Directed participants. The conceptual framework of the intervention [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref>] and empirical literature on weight loss and maintenance guided the selection of mediators. The Keep It Off measurement protocol enabled a robust examination of mediators of weight loss maintenance. Potential mediators and weight were measured every 6 months for the 24-month post-randomization period so that short- or long-term changes, or relationships between them, would more likely be observed. Due to random assignment and repeated measurement of mediators and outcomes, it was possible to assert causality in the relationships between treatment group and change in mediators and identify patterns of results consistent with causal meditation among mediators that were related to weight. This mediation analysis has the potential to both identify behavioral targets that are most strongly related to weight and to shed light on areas where the intervention could be enhanced by focusing on behaviors that were related to weight change but not influenced by the intervention.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s10">
              <title>Method</title>
              <sec id="s11">
                <title>Recruitment</title>
                <p>We used multiple strategies to recruit eligible participants who intentionally lost at least 10% of their body weight during the past year. Adopting National Weight Control Registry [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] procedures, participants were asked to provide documentation to ensure the veracity of their self-reported weight loss. Additional eligibility criteria were as follows: 19 to 70 years old, previous year enrollment in the HealthPartners health plan, and BMI ≥20.5 kg/m2. Exclusion criteria included anorexia nervosa history, bariatric surgery, modified Charlson [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] score ≥3, non-skin cancer, congestive heart failure, use of a phone-based weight loss program to achieve their recent weight loss, or current participation in another weight management study. Participants consented to study participation and provided baseline weight and questionnaire data at an in-person baseline visit prior to being randomized equally to the Keep It Off Guided or Self-Directed Intervention. The recruitment and enrollment processes are described in greater detail elsewhere [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s12">
                <title>Intervention</title>
                <p>The Self-Directed study arm included two phone coaching sessions that took place in the first month after randomization. Self-Directed participants received a 10-chapter Keep It Off course book with topics such as key weight loss maintenance behaviors, weight loss history, physical activity, menu planning, stimulus control, problem solving, overcoming barriers to physical activity and healthy eating, relapse prevention, and body image and weight goals. Participants also received a Keep It Off logbook to record their eating, physical activity, and weight for a month. During the two calls, participants reviewed the instructions for self-monitoring and the course book. Participants had no further contact with their phone coach.</p>
                <p>The Guided study arm included 10 biweekly phone coaching sessions followed by eight monthly and six bimonthly calls and bimonthly weight graphs and letters beginning at month 8. Guided participants worked through the Keep It Off course book [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] during the biweekly calls and then transitioned to the monthly and bimonthly call phase. Guided participants received Keep It Off logbooks and reported their weight weekly for the study duration either during scheduled calls, by email, or on the study website. Participants were not given specific calorie and fat goals but were encouraged to self-monitor dietary intake, calories, fat grams, and body weight to establish their optimal calorie range for weight maintenance. Participants were encouraged to work toward the goal of engaging in 60 to 90 min of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity, most days a week. Participants also received bimonthly feedback weight graphs and reports based on their weight loss maintenance progress. Accompanying each mailing was a small incentive for continuing participation. Finally, if participants showed a weight gain trend (i.e., 2 lb or greater) and did not have a call scheduled in the next 2 weeks, phone coaches emailed or called them to provide extra support to help reverse the weight gain. Participant reports of diet and activity were used to target which components of their weight maintenance plan appeared to be contributing to weight gain. An action plan was developed, and follow-up phone calls were scheduled as needed to help the participant stabilize their weight.</p>
                <p>Keep It Off study protocols were reviewed and approved by the HealthPartners Institutional Review Board, and informed consent was obtained from all individual participants in the study. The trial is registered with<ext-link xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov" ext-link-type="uri">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> (Identifier: NCT00702455<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00702455?term=Keep+It+Off&amp;rank=1" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00702455?term=Keep+It+Off&amp;rank=1</ext-link>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s13">
                <title>Measures</title>
                <p>Data collection points were at baseline (0 months) and at 6, 12, 18, and 24-month follow-ups. The baseline, 12-month, and 24-month measurements were conducted in person; 6- and 18-month measurements were conducted via telephone by evaluation staff blind to study condition. The exceptions to this schedule were dietary intake and body image, which were only measured annually.</p>
                <sec id="s14">
                  <title>Weight Change Outcome</title>
                  <p>The outcome in all reported analyses is percent weight change relative to baseline. Three measures were calculated for each randomized participant as 12-, 18-, or 24-month weight minus baseline weight divided by baseline weight. At baseline and 12 and 24 months, weight and height were measured in person with participants in light clothing without shoes (Seca 770 Medical Scale; Seca 214 Portable Height Rod). The 6- and 18-month observations were self-reported and adjusted for potential underreporting [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s15">
                  <title>Hypothesized Mediators of Weight Loss Maintenance</title>
                  <p>For each hypothesized mediator, three mediator change measures per person were calculated as 6, 12, or 18 months minus baseline.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s16">
                  <title>Moderate to Vigorous Physical Activity</title>
                  <p>Physical activity was assessed using the Paffenbarger Physical Activity Questionnaire [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This instrument asks individuals to indicate the number of city blocks walked, flights of stairs climbed, and light, medium, and heavy leisure time activities in the past week. It has been shown to have satisfactory reliability [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and predictive validity [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and to be sensitive to physical activity change in intervention studies [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The caloric expenditures from self-reported moderate and heavy activities were summed to estimate weekly kilocalorie of energy expenditure from moderate to vigorous physical activity (MVPA).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s17">
                  <title>Dietary Intake</title>
                  <p>Dietary intake was assessed using the National Cancer Institute’s web-based Diet History Questionnaire (DHQ). Although no formal, large validation study of the web-based DHQ has been conducted, several studies document acceptable reliability and validity of the paper-and-pencil version [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. DHQ-derived total daily energy intake (kcals) was calculated from baseline and 12-and 24-month reports.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s18">
                  <title>Lifestyle Behaviors</title>
                  <p>Participants reported on lifestyle behaviors potentially related to weight regain. Meal regularity was calculated as the mean of the number of times in the past week participants reported they ate (a) breakfast, (b) lunch, and (c) dinner. TV-related eating was calculated as the mean of five items that assessed the number of times in the past week participants reported (a) eating after 7 PM, (b) eating a snack while watching TV, (c) eating meal while watching TV, and the number of hours spent watching TV on an average (d) weekday and (e) weekend day. Eating away from home was as the mean number of times in the past week participants reported eating (a) fast food and (b) food purchased from a convenience store. For each composite, item responses were averaged so that higher scores indicated more meal regularity, more TV-related eating, and more eating away from home.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s19">
                  <title>Self-Monitoring Behaviors</title>
                  <p>The frequency with which participants implemented intentional weight control strategies was calculated as the mean of how often participants wrote down (a) the calorie content of foods they ate and (b) the amount and type of exercise they had done and (c) used meal replacements, (d) planned meals, and (e) planned exercise to manage their weight.</p>
                  <p>Participants also responded to “How often do you weigh yourself?” [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] with options ranging from “never” through “every day” and “more than once a day.” Responses were dichotomized as less than daily self-weighing and at least daily self-weighing. Change in daily self-weighing (stopped daily self-weighing, no change, started daily self-weighing at 6, 12. or 18 months relative to baseline) was represented by two binary indicators: starting daily self-weighing and stopping daily self-weighing relative to baseline.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s20">
                  <title>Body Shape Satisfaction</title>
                  <p>A 16-item version of the Body Shape Questionnaire shown to have acceptable reliability and validity [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] measured body shape satisfaction. Participants rated the frequency with which they experience body shape concerns on items such as “Have you been so worried about your shape that you have been feeling you ought to diet?” Responses to all items were averaged so that higher scores indicated greater body shape satisfaction.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s21">
                <title>Analysis Plan</title>
                <p>The analytic dataset was constructed to support the primary hypothesis test of whether experimentally induced changes in mediators from baseline to the 6-, 12-, and 18-month follow-ups could mediate changes in weight from baseline to 12, 18, and 24 months. Each randomized participant had three observations that represented 6-month lags between changes in mediators and in weight. The first observation consisted of the baseline to 6-month mediator change scores and baseline to 12-month percent weight change. The second and third observations consisted of the baseline to 12- and 18-month mediator change scores, respectively, and baseline to 18 and 24 month weight changes.</p>
                <p>The primary efficacy analyses demonstrated that Guided participants regained significantly less weight than Self-Directed participants at 12 and 24 months [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. For the mediation analyses, one multilevel regression model predicted each participant’s three weight change measures from randomized treatment group to estimate the average percent weight change across all follow-ups among Guided relative to Self-Directed participants. This model quantified the total treatment effect that could then be partitioned into direct and indirect effects of the Guided intervention. A general linear model predicted percent weight change at 18 months from treatment group to quantify the total treatment effect for which only one baseline to 12-month mediator change score was available (i.e., dietary intake, body image).</p>
                <p>Seven multilevel path models each simultaneously estimated the direct, non-mediated effect of the Guided vs. Self-Directed treatment group on percent weight change (c′ path) as well as the parameters necessary for calculating strength of the indirect, mediated effect of the Guided vs. Self-Directed treatment group on change in one selected mediator (a path) and its association with subsequent percent weight change (b path). As a result of the 6-month lags built into the structure of the dataset, the a path estimated the effects of randomization to the Guided vs. Self-Directed treatment group on changes in mediators at 6, 12, and 18 months, and the c′ path estimated the treatment group effect on changes in weight at 12, 18, and 24 months. The b path estimated the association between change in a mediator and percent weight change 6 months later.</p>
                <p>In these seven multilevel path models, treatment group was a binary classification variable, mediator and percent weight change scores were specified as normally distributed, and path coefficients were estimated as fixed parameters. The mediators representing starting and stopping daily self-weighing were specified as binomial. The multilevel path models nested three mediator-percent weight change observations within each participant, specified participant-specific random intercepts, and implemented restricted maximum likelihood (for normal mediators) or weighted least squares (for binary mediators) estimation. Two additional path models assessed mediation through dietary intake and body image from a single observation per person (percent weight change at 18 months, mediator change at 12 months).</p>
                <p>Indirect effects were calculated using a distribution of the product approach for models in which the a or b path was significant (p &lt; .05), and the other was significant (p &lt; .05) or approached significance (p &lt; .10). The strength of the indirect effects was estimated as the multiplicative product of the a and b coefficients, and their significance was assessed by means of asymptotic 95% confidence limits around the ab estimates [<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>
                <p>Interpretation of these path models follows the approach described by Kraemer and colleagues [<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. This approach advocates assessing whether a post-intervention measure is predicted by the intervention (i.e., is the a path p &lt; .10?) and whether it is related to the outcome (i.e., is the b path p &lt; .10?). The intersection of answers to these two questions is then used to characterize the relationship of each measure with respect to the significant treatment-outcome relationship. Measures for which both answers are ‘yes’ and the indirect effect is at p &lt; .05 will be considered significant mediators of the Guided intervention effect on percent weight change.</p>
                <p>The percent weight change outcome was calculated from weight values used in the primary efficacy analyses [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. For sporadically missing values, participants’ previously and subsequently observed weights were used for imputation via linear interpolation. For monotonically missing values, 3.96 lb per missed follow-up was added to the last observed weight [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Missing mediator change scores resulted from monotonic and non-monotonic survey non-response at the 6-, 12-, or 18-month follow-up. The models with normally distributed mediators were estimated via maximum likelihood estimation with standard errors calculated using robust sandwich estimators.Modelswith binary mediators were estimated via weighted least square parameter estimation using a diagonal weight matrix with standard errors calculated using a full weight matrix.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s22">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Study participants (N = 419) were primarily non-Hispanic White (86.9%) women (81.6%) who were on average 46.4 (SD = 10.7) years old, overweight (BMI M = 28.5, SD = 4.9; weight M = 175.9, SD = 35.5), and had lost 16.2% (SD = 5.3) of their body weight prior to enrolling in Keep It Off (<xref rid="T01" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There were no baseline differences by treatment group in these or other key demographic characteristics [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T01">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Baseline characteristics of Keep It Off participants</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guided</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-Directed</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, M (SD)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6 (10.9)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3 (10.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.4 (10.7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.9</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, M (SD)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 (4.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4 (5.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5 (4.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.1</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.7</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.9</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">College degree (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed part-time or full-time (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.6</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.6</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.1</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% weight loss prior to study, M (SD)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6 (5.6)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 (5.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 (5.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Most participants (n = 334, 79.7%) were retained at all follow-ups. Forty-one (9.8%) missed follow-ups sporadically, representing 58 missed observations; and 44 (10.5%) dropped out at 6 (n = 21), 12 (n = 10), 18 (n = 2), or 24 months (n = 11), representing 129 missed observations. Participants with complete data were more likely to be non-Hispanic white (89.8%) than those who dropped out (75.0%) or sporadically missed follow-ups (75.6%). They also had lower baseline weight (M = 173.6) and BMI (M = 28.1) than those with sporadically missing data (M = 194.6, M = 30.9).</p>
              <p>Presented in<xref rid="T02" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> are the percent changes in weight from baseline to 12, 18, and 24 months and changes in potential mediators from baseline to 6, 12 and 18 months, that formed the basis of the mediational analyses. While participants in both treatment groups regained weight over time, by 12 months, the Self-Directed participants had regained 2% more weight relative to baseline (M = 3.12%) than Guided participants (M = 1.04%), a difference that remained at 18 and 24 months. Other notable patterns were observed for MVPA and self-weighing. Self-Directed participants reported engaging in about 225–270 fewer kcal of MVPA at the three follow-ups than at baseline in contrast to Guided participants whose activity fluctuated by fewer than 100 kcal relative to baseline. Even though fewer Guided than Self-Directed participants reported daily self-weighing at baseline (42.6 vs. 52.4%, p &lt; .05), the Guided participants tended to report more starting (34, 32, 25%) than stopping (9, 8, 12%) of self-weighing, whereas the Self-Directed participants appeared almost as likely to report starting (13, 10, 8%) as stopping (13, 15, 20%).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T02">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean and (SD) or percent for primary weight outcome and potential mediators and change relative to baseline (∆ vs. 0 months), by treatment group and measurement point</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guided</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self–Directed</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 months</th>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 months</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, pounds</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.71(34.73)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.67 (35.56)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.40 (36.78)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.31 (38.73)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.55 (39.27)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.12 (36.29)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.22 (37.22)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.47 (39.41)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.45 (39.92)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.65 (40.68)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% ∆ vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04(7.15)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 (8.46)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96 (9.52)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12(7.61)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87 (8.83)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14 (9.56)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MVPA, kcal/100</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.99(11.56)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.53 (13.23)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10 (10.22)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.87 (12.03)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.63 (13.18)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.99 (13.95)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62(11.75)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.64(11.35)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 (12.35)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.42 (12.72)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.55 (10.42)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.87 (9.21)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.15 (12.34)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.25 (11.30)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.26 (10.91)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2.69 (13.24)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily self–weighing (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6<xref rid="nt2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.7</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.3</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.4</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Start vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight control<xref rid="nt1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67 (.68)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94 (.79)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 (.72)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62 (.75)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66 (.70)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68 (.76)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77 (.78)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 (.80)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 (.74)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 (.80)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23 (.80)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19 (.68)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.07 (.81)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08 (.68)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04 (.66)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.12 (.73)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary intake, kcal/100</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.87 (6.33)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.66 (5.85)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29 (5.72)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.11 (6.41)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.05 (6.08)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.87(6.33)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.74 (5.46)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1.17(5.20)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meal regularity<xref rid="nt1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 (.61)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 (.46)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54 (.57)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 (.46)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 (.60)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53 (.65)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62 (.50)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56 (.57)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62 (.50)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 (.60)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04 (.48)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03 (.52)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.18 (.51)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.18 (.51)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04 (.48)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08 (.53)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TV–related eating<xref rid="nt1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 (.81)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (.78)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 (.84)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (.78)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 (.82)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 (.79)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 (.77)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 (.76)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 (.78)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 (.76)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.19 (.58)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.06 (.55)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.21 (.59)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.17 (.67)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.06 (.60)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.08 (.72)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eating away from home<xref rid="nt1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (.52)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (.54)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (.52)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (.54)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (.49)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (.50)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (.47)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (.48)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (.53)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (.50)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.03 (.51)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03 (.56)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01 (.63)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01 (.45)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.01 (.51)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.09 (.62)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body shape satisfaction<xref rid="nt1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62 (.86)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 (.97)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71 (.93)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65 (.86)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 (.97)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47(1.03)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆ vs. 0 months</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05 (.71)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–.07 (.66)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="nt1">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Range = 1–5</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="nt2">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p><italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> .05, baseline Guided vs. Self–Directed comparison</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <sec id="s23">
                <title>Efficacy of Guided Intervention</title>
                <p>The first objective of these analyses was to quantify the direct relationship between the Guided vs. Self-Directed treatment groups and percent weight change. Averaged across three time lags (Baseline to 12, 18. and 24 months), Guided participants gained 2.18% less of their baseline weight (LS Mean = 2.53%) than Self-Directed participants (LS Mean = 4.71%, p &lt; .006). This direct intervention–outcome effect is the benchmark that will be decomposed into direct and indirect components to identify significant mediators of weight loss maintenance.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s24">
                <title>Does Guided Intervention Predict Mediator Change?</title>
                <p>If a mediated relationship is to be viable, randomization into the Guided rather than Self-Directed group must be predictive of subsequent change in the mediator (a path). Of the nine relationships assessed, four resulted in a marginal or significant change in the mediator as a function of the Guided intervention (<xref rid="T03" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, first column). Guided participants were more likely than Self-Directed participants to have started p &lt; .001), and less likely to have stopped (p &lt; .05), daily self-weighing. They also reported engaging in about 225 more kcal of MVPA per week (p &lt; .05) and more frequently implemented weight control strategies (p &lt; .10) at 6, 12, or 18 months.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T03">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Path coefficients (standard errors) from models decomposing the total relationship between treatment group and percent weight change into the relationships between the Guided vs. Self-Directed intervention and mediator change (a path), mediator change and percent weight change (b path), and residual direct effect of the Guided vs. Self-Directed intervention on percent weight change (c′ path) and the resulting indirect effect</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a path (se): Guided vs. Self-Directed to mediator change</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b path (se): mediator change to percent weight change</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c′ path (se): Guided vs. Self-Directed to percent weight change</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indirect effect (95% CL)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant mediators of weight change</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Start daily self-weighing</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.74 (.13)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.30 (.58)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.48 (.90)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.70 (−2.72, −.67)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stop daily self-weighing</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.30 (.14)<xref rid="nt4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 (.43)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.42 (.79)<xref rid="nt3" ref-type="table-fn">+</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.75 (−1.47, −.04)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential mediators of weight change</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MVPA, kcal/100</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24 (.94)<xref rid="nt4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.09 (.03)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.99 (.77)<xref rid="nt5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.19 (−.38, .00)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Weight control</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11 (.06)<xref rid="nt3" ref-type="table-fn">+</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.81 (.50)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.86 (.75)<xref rid="nt4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.32 (−.67, .04)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonspecific predictor of weight change</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Eating away from home</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.02 (.05)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 (.60)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.12 (.77)<xref rid="nt5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Body shape satisfaction</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11 (.07)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.76 (.67)<xref rid="nt6" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.74 (.79)<xref rid="nt4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dietary intake, kcal/100</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.44 (.57)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.22 (.10)<xref rid="nt4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.27 (.77)<xref rid="nt5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irrelevant to weight change</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Meal regularity</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03 (.04)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.21 (.88)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.15 (.78)<xref rid="nt5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TV-related eating</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.05 (.05)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.95 (.65)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.13 (.77)<xref rid="nt5" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt3">
                      <label>+</label>
                      <p>p &lt; .10</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="nt4">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p>p &lt; .05</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="nt5">
                      <label>**</label>
                      <p>p &lt; .01</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="nt6">
                      <label>***</label>
                      <p>p &lt; .001</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s25">
                <title>Does Mediator Change Predict Percent Weight Change?</title>
                <p>For eight of the nine potential mediators, change from baseline was marginally or significantly related in the expected direction to percent weight change relative to baseline measured 6 months later (<xref rid="T03" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, second column; b path). For example, each 100 kcal expended on MVPA per week was associated with .09% weight loss 6 months later (p &lt; .001). Similarly, each increase of 100 cal consumed per day was associated with a weight increase of .22% 6 months later (p &lt; .05). More frequently employing weight control strategies (p &lt; .001), starting daily self-weighing (p &lt; .001), and improved body image (p &lt; .001) were each associated with weight decreases; eating more meals at fast food venues (p &lt; .001) and stopping self-weighing (p &lt; .001) were associated with weight increase.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s26">
                <title>Significant Mediators of Weight Change</title>
                <p>Critical for the task of identifying significant mediators of percent weight change, all four mediator changes that differed by treatment group were also significantly related to percent weight change. The higher proportion of Guided participants who started to weigh themselves daily predicted 1.70% (95% CI −2.72, −.67) less weight regain. The fewer Guided participants who stopped daily self-weighing predicted .75% (95% CI −1.47, −.04) less weight regain. Starting and stopping self-weighing were the only post-intervention measures that met all three criteria (caused by the intervention, predictive of percent weight change, significant indirect effect) to be considered significant mediators of the Guided intervention on percent weight change. Because each mediated relationship was estimated separately, it is possible that simultaneously estimating other mediators would reduce the magnitude of these estimated indirect effects.</p>
                <p>MVPA and the use of weight control strategies were both sufficiently related to the intervention and weight change for the mediated relationships to be considered potential mediators of percent weight change. The indirect effects of MVPA (−.19%, 95% CI −.38, .00) and weight control strategies (−.32%, 95% CI −.67, .04) predicted lower percent weight regains among Guided participants but neither was statistically significant.</p>
                <p>Three of the potential mediators—eating away from home, body shape satisfaction, and dietary intake—were nonspecific predictors of percent weight change. Each was predictably related to changes in weight but was not affected by exposure to the Guided intervention. These constructs represent opportunities for future interventions. meal regularity and TV-related eating were not related to either the Guided intervention or weight change.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s27">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The goal of the present work is to assess the potential for each of nine factors to mediate a successful weight loss maintenance intervention, the Keep It Off Guided intervention. The results reported here have added to our understanding of the behavioral mediators of weight loss maintenance by documenting the temporal ordering of intervention delivery, changes in mediators, and percent changes in weight and by comparing the proportional contribution of each potential weight change mediator. We assert that self-weighing behaviors are significant mediators of weight change that could have been caused by the Guided intervention. There was more change in these behaviors among participants randomized to the Guided than the Self-Directed intervention, and changes in mediators lagged changes in outcomes by 6 months making the pattern of effects consistent with causal mediation.</p>
              <p>Specifically, results indicated that uptake and maintenance of daily self-weighing were significant mediators of the Keep It Off Guided intervention. Guided intervention participants regained about 2% less weight over the 24 months post-randomization than Self-Directed participants. Starting daily self-weighing explained a greater share of this relative difference than any other potential mediator that was assessed. Continuing with (i.e., not stopping) self-weighing explained a smaller but significant share. Although not reported in detail, this same pattern of results obtained when BMI was treated as the outcome and when the analysis was limited to women.</p>
              <p>The benefits of regular self-weighing on weight change have been systematically documented [<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], with concurring evidence from the direct manipulation of self-weighing in efficacy trials [<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and from the associations between self-weighing and weight change in trials [<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and observational studies. [<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p>
              <p>Associations between moderate-to-vigorous physical activity and long-term weight loss maintenance have been reported [<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50–54</xref>] but a possible causal role of MVPA remains undocumented. Surprisingly, self-monitoring behaviors such as writing down calorie content of foods and the amount and type of exercise were predictive of percent weight change but were not determined to be significant mediators of the intervention effect. Increases in caloric intake and in the frequency with which participants reported eating away from home were associated with increases in weight. Increases in body shape satisfaction were related to decreases in body weight over time.</p>
              <p>The question of why self-weighing was the strongest mediator of the intervention effect on weight change remains open. Reductions in dietary intake and increases in physical activity were both predictably associated with weight change but neither proved to be as markedly strong a mediator as self-weighing. Recommending a behavior as simple to adhere to as self-weighing may have prompted participants to notice and respond to weight increases via changes in diet or activity while they were still small enough to reverse and prevent more substantial regain (i.e., moderated mediation) [<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, these energy balance factors are complex intermediaries in the self-weighing–weight change relationship that were likely not assessed with sufficiently precise timing or specificity to capture such complex relationships. Another possibility is that self-weighing is a behavioral manifestation of intervention-induced changes in affect, cognition, or motivation that were not anticipated or measured. Given the magnitude of the self-weighing indirect effect, and the promise it may hold for successful weight loss, efforts directed toward identifying modifiable factors that promote self-weighing and effectively managing the resulting behavioral cascade are warranted. The lack of intervention effect on changes in several factors predictive of weight change could be due to issues such as a lack of emphasis on these behaviors in the intervention, poor measurement sensitivity (e.g., dietary intake), or not being very amenable to direct intervention (e.g., body shape satisfaction).</p>
              <p>As is often true for randomized trials, it would be inappropriate to generalize these results beyond the population from which the participants were recruited—educated, employed middle age non-Hispanic White women who were successful at achieving a significant weight loss in the previous year. The annual rather than biannual measurement of dietary intake made it infeasible to more fully explore the intriguing and potentially complex relationships among self-weighing, MVPA, and dietary intake in mediating weight loss maintenance.</p>
              <p>Daily self-weighing emerged as a clear mediator of weight loss maintenance and there appeared to be opportunities for improving weight loss maintenance to be realized in future work. As one example, eating away from home and dietary intake were associated with weight increases but not affected by the intervention. This and other interventions might be strengthened by devising strategies to promote changes in behaviors such as eating away from home, body shape satisfaction, and dietary intake that in this study were nonspecific predictors of weight loss maintenance.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s28">
              <title>Authors’ Statement of Conflict of Interest and Adherence to Ethical Standards</title>
              <p>Authors AL Crain, NE Sherwood, BC Martinson, and RW Jeffery declare that they have no conflict of interest. All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/ or national research and with the 1964 Helsinki Declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s29">
              <title>Informed Consent</title>
              <p>Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R01">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname>
 <given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Drewnowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Long-term maintenance of weight loss: current status</article-title>.<source>Health Psychol.</source><year>2000</year>,<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R02">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sarwer</surname>
 <given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>von Sydow Green</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name></person-group>,<article-title>Wadden TA: Behavior therapy for obesity: where are we now</article-title>?<source>Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes.</source><year>2009</year>,<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19623061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R03">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Levy</surname>
 <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Maintenance-tailored therapy vs. standard behavior therapy for 30-month maintenance of weight loss</article-title>.<source>Prev Med.</source><year>2010</year>,<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20869984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R04">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Perri</surname>
 <given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Nezu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>McKelvey</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Relapse prevention training and problem-solving therapy in the long-term management of obesity</article-title>.<source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source>.<year>2001</year>,<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11550740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R05">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Perri</surname>
 <given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Nezu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Patti</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></string-name></person-group>,<article-title>McCann KL: Effect of length of treatment on weight loss</article-title>.<source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source>.<year>1989</year>,<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2500466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R06">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname>
 <given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name></person-group>,<article-title>Tate D: Physical activity and weight loss: Does prescribing higher physical activity goals improve outcome</article-title>?<source>American Journal of Clinical Nutrition.</source><year>2003</year>,<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R07">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tate</surname>
 <given-names>DF</given-names>
 <suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
 <article-title>Long-term weight losses associated with prescription of higher physical activity goals. Are higher levels of physical activity protective against weight regain</article-title>?<source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source><year>2007</year>,<volume>85</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>954</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17413092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R08">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Svetkey</surname>
 <given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Brantley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Comparison of strategies for sustaining weight loss: the weight loss maintenance randomized controlled trial</article-title>.<source>Jama</source>.<year>2008</year>,<volume>299</volume>:<fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R09">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
 <given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Gorin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>A self-regulation program for maintenance of weight loss</article-title>.<source>N Engl J Med.</source><year>2006</year>,<volume>355</volume>:<fpage>1563</fpage>–<lpage>1571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17035649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname>
 <given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Martinson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Keep it off: a phone-based intervention for long-term weight-loss maintenance</article-title>.<source>Contemp Clin Trials.</source><year>2011</year>,<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21453791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname>
 <given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Martinson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Enhancing long-term weight loss maintenance: 2 year results from the Keep It Off randomized controlled trial</article-title>.<source>Prev Med</source>.<year>2013</year>,<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23276775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wadden</surname>
 <given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Neiberg</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Four-year weight losses in the Look AHEAD study: factors associated with long-term success</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2011</year>,<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1987</fpage>–<lpage>1998</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21779086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wadden</surname>
 <given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>West</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Neiberg</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>One-year weight losses in the Look AHEAD study: factors associated with success</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2009</year>,<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19180071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Palmeira</surname>
 <given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Change in body image and psychological well-being during behavioral obesity treatment: associations with weight loss and maintenance</article-title>.<source>Body Image</source>.<year>2010</year>,<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Faulconbridge</surname>
 <given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wadden</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Changes in symptoms of depression with weight loss: results of a randomized trial</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2009</year>,<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19197266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baranowski</surname>
 <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Jago</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Understanding the mechanisms of change in children’s physical activity programs</article-title>.<source>Exerc Sport Sci Rev.</source><year>2005</year>,<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16239832</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Crain</surname>
 <given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Martinson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>The long and winding road to physical activity maintenance</article-title>.<source>Am J Health Behav</source>.<year>2010</year>,<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20604700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
 <given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Psychosocial mediators of physical activity behavior among adults and children</article-title>.<source>Am J Prev Med</source>.<year>2002</year>,<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12133735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Napolitano</surname>
 <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Papandonatos</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Mediators of physical activity behavior change: a multivariate approach</article-title>.<source>Health Psychol.</source><year>2008</year>,<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18642998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Papandonatos</surname>
 <given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Mediators of physical activity behavior change: findings from a 12-month randomized controlled trial</article-title>.<source>Health Psychol.</source><year>2012</year>,<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22149130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baranowski</surname>
 <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Carmack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Mediating variable framework in physical activity interventions. How are we doing</article-title>?<source>How might we do better? Am J Prev Med.</source><year>1998</year>,<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9838973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mosher</surname>
 <given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Lipkus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sloane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Long-term outcomes of the FRESH START trial: exploring the role of self-efficacy in cancer survivors’ maintenance of dietary practices and physical activity</article-title>.<source>Psychooncology</source>.<year>2013</year>,<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>876</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shaikh</surname>
 <given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Vinokur</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Yaroch</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Resnicow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Direct and mediated effects of two theoretically based interventions to increase consumption of fruits and vegetables in the Healthy Body Healthy Spirit trial</article-title>.<source>Health Educ Behav.</source><year>2011</year>,<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21596903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname>
 <given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Mediators of weight loss and weight loss maintenance in middle-aged women</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring).</source><year>2010</year>,<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19696752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rothman</surname>
 <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Toward a theory-based analysis of behavioral maintenance</article-title>.<source>Health Psychol</source>.<year>2000</year>,<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marlatt</surname>
 <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Relapse prevention: maintenance strategies in the treatment of addictive behaviors</article-title>.<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.<year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Catenacci</surname>
 <given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Stuht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Physical activity patterns in the National Weight Control Registry</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring).</source><year>2008</year>,<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18223628</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
 <given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Successful weight loss maintenance</article-title>.<source>Annu Rev Nutr</source>.<year>2001</year>,<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11375440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gorin</surname>
 <given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Promoting long-term weight control: does dieting consistency matter</article-title>?<source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>.<year>2004</year>,<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14647183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Klem</surname>
 <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Seagle</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>A descriptive study of individuals successful at long-term maintenance of substantial weight loss</article-title>.<source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>.<year>1997</year>,<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9250100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Charlson</surname>
 <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>The Charlson co-morbidity index is adapted to predict costs of chronic disease in primary care patients</article-title>.<source>J Clin Epidemiol.</source><year>2008</year>,<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1234</fpage>–<lpage>1240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18619805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Spencer</surname>
 <given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Validity of self-reported height and weight in 4808 EPIC-Oxford participants</article-title>.<source>Public Health Nutr</source>.<year>2002</year>,<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12186665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Paffenbarger</surname>
 <given-names>RS</given-names>,<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>.,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Physical activity as an index of heart attack risk in college alumni</article-title>.<source>Am J Epidemiol.</source><year>1978</year>,<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">707484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
 <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>FitzerGerald</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>A collection of Physical Activity Questionnaires for health-related research</article-title>.<source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>.<year>1997</year>,<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>S1</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9243481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harris</surname>
 <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>French</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Dietary and physical activity correlates of long-term weight loss</article-title>.<source>Obes Res</source>.<year>1994</year>,<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16358394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname>
 <given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Physical activity and weight loss: does prescribing higher physical activity goals improve outcome</article-title>?<source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source><year>2003</year>,<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>684</fpage>–<lpage>689</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14522725</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Subar</surname>
 <given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Kipnis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Comparative validation of the Block, Willett, and National Cancer Institute food frequency questionnaires: the Eating at America’s Table Study</article-title>.<source>Am J Epidemiol.</source><year>2001</year>,<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1099</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11744511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
 <given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Subar</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Cognitive research enhances accuracy of food frequency questionnaire reports: results of an experimental validation study</article-title>.<source>J Am Diet Assoc.</source><year>2002</year>,<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Linde</surname>
 <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>French</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Self-weighing in weight gain prevention and weight loss trials</article-title>.<source>Ann Behav Med</source>.<year>2005</year>,<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
 <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Body Shape Questionnaire: derivation of shortened “alternate forms”</article-title>.<source>Int J Eat Disord</source>.<year>1993</year>,<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8477304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>MacKinnon</surname>
 <given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Confidence limits for the indirect effect: distribution of the product and resampling methods Multivariate Behavioral Research</article-title>.<year>2004</year>,<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kraemer</surname>
 <given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Toward non-parametric and clinically meaningful moderators and mediators</article-title>.<source>Stat Med.</source><year>2008</year>,<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1679</fpage>–<lpage>1692</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18008395</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kraemer</surname>
 <given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Fairburn</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Agras</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Mediators and moderators of treatment effects in randomized clinical trials</article-title>.<source>Arch Gen Psychiatry.</source><year>2002</year>,<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>883</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12365874</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
 <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Klem</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Sereika</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Self-weighing in weight management: a systematic literature review</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2015</year>,<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25521523</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Steinberg</surname>
 <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>The efficacy of a daily self-weighing weight loss intervention using smart scales and email</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2013</year>,<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>–<lpage>1797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23512320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Steinberg</surname>
 <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>,<article-title>Tate DF: Weighing every day matters: daily weighing improves weight loss and adoption of weight control behaviors</article-title>.<source>J Acad Nutr Diet.</source><year>2015</year>,<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Turk</surname>
 <given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Elci</surname><given-names>OU</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Self-monitoring as a mediator of weight loss in the SMART randomized clinical trial</article-title>.<source>Int J Behav Med.</source><year>2013</year>,<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22936524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
 <given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Nackers</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Dietary self-monitoring and long-term success with weight management</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2014</year>,<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1962</fpage>–<lpage>1967</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24931055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Butryn</surname>
 <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Consistent self-monitoring of weight: a key component of successful weight loss maintenance</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2007</year>,<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>3091</fpage>–<lpage>3096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18198319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
 <given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Konz</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Frederich</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Long-term weight-loss maintenance: a meta-analysis of US studies</article-title>.<source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>.<year>2001</year>,<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11684524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R51">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Befort</surname>
 <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Weight maintenance, behaviors and barriers among previous participants of a university-based weight control program</article-title>.<source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source>.<year>2008</year>,<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18059404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R52">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Catenacci</surname>
 <given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Ingebrigtsen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>, et al.:<article-title>Physical activity patterns using accelerometry in the National Weight Control Registry</article-title>.<source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>.<year>2011</year>,<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21030947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R53">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kruger</surname>
 <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Blanck</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Dietary and physical activity behaviors among adults successful at weight loss maintenance</article-title>.<source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act.</source><year>2006</year>,<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16854220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R54">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
 <given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>,<string-name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>:<article-title>Long-term weight loss maintenance</article-title>.<source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>.<year>2005</year>,<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>222S</fpage>–<lpage>225S</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002825</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
