<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T09:03:04Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10949593" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10949593</identifier>
        <datestamp>2024-03-19</datestamp>
        <setSpec>cardiab</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cardiovasc Diabetol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cardiovasc Diabetol</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Cardiovascular Diabetology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1475-2840</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10949593</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10949593</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10949593</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38500197</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38500197</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2185</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-024-02185-3</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Prevalence and prognostic significance of cardiac autonomic neuropathy in community-based people with type 2 diabetes: the Fremantle Diabetes Study Phase II</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davis</surname>
                    <given-names>Timothy M. E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>tim.davis@uwa.edu.au</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tan</surname>
                    <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davis</surname>
                    <given-names>Wendy A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1012.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7910</institution-id><institution>Medical School, Fremantle Hospital, </institution><institution>University of Western Australia, </institution></institution-wrap>PO Box 480, Fremantle, WA 6959 Australia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xba7c91</institution-id><institution>Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes, </institution><institution>Fiona Stanley and Fremantle Hospitals, </institution></institution-wrap>Murdoch, WA Australia </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01ej9dk98</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1008.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2179 088X</institution-id><institution>Australian Centre for Accelerating Diabetes Innovations (ACADI), </institution><institution>The University of Melbourne, </institution></institution-wrap>Melbourne, VIC Australia </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2024</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <elocation-id>102</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2024</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">There is a paucity of contemporary data on the prevalence and prognostic significance of cardiac autonomic neuropathy (CAN) from community-based cohorts with type 2 diabetes assessed using gold standard methods. The aim of this study was to assess these aspects of CAN in the longitudinal observational Fremantle Diabetes Study Phase II (FDS2).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">FDS2 participants were screened at baseline using standardised cardiovascular reflex tests (CARTs) of heart rate variation during deep breathing, Valsalva manoeuvre and standing. CAN (no/possible/definite) was assessed from the number of abnormal CARTs. Multinomial regression identified independent associates of CAN status. Cox proportional hazards modelling determined independent baseline predictors of incident heart failure (HF) and ischaemic heart disease (IHD), and all-cause mortality.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">Of 1254 participants assessed for CAN, 86 (6.9%) were outside CART age reference ranges and valid CART data were unavailable for 338 (27.0%). Of the remaining 830 (mean age 62.3 years, 55.3% males, median diabetes duration 7.3 years), 51.0%, 33.7% and 15.3% had no, possible or definite CAN, respectively. Independent associates of definite CAN (longer diabetes duration, higher body mass index and resting pulse rate, antidepressant and antihypertensive therapies, albuminuria, distal sensory polyneuropathy, prior HF) were consistent with those reported previously. In Kaplan–Meier analysis, definite CAN was associated with a lower likelihood of incident IHD and HF versus no/possible CAN (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and there was a graded increase in all-cause mortality risk from no CAN to possible and definite CAN (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). When CAN category was added to the most parsimonious models, it was not a significant independent predictor of IHD (<italic>P</italic> ≥ 0.851) or HF (<italic>P</italic> ≥ 0.342). Possible CAN (hazard ratio (95% CI) 1.47 (1.01, 2.14), <italic>P</italic> = 0.046) and definite CAN (2.42 (1.60, 3.67), <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) increased the risk of all-cause mortality versus no CAN.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Routine screening for CAN in type 2 diabetes has limited clinical but some prognostic value.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
                  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12933-024-02185-3.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Type 2 diabetes</kwd>
                <kwd>Cardiac autonomic neuropathy</kwd>
                <kwd>Ischemic heart disease</kwd>
                <kwd>Heart failure</kwd>
                <kwd>Mortality</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000925</institution-id>
                      <institution>National Health and Medical Research Council</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>513781 and 1042231</award-id>
                  <award-id>513781 and 1042231</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>Timothy M. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>Wendy A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Australian Centre for Accelerating Diabetes Innovations</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par23">Cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy (CAN) is characterised by orthostatic hypotension, resting tachycardia, impaired exercise tolerance and abnormal blood pressure regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], but it may also remain asymptomatic and thus elude timely diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It is a common chronic complication of type 2 diabetes with a prevalence estimated at between 9 and 78% from studies conducted in primary but mainly secondary care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Among a number of available CAN diagnostic tests, the gold standard comprises several standardised cardiovascular reflex tests (CARTs) including the electrocardiographic R-R interval response to deep breathing, the Valsalva manoeuvre and postural changes in blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. CARTs are, however, not widely available, time-consuming, and difficult to perform in people with mobility challenges and in whom forceful breathing is difficult or even contra-indicated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par24">These considerations may underlie the wide range of CAN prevalence estimates in type 2 diabetes, but may also have implications for assessment of the relationship between CAN and both cardiovascular disease (CVD) and death. A recent meta-analysis of unadjusted data suggested that CAN increases the risk of CVD events and all-cause mortality in type 2 diabetes more than threefold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], but there was substantial heterogeneity between studies. Indeed, the risk of all-cause death in the high CVD risk Action to Control Cardiovascular Risk in Diabetes (ACCORD) trial sample was lower, if still significantly increased, in fully adjusted statistical models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Furthermore, CVD risk factors are closely associated with the development of CAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A number of studies included in the meta-analysis were conducted before the publication of the results of intervention trials supporting more intensive management of hypertension and dyslipidaemia in type 2 diabetes which have resulted in improved CVD risk factor management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and a reduction in CVD events [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] over recent decades.</p>
              <p id="Par25">Although testing for autonomic dysfunction has been recommended as part of routine early screening in diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], its role as an independent predictor of CVD events and mortality needs to be established in contemporary cohorts of people with type 2 diabetes. The aim of this study was, therefore, to assess the prevalence and prognostic significance of CAN in well characterised, representative, community-based participants from the Fremantle Diabetes Study Phase II (FDS2).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec3">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Study site, participants and approvals</title>
                <p id="Par26">The FDS2 is an observational study conducted in a postcode-defined urban community of 157,000 people in the state of Western Australia (WA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Socio-economic data relating to income, employment, housing, transportation and other variables in the study area show an average Index of Relative Socio-economic Advantage and Disadvantage of 1033 with a range by postcode of 977 to 1113, figures similar to the Australian national mean ± SD of 1000 ± 100 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Descriptions of FDS2 recruitment, sample characteristics and details of non-recruited people with diabetes have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Individuals resident in the catchment area with a clinician-verified diagnosis of diabetes (excluding gestational diabetes) were identified through available hospital and community sources. Of 4639 with known diabetes found between 2008 and 2011, 1668 (36.0%) were recruited. Sixty-four FDS Phase I participants recruited between 1993 and 1996 who had moved out of the catchment area were also enrolled (total cohort 1732, of whom 1551 had clinically diagnosed type 2 diabetes). For the purposes of the present study, there were 1254 participants (89.9% of the FDS2 type 2 diabetes cohort) who were eligible for CAN testing after it first became available in May 2009 as part of baseline assessment.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Clinical and laboratory assessments</title>
                <p id="Par27">All FDS2 participants were invited to face-to-face assessments at entry and then biennially [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Each assessment included a standardised comprehensive questionnaire and physical examination, and fasting biochemical tests performed in a single nationally accredited laboratory. Participants were requested to bring all medications and/or prescriptions to each visit. Racial/ethnic background was categorised based on self-selection, country/countries of birth and parents’/grandparents’ birth, and language(s) spoken at home as Anglo-Celt, Southern European, Other European, Asian, Aboriginal or mixed/other. Body mass index (BMI) was determined together with a body shape index (ABSI) which represents a more reliable estimate of visceral adiposity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Orthostatic hypotension was defined as a fall in systolic blood pressure of ≥ 20 mmHg or in diastolic blood pressure of ≥ 10 mmHg within three minutes of standing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par28">The CARTs were performed on each eligible participant in the morning after an overnight fast, and comprised measurement and analysis of heart rate variation during deep breathing, the Valsalva manoeuvre, and on standing by electrocardiography using the ANS 2000 system (Hokanson Inc, Bellevue, Washington, US) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The deep breathing test was performed with the participant supine and breathing at a paced rate of five breaths/minute for six minutes, as recommended by the manufacturer. The ratio of the mean of the shortest R-R interval during inspiration to the mean of the longest R-R wave during expiration (E:I ratio) was calculated, and the MCR determined by vector analysis of the R–R intervals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. During the Valsalva manoeuvre, participants performed continuous forced exhalation to a pressure of 40 mmHg for 15 s. The ratio of the longest R–R interval after the manoeuvre to the shortest R–R interval during the manoeuvre was calculated (the Valsalva ratio) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Evaluation of changes in heart rate was performed during the initial phase of adaptation to orthostasis (first 45 s), and the 30:15 stand ratio calculated from the maximal (around 30th heart beat) to minimal (near 15th heart beat) R-R interval [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par29">Abnormalities in the three CART components (one or other of E:I ratio and MCR in the case of the deep breathing CART) were identified from age-corrected normal ranges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and given a score of 1. Since the age of the healthy individuals used to derive the normal ranges spanned 15–67 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], linear (for E:I ratio, MCR and Valsalva ratio; r<sup>2</sup> ≥ 0.983) and quadratic (for 30:15 stand ratio; r<sup>2</sup> = 0.996) equations were derived from the table of age versus the 2.3 centiles of each CART [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and extrapolated to age 80 years to better capture reflect the age range of the FDS2 type 2 diabetes cohort and to parallel other studies with age-specific reference ranges which did not include very elderly participants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Diagnosis of CAN and its stage was determined from modified Toronto Consensus Panel criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] as no CAN (total score = 0), possible CAN (total score = 1) or definite CAN (total score ≥ 2).</p>
                <p id="Par30">Chronic complications of diabetes were identified using standard definitions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Albuminuria was assessed by early morning spot urinary albumin:creatinine ratio (uACR) measurement and renal impairment from the estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy (DSPN) was defined using the vibration perception threshold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Retinopathy was defined as one microaneurysm in either eye or worse and/or previous laser treatment on fundus photography and/or ophthalmologist assessment. Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) was defined as an ankle brachial index ≤ 0.90 or a diabetes-related lower extremity amputation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Ascertainment of cardiovascular outcomes and deaths</title>
                <p id="Par31">The Hospital Morbidity Data Collection (HMDC) contains validated information regarding all public/private hospitalisations in WA since 1970 and the Death Register contains information on all deaths in WA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The FDS2 database has been linked to these databases through the WA Data Linkage System (WADLS), as approved by the WA Department of Health Human Research Ethics Committee. The HMDC was used to supplement data obtained through FDS assessments relating to prevalent/prior complications/conditions during the five years prior to study entry. A prior history of ischaemic heart disease (IHD), cerebrovascular disease or heart failure (HF) were defined as hospitalisations or death with/for/of IHD, cerebrovascular disease or HF, respectively, before the first CAN assessment. Incident IHD was defined as hospitalisations or death with/for/of IHD or cardiac/sudden death, and incident HF as hospitalisations or death with/for/of HF, both endpoints being ascertained from the first CAN assessment to end-December 2021. Causes of death on the death certificate or coroner’s report were reviewed independently by two study physicians and classified under the system used in the UK Prospective Diabetes Study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In the case of discrepant coding, case notes were consulted and a consensus obtained. Death from IHD was defined as death from non-HF cardiac or sudden death, and death from HF was defined as cardiac death in which HF dominated. All endpoints were ascertained from the first CAN assessment to end-December 2021.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p id="Par32">The computer packages IBM SPSS Statistics 29 (IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY, USA) and StataSE 15 (College Station, TX: StataCorp LP) were used for statistical analysis. Data are reported as percentage, mean ± SD, geometric mean (SD range), or, when variables are not normally distributed, median [interquartile range]. Two-way comparisons were performed using Fisher’s exact test for independent samples, the normally distributed variables compared using Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test, and the non-normally distributed variables using Mann–Whitney U-test. Comparisons between multiple groups for categoric variables were by Fisher-Freeman-Halton exact or Chi-squared tests, for normally/log-normally distributed continuous variables by one-way ANOVA, and for variables not conforming to normal/log-normal distribution by Kruskal–Wallis test. Where the overall trend for these multiple comparisons was statistically significant, <italic>post-hoc</italic> Bonferroni-corrected pairwise comparisons were performed.</p>
                <p id="Par33">Multinomial regression was used to identify independent associates of CAN status with the no CAN group as reference. Clinically relevant and biologically plausible variables with bivariable <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.20 were considered for model entry. Variables were removed sequentially if <italic>P</italic> ≥ 0.050 for every CAN group (relative to the reference category), the least significant being removed first, until all variables in the model were significant in at least one group.</p>
                <p id="Par34">Cox proportional hazards modelling (backward conditional variable selection with <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.050 for entry and ≥ 0.050 for removal) was used to determine independent baseline predictors of incident HF and IHD, and all-cause mortality. All clinically plausible variables with bivariable <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.20 were considered for entry into these models in a backward stepwise manner and included demographic and diabetes-related factors, the presence of other complications and cardiovascular risk factors. Aboriginal status was also considered for entry since Aboriginal participants were significantly younger than other ethnic groups. After the most parsimonious model in each instance was defined, CAN status was entered. The proportional hazards assumption was assessed and, if violated, adjusted for by adding significant time-varying covariates. A two-tailed significance level of <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was used throughout.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Baseline participant characteristics</title>
                <p id="Par35">Of the 1254 FDS2 participants who underwent CAN testing at baseline, 86 (6.9%) were excluded because they were aged &lt; 20 years or &gt; 80 years and so their CART data could not be assessed against extrapolated age-specific normal ranges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Of the remaining 1168 participants, a further 338 (27.0%) were excluded because they could not perform all the tests according to protocol, they had poor quality electrocardiographic recordings that were unsuitable for analysis, or they had a significant cardiac arrhythmia that confounded interpretation of the results. Compared to the 830 with complete CART data required for CAN categorisation, the 424 who were excluded were significantly older (age 62.3 ± 10.5 versus 71.0 ± 10.6 years, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), less likely to be males (56.0% versus 45.8%, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), had longer diabetes duration (7.1 versus 11.2 years, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and were significantly more likely to have chronic complications (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1).</p>
                <p id="Par36">The baseline characteristics of included participants are summarised by CAN status in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Approximately 15% had definite CAN, one third had possible CAN and around one half had no CAN. Compared with the other two groups, those with definite CAN were more likely to have an Aboriginal background, to be diagnosed with diabetes at a younger age and to have longer diabetes duration, to be obese, and to have a higher HbA<sub>1c</sub> despite a greater likelihood of insulin therapy. They were also more likely to be treated with antidepressants, to have a higher resting pulse rate in the presence of greater beta blocker and calcium channel blocker use, to have hypertriglyceridemia and microalbuminuria, to have greater degrees of renal impairment, to have DSPN, and to have a prior history of IHD and HF. Those with possible CAN had diabetes duration, and prevalences of IHD and HF, that were intermediate between those in the no CAN and definite CAN groups.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of FDS2 participants categorised by CAN status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">No CAN</th><th align="left">Possible CAN</th><th align="left">Definite CAN</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">N (%)</td><td align="left">423 (51.0)</td><td align="left">280 (33.7)</td><td align="left">127 (15.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Orthostatic hypotension (%)</td><td align="left">12.3</td><td align="left">11.5</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.945</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">62.2 ± 10.5</td><td align="left">62.1 ± 10.2</td><td align="left">63.2 ± 11.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.555</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male (%)</td><td align="left">57.9</td><td align="left">54.6</td><td align="left">52.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.497</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education beyond primary level (%)</td><td align="left">92.3</td><td align="left">94.2</td><td align="left">90.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.366</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not fluent in English (%)</td><td align="left">6.6</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.946</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Ethnic background (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.053</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Anglo-Celt</td><td align="left">55.1</td><td align="left">51.4</td><td align="left">48.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Southern European</td><td align="left">10.6</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td align="left">10.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other European</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">8.9</td><td align="left">10.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asian</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">5.7</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal</td><td align="left">5.2</td><td align="left">10.0</td><td align="left">11.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mixed/other</td><td align="left">19.1</td><td align="left">12.9</td><td align="left">15.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Smoking status (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.262</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Never</td><td align="left">53.5</td><td align="left">50.9</td><td align="left">50.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ex-</td><td align="left">37.7</td><td align="left">36.5</td><td align="left">34.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Current</td><td align="left">8.8</td><td align="left">12.6</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Alcohol use (standard drinks<sup>a</sup>/day)</td><td align="left">0.3 [0–1.5]</td><td align="left">0.3 [0–1.5]</td><td align="left">0.1 [0–1.0]</td><td char="." align="char">0.455</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antidepressant use (%)</td><td align="left">10.6</td><td align="left">16.4</td><td align="left">24.4<sup>***</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tricyclic antidepressants</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">8.7<sup>*,†</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors</td><td align="left">6.1</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age at diabetes diagnosis (years)</td><td align="left">53.8 ± 11.0</td><td align="left">53.1 ± 10.7</td><td align="left">49.4 ± 13.9<sup>***,††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes duration (years)</td><td align="left">6.0 [2.6–11.9]</td><td align="left">8.0 [3.0–15.1]</td><td align="left">10.0 [4.0–17.2]<sup>***,†††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes treatment (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"><sup>***,†††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diet/exercise alone</td><td align="left">26.5</td><td align="left">22.7</td><td align="left">12.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Oral glucose lowering agents</td><td align="left">55.7</td><td align="left">55.6</td><td align="left">46.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin alone</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">8.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin + oral agents</td><td align="left">14.5</td><td align="left">19.1</td><td align="left">32.5</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (%)</td><td align="left">6.8 [6.2–7.8]</td><td align="left">6.9 [6.2–7.8]</td><td align="left">7.3 [6.6–8.4]<sup>***,††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (mmol/mol)</td><td align="left">50 [44–58]</td><td align="left">51 [44–61]</td><td align="left">57 [49–74]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fasting serum glucose (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">7.2 [6.3–8.6]</td><td align="left">7.4 [6.4–9.3]</td><td align="left">8.2 [6.7–10.3]<sup>***,†</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABSI (m<sup>11/6</sup> kg<sup>−2/3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.081 ± 0.005</td><td align="left">0.081 ± 0.005</td><td align="left">0.082 ± 0.005</td><td char="." align="char">0.051</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">31.2 ± 5.9</td><td align="left">32.4 ± 6.2<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">33.5 ± 7.1<sup>**</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heart rate (beats/min)</td><td align="left">69 ± 11</td><td align="left">70 ± 11</td><td align="left">74 ± 13<sup>***,††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine systolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">141 ± 19</td><td align="left">143 ± 21</td><td align="left">143 ± 22</td><td char="." align="char">0.478</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine diastolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">81 ± 11</td><td align="left">81 ± 11</td><td align="left">78 ± 14</td><td char="." align="char">0.071</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antihypertensive medication (%)</td><td align="left">66.0</td><td align="left">72.1</td><td align="left">78.7<sup>*</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors</td><td align="left">32.9</td><td align="left">33.6</td><td align="left">38.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.479</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin receptor blockers</td><td align="left">30.5</td><td align="left">36.4</td><td align="left">38.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.119</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Beta-blockers</td><td align="left">10.9</td><td align="left">21.4<sup>***</sup></td><td align="left">29.9<sup>***</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Calcium channel blockers</td><td align="left">16.8</td><td align="left">26.1<sup>**</sup></td><td align="left">36.2<sup>***</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diuretics</td><td align="left">20.1</td><td align="left">29.3<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">37.8<sup>***</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total serum cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">4.3 ± 0.9</td><td align="left">4.4 ± 1.1</td><td align="left">4.5 ± 1.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.215</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum HDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.21 ± 0.32</td><td align="left">1.16 ± 0.28</td><td align="left">1.17 ± 0.32</td><td char="." align="char">0.064</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum triglycerides (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.5 (0.9–2.4)</td><td align="left">1.6 (0.9–2.7)</td><td align="left">1.7 (1.1–2.8)<sup>**</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lipid-lowering medication (%)</td><td align="left">67.8</td><td align="left">67.5</td><td align="left">69.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.947</td></tr><tr><td align="left">uACR (mg/mmol)</td><td align="left">2.2 (0.7–6.7)</td><td align="left">2.9 (0.8–10.4)<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">5.2 (0.9–30.5)<sup>***,†††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR (mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">85 ± 17</td><td align="left">84 ± 20</td><td align="left">77 ± 23<sup>***,††</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR categories (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><sup>*</sup></td><td align="left"><sup>***,†</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ≥ 90 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">43.0</td><td align="left">47.9</td><td align="left">30.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 60–89 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">49.9</td><td align="left">39.6</td><td align="left">44.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 45–59 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">5.2</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left">13.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 30–44 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">4.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy (%)</td><td align="left">29.4</td><td align="left">32.1</td><td align="left">44.4<sup>**</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peripheral arterial disease (%)</td><td align="left">18.2</td><td align="left">20.1</td><td align="left">27.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.076</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior IHD hospitalisation (%)</td><td align="left">15.1</td><td align="left">23.2<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">32.3<sup>***</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior cerebrovascular disease hospitalisation (%)</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">4.6</td><td align="left">7.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior HF hospitalisation (%)</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">5.7<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">8.7<sup>**</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>1 standard drink = 10 U ethanol; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs no CAN, <sup>†</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>††</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <sup>†††</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs possible CAN in Bonferroni-corrected multiple comparisons</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="Par37">The independent associates of CAN group identified by multinomial modelling are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Compared to the group without CAN, those with possible or definite CAN were more likely to be treated with beta blockers, calcium channel blockers and antidepressants, and to have a history of HF. In addition, those with possible CAN were more likely to be Aboriginal, while those with definite CAN were had a higher BMI and resting pulse rate, longer diabetes duration, a greater uACR, and a higher likelihood of DSPN.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Independent associates of CAN category in FDS2 participants with type 2 diabetes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left">Possible CAN</th><th align="left">Definite CAN</th></tr><tr><th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">1.91 (1.01, 3.62)</td><td align="left">1.65 (0.72, 3.78)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes duration (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.01 (0.98, 1.03)</td><td align="left">1.05 (1.02, 1.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Body mass index (increase of 1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">1.02 (0.99, 1.05)</td><td align="left">1.04 (1.005, 1.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pulse rate (increase of 1 beat/min)</td><td align="left">1.01 (0.996, 1.03)</td><td align="left">1.04 (1.02, 1.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">On beta-blockers</td><td align="left">1.95 (1.24, 3.09)</td><td align="left">2.86 (1.60, 4.93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">On calcium channel blockers</td><td align="left">1.70 (1.15, 2.50)</td><td align="left">2.44 (1.47, 4.04)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">On antidepressant medication</td><td align="left">1.67 (1.06, 2.64)</td><td align="left">2.81 (1.60, 4.93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ln [urinary albumin:creatinine ratio (mg/mmol)]<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.09 (0.95, 1.24)</td><td align="left">1.29 (1.10, 1.53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.12 (0.79, 1.58)</td><td align="left">1.65 (1.04, 2.61)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for heart failure</td><td align="left">2.96 (1.11, 7.92)</td><td align="left">3.46 (1.15, 10.4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Multinomial regression was used with no prevalent CAN as the reference. Data are odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Values are provided for both CAN categories where variables were significant for at least category</p><p><sup>a</sup>A 2.72-fold increase in urinary albumin:creatinine ratio corresponds to an increased risk of 1 in ln(urinary albumin:creatinine)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Incident ischaemic heart disease</title>
                <p id="Par38">The characteristics of the 142 FDS2 participants (21.6%) who had an IHD event during follow-up and those who did not are summarised in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The Kaplan–Meier curves of IHD events during a mean ± SD follow-up period of 9.7 ± 3.2 (range 0.0–12.6) years (equivalent to 6354 person-years) are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> (upper panel). There was a statistically significant difference between the three groups (log rank test <italic>P</italic> = 0.030) with definite CAN significantly different from both the no CAN group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.009) and possible CAN group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.039) in unadjusted pairwise comparisons. In Cox proportional hazards modelling, longer diabetes duration, a higher heart rate and uACR, and DSPN were independent predictors of incident IHD events, but CAN category did not add significantly to the model (see Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of FDS2 participants with type 2 diabetes by incident IHD status, excluding those with pre-recruitment hospitalisation for/with IHD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">No hospitalisation for/with IHD or non-HF cardiac/sudden death</th><th align="left">Incident hospitalisation for IHD or non-HF cardiac/sudden death<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">N (%)</td><td align="left">516 (78.4)</td><td align="left">142 (21.6)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">CAN group (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.099</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> None</td><td align="left">55.6</td><td align="left">50.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">32.9</td><td align="left">31.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">11.4</td><td align="left">18.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">MCR (n = 658)</td><td align="left">21.4 [12.4–34.8]</td><td align="left">22.1 [11.9–31.0]</td><td char="." align="char">0.578</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E:I ratio (n = 658)</td><td align="left">1.13 [1.09–1.20]</td><td align="left">1.13 [1.08–1.18]</td><td char="." align="char">0.198</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Valsalva ratio (n = 642)</td><td align="left">1.51 [1.33–1.73]</td><td align="left">1.44 [1.28–1.58]</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30:15 Stand ratio (n = 657)</td><td align="left">1.16 [1.09–1.25]</td><td align="left">1.12 [1.07–1.21]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Orthostatic hypotension (%)</td><td align="left">14.8</td><td align="left">8.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.069</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">60.9 ± 10.5</td><td align="left">62.0 ± 10.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.257</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male (%)</td><td align="left">53.1</td><td align="left">54.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.705</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education beyond primary level (%)</td><td align="left">93.7</td><td align="left">92.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.702</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not fluent in English (%)</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td char="." align="char">&gt; 0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Ethnic background (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.046</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Anglo-Celt</td><td align="left">54.1</td><td align="left">50.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Southern European</td><td align="left">11.0</td><td align="left">10.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other European</td><td align="left">7.2</td><td align="left">7.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asian</td><td align="left">4.8</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal</td><td align="left">5.6</td><td align="left">14.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mixed/other</td><td align="left">17.2</td><td align="left">14.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Smoking status (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.225</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Never</td><td align="left">54.5</td><td align="left">46.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ex-</td><td align="left">34.9</td><td align="left">40.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Current</td><td align="left">10.6</td><td align="left">12.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Alcohol consumption (standard drinks<sup>a</sup>/day)</td><td align="left">0.3 [0–1.5]</td><td align="left">0.1 [0–0.8]</td><td char="." align="char">0.034</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antidepressant use (%)</td><td align="left">14.1</td><td align="left">15.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.687</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tricyclic antidepressants</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">4.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.267</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors</td><td align="left">8.9</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.394</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age at diabetes diagnosis (years)</td><td align="left">52.8 ± 11.2</td><td align="left">50.9 ± 12.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.076</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes duration (years)</td><td align="left">5.7 [2.6–13.0]</td><td align="left">10.0 [4.2–16.1]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes treatment (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diet/exercise</td><td align="left">25.5</td><td align="left">17.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">56.1</td><td align="left">53.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin alone</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin ± oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">15.6</td><td align="left">24.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (%)</td><td align="left">6.8 [6.2–7.6]</td><td align="left">7.1 [6.3–8.3]</td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (mmol/mol)</td><td align="left">51 [44–60]</td><td align="left">54 [45–67]</td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fasting serum glucose (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">7.3 [6.4–8.9]</td><td align="left">7.6 [6.5–10.6]</td><td char="." align="char">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABSI (m<sup>11/6</sup> kg<sup>−2/3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.080 ± 0.005</td><td align="left">0.082 ± 0.005</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">32.2 ± 6.2</td><td align="left">31.8 ± 7.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.502</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pulse rate (beats/min)</td><td align="left">70 ± 11</td><td align="left">73 ± 12</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine systolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">141 ± 20</td><td align="left">146 ± 20</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine diastolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">81 ± 12</td><td align="left">81 ± 13</td><td char="." align="char">0.851</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antihypertensive medication (%)</td><td align="left">64.3</td><td align="left">65.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.843</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors</td><td align="left">30.2</td><td align="left">33.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.539</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin receptor blockers</td><td align="left">31.2</td><td align="left">35.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.363</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Beta-blockers</td><td align="left">8.9</td><td align="left">9.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.743</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Calcium channel blockers</td><td align="left">20.2</td><td align="left">21.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.814</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diuretics</td><td align="left">24.0</td><td align="left">28.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.274</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total serum cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">4.3 ± 1.0</td><td align="left">4.5 ± 1.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.040</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum HDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.21 ± 0.33</td><td align="left">1.19 ± 0.29</td><td char="." align="char">0.534</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum triglycerides (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.5 (0.9–2.4)</td><td align="left">1.6 (1.0–2.7)</td><td char="." align="char">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lipid-lowering medication (%)</td><td align="left">64.1</td><td align="left">61.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.555</td></tr><tr><td align="left">uACR (mg/mmol)</td><td align="left">2.3 (0.7–7.5)</td><td align="left">4.1 (0.8–21.6)</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR (mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">86 ± 18</td><td align="left">82 ± 21</td><td char="." align="char">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR categories (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ≥ 90 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">47.2</td><td align="left">41.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 60–89 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">43.7</td><td align="left">44.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 45–59 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">6.0</td><td align="left">7.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 30–44 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy (%)</td><td align="left">28.7</td><td align="left">38.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peripheral arterial disease (%)</td><td align="left">17.9</td><td align="left">23.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.184</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for cerebrovascular disease (%)</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.073</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for HF (%)</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.264</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>1 standard drink = 10 U ethanol; <sup>b</sup>three participants with unknown cause of death excluded from this analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Kaplan–Meier plots of incident IHD, HF and all-cause mortality for FDS2 participants with no CAN (green square), possible CAN (red circle) and definite CAN (blue up-pointing triangle). <italic>P</italic>-values are from log-rank tests</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12933_2024_2185_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Most parsimonious Cox models of independent predictors of IHD, HF and all-cause death in the FDS2 cohort with CAN category defined (n = 830) and added</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">IHD (n = 651)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diabetes duration (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.02 (1.004, 1.04)</td><td char="." align="char">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Heart rate (increase of 1 beat/min)</td><td align="left">1.02 (1.005, 1.03)</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ln(uACR)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.21 (1.08, 1.35)</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.29 (1.05, 1.57)</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CAN category: none</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">0.96 (0.66, 1.41)</td><td char="." align="char">0.851</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">1.00 (0.60, 1.68)</td><td char="." align="char">0.993</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">HF (n = 788)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Age (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.05 (1.02, 1.07)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">2.79 (1.51, 5.18)</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diabetes duration (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.03 (1.01, 1.05)</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ln(uACR)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.33 (1.18, 1.49)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.49 (1.19, 1.85)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Peripheral arterial disease</td><td align="left">1.66 (1.11, 2.48)</td><td char="." align="char">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ischaemic heart disease</td><td align="left">1.95 (1.32, 2.88)</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CAN category: None</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">0.94 (0.61, 1.46)</td><td char="." align="char">0.789</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">1.27 (0.78, 2.06)</td><td char="." align="char">0.342</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">All-cause mortality (n = 827)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Age (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.07 (1.05, 1.09)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Male sex</td><td align="left">1.55 (1.12, 2.15)</td><td char="." align="char">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">8.82 (3.20, 24.3)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other European ethnic background</td><td align="left">0.36 (0.16, 0.79)</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Antidepressant therapy</td><td align="left">3.06 (1.29, 7.26)</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin receptor blocker use</td><td align="left">1.42 (1.03, 1.95)</td><td char="." align="char">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">2.82 (1.40, 5.69)</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.14 (0.94, 1.38)</td><td char="." align="char">0.174</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Cerebrovascular disease</td><td align="left">1.67 (1.03, 2.73)</td><td char="." align="char">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> HF</td><td align="left">2.42 (1.42, 4.13)</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CAN category: None</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">1.47 (1.01, 2.14)</td><td char="." align="char">0.046</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">2.42 (1.60, 3.67)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Time-varying covariates</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">0.42 (0.24, 0.75)</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Antidepressant therapy</td><td align="left">0.62 (0.39, 0.99)</td><td char="." align="char">0.047</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) are shown. The proportional hazards assumption was violated in the model for all-cause mortality but not for IHD or HF</p><p><sup>a</sup>A 2.72-fold increase in urinary albumin:creatinine ratio corresponds to an increased risk of 1 in ln(urinary albumin:creatinine)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Incident heart failure</title>
                <p id="Par39">The characteristics of the 119 FDS2 participants (15.0%) who had a HF event during follow-up and those who did not are summarised in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The Kaplan–Meier curves of HF events during a mean ± SD follow-up period of 10.1 ± 2.8 (range 0.0–12.6) years (equivalent to 7992 person-years) are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> (middle panel). There was a significant difference between the three groups (log rank test <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), with definite CAN different from both the no CAN group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and possible CAN group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.002) in unadjusted pairwise comparisons. In Cox proportional hazards modelling, increasing age, Aboriginal ethnic background, longer diabetes duration, a higher uACR, DSPN, PAD and a prior history of IHD were independent predictors of incident HF events but CAN category did not add significantly to the model (see Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of FDS2 type 2 diabetes participants attending for their first ANS examination between May 2009 and November 2012 by incident hospitalisation for/with heart failure or death from heart failure to 31 December 2021, excluding those with prior hospitalisation for/with heart failure</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">No hospitalisation for/with or death from HF</th><th align="left">Incident hospitalisation for/with or death from HF<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">N (%)</td><td align="left">675 (85.0)</td><td align="left">119 (15.0)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">CAN group (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> None</td><td align="left">53.8</td><td align="left">43.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">33.6</td><td align="left">31.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">12.6</td><td align="left">25.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">MCR (n = 794)</td><td align="left">21.3 [12.1–33.3]</td><td align="left">16.1 [7.9–25.3]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E:I ratio (n = 794)</td><td align="left">1.13 [1.08–1.19]</td><td align="left">1.11 [1.06–1.17]</td><td char="." align="char">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Valsalva ratio (n = 775)</td><td align="left">1.47 [1.31–1.68]</td><td align="left">1.38 [1.22–1.52]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30:15 Stand ratio (n = 794)</td><td align="left">1.15 [1.08–1.23]</td><td align="left">1.12 [1.06–1.18]</td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Orthostatic hypotension (%)</td><td align="left">12.5</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.223</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">61.4 ± 10.2</td><td align="left">66.5 ± 11.2</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male (%)</td><td align="left">56.4</td><td align="left">55.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education beyond primary level (%)</td><td align="left">93.2</td><td align="left">93.1</td><td char="." align="char">&gt; 0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not fluent in English (%)</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.425</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Ethnic background (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Anglo-Celt</td><td align="left">53.3</td><td align="left">50.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Southern European</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td align="left">9.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other European</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asian</td><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">15.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mixed/other</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td align="left">15.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Smoking status (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.306</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Never</td><td align="left">52.8</td><td align="left">51.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ex-</td><td align="left">37.2</td><td align="left">33.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Current</td><td align="left">10.0</td><td align="left">14.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Alcohol consumption (standard drinks<sup>a</sup>/day)</td><td align="left">0.3 [0–1.5]</td><td align="left">0.1 [0–0.8]</td><td char="." align="char">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antidepressant use (%)</td><td align="left">14.7</td><td align="left">15.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.889</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Tricyclic antidepressants</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">4.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.583</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors</td><td align="left">8.3</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.715</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Age at diabetes diagnosis (years)</td><td align="left">52.9 ± 11.0</td><td align="left">52.5 ± 13.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.764</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes duration (years)</td><td align="left">6.1 [2.9–13.1]</td><td align="left">14.0 [5.8–19.2]</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes treatment (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diet/exercise</td><td align="left">24.4</td><td align="left">16.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">56.0</td><td align="left">47.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin alone</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">6.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin ± oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">16.5</td><td align="left">29.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (%)</td><td align="left">6.9 [6.2–7.7]</td><td align="left">7.1 [6.4–8.2]</td><td char="." align="char">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (mmol/mol)</td><td align="left">52 [44–61]</td><td align="left">54 [46–66]</td><td char="." align="char">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fasting serum glucose (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">7.4 [6.5–9.1]</td><td align="left">7.5 [6.3–9.3]</td><td char="." align="char">0.805</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABSI (m<sup>11/6</sup> kg<sup>−2/3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.081 ± 0.005</td><td align="left">0.082 ± 0.005</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">31.9 ± 6.1</td><td align="left">31.6 ± 6.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.663</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pulse rate (beats/min)</td><td align="left">70 ± 11</td><td align="left">70 ± 13</td><td char="." align="char">0.573</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine systolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">141 ± 19</td><td align="left">150 ± 23</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine diastolic blood pressure (mmHg)</td><td align="left">81 ± 11</td><td align="left">80 ± 13</td><td char="." align="char">0.796</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antihypertensive medication (%)</td><td align="left">68.1</td><td align="left">77.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.052</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors</td><td align="left">31.9</td><td align="left">38.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Angiotensin receptor blockers</td><td align="left">32.9</td><td align="left">40.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.117</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Beta-blockers</td><td align="left">13.9</td><td align="left">26.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Calcium channel blockers</td><td align="left">20.9</td><td align="left">35.3</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diuretics</td><td align="left">24.1</td><td align="left">30.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total serum cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">4.3 ± 1.0</td><td align="left">4.4 ± 1.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.569</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum HDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.19 ± 0.30</td><td align="left">1.23 ± 0.35</td><td char="." align="char">0.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum triglycerides (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.5 (0.9–2.5)</td><td align="left">1.6 (0.9–2.8)</td><td char="." align="char">0.349</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lipid-lowering medication (%)</td><td align="left">66.7</td><td align="left">74.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.089</td></tr><tr><td align="left">uACR (mg/mmol)</td><td align="left">2.3 (0.7–7.1)</td><td align="left">5.9 (1.1–32.4)</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR (mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">85 ± 18</td><td align="left">79 ± 21</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR categories (%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ≥ 90 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">45.6</td><td align="left">31.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 60–89 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">45.2</td><td align="left">48.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 45–59 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">5.6</td><td align="left">12.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> &lt; 45 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy (%)</td><td align="left">30.3</td><td align="left">45.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peripheral arterial disease (%)</td><td align="left">16.8</td><td align="left">35.3</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for IHD (%)</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td align="left">36.1</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for cerebrovascular disease (%)</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">10.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>1 standard drink = 10 U ethanol; <sup>b</sup>two participants with unknown cause of death excluded from this analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>All-cause mortality</title>
                <p id="Par40">The characteristics of the 162 FDS2 participants (19.5%) who died during follow-up and those who did not are summarised in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>. The Kaplan–Meier curves of HF events during a mean ± SD follow-up period of 10.5 ± 2.4 (range 0.2–12.6) years (equivalent to 8,684 person-years) are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> (lower panel). There was a significant difference between the three groups (log rank test <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), with both possible (<italic>P</italic> = 0.015) and definite (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) CAN significantly different from the no CAN group, and possible CAN significantly different from definite CAN (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), in unadjusted pairwise comparisons. In Cox proportional hazards modelling, increasing age, male sex, Aboriginal descent, Other European ethnic background, use of antidepressant therapy and of angiotensin receptor blockers, an eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>, DSPN, and a prior history of both cerebrovascular disease and HF were independent predictors of mortality. CAN category added significantly to the model at the expense of DSPN (see Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of FDS2 participants with type 2 diabetes by all-cause mortality at end of follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Alive</th><th align="left">Deceased</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">668 (80.5)</td><td align="left">162 (19.5)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">CAN group (%)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> None</td><td align="left">54.6</td><td align="left">35.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Possible</td><td align="left">33.4</td><td align="left">35.2</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Definite</td><td align="left">12.0</td><td align="left">29.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">MCR (n = 830)</td><td align="left">21.5 [12.9–33.9]</td><td align="left">11.8 [6.8–23.7]</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E:I ratio (n = 830)</td><td align="left">1.13 [1.08–1.19]</td><td align="left">1.11 [1.06–1.15]</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Valsalva ratio (n = 809)</td><td align="left">1.47 [1.31–1.68]</td><td align="left">1.37 [1.22–1.51]</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30:15 Stand ratio (n = 829)</td><td align="left">1.15 [1.09–1.23]</td><td align="left">1.12 [1.05–1.18]</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Orthostatic hypotension (%)</td><td align="left">12.6</td><td align="left">8.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.220</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">60.9 ± 10.2</td><td align="left">68.0 ± 9.7</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male (%)</td><td align="left">54.3</td><td align="left">63.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.052</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education beyond primary level (%)</td><td align="left">93.3</td><td align="left">90.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.178</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not fluent in English (%)</td><td align="left">6.9</td><td align="left">6.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.862</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Ethnic background (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.093</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Anglo-Celt</td><td align="left">51.2</td><td align="left">59.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Southern European</td><td align="left">11.4</td><td align="left">8.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other European</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asian</td><td align="left">5.1</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Aboriginal/TSI</td><td align="left">7.6</td><td align="left">8.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mixed/other</td><td align="left">16.3</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Smoking status (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.359</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Never</td><td align="left">53.1</td><td align="left">48.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Ex-</td><td align="left">35.6</td><td align="left">41.8</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Current</td><td align="left">11.3</td><td align="left">10.1</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Alcohol consumption (standard drinks<sup>a</sup>/day)</td><td align="left">0.3 [0–1.2]</td><td align="left">0.1 [0–1.5]</td><td char="." align="char">0.106</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antidepressant use (%)</td><td align="left">13.5</td><td align="left">19.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TCAs</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">4.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.213</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> SSRIs</td><td align="left">7.9</td><td align="left">8.0</td><td char="." align="char"> &gt; 0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age at diabetes diagnosis (years)</td><td align="left">52.2 ± 11.0</td><td align="left">55.8 ± 12.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes duration (years)</td><td align="left">6.5 [3.0–14.0]</td><td align="left">11.0 [4.5–17.1]</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Diabetes treatment (%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.223</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diet/exercise</td><td align="left">23.6</td><td align="left">21.3</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">55.2</td><td align="left">50.0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin alone</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Insulin ± oral agents ± non-insulin injectables</td><td align="left">17.4</td><td align="left">24.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (%)</td><td align="left">6.9 [6.3–7.8]</td><td align="left">6.8 [6.3–7.7]</td><td char="." align="char">0.347</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (mmol/mol)</td><td align="left">52 [45–62]</td><td align="left">51 [45–61]</td><td char="." align="char">0.347</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fasting plasma glucose (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">7.4 [6.4–9.2]</td><td align="left">7.5 [6.2–9.0]</td><td char="." align="char">0.199</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABSI (m<sup>11/6</sup> kg<sup>−2/3</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.081 ± 0.005</td><td align="left">0.082 ± 0.005</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">32.1 ± 6.2</td><td align="left">31.3 ± 6.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.138</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pulse rate (bpm)</td><td align="left">70 ± 11</td><td align="left">70 ± 12</td><td char="." align="char">0.391</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine SBP (mmHg)</td><td align="left">142 ± 20</td><td align="left">145 ± 20</td><td char="." align="char">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Supine DBP (mmHg)</td><td align="left">81 ± 12</td><td align="left">79 ± 12</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left">On BP-lowering medication (%)</td><td align="left">67.5</td><td align="left">80.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ACE-I</td><td align="left">33.2</td><td align="left">37.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.357</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ARB</td><td align="left">31.1</td><td align="left">44.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Beta-blockers</td><td align="left">15.0</td><td align="left">27.2</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Calcium channel blockers</td><td align="left">20.7</td><td align="left">32.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Diuretics</td><td align="left">23.8</td><td align="left">34.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total serum cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">4.3 ± 1.0</td><td align="left">4.3 ± 1.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.840</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.19 ± 0.30</td><td align="left">1.19 ± 0.34</td><td char="." align="char">0.806</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Serum triglycerides (mmol/L)</td><td align="left">1.5 (0.9–2.6)</td><td align="left">1.5 (0.9–2.6)</td><td char="." align="char">0.958</td></tr><tr><td align="left">On lipid-lowering medication (%)</td><td align="left">67.2</td><td align="left">71.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.399</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Urinary albumin:creatinine ratio (mg/mmol)</td><td align="left">2.5 (0.7–9.3)</td><td align="left">3.9 (1.0–15.2)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">eGFR (mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">eGFR (CKD-EPI) stages (ml/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> ≥ 90</td><td align="left">46.8</td><td align="left">25.9</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 60–89</td><td align="left">45.2</td><td align="left">47.5</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 45–59</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">13.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 30–44</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> &lt; 30</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">5.6</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy (%)</td><td align="left">29.8</td><td align="left">44.1</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peripheral arterial disease (%)</td><td align="left">17.7</td><td align="left">30.9</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for IHD (%)</td><td align="left">16.8</td><td align="left">35.8</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for cerebrovascular disease (%)</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">11.7</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Prior hospitalisation for HF (%)</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">10.5</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>1 standard drink = 10 U ethanol</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec13">
                <title>Relationship between individual CAN tests and outcome</title>
                <p id="Par41">Individual CART test results were included as continuous variables in separate Cox models of the three outcomes in place of CAN category. This allowed use of data from participants of all ages and those whose incomplete CART testing precluded CAN categorisation. Two models for each variable were constructed, the first involved participants in whom CAN category was determined (n = 830) and the second utilised available data from the 1254 participants who underwent CAN testing. None of the CART variables was a significant predictor of incident IHD or HF after adjusting for the most parsimonious model. The results of analyses for all-cause mortality are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>. The proportional hazards assumption was violated in the model involving CAN-categorised participants, with the effects of Aboriginal descent and antidepressant therapy attenuating over time. For the second model, there were 1,101 participants with an MCR and E:I ratio (age range 17–95 years), 1100 with a 30:15 stand ratio (age range 17–95 years), and 904 with a Valsalva ratio (age range 17–89 years). The proportional hazards assumption was violated in this latter model, with the effect of age strengthening over time. In both models, MCR showed a significant inverse association with all-cause death.<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Most parsimonious Cox models of independent predictors of all-cause death in the FDS2 type 2 diabetes cohort with CAN category defined (n = 830) and valid CARTs variables as continuous variables added and retained if statistically significant (up to n = 1101)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">CAN category defined and valid CART results</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"> All-cause mortality (n = 827)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Age (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.06 (1.04, 1.08)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Male sex</td><td align="left">1.55 (1.12, 2.15)</td><td char="." align="char">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">8.95 (3.26, 24.6)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Other European background</td><td align="left">0.41 (0.19, 0.90)</td><td char="." align="char">0.026</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Antidepressant therapy</td><td align="left">3.40 (1.44, 8.00)</td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Angiotensin receptor blocker use</td><td align="left">1.38 (1.001, 1.89)</td><td char="." align="char">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">3.03 (1.51, 6.06)</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.15 (0.96, 1.39)</td><td char="." align="char">0.130</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Cerebrovascular disease</td><td align="left">1.70 (1.04, 2.77)</td><td char="." align="char">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  HF</td><td align="left">2.31 (1.36, 3.93)</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  MCR (increase of 1.0)</td><td align="left">0.98 (0.97, 0.99)</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"> Time-varying covariates</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">0.43 (0.24, 0.76)</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Antidepressant therapy</td><td align="left">0.57 (0.38, 0.98)</td><td char="." align="char">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Participants of all ages and valid CART results</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"> All-cause mortality (n = 1091)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Age (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.02 (0.998, 1.05)</td><td char="." align="char">0.070</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Male sex</td><td align="left">1.45 (1.13, 1.87)</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Aboriginal descent</td><td align="left">2.61 (1.58, 4.31)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Antidepressant therapy</td><td align="left">1.47 (1.08, 2.01)</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Ln(uACR)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.10 (1.004, 1.21)</td><td char="." align="char">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">3.20 (1.88, 5.44)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</td><td align="left">1.31 (1.09, 1.57)</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Peripheral arterial disease</td><td align="left">1.42 (1.09, 1.85)</td><td char="." align="char">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  HF</td><td align="left">1.67 (1.11, 2.50)</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  MCR (increase of 1.0)</td><td align="left">0.99 (0.98, 0.998)</td><td char="." align="char">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"> Time-varying covariates</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Age (increase of 1 year)</td><td align="left">1.03 (1.02, 1.05)</td><td char="." align="char"> &lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) are shown</p><p><sup>a</sup>A 2.72-fold increase in urinary albumin:creatinine ratio corresponds to an increased risk of 1 in ln (urinary albumin:creatinine)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec14">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par42">The present study involving representative, community-based people with type 2 diabetes followed for an average of 10 years, showed that definite CAN was significantly associated with incident IHD and HF compared to both no CAN and possible CAN in survival analyses. However, when CAN category was included in multivariable models of these two incident events, it did not add to other independent predictors. Survival analysis also showed that there was a graded increase in risk of all-cause mortality from no CAN through possible CAN to definite CAN which was observed in multivariable analysis after adjustment for confounders. The only individual CART test predictive of all-cause death was MCR. Taken together, these findings question the need for screening for CAN, as has been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], as part of routine care of type 2 diabetes, especially since the gold standard CART evaluation is demanding for both patients and staff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In addition, the present data suggest that around one-third of patients will either be ineligible because of age or they will, for various reasons, be unable to complete a valid CART assessment.</p>
              <p id="Par43">In a recent narrative review, the prevalence of CAN in type 2 diabetes was reported as between 31 and 73% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], but a subsequent Danish primary care study found a much lower prevalence of 9% after 6 years of screening-detected diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Our prevalence of definite CAN was intermediate between these values at 15.3%. Since almost all of the studies in the narrative review were conducted in secondary care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], it is likely that our community-based cohort had less at-risk participants than secondary care studies with referred patients but more than in a pure primary care context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The CAN risk factor profile in our FDS2 participants included independent variables that have been reported previously including BMI, longer diabetes duration, resting tachycardia (reflecting increased sympathetic tone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]), as well as a prior history of HF (another potential manifestation of sympathetic overactivity and neurohormonal dysregulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]). A previously recognised positive association with antidepressant use in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] was confirmed in the present case of type 2 diabetes. These considerations suggest that, despite the exclusion of FDS2 participants who were recruited before CAN testing was available as part of baseline assessment, those (largely elderly) whose CART data could not be assessed against reference ranges and those in whom valid CART data could not be collected, our final sample of 830 generated representative data and was amongst the larger of studies reporting CAN prevalence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par44">Our Kaplan–Meier analyses showed a significant relationship between CAN category and incident IHD. This was consistent with the results of a recent meta-analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] in which there was significant heterogeneity, reflecting a variety of sample sizes, participant sources including people with type 1 diabetes and those with type 2 diabetes selected for clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and methods of diagnosing CAN which ranged from full CARTs to change in heart rate on standing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and heart rate variability (HRV) and QT index on resting electrocardiography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Our multivariable analysis showed HRs for possible and definite CAN that were close to unity in the presence of other recognised predictors of incident IHD (longer diabetes duration, higher heart rate and increased uACR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]). It is possible that relatively intensive CVD risk factor management in FDS2 paralleling trends in other high income countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] (for example, approximately two-thirds of our participants were taking renin-angiotensin blocking drugs and statins) attenuated both the risk of CAN and its effect on CVD outcomes found in earlier studies, most of which were published before the first FDS2 patient was assessed for CAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In addition, we excluded participants with a history of IHD at baseline which may not have been the case in at least some of the studies with consequently higher risk samples in the meta-analysis, a consideration that may have contributed to the heterogeneity observed.</p>
              <p id="Par45">There are limited data assessing the relationship between CAN complicating type 2 diabetes and incident HF. In a report from the ACCORD trial involving trial participants with high CVD risk followed for a mean of 4.9 years, those with CAN defined from quartiles of HRV had a 2.7-fold greater risk of HF in adjusted analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In our community-based participants assessed using CART, there was a significant relationship between definite CAN and incident HF in Kaplan–Meier analysis, with a more than doubling of the risk at 10 years. However, as with incident IHD, multivariable analysis showed HRs for possible and definite CAN that were close to unity in the presence of other recognised significant independent predictors of incident HF (older age, Aboriginal descent, longer diabetes duration, higher uACR, DSPN, and prior IHD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. We hypothesise that relatively intensive CVD risk factor management in FDS2, especially the large proportion of our participants who were taking renin-angiotensin blocking drugs, contributed to the lack of a significant association in a cohort studied before the widespread availability in Australia of the newer blood glucose-lowering agents (sodium-glucose co-transporter-2 inhibitors and glucagon-like peptide 1 receptor agonists) with beneficial effects on HF. As with IHD, we also excluded those with a history of HF at baseline.</p>
              <p id="Par46">In both Kaplan–Meier and Cox proportional hazard analyses, there was a significant and graded relationship between CAN category and all-cause mortality, with definite CAN associated with a more than doubling of risk at 10 years after adjustment for the presence of other recognised significant independent predictors of death (increasing age, male sex, Aboriginal descent, antidepressant therapy, eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m<sup>2</sup>, DSPN, and prior cerebrovascular disease and HF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In a recent meta-analysis, the unadjusted risk ratio for death was more than three-fold increased in people with CAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. By far the largest contributor of participants and events in this study was the ACCORD trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] in which CAN was associated with a 1.55–2.14-fold risk of mortality after full adjustment for confounders, the risk ratio range reflecting three different methods of CAN ascertainment. However, the ACCORD participants were selected as having high CVD risk, the definition and staging of CAN was based on electrocardiographic indices with or without the presence of DSPN, and the follow-up duration was relatively short (3.5 years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Although these considerations complicate comparisons with the present study, the ACCORD findings are largely consistent with those of the present study.</p>
              <p id="Par47">The use of a representative, community-based sample in the present study may have masked sub-groups of people with type 2 diabetes in whom CAN has independent predictive value for IHD and HF. Such a sub-group may comprise those who are at high cardiovascular risk or who have established CVD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Nevertheless, in the Detection of Ischemia in Asymptomatic Diabetics (DIAD) study involving participants with type 2 diabetes without known heart disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], the incidence of the composite clinical outcome of cardiac death, acute coronary syndromes, HF, or coronary revascularization over 5 years was significantly increased in those in the lowest quartile of the Valsalva heart rate ratio (hazard ratio 1.60) amongst a range of tests of autonomic heart rate/blood pressure responses and power spectral analysis of HRV. The results of these studies should be interpreted against the heterogeneity in meta-analysis of prognostic studies of CAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] which highlights the influence of sample selection and CAN assessment methods. In addition, the duration of follow-up may be an important consideration since there is evidence that CART indices of autonomic dysfunction attenuate over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Our mean 10-year follow-up may have captured the effect of this on incident IHD and HF events compared to the ≤ 5 year follow-up in studies such as ACCORD and DIAD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par48">We found evidence that, of the individual CARTs performed, only reduced HRV as assessed from MCR was independently associated with all-cause mortality. MCR is one of the more robust CARTS as it is not influenced by changes in heart rate and presence of extrasystoles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. HRV has been shown to be a strong predictor of death in general population studies independently of cardiac or all-cause mortality and other clinical covariates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. It is a nonspecific predictor of mortality which reflects central-autonomic moment-to-moment adaption of somatic responses and emotional appraisal to maintain homeostasis and adapt to environmental stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In the context of diabetes, detection of a low HRV through measures such as MCR should prompt consideration of improved lifestyle factors including exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par49">The present study had limitations. As acknowledged, we excluded around one in 14 potentially eligible participants because of their age. Although we could have included them by using fixed thresholds for the various CART tests, as has been done in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], there are important effects of age and sex on CART reference ranges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In any case, we included CART results as continuous variables and found that they were not predictive of endpoints apart from MCR for all-cause death. The presence of orthostatic hypotension in addition to abnormal heart rate test results identifies severe or advanced CAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. However, probably due to the high percentage of our participants taking at least one antihypertensive medication (69.5%), a recognised confounding variable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], severe CAN was not an independent predictor in any of our multivariable analyses (data not shown). In addition, anaemia is a recognised complication of type 2 diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and can contribute to orthostatic hypotension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The major strengths of our study include its relatively large, community-based sample with rich phenotypic data, the use of gold standard CAN tests, and long follow-up for outcomes of interest.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec15">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="Par50">The present study has provided no evidence that either possible or definite CAN assessed by the range of recommended CARTs is an independent predictor of incident IHD or HF during relatively long-term follow-up in community-based people with type 2 diabetes. Possible and especially definite CAN were associated with all-cause mortality. There was evidence that this was mediated through a reduced MCR which has also been found to be a nonspecific adverse prognostic indicator in general population studies. Although the clinical value of routine assessment of CAN in type 2 diabetes is questionable as a result of our findings, the presence of CAN should still be established where typical symptoms (including light-headedness, weakness, palpitations and syncope on standing) or other features of autonomic neuropathy such as gastroparesis are present. The results could guide use of fludrocortisone and midodrine, and help tailor use of established therapies for CVD and glycaemic control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In resource-limited settings, or where there are physical impairments to full CART testing, single diagnostic tests could be employed such as heart rate variation on deep breathing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] or analysis of ten-second resting electrocardiographic tracings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <sec id="Sec16">
                <title>Supplementary Information</title>
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                    <media xlink:href="12933_2024_2185_MOESM1_ESM.docx">
                      <caption>
                        <p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Baseline characteristics of FDS2 type 2 diabetes participants attending their first ANS examination between May 2009 and November 2012 categorised by eligibility (valid CART data and aged 20 to 80 years old).</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ABSI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par5">A body shape index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ACCORD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Action to Control Cardiovascular Risk in Diabetes</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>BMI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Body mass index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CAN</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par8">Cardiac autonomic neuropathy</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CVD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par9">Cardiovascular disease</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CART</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par10">Cardiovascular reflex test</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CHD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par11">Coronary heart disease</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>DIAD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par12">Detection of Ischemia in Asymptomatic Diabetics</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>DSPN</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par13">Distal symmetrical polyneuropathy</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>eGFR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par14">Estimated glomerular filtration rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>E:I</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par15">Expiration to inspiration ratio</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>FDS2</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par16">Fremantle Diabetes Study Phase II</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HF</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par17">Heart failure</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HMDC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par18">Hospital Morbidity Data Collection</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IHD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par19">Ischaemic heart disease</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>MCR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par20">Mean circular resultant</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>WA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par21">Western Australia</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>WADLS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par22">WA Data Linkage System</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>The authors wish to thank the FDS2 staff, investigators and participants, the staff at the West Australian Data Linkage Branch, the Hospital Morbidity Data Collection, and the Registry for Births, Deaths and Marriages.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Author contributions</title>
              <p>TMED, the Principal Investigator of the FDS2, conceived the study, provided clinical interpretation and produced the final version of the manuscript. ET extracted CART data, participated in data analysis and produced the first draft of the manuscript. WAD, a Co-Investigator of the FDS2, co-ordinated statistical advice and edited the manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The present study was funded by the National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (project grants 513781 and 1042231). TMED is supported by a Medical Research Future Fund Practitioner Fellowship. The present analyses were supported by Australian Centre for Accelerating Diabetes Innovations. The funding bodies had no involvement in the study design, data collection, analysis and interpretation of results or writing this manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>Some outcome data supporting the findings of this study are available from the Western Australian Department of Health, but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under strict conditions of confidentiality for the current study, and so are not publicly available. Data are however available from the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of Western Australian Department of Health.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par51">The FDS2 protocol by the Human Research Ethics Committee of the Southern Metropolitan Area Health Service (reference 07/397). All participants gave written informed consent before study entry.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par52">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spallone</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freeman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernardi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frontoni</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stevens</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kempler</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hilsted</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tesfaye</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy in diabetes: clinical impact, assessment, diagnosis, and management</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab Res Rev</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>639</fpage>
                  <lpage>653</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dmrr.1239</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21695768?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21695768</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raheim</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>MI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rubab</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanagala</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brown</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alam</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiac autonomic neuropathy in type 1 and 2 diabetes: epidemiology, pathophysiology, and management</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Ther</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <fpage>1394</fpage>
                  <lpage>1416</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2022.09.002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 36272822?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36272822</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fisher</surname>
                      <given-names>VL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tahrani</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiac autonomic neuropathy in patients with diabetes mellitus: current perspectives</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
                  <lpage>434</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DMSO.S129797</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29062239?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29062239</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andersen</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Witte</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleischer</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andersen</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauritzen</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jorgensen</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jensen</surname>
                      <given-names>TS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Charles</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Risk factors for the presence and progression of cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy in type 2 diabetes: ADDITION-Denmark</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>2586</fpage>
                  <lpage>2594</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc18-1411</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30305347?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30305347</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boulton</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldman</surname>
                      <given-names>EL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bril</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freeman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malik</surname>
                      <given-names>RA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sosenko</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetic neuropathy: a position statement by the American Diabetes Association</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <lpage>154</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc16-2042</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27999003?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27999003</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stranieri</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abawajy</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelarev</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huda</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jelinek</surname>
                      <given-names>HF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An approach for Ewing test selection to support the clinical assessment of cardiac autonomic neuropathy</article-title>
                  <source>Artif Intell Med</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>58</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <lpage>193</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artmed.2013.04.007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23768975?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768975</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nevitt</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eleftheriadou</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kanagala</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Esa</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cuthbertson</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tahrani</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alam</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiac autonomic neuropathy and risk of cardiovascular disease and mortality in type 1 and type 2 diabetes: a meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>e002480</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjdrc-2021-002480</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34969689?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34969689</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Evans</surname>
                      <given-names>GW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gerstein</surname>
                      <given-names>HC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fonseca</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fleg</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoogwerf</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Genuth</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grimm</surname>
                      <given-names>RH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Corson</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prineas</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of cardiac autonomic dysfunction on mortality risk in the Action to Control Cardiovascular Risk in Diabetes (ACCORD) trial</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1578</fpage>
                  <lpage>1584</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc10-0125</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20215456?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20215456</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coresh</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Selvin</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Trends in Diabetes Treatment and Control in U.S. Adults, 1999–2018</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>384</volume>
                  <issue>23</issue>
                  <fpage>2219</fpage>
                  <lpage>2228</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa2032271</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34107181?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34107181</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ford</surname>
                      <given-names>ES</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Trends in the control of risk factors for cardiovascular disease among adults with diagnosed diabetes: findings from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 1999–2008*</article-title>
                  <source>J Diabetes</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <lpage>347</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1753-0407.2011.00148.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21767347?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21767347</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>WA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gregg</surname>
                      <given-names>EW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>TME</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Temporal trends in cardiovascular complications in people with or without type 2 diabetes: the Fremantle Diabetes Study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>105</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>e2471</fpage>
                  <lpage>e2482</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgaa215</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gregg</surname>
                      <given-names>EW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>YJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geiss</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albright</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imperatore</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Trends in cause-specific mortality among adults with and without diagnosed diabetes in the USA: an epidemiological analysis of linked national survey and vital statistics data</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>391</volume>
                  <issue>10138</issue>
                  <fpage>2430</fpage>
                  <lpage>2440</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30314-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 29784146?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29784146</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gregg</surname>
                      <given-names>EW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burrows</surname>
                      <given-names>NR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rolka</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>DE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geiss</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Changes in diabetes-related complications in the United States, 1990–2010</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>370</volume>
                  <issue>16</issue>
                  <fpage>1514</fpage>
                  <lpage>1523</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1310799</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 24738668?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24738668</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harding</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pavkov</surname>
                      <given-names>ME</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magliano</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaw</surname>
                      <given-names>JE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gregg</surname>
                      <given-names>EW</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global trends in diabetes complications: a review of current evidence</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetologia</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>16</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-018-4711-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30171279?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30171279</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bruce</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cohort profile: the Fremantle Diabetes Study</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>412</fpage>
                  <lpage>421</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dys065</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22544845?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544845</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Socio-economic indexes for areas. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abs.gov.au/websitedbs/censushome.nsf/home/seifa">http://www.abs.gov.au/websitedbs/censushome.nsf/home/seifa</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krakauer</surname>
                      <given-names>NY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krakauer</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anthropometrics, metabolic syndrome, and mortality hazard</article-title>
                  <source>J Obes</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>2018</volume>
                  <fpage>9241904</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9241904</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30123583?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30123583</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freeman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wieling</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Axelrod</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benditt</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benarroch</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biaggioni</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheshire</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chelimsky</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cortelli</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Consensus statement on the definition of orthostatic hypotension, neurally mediated syncope and the postural tachycardia syndrome</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Auton Res</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10286-011-0119-5</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21431947?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21431947</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Backlund</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bebu</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Braffett</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lorenzi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>NH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lachin</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soliman</surname>
                      <given-names>EZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Group</surname>
                      <given-names>DER</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Utility of using electrocardiogram measures of heart rate variability as a measure of cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy in type 1 diabetes patients</article-title>
                  <source>J Diabetes Investig</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <lpage>133</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdi.13635</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 34309223?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34309223</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pop-Busui</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Low</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waberski</surname>
                      <given-names>BH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albers</surname>
                      <given-names>JW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldman</surname>
                      <given-names>EL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sommer</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cleary</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lachin</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herman</surname>
                      <given-names>WH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of prior intensive insulin therapy on cardiac autonomic nervous system function in type 1 diabetes mellitus: the Diabetes Control and Complications Trial/Epidemiology of Diabetes Interventions and Complications study (DCCT/EDIC)</article-title>
                  <source>Circulation</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>119</volume>
                  <issue>22</issue>
                  <fpage>2886</fpage>
                  <lpage>2893</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.837369</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19470886?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470886</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ewing</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clarke</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of cardiovascular effects in diabetic autonomic neuropathy and prognostic implications</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <year>1980</year>
                  <volume>92</volume>
                  <issue>2_Part_2</issue>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <lpage>311</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-92-2-308</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 7356219?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7356219</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laux</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dannehl</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spuler</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muhlen</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mayer</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gries</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of cardiovascular autonomic function: age-related normal ranges and reproducibility of spectral analysis, vector analysis, and standard tests of heart rate variation and blood pressure responses</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetic Med</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <lpage>175</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.1992.tb01754.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 1563252?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1563252</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gelber</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dawson</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schumer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular autonomic nervous system tests: determination of normative values and effect of confounding variables</article-title>
                  <source>J Auton Nerv Syst</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>1–2</issue>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <lpage>44</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-1838(96)00107-5</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9021648?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9021648</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Risk M, Bril V, Broadbridge C, Cohen A. Heart rate variability measurement in diabetic neuropathy: review of methods. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2001; 3(1):63–76.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spallone</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bellavere</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scionti</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maule</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quadri</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bax</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Melga</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viviani</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Esposito</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morganti</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recommendations for the use of cardiovascular tests in diagnosing diabetic autonomic neuropathy</article-title>
                  <source>Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <lpage>78</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2010.07.005</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 21247746?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21247746</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levey</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bosch</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lewis</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Greene</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rogers</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roth</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A more accurate method to estimate glomerular filtration rate from serum creatinine: a new prediction equation. Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study Group</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>130</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>461</fpage>
                  <lpage>470</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-130-6-199903160-00002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10075613?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10075613</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>WA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>TME</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Temporal trends in distal symmetric polyneuropathy in type 2 diabetes: the Fremantle Diabetes Study</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>109</volume>
                  <fpage>e1083</fpage>
                  <lpage>e1094</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgad646</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holman</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bass</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rouse</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hobbs</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Population-based linkage of health records in Western Australia: development of a health services research linked database</article-title>
                  <source>Aust N Z J Public Health</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <lpage>459</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-842X.1999.tb01297.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 10575763?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10575763</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinik</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetic cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy</article-title>
                  <source>Circulation</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <lpage>397</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.634949</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17242296?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17242296</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>MX</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Milaneschi</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lamers</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nolte</surname>
                      <given-names>IM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Snieder</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dolan</surname>
                      <given-names>CV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penninx</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Geus</surname>
                      <given-names>EJC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The association of depression and anxiety with cardiac autonomic activity: the role of confounding effects of antidepressants</article-title>
                  <source>Depress Anxiety</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1163</fpage>
                  <lpage>1172</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22966</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31622521?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31622521</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Pop-Busui R, Braffett BH, Zinman B, Martin C, White NH, Herman WH, Genuth S, Gubitosi-Klug R, Group DER</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy and cardiovascular outcomes in the diabetes control and complications trial/epidemiology of diabetes interventions and complications (DCCT/EDIC) study</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <lpage>100</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc16-1397</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27803120</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>LH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wackers</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chyun</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davey</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barrett</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taillefer</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heller</surname>
                      <given-names>GV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iskandrian</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wittlin</surname>
                      <given-names>SD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Filipchuk</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiac outcomes after screening for asymptomatic coronary artery disease in patients with type 2 diabetes: the DIAD study: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>301</volume>
                  <issue>15</issue>
                  <fpage>1547</fpage>
                  <lpage>1555</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2009.476</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19366774?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19366774</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaze</surname>
                      <given-names>AD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuyun</surname>
                      <given-names>MF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Erqou</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fonarow</surname>
                      <given-names>GC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Echouffo-Tcheugui</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cardiac autonomic neuropathy and risk of incident heart failure among adults with type 2 diabetes</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Heart Fail</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>634</fpage>
                  <lpage>641</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejhf.2432</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 35064959?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35064959</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Woods</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katzenellenbogen</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davidson</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Heart failure among Indigenous Australians: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-12-99</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23116367?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23116367</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence, incidence and risk factors of chronic heart failure in the type 2 diabetic population: systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Curr Diabetes Rev</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <lpage>184</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157339909788920938</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19689252?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19689252</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McAullay</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>WA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bruce</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characteristics and outcome of type 2 diabetes in urban Aboriginal people: the Fremantle Diabetes Study</article-title>
                  <source>Intern Med J</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <lpage>63</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1445-5994.2006.01247.x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 17199846?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17199846</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raghavan</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vassy</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ho</surname>
                      <given-names>YL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gagnon</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cho</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>PWF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phillips</surname>
                      <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetes mellitus-related all-cause and cardiovascular mortality in a national cohort of adults</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>e011295</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.118.011295</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 30776949?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30776949</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Dooren</surname>
                      <given-names>FE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nefs</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schram</surname>
                      <given-names>MT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verhey</surname>
                      <given-names>FR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Denollet</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pouwer</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Depression and risk of mortality in people with diabetes mellitus: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>e57058</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057058</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23472075?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23472075</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chyun</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wackers</surname>
                      <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inzucchi</surname>
                      <given-names>SE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jose</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weiss</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davey</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heller</surname>
                      <given-names>GV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Iskandrian</surname>
                      <given-names>AE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>LH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Investigators</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Autonomic dysfunction independently predicts poor cardiovascular outcomes in asymptomatic individuals with type 2 diabetes in the DIAD study</article-title>
                  <source>SAGE Open Med</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>2050312114568476</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2050312114568476</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26770763?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26770763</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinberg</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An improved method for measuring heart-rate variability: assessment of cardiac autonomic function</article-title>
                  <source>Biometrics</source>
                  <year>1984</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>855</fpage>
                  <lpage>861</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2530931</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 6518250?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6518250</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jarczok</surname>
                      <given-names>MN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weimer</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Braun</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Williams</surname>
                      <given-names>DP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thayer</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gundel</surname>
                      <given-names>HO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balint</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Heart rate variability in the prediction of mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of healthy and patient populations</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
                  <year>2022</year>
                  <volume>143</volume>
                  <fpage>104907</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2022.104907</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 36243195?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36243195</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thayer</surname>
                      <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahs</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fredrikson</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sollers</surname>
                      <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                      <suffix>3rd</suffix>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wager</surname>
                      <given-names>TD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A meta-analysis of heart rate variability and neuroimaging studies: implications for heart rate variability as a marker of stress and health</article-title>
                  <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>747</fpage>
                  <lpage>756</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2011.11.009</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 22178086?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22178086</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamasaki</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of exercise on cardiovascular autonomic nervous function in patients with diabetes: a systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>Healthcare (Basel)</source>
                  <year>2023</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>19</issue>
                  <fpage>2668</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/healthcare11192668</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 37830705?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37830705</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soedamah-Muthu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Witte</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stevens</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Porta</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fuller</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relationship between risk factors and mortality in type 1 diabetic patients in Europe: the EURODIAB Prospective Complications Study (PCS)</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1360</fpage>
                  <lpage>1366</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc08-0107</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18375412?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18375412</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Low</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Denq</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Opfer-Gehrking</surname>
                      <given-names>TL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dyck</surname>
                      <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                      <given-names>PC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slezak</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of age and gender on sudomotor and cardiovagal function and blood pressure response to tilt in normal subjects</article-title>
                  <source>Muscle Nerve</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <fpage>1561</fpage>
                  <lpage>1568</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4598(199712)20:12&lt;1561::AID-MUS11&gt;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 9390669?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9390669</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gauci</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hunter</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bruce</surname>
                      <given-names>DG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>WA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>TME</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Anemia complicating type 2 diabetes: prevalence, risk factors and prognosis</article-title>
                  <source>J Diabetes Complications</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <fpage>1169</fpage>
                  <lpage>1174</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2017.04.002</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28433448?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28433448</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impaired orthostatic blood pressure stabilization and reduced hemoglobin in chronic kidney disease</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>1317</fpage>
                  <lpage>1324</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.13658</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 31471946?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31471946</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
