<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:22:10Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8693229" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8693229</identifier>
        <datestamp>2022-01-10</datestamp>
        <setSpec>jamasd</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8693229</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8693229</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8693229</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932104</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932104</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.40071</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi211125</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="online-only">
                  <subject>Online Only</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area">
                  <subject>Cardiology</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>The Effects of Implementing a Mobile Health–Technology Supported Pathway on Atrial Fibrillation–Related Adverse Events Among Patients With Multimorbidity</article-title>
                <subtitle>The mAFA-II Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Effects of Mobile Health Technology on AF-Related Adverse Events Among Patients with Multimorbidity</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Effects of Mobile Health Technology on AF-Related Adverse Events Among Patients with Multimorbidity</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yao</surname>
                    <given-names>Yuan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Guo</surname>
                    <given-names>Yutao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lip</surname>
                    <given-names>Gregory Y. H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="zoi211125aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <on-behalf-of>for the mAF-App II Trial investigators</on-behalf-of>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="zoi211125aff1"><label>1</label>Institute for Hospital Management Research, Chinese PLA General Hospital, Beijing, China</aff>
              <aff id="zoi211125aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pulmonary Vessel and Thrombotic Disease, Medical School of Chinese PLA, Chinese PLA General Hospital, Beijing, China</aff>
              <aff id="zoi211125aff3"><label>3</label>Liverpool Centre for Cardiovascular Sciences, University of Liverpool, Liverpool Heart &amp; Chest Hospital, Liverpool, United Kingdom</aff>
              <aff id="zoi211125aff4"><label>4</label>Aalborg Thrombosis Research Unit, Department of Clinical Medicine, Aalborg University, Aalborg, Denmark</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <title>Article Information</title>
                <p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> October 18, 2021.</p>
                <p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> December 21, 2021. <?xpp bx;1?>doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.40071</uri></p>
                <p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2021 Yao Y et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p>
                <corresp id="zoi211125cor1"><bold>Corresponding Authors:</bold> Yutao Guo, MD, PhD, Department of Pulmonary Vessel and Thrombotic Disease, Chinese PLA General Hospital, Five Fucheng Road, Beijing 100048, China (<email xlink:href="dor_guoyt@hotmail.com">dor_guoyt@hotmail.com</email>); Gregory Y. H. Lip, MD, Liverpool Centre for Cardiovascular Sciences, University of Liverpool, Liverpool Heart &amp; Chest Hospital, William Henry Duncan Building, Liverpool L69 7TX, United Kingdom (<email xlink:href="gregory.lip@liverpool.ac.uk">gregory.lip@liverpool.ac.uk</email>).</corresp>
                <p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Drs Yao and Guo had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Drs Yao and Guo contributed equally to this manuscript.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Guo, Lip.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Guo, Lip.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Yao, Guo.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Guo.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Yao, Guo.</p>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Guo, Lip.</p>
                <p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Lip reported consulting for Bayer/Janssen Pharmaceuticals, BMS/Pfizer, Medtronic, Boehringer Ingelheim, Novartis, Verseon, and Daiichi-Sankyo and receiving speaking fees from Bayer, BMS/Pfizer, Medtronic, Boehringer Ingelheim, and Daiichi-Sankyo outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
                <p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This research project was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (H2501). This study was an investigator-initiated project, with limited funding by independent research and educational grants.</p>
                <p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
                <p><bold>Group Information:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI211125-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p>
                <p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI211125-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 4</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Our sincere thanks to all participants in the Mobile Health Technology for Improved Screening and Optimized Integrated Care in Atrial Fibrillation program for their contributions.</p>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-12-21T10:00">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.-->
              <volume>4</volume>
              <issue>12</issue>
              <elocation-id>e2140071</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2021 Yao Y et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2140071.pdf</self-uri>
              <self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.40071"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="key-points">
                <title>Key Points</title>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-1">
                  <title>Question</title>
                  <p>Does implementing mobile health technology–supported integrated care reduce atrial fibrillation (AF)–related adverse events in patients with multimorbidity?</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-2">
                  <title>Findings</title>
                  <p>In this prespecified ancillary analysis of data that included 1890 adults with AF and multimorbidity, mobile health–supported integrated care reduced the composite outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization, irrespective of age, sex, and prior stroke.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-3">
                  <title>Meaning</title>
                  <p>In this study, an integrated care approach supported by mobile health technology reduced cardiovascular adverse events for older patients with AF and multimorbidity.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic">
                <p>This randomized clinical trial evaluates whether implementation of the integrated Atrial Fibrillation Better Care (ABC) pathway, supported by mobile health technology, reduces atrial fibrillation–related adverse events in patients with multimorbidity.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-4">
                  <title>Importance</title>
                  <p>The Mobile Health Technology for Improved Screening and Optimized Integrated Care in Atrial Fibrillation (mAFA-II) trial is a prospective cluster randomized trial that found a significant reduction in the composite clinical outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization among patients with atrial fibrillation (AF) who used a mobile health (mHealth) technology that implemented the Atrial Fibrillation Better Care (ABC) pathway (ie, A, anticoagulation/avoid stroke; B, better symptom control; and C, cardiovascular disease and comorbidity management) compared with those receiving usual care. Multimorbidity (defined as ≥2 chronic long-term conditions) is common in older patients with AF, but the impact of integrated or holistic care (based on the ABC pathway) on clinical outcomes in this population is uncertain.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-5">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To evaluate whether implementation of the integrated ABC pathway, supported by mHealth technology, would reduce AF-related adverse events in patients with multimorbidity.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-6">
                  <title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title>
                  <p>This prespecified ancillary analysis of data from the extended follow-up of the mAFA II trial was conducted between June 2018 and April 2021. Adult patients with AF were included in the analysis if they had at least 2 comorbidities. Participants were enrolled across 40 centers in China.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-7">
                  <title>Intervention</title>
                  <p>Integrated care supported by mHealth technology (mAFA intervention) vs usual care.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-8">
                  <title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title>
                  <p>The main outcome was the composite outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization. Cox proportional hazard modeling was performed for adverse outcomes after adjusting for cluster effect and baseline risk factors.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-9">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Of 1890 patients, 833 (mean [SD] age, 72.0 [12.0] years; 278 [33.4%] women) with multimorbidity were allocated to the intervention group (ABC pathway), with a mean (SD) follow-up of 419 (257) days, and 1057 patients (mean [SD] age, 72.8 [13.0] years; 443 [41.9%] women) with multimorbidity were allocated to usual care, with a mean (SD) follow-up of 457 (154) days. Compared with usual care, the composite outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization was significantly reduced in the intervention group (hazard ratio [HR], 0.37; 95% CI, 0.26-0.53; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001), as were rehospitalizations alone (HR, 0.42; 95% CI, 0.27-0.64; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). For the C criterion of the ABC pathway, rates of acute coronary syndrome, heart failure, and uncontrolled blood pressure during follow-up were lower in the intervention group than the usual care group (27 patients [3.2%] vs 145 patients [13.7%]; HR, 0.29; 95% CI, 0.19-0.45; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Subgroup analyses by age, prior stroke, and sex demonstrated consistently lower HRs for the primary composite outcome and rehospitalization for patients with AF allocated to the intervention group compared with patients receiving usual care.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-10">
                  <title>Conclusions and Relevance</title>
                  <p>In this study, mHealth technology–based integrated care that facilitated the implementation of the ABC pathway reduced meaningful clinical adverse events in older patients with AF and multimorbidity vs usual care.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="ab-zoi211125-11">
                  <title>Trial Registration</title>
                  <p>WHO International Clinical Trials Registry Platform (ICTRP) Registration number: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn/showprojen.aspx?proj=24191" ext-link-type="uri">ChiCTR-OOC-17014138</ext-link></p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="H1-1-ZOI211125">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common type of cardiac arrhythmia worldwide, and it is associated with many other cardiac and noncardiac chronic conditions. For example, one-third of patients with AF have at least 3 associated chronic diseases, including cancer, hematological disorders, and immunological disorders.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> With AF, we are also dealing with a common chronic condition in which associated comorbidities lead to higher risks of hospitalization, impaired quality of life, the development of heart failure, and dementia. In a retrospective analysis of the AF Follow-up Investigation of Rhythm Management (AFFIRM) trial, multimorbidity (AF plus ≥2 chronic long-term conditions) was present in 54.4% of patients.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Appropriate AF care requires attention to comorbidities associated with AF, which often occur in clusters rather than as isolated risk factors.</p>
              <p>The various AF-related clinical sequelae, symptoms, and complications have a major impact on health care resources.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> A considerable part of the health care budget is used by noncardiovascular hospitalizations, which have remained almost unchanged over the years and are likely to increase substantially over the next decades.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> The high multimorbidity associated with AF also has implications for uptake of evidence-based therapies, eg, stroke prevention, despite their higher inherent cardiovascular and stroke risks.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Unsurprisingly, the number and types of multimorbidity in patients with AF has been linked to worse outcomes, including higher incidence of stroke, death, and major bleeding.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <p>The Mobile Health Technology for Improved Screening and Optimized Integrated Care in AF (mAFA-II) trial was a prospective cluster randomized trial that investigated the implementation of holistic or integrated care in patients with AF using mobile health (mHealth) technology implementing the AF Better Care (ABC) pathway,<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> in which A indicates anticoagulation/avoid stroke; B, better symptom control; and C, cardiovascular disease and comorbidity management. In the primary analysis of the mAFA-II trial, the rates of the composite outcome of ischemic stroke or systemic thromboembolism, death, and rehospitalization were lower in the mAFA intervention group compared with the usual care group.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The mAFA program also included awareness, screening, and detection of AF (the Huawei Heart Study),<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> followed by a structured management program. This program required used of a mobile application installed on a smartphone and interactions with the mAFA network of researchers to implement the ABC pathway.</p>
              <p>Given that multimorbidity (defined as ≥2 chronic long-term conditions) is common in older patients with AF, the impact of mHealth-facilitated holistic or integrated care on clinical outcomes is uncertain. The objective of the present ancillary analysis from continued follow-up of the mAFA-II trial was to evaluate whether implementation of an mHealth technology–supported ABC Pathway would reduce AF-related adverse events in patients with multimorbidity.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-2-ZOI211125">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>The design and results of the mAFA-II trial have been previously published.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The trial protocol appears in <xref rid="note-ZOI211125-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>. The study was approved by the Central Medical Ethic Committee of Chinese PLA General Hospital and by local institutional review boards. The study followed Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" ext-link-type="uri">CONSORT</ext-link>) reporting guideline and complied with the Declaration of Helsinki,<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and all patients gave written informed consent. In brief, 1646 patients with AF were allocated to the mAFA intervention (mean age, 67.0 years; 38.0% women) and compared with 1678 patients allocated to usual care. Rates of the composite outcome of ischemic stroke or systemic thromboembolism, death, and rehospitalization were significantly lower with the mAFA intervention compared with usual care (hazard ratio [HR], 0.39; 95% CI, 0.22-0.67; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001), largely because of lower hospitalization rates.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Patients aged 18 years or older, diagnosed with new-onset, paroxysmal, persistent, or permanent AF confirmed with electrocardiogram or 24-hour Holter monitors were included, while patients younger than 18 years of age, those with mechanical prosthetic valve or moderate or severe mitral stenosis, those unable to provide informed consent, or those unable to be followed up for 1 year for any reason were excluded.</p>
              <p>To investigate the value of using the ABC pathway mAFA intervention in AF patients with multimorbidity (≥2 comorbidities, including hypertension, coronary artery disease, heart failure [HF], cardiomyopathy, peripheral arterial disease, diabetes, liver or kidney dysfunction, pulmonary disease, prior stroke), we studied those participating in the mAFA-II trial between June 1, 2018, and April 1, 2020, across 40 centers in China (<xref rid="zoi211125f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). For the mHealth-supported ABC pathway, we defined the components as follows: the A-criterion intervention was performed through regular stroke and bleeding risk assessment and reassessment, dose adjustments based on dynamic evaluation of kidney and liver function, and changes in therapeutic range if appropriate. The B-criterion intervention was carried out with patient-centered symptom-directed management, and AF symptoms were evaluated using the European Heart Rhythm Association classification and assessment.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Antiarrhythmic drugs or rate control therapies based on guidelines on AF management were proposed based on patient’s reported AF symptoms. Third, the C-criterion intervention was achieved through proactive management of comorbidities, eg, optimized treatment on monitoring blood pressure. Patients in the usual care clusters received management based on local clinical practice.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zoi211125f1" fig-type="figure">
                <label>Figure 1. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Flowchart of Patients Included in the Mobile Health Technology for Improved Screening and Optimized Integrated Care in Atrial Fibrillation Trial</title>
                  <p>Included participants were patients with atrial fibrillation (AF) and multimorbidity, ie, at least 2 comorbidities, including hypertension, coronary artery disease, heart failure, cardiomyopathy, peripheral arterial disease, diabetes, liver or kidney dysfunction, pulmonary disease, and prior stroke. mAFA indicates mobile atrial fibrillation application.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-g001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <sec id="H2-1-ZOI211125">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>Baseline characteristics for continuous variables are summarized as means and SDs. Frequencies and percentages per group as well as HRs with 95% CIs are reported for binary outcomes. We used Cox proportional hazard modeling after adjusting for cluster effect and baseline risk factors to analyze the primary composite outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization.</p>
                <p>Outcomes in relation to components of the ABC Pathway were assessed as follows. For the A criterion, thromboembolism (ischemic stroke and other systemic thromboembolism) and bleeding events (intracranial bleeding and extracranial bleeding) were analyzed, after adjustment of baseline risk factors. Extracranial bleeding events included gastrointestinal, urogenital, skin, eye bleeding, and other nonmajor bleeding. For the B criterion, recurrent AF and its related symptoms (eg, palpitation) were assessed after adjustment of baseline risk factors. For the C criterion, the occurrence of acute coronary syndromes, HF, and uncontrolled blood pressure during the follow-up period was assessed, after adjusting confounders. Subgroup analyses for the primary composite outcome and secondary outcomes (thromboembolism) were conducted by age, sex, and prior stroke (as secondary stroke prevention) after adjusting for baseline risk factors.</p>
                <p>All statistical tests were done using the nominal <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 significance level, and tests were 2-tailed. All statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS statistical software version 22.0 (IBM Corp) and MedCalc version 19.0.4 (MedCalc Software).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-3-ZOI211125">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Of 1890 patients, 833 patients (mean [SD] age, 72.0 [12.0] years; 278 [33.4%] women) with multimorbidity were allocated to the intervention group (ABC pathway), with a mean (SD) follow-up of 419 (257) days (median [IQR], 309 [203-763] days), and 1057 patients (mean [SD] age 72.8 [13.0] years; 443 [41.9%] women) with multimorbidity were allocated to usual care, with a mean (SD) follow-up of 457 (154) days (median [IQR], 478 [355-561] days). Baseline characteristics are shown in <xref rid="zoi211125t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, and treatments by group appear in the eTable in <xref rid="note-ZOI211125-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zoi211125t1">
                <label>Table 1. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Baseline Characteristics of Patients With AF and at Least 2 Comorbidities Included in the mAFA Intervention and Usual Care Groups</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="59.4%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="23.61%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="16.99%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                      <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Patients, No. (%)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">mAFA intervention (n = 833)</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Usual care (n = 1057)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), y</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0 (12.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8 (13.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (33.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443 (41.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">555 (67.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">667 (58.1)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoking</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (12.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (13.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical history</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">676 (81.1)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">797 (75.4)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Systolic blood pressure &gt;160 mm Hg</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (11.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (8.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CAD</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">523 (62.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">763 (72.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331 (39.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 (34.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pulmonary disease<xref rid="zoi211125t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (31.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274 (25.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PAD</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (28.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (18.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prior ischemic stroke or other TE</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (27.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338 (32.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart failure</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (19.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215 (20.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prior bleeding</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (9.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (8.1)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dilated or hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (5.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (6.3)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF type</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> New onset</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (10.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (6.7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Paroxysmal</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394 (47.3)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351 (33.2)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Persistent</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (25.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (32.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Long-standing</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (2.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (12.7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Permanent</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (3.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (10.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (11.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (3.9)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior AF treatment</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pharmacy cardioversion</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204 (24.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (11.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Electrical cardioversion</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (1.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AF ablation</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (13.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (7.7)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHA<sub>2</sub>DS<sub>2</sub>-VASc score, mean (SD)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAS-BLED score, mean (SD)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.0)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <p>Abbreviations: AF, atrial fibrillation; CAD, coronary artery disease; CHA<sub>2</sub>DS<sub>2</sub>-VASc, chronic heart failure, hypertension, older than 75 years, diabetes, stroke, vascular disease, aged 65 to 74 years, sex; HAS-BLED, hypertension, abnormal kidney/liver function, stroke, bleeding history or predisposition, labile international normalized ratio, elderly, drugs/alcohol concomitantly; mAFA, mobile atrial fibrillation application; PAD, peripheral arterial disease; TE, thromboembolism.</p>
                  <fn id="zoi211125t1n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Pulmonary diseases include obstructive sleep apnea hypopnea syndrome, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and pulmonary hypertension.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Compared with usual care, the composite outcome of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization was significantly reduced in the intervention group compared with the usual care group (HR, 0.37; 95% CI, 0.26-0.53; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001), as were rehospitalizations alone (HR, 0.42; 95% CI, 0.27-0.64; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). The difference between groups for all-cause death was not statistically significant (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.27-1.00; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .06) (<xref rid="zoi211125t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="zoi211125f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zoi211125t2">
                <label>Table 2. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Clinical Outcomes in the mAFA and Usual Care Groups</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <col width="41.35%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="12.23%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="14.78%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="21.27%" span="1"/>
                  <col width="10.37%" span="1"/>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome</th>
                      <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Patients, No. (%)</th>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">mAFA vs usual care, HR (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi211125t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
                      <th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">mAFA (n = 833)</th>
                      <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Usual care (n = 1057)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A criterion: anticoagulation/avoid stroke</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thromboembolism</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Any</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (2.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.05-0.51)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ischemic stroke</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.16-1.85)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.33</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other systemic thromboembolism</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (1.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bleeding events</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Any</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (2.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (4.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.36-1.11)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intracranial</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.8)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Extracranial<xref rid="zoi211125t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (2.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (3.6)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.44-1.40)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.41</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B criterion: better symptom control</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Reported recurrent AF symptoms, eg, palpitations</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (6.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (8.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.56-1.20)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C criterion: cardiovascular risk factor and comorbidity management</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Composite of acute coronary syndrome, HF, and uncontrolled blood pressure</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (3.2)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (13.7)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.19-0.45)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> All-cause death</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (1.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (4.5)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.27-1.00)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rehospitalization<xref rid="zoi211125t2n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (4.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (11.0)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.27-0.64)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Composite outcome of ischemic stroke or thromboembolism, death, and rehospitalization</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (5.9)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (18.4)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 (0.26-0.53)</td>
                      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <p>Abbreviations: AF, atrial fibrillation; HF, heart failure; HR, hazard ratio; mAFA, mobile atrial fibrillation application; NA, not applicable.</p>
                  <fn id="zoi211125t2n1">
                    <label>
                      <sup>a</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>After adjustment of cluster effect, age, comorbidities, AF type, and prior AF treatment, the effect of mAFA intervention on the clinical events was assessed.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="zoi211125t2n2">
                    <label>
                      <sup>b</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Extracranial bleeding included gastrointestinal, urogenital, skin, eye bleeding, and other nonmajor bleeding.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="zoi211125t2n3">
                    <label>
                      <sup>c</sup>
                    </label>
                    <p>Reasons for rehospitalization included any cause for AF, HF, thromboembolism, major bleeding, artery coronary disease, and other cardiovascular disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig position="float" id="zoi211125f2" fig-type="figure">
                <label>Figure 2. </label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Hazard Ratios of Clinical Events, Adjusted for Baseline Risk Factors</title>
                  <p>B criterion was assessed by reported recurrent atrial fibrillation symptoms, eg, palpitations. C criterion was assessed by the occurrence of acute coronary syndrome, heart failure, or uncontrolled blood pressure during the follow-up period. IS indicates ischemic stroke; mAFA, mobile atrial fibrillation application; and TE, thromboembolism.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-g002" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>Rates of stroke or thromboembolism were lower with the mAFA intervention vs usual care (4 [0.5%] vs 31 [2.9%]; HR, 0.17; 95% CI, 0.05-0.51; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .002), with no significant difference in bleeding (HR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.36-1.11; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .11) (<xref rid="zoi211125t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The mAFA intervention led to less frequent occurrence of acute coronary syndrome, HF, and uncontrolled blood pressure during the follow-up period (27 [3.2%] vs 145 [13.7%], HR, 0.29; 95% CI, 0.19-0.45; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) (<xref rid="zoi211125t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There were no significant differences in AF symptoms between mAFA and usual care in this group with multimorbidity (<xref rid="zoi211125t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
              <sec id="H2-2-ZOI211125">
                <title>Subgroup Analyses</title>
                <p>Subgroup analyses by age, prior stroke, and sex demonstrated consistently lower HRs for the primary composite outcome and rehospitalization for patients allocated to the mAFA intervention vs patients receiving usual care (<xref rid="zoi211125f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The mAFA intervention reduced the risk of the primary composite of stroke or thromboembolism, all-cause death, and rehospitalization in patients aged 75 years or older (HR, 0.16; 95% CI, 0.09-0.28; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) and those younger than 75 years (HR, 0.25; 95% CI, 0.14-0.45; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = .84) as well as in patients with prior stroke (HR, 0.18; 95% CI, 0.07-0.45; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) and without prior stoke (HR, 0.20; 95% CI, 0.13-0.32; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = .51) (<xref rid="zoi211125f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A). The risk of rehospitalization was also consistently reduced in those aged 75 years or older (HR, 0.29; 95% CI, 0.17-0.49; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) and younger than 75 years (HR, 0.51; 95% CI, 0.29-0.89; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .02) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = .54) as well as in patients with prior stroke (HR, 0.34; 95% CI, 0.15-0.72; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .005) and without prior stoke (HR, 0.39; 95% CI, 0.24-0.61; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = .13) (<xref rid="zoi211125f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="zoi211125f3" fig-type="figure">
                  <label>Figure 3. </label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Hazard Rates of Primary Composite Outcome of Ischemic Stroke/Thromboembolism (IS/TE), Death, and Rehospitalization and Secondary End Point of Rehospitalization by Sex, Age, and Prior Stroke, Adjusting for Cluster Effect and Baseline Risk Factors</title>
                    <p>There were 721 women and 1169 men; 875 patients aged 75 years or older and 1015 younger than 75 years; and 471 with prior stroke and 1419 without prior stroke. HR indicates hazard ratio; and mAFA, mobile atrial fibrillation application.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-g003" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-4-ZOI211125">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this prespecified ancillary analysis from the mAFA II trial, an mHealth technology–based integrated care approach that facilitated the implementation of the ABC pathway reduced clinical adverse events in older patients with AF and multimorbidity compared with usual care. Second, with the implementation of the A criterion, there was a reduction in thromboembolism without increasing bleeding risk, while implementation of the C criterion effectively decreased the occurrence of acute coronary syndrome, HF, and uncontrolled blood pressure vs usual care. Third, the integrated care approach of the ABC pathway in patients with multimorbidity was consistent, irrespective of age, sex, and prior stroke.</p>
              <p>Current medical practice has tended to focus on individual conditions or disease states. However, in reality, many comorbidities do not occur in isolation but tend to cluster together.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> This has major implications for risks associated with AF. Health care professionals are increasingly aware of the clinical relevance of multimorbidity, but major challenges remain between health care professionals’ need for supportive tools and care pathways and stakeholders’ limited understanding of these issues.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> There are also challenges with designing clinical guidelines for managing multimorbidity, requiring a shift from a disease-specific approach to a more patient-centered, holistic perspective.</p>
              <p>The high clinical risks of multimorbidity are evident from various studies, including those with AF.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> For example, in an analysis of adjudicated outcomes in patients with AF and multimorbidity enrolled in the AFFIRM trial, after a median (IQR) 3.63 (2.73-4.54) years of follow-up, the rate of the composite outcome of all-cause hospitalization and all-cause death was 37.8 per 100 patient-years<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>; hospitalization events occurred in 36.2 per 100 patient-years, all-cause death in 4.21 per 100 patient-years, and cardiovascular events in 20.3 per 100 patient-years. Nonetheless, the value of interventions to improve hard clinical outcomes in patients with AF and multimorbidity are limited. In 2018, the largest pragmatic randomized clinical trial on the management of patients with multimorbidity (1546 adults with ≥3 chronic conditions, not necessarily AF) tested the efficacy of a patient-centered approach based on several physical health dimensions, depression, and drugs/medication—a so-called 3D approach—in 33 primary care practices in the United Kingdom. The study showed no significant improvement in patients’ quality of life, the primary outcome.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Alternative strategies are therefore needed.</p>
              <p>A systematic review and meta-analysis of the use of the ABC pathway found a lower risk of all-cause death (odds ratio [OR], 0.42; 95% CI, 0.31-0.56), cardiovascular death (OR, 0.37; 95% CI, 0.23-0.58), stroke (OR, 0.55; 95% CI, 0.37-0.82), and major bleeding (OR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.51-0.94), with management adherent to the ABC pathway compared with nonadherent management.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> The results were consistent in different cohorts globally.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi211125r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> The ABC pathway has also been tested in a prospective cluster randomized trial (mAFA-II),<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> which showed that patients allocated to the ABC pathway intervention (using mHealth technology) had lower rates of the composite outcome of ischemic stroke or systemic thromboembolism, death, and rehospitalization compared with usual care (1.9% vs 6.0%; HR, 0.39; 95% CI, 0.22 to 0.67; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Rates of rehospitalization were lower in the intervention group than the usual care group (1.2% vs 4.5%; HR, 0.32; 95% CI, 0.17 to 0.60; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). In the main trial, the ABC pathway intervention also led to reduced major bleeding events and increased oral anticoagulation uptake vs usual care.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> The long-term extension cohort of mAFA-II showed that the beneficial impact of ABC pathway on clinical outcomes was maintained for more than 1 year with high adherence (&gt;70%) and persistence (&gt;90%) of the intervention.<sup><xref rid="zoi211125r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> The present ancillary analysis from the mAFA-II trial found results consistent with the main trial outcomes for this high-risk cohort of older patients with AF and multimorbidity.</p>
              <sec id="H2-3-ZOI211125">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>This study has limitations. It is a post hoc ancillary analysis of a clinical trial, which may not be adequately powered for some of the individual outcomes. The trial was also based on a cluster design, resulting in some imbalance with regard to clinical factors and the proportions of patients with multimorbidity in the mAFA intervention and usual care groups; however, our statistical methods have adjusted for the cluster effect.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="H1-5-ZOI211125">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>In this prespecified ancillary analysis from the mAFA-II trial, an mHealth technology–based integrated care approach that facilitates the implementation of the ABC pathway reduced meaningful clinical adverse events in older patients with AF and multimorbidity compared with usual care.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="REF-ZOI211125">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zoi211125r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Zoni-Berisso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lercari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carazza</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domenicucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of atrial fibrillation: European perspective</article-title>. <source>Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CLEP.S47385</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24966695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24966695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romiti</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olshansky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive management with the ABC (Atrial Fibrillation Better Care) pathway in clinically complex patients with atrial fibrillation: a post hoc ancillary analysis from the AFFIRM Trial</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<elocation-id>e014932</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.119.014932</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32370588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32370588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dondi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andreotti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Four-year trends in oral anticoagulant use and declining rates of ischemic stroke among 194,030 atrial fibrillation patients drawn from a sample of 12 million people</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>220</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ahj.2019.10.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31759279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31759279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Burdett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation in the United Kingdom: predicting costs of an emerging epidemic recognising and forecasting the cost drivers of atrial fibrillation-related costs</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J Qual Care Clin Outcomes</source>. Published online December 21, <year>2020</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ehjqcco/qcaa093</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33346822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33346822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marzona</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term relationship between atrial fibrillation, multimorbidity and oral anticoagulant drug use</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2427</fpage>-<lpage>2436</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2019.06.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31668449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31668449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Fushimi AF Registry Investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics and clinical outcomes in atrial fibrillation patients classified using cluster analysis: the Fushimi AF Registry</article-title>. <source>Europace</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1369</fpage>-<lpage>1379</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/euab079</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33930126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33930126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The ABC pathway: an integrated approach to improve AF management</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cardiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrcardio.2017.153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28960189?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28960189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>mAF-App II Trial Investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Mobile health technology to improve care for patients with atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1523</fpage>-<lpage>1534</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2020.01.052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32241367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32241367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>MAFA II Investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Mobile photoplethysmographic technology to detect atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>2365</fpage>-<lpage>2375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2019.08.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31487545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31487545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name>; <collab>mAF-App II Trial investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Mobile health (mHealth) technology for improved screening, patient involvement and optimising integrated care in atrial fibrillation: the mAFA (mAF-App) II randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Pract</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>e13352</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijcp.13352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31002434?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31002434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>World Medical Association</collab></person-group>. <article-title>World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects.</article-title><source>JAMA</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>310</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2191</fpage>-<lpage>2194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.281053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The European Heart Rhythm Association symptom classification for atrial fibrillation: validation and improvement through a simple modification</article-title>. <source>Europace</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>-<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/eut395</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24534264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24534264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Muth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence supporting the best clinical management of patients with multimorbidity and polypharmacy: a systematic guideline review and expert consensus</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>285</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.12842</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30357955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30357955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Iñiguez Vázquez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matesanz Fernández</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romay Lema</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictor of enhanced mortality in patients with multimorbidity and atrial fibrillation in an acute hospital setting</article-title>. <source>QJM</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>335</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcz302</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31738421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31738421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Claxton</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lutsey</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of multimorbidity with cardiovascular endpoints and treatment effectiveness in patients 75 years and older with atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e554</fpage>-<lpage>e567</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2020.03.038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32320695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32320695</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Jani</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicholl</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McQueenie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multimorbidity and co-morbidity in atrial fibrillation and effects on survival: findings from UK Biobank cohort</article-title>. <source>Europace</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>FI_3</issue>):<fpage>f329</fpage>-<lpage>f336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/eux322</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29112751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29112751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gersh</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multimorbidity and the risk of hospitalization and death in atrial fibrillation: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ahj.2016.11.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28267478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28267478</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Vanbeselaere</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Truyers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between atrial fibrillation, anticoagulation, risk of cerebrovascular events and multimorbidity in general practice: a registry-based study</article-title>. <source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-016-0235-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27021333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27021333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Salisbury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Management of multimorbidity using a patient-centred care model: a pragmatic cluster-randomised trial of the 3D approach</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>392</volume>(<issue>10141</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31308-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29961638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29961638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Romiti</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pastori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivera-Caravaca</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adherence to the ‘Atrial Fibrillation Better Care’ (ABC) pathway in patients with atrial fibrillation: impact on clinical outcomes—a systematic review and meta-analysis of 285,000 patients</article-title>. <source>Thromb Haemost</source>. Published online May 21, <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-1515-9630</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 34020488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34020488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Pastori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farcomeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Violi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>ABC (Atrial Fibrillation Better Care) pathway and healthcare costs in atrial fibrillation: the ATHERO-AF Study</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>856</fpage>-<lpage>861</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2019.01.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30659810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Domek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gumprecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Compliance of atrial fibrillation treatment with the ABC pathway in patients with concomitant diabetes mellitus in the Middle East based on the Gulf SAFE registry</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e13385</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eci.13385</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32810282?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32810282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Gumprecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Compliance of atrial fibrillation treatment with the Atrial Fibrillation Better Care (ABC) pathway improves the clinical outcomes in the Middle East population: a report from the Gulf Survey of Atrial Fibrillation Events (SAFE) registry</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>E1286</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9051286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32365582?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32365582</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Improved population-based clinical outcomes of patients with atrial fibrillation by compliance with the simple ABC (Atrial Fibrillation Better Care) pathway for integrated care management: a nationwide cohort study</article-title>. <source>Thromb Haemost</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1695</fpage>-<lpage>1703</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-1693516</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31266082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31266082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>ESC-EORP Atrial Fibrillation General Long-Term Registry Investigators Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Relation of outcomes to ABC (Atrial Fibrillation Better Care) pathway adherent care in European patients with atrial fibrillation: an analysis from the ESC-EHRA EORP Atrial Fibrillation General Long-Term (AFGen LT) Registry</article-title>. <source>Europace</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/euaa274</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33006613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33006613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name>; <collab>mAF-App II Trial investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Regular bleeding risk assessment associated with reduction in bleeding outcomes: the mAFA-II randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1195</fpage>-<lpage>1202.e2, e2</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2020.03.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32289310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32289310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zoi211125r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>mAF-App II Trial investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Mobile health technology-supported atrial fibrillation screening and integrated care: a report from the mAFA-II trial Long-term Extension Cohort</article-title>. <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>. published Online First: Epub Date|. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2020.09.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33067121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33067121</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI211125-1">
              <supplementary-material id="note-ZOI211125-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Trial Protocol
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-s001.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>eTable. </bold>Treatments in mAFA Intervention and Usual Care Group</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-s002.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Nonauthor Collaborators
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-s003.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>Supplement 4.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2140071-s004.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </notes>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
