<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T11:35:22Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3024335" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3024335</identifier>
        <datestamp>2012-02-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>diacare</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diacare</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dcare</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3024335</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3024335</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3024335</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21270186</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1293</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc10-1293</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Clinical Care/Education/Nutrition/Psychosocial Research</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Urinary C-Peptide Creatinine Ratio Is a Practical Outpatient Tool for Identifying Hepatocyte Nuclear Factor 1-α/Hepatocyte Nuclear Factor 4-α Maturity-Onset Diabetes of the Young From Long-Duration Type 1 Diabetes</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Besser</surname>
                    <given-names>Rachel E.J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MBBS</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shepherd</surname>
                    <given-names>Maggie H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PHD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McDonald</surname>
                    <given-names>Timothy J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSC</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shields</surname>
                    <given-names>Beverley M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PHD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Knight</surname>
                    <given-names>Bridget A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PHD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ellard</surname>
                    <given-names>Sian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PHD</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hattersley</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrew T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DM</degrees>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Peninsula National Institute for Health Research Clinical Research Facility, Peninsula Medical School, University of Exeter, Exeter, United Kingdom.</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, Royal Devon and Exeter National Health Service Foundation Trust, Exeter, United Kingdom.</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Molecular Genetics, Royal Devon and Exeter National Health Service Foundation Trust, Exeter, United Kingdom.</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Andrew T. Hattersley, <email>andrew.hattersley@pms.ac.uk</email>.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2011</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>34</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>286</fpage>
              <lpage>291</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>7</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>8</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2010</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2011 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons">
                  <license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="286.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="s1">
                  <title>OBJECTIVE</title>
                  <p>Hepatocyte nuclear factor 1-α (HNF1A)/hepatocyte nuclear factor 4-α (HNF4A) maturity-onset diabetes of the young (MODY) is frequently misdiagnosed as type 1 diabetes, and patients are inappropriately treated with insulin. Blood C-peptide can aid in the diagnosis of MODY, but practical reasons limit its widespread use. Urinary C-peptide creatinine ratio (UCPCR), a stable measure of endogenous insulin secretion, is a noninvasive alternative. We aimed to compare stimulated UCPCR in adults with HNF1A/4A MODY, type 1 diabetes, and type 2 diabetes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2">
                  <title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title>
                  <p>Adults with diabetes for ≥5years, without renal impairment, were studied (HNF1A MODY [<italic>n</italic> = 54], HNF4A MODY [<italic>n</italic> = 23], glucokinase MODY [<italic>n</italic> = 20], type 1 diabetes [<italic>n</italic> = 69], and type 2 diabetes [<italic>n</italic> = 54]). The UCPCR was collected in boric acid 120 min after the largest meal of the day and mailed for analysis. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to identify optimal UCPCR cutoffs to differentiate HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 and type 2 diabetes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3">
                  <title>RESULTS</title>
                  <p>UCPCR was lower in type 1 diabetes than HNF1A/4A MODY (median [interquartile range]) (&lt;0.02 nmol/mmol [&lt;0.02 to &lt;0.02] vs. 1.72 nmol/mmol [0.98–2.90]; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). ROC curves showed excellent discrimination (area under curve [AUC] 0.98) and identified a cutoff UCPCR of ≥0.2 nmol/mmol for differentiating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes (97% sensitivity, 96% specificity). UCPCR was lower in HNF1A/4A MODY than in type 2 diabetes (1.72 nmol/mmol [0.98–2.90] vs. 2.47 nmol/mmol [1.4–4.13]); <italic>P</italic> = 0.007). ROC curves showed a weak distinction between HNF1A/4A MODY and type 2 diabetes (AUC 0.64).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s4">
                  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
                  <p>UCPCR is a noninvasive outpatient tool that can be used to discriminate HNF1A and HNF4A MODY from long-duration type 1 diabetes. To differentiate MODY from type 1 diabetes of &gt;5 years’ duration, UCPCR could be used to determine whether genetic testing is indicated.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>Maturity-onset diabetes of the young (MODY) describes dominantly inherited young-onset non–insulin-dependent diabetes (often &lt;25 years’ duration) with persistent endogenous insulin secretion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Heterozygous activating mutations in the transcription factor genes hepatocyte nuclear factor 1-α (HNF1A) and hepatocyte nuclear factor 4-α (HNF4A) are common causes of monogenic diabetes, accounting for 52 and 10% of MODY cases, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>)</p>
            <p>Recognition and genetic diagnosis of HNF1A/4A MODY is crucial for optimal management. HNF1A/4A MODY frequently is misdiagnosed as type 1 diabetes because patients are diagnosed young (mean age of diagnosis: HNF1A age 20 years and HNF4A age 23 years) and are nonobese (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). In our diagnostic genetics service in Exeter, of 405 referrals for HNF1A MODY, 140 (35.5%) initially were misdiagnosed with type 1 diabetes and inappropriately treated with insulin (R.E.J.B., S.E., A.T.H., unpublished data). Patients are extremely sulfonylurea sensitive and, once diagnosed, often are able to stop insulin treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>).</p>
            <p>Genetic testing is needed to confirm HNF1A and HNF4A MODY, but it is too costly to be used to screen all patients with diabetes. An alternative cheap and practical biomarker to identify patients with a higher probability of HNF1A/4A MODY for genetic testing would improve diagnosis.</p>
            <p>Various biomarkers have been proposed (apoliprotein M, complement 5 [C5], complement 8 [C8], transthyretin [TTR], and 1,5-anhydroglucitol). All have attempted to discriminate HNF1A or HNF4A MODY from type 2 diabetes rather than type 1 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), but they were not sufficiently accurate for routine clinical use.</p>
            <p>C-peptide is a good candidate biomarker to differentiate patients with MODY from type 1 diabetes. C-peptide is a polypeptide cosecreted in equimolar amounts with insulin. Measurement of blood C-peptide is available in hospital and will identify patients who still are making their own insulin. In type 1 diabetes, autoimmune destruction of β-cells results in absolute insulin deficiency, usually within 5 years of diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In HNF1A and HNF4A MODY, β-cell function is maintained despite a reduction in insulin secretion and progressive hyperglycemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Blood C-peptide outside the honeymoon period should alert the clinician to a diagnosis of MODY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Although blood C-peptide is available, it is not routinely measured because of practical limitations. The rapid degradation by proteases means that samples need to be separated and frozen prior to analysis, restricting testing to the hospital setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). C-peptide usually is measured after stimulation with a mixed meal or glucagon to detect β-cell reserve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), and the need to discontinue short-acting insulin prior to testing may further limit its clinical use.</p>
            <p>C-peptide is renally metabolized, and 5–10% of C-peptide is excreted unchanged in urine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Urinary C-peptide, creatinine ratio (UCPCR) is a useful alternative method to measuring C-peptide, and the use of a creatinine ratio accounts for the effects in urine concentration. UCPCR is stable for 3 days in boric acid preservative at room temperature, offering the potential to use postal samples in the community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). No studies to date have used UCPCR to differentiate MODY from other types of diabetes.</p>
            <p>We hypothesize that endogenous insulin secretion persists in HNF1A/4A MODY, and UCPCR will discriminate HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 in long-standing diabetes. The aim of this study was to compare stimulated UCPCR in adults with HNF1A/4A MODY, type 1 diabetes, and type 2 diabetes.</p>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title>
              <p>Adults with diabetes of ≥5 years’ duration were identified from existing research databases at the Peninsula Medical School, Exeter, U.K., and from routine diabetes clinics. Because C-peptide is metabolized largely in the kidney, patients were excluded from taking part if they had known renal impairment (estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt;60 ml/min per 1.73 m<sup>2</sup>). A total of 97 patients with a genetic diagnosis of MODY were recruited (54 patients with mutations in the HNF1A gene, 23 with HNF4A mutations, and 20 with glucokinase [GCK] mutations). A total of 69 patients with type 1 diabetes were studied (defined as those who had an age of diagnosis of &lt;30 years and on insulin since diagnosis) as well as 54 patients with type 2 diabetes (defined as those with an age of diagnosis of ≥35 years and not on insulin for the first year of diagnosis). Patients were contacted initially either by letter or by their health care professional. Follow-up contact was made by telephone by the research team, and the following information was documented: age of diagnosis, current medication, A1C, creatinine, weight, and height. Consent was gained to contact the patient’s general practitioners for missing information.</p>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Sample collection</title>
                <p>Urine containers with boric acid preservative were mailed to participants. A urine sample was collected 120 min after completing the largest meal of the day, having voided prior to eating. Participants took their normal medication during the test. The sample was either mailed the same day or refrigerated overnight and mailed first class to the research laboratory the following morning. Samples were analyzed only if they reached the biochemistry laboratory within 72 h of the sample void.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s7">
                <title>Ethics</title>
                <p>The study was approved by the Devon and Torbay Research and Ethics Committee. All subjects gave informed consent.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s8">
                <title>UCPCR analyses</title>
                <p>Urinary C-peptide was measured by electrochemiluminescence immunoassay (intra-assay coefficient of variation &lt;3.3%; interassay coefficient of variation &lt;4.5%) on a Roche Diagnostics (Mannheim, Germany) E170 analyzer by the biochemistry department at the Royal Devon and Exeter National Health Service Foundation Trust, Exeter, U.K. Urinary creatinine was analyzed on the Roche P800 platform using creatinine Jaffé reagent (standardized against isotope dilution mass spectrometry) to UCPCR (nmol/mmol).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s9">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Results are presented as medians (interquartile range), unless otherwise stated. Patients with HNF1A and HNF4A MODY were combined for the purposes of the analyses because there was no significant difference in UCPCR values (<italic>P</italic> = 0.87), clinical characteristics, or treatment between the two groups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>).</p>
                <p>Characteristics of patients in the HNF1A/4A MODY and type 1 diabetic (or type 2 diabetic) groups were compared using a χ<sup>2</sup> or generalized Fisher exact test for categorical data (sex and treatment) and Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test for continuous variables not normally distributed (age of diagnosis, current age, diabetes duration, BMI, and UCPCR). Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves were used to identify cutoffs of UCPCR that provided the optimal sensitivity and specificity for discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes (which we defined as absolute insulin deficiency) and HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes. Analysis was repeated examining only those who were treated with insulin. Likelihood ratios were calculated to estimate the effect of a UCPCR value above the cutoff identified to discriminate between HNF1A/4A MODY and type 1 or type 2 diabetes to calculate a posttest probability.</p>
                <p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS version 15, and <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was assumed to be significant.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s10">
                <title>Assessment of patients with type 1 diabetes with persistent C-peptide</title>
                <p>Type 1 diabetic patients who were identified as having UCPCR values greater than the identified cutoff for insulin deficiency (as defined by ROC analysis) provided a repeat urine sample and were contacted again for a mixed-meal tolerance test. Patients arrived having fasted and were given an Ensure high-protein milkshake (6 ml/kg, maximum 360 ml). A sample was taken at 90 min for measurement of stimulated serum C-peptide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), with a value of 0.2 nmol/L indicating persistent endogenous insulin production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). These patients also were tested for GAD and IA2 antibodies, and the HNF1A and HNF4A genes were sequenced. Pancreatic antibodies were considered positive if &gt;99th percentile of 500 control samples.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s11">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Patient characteristics are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
              <sec id="s12">
                <title>HNF1A/4A MODY versus type 1 diabetes</title>
                <p>Postprandial UCPCR was markedly lower in type 1 diabetes than HNF1A/4A MODY (median [interquartile range]; &lt;0.02 nmol/mmol [&lt;0.02 to &lt;0.02] vs. 1.72 nmol/mmol [0.98–2.90]; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). ROC curves showed excellent discrimination (area under curve [AUC] 0.98) and identified a cutoff UCPCR ≥0.2 nmol/mmol for discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes with 97% sensitivity and 96% specificity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>). This translates to a likelihood ratio of 24 for identifying HNF1A/4A MODY using a UCPCR ≥0.2 nmol/mmol.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Patient characteristics</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead valign="bottom">
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HNF1A/4A MODY</th>
                        <th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 1 diabetes</th>
                        <th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value (MODY vs. type 1 diabetes)</th>
                        <th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 2 diabetes</th>
                        <th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value (MODY vs. type 2 diabetes)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n </italic>(% male)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (42.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (47.8)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (44.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of diagnosis (years)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (15–30)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (8–19)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (50.8–65.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6 (38.1–64.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4 (37–58.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (66.3–75.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of diabetes (years)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 (14.7–35.4)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5 (21.9–42.2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (8.7–15.3)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 (22.4–26.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 (24.0–29.0)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5 (26.1–32.7)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (<italic>n</italic>)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet alone</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OHA alone</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin with or without OHA</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1C (%)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 (6.6–8.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n2">†</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 (7.3–8.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (7.0–8.2)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent affected (<italic>n </italic>[%])</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (91)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (23)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three or more consecutive generations affected</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (83)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9)</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCPCR (nmol/mmol)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 (0.98–2.9)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.02 (&lt;0.02 to &lt;0.02)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 (1.4–4.13)</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1"><italic>*</italic></xref></td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn>
                      <p>Data are median (interquartile range), unless otherwise stated. OHA, oral hypoglycemic agent.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t1n1">
                      <p><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n1">*</xref>Statistical significance.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="t1n2">
                      <p><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1n2">†</xref>Missing data for A1C; HNF1A/4A MODY (<italic>n</italic> = 20).</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Box plot and ROC curve to identify HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes. <italic>A</italic>: Box plot to show the UCPCR in HNF1A/4A MODY (<italic>n</italic> = 77) and type 1 diabetes (<italic>n</italic> = 69). Dotted line indicates a UCPCR cutoff of 0.2 nmol/mmol. Circles, outliers; stars, extreme outliers. <italic>B</italic>: The ROC curve identified a cutoff UCPCR ≥0.2 nmol/mmol for discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes (AUC 0.98) with 97% sensitivity and 96% specificity.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="286fig1"/>
                </fig>
                <p>This relationship persisted when assessing the discrimination of insulin-treated HNF1A/HNF4A from type 1 subjects (AUC 0.96, 94% sensitivity, and 96% specificity) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>). We showed that diabetes duration did not interfere with the discriminatory ability of UCPCR by performing further analysis on 50 HNF1A/4A MODY and 50 type 1 diabetic patients, matched within ±2 years’ diabetes duration, and a further subanalysis on patients with 5–25 years’ diabetes duration (Supplementary results).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s13">
                <title>UCPCR-positive type 1 diabetes</title>
                <p>We went on to study further the 3 of 69 (4%) type 1 diabetic patients with diabetes duration of ≥5 years who had a UCPCR ≥0.2 nmol/mmol. All three patients remained positive on repeat UCPCR testing. Two of three patients exceeded the serum C-peptide concentration that is used to define significant endogenous insulin secretion (0.2 nmol/l) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), despite diabetes duration of over 25 years (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>). Two of three patients had either elevated GAD65 or IA2 antibodies (see supplementary material), and none of these patients had mutations in HNF1A and HNF4A genes.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s14">
                <title>HNF1A/4A MODY versus type 2 diabetes</title>
                <p>Although postprandial UCPCR was lower in HNF1A/4A MODY than in type 2 diabetes (1.72 nmol/mmol [0.98–2.90] vs. 2.47 nmol/mmol [1.4–4.13]; <italic>P</italic> = 0.007), the ROC curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) showed weak discrimination between HNF1A/4A MODY and type 2 diabetes (AUC 0.64). A UCPCR ≤3.1 nmol/mmol could discriminate HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes with 81% sensitivity and 44% specificity. In patients treated with insulin, UCPCR was better, identifying a cutoff of 1.27 for discriminating type 2 diabetes (<italic>n</italic> = 19) from HNF1A/4A MODY (<italic>n</italic> = 31), (AUC 0.69, 74% sensitivity, and 68% specificity) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>). UCPCR results did not differentiate HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes in patients treated with oral agents (AUC 0.54, <italic>P</italic> = 0.55) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 3</ext-link>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Box plot and ROC curve to identify HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes. <italic>A</italic>: Box plot to show the UCPCR in HNF1A/4A MODY (<italic>n</italic> = 77) and type 2 diabetes (<italic>n </italic>= 54). Circles, outliers; stars, extreme outliers. <italic>B</italic>: The ROC curve indicates that UCPCR was not able to easily discriminate HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes (AUC 0.64).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="286fig2"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s15">
                <title>MODY subtypes (HNF1A, HNF4A, and GCK MODY)</title>
                <p>There was no difference in UCPCR between HNF1A and HNF4A MODY (1.72 nmol/mmol [0.90–2.90] vs. 1.48 nmol/mmol [1.01–2.93]; <italic>P</italic> = 0.87), but combined values were significantly lower than GCK MODY (1.72 nmol/mmol [0.98–2.90] vs. 3.1 nmol/mmol [2.16–4.05]; <italic>P</italic> = 0.002) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s16">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
              <p>In this study, UCPCR showed excellent discrimination between HNF1A/HNF4A MODY and type 1 diabetes in patients &gt;5 years after diabetes diagnosis, suggesting that this is a useful tool to detect patients with possible HNF1A or HNF4A MODY in clinical practice.</p>
              <sec id="s17">
                <title>UCPCR compared with serum C-peptide</title>
                <p>We have shown that a value of ≥0.2 nmol/mmol is highly specific (96%) and sensitive (97%) in discriminating HNF1A/HNF4A MODY from type 1 diabetes when patients are tested &gt;5 years after diagnosis. This high level of discrimination remains even when the MODY patients are treated with insulin. The ability to discriminate whether an insulin-treated patient should be considered for genetic analysis is important for diagnosis and family screening. Finding a UCPCR &gt;0.2 nmol/mmol would suggest that a genetic test may be appropriate. If a diagnosis of HNF1A/4A MODY is made in a patient treated with insulin from diagnosis, this may bring about treatment change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). A diagnosis of monogenic diabetes also has implications for the genetic testing of other family members.</p>
                <p>This test cannot be used close to diagnosis because persistent C-peptide is likely to still be present in patients with type 1 diabetes in the first few months and occasionally years after diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In cases where there is an affected parent, this will usually be of long duration at the time the child is first diagnosed. If the parents’ duration is &gt;5 years, UCPCR testing and, if appropriate, subsequent genetic testing could be performed in the parent.</p>
                <p>This result is not surprising because persistent endogenous insulin secretion resulting in patients not being insulin dependent is a key feature of MODY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). It already has been established that serum C-peptide is likely to be persistent in MODY (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), and this can be used to distinguish it from type 1 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Our results from patients who had both a serum C-peptide measured in a mixed-meal tolerance test and UCPCR show that the results are similar and both can detect relatively low levels of endogenous insulin secretion.</p>
                <p>The major advantage of UCPCR over serum C-peptide is its practical utility. Serum C-peptide requires separating the serum by spinning rapidly and subsequent freezing of the sample. This effectively limits its use to hospital settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). In contrast, UCPCR is stable at room temperature for 3 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), and our results using mailed samples offer an approach that can be used in the patient’s home or other settings away from laboratory equipment.</p>
                <p>Likelihood ratios can be used to alter the pretest probabilities, or prevalence of a disease, to help the clinician decide who would benefit from diagnostic genetic testing. Based on our results, a UCPCR ≥0.2 nmol/mmol gave a likelihood ratio of 24, and conversely a UCPCR &lt;0.2 nmol/mmol would give a likelihood ratio of 0.03. This means that assuming the prevalence of MODY is 0.7% of patients with young-onset diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), the posttest probability of a patient having HNF1A/4A MODY would be 0.0002% if UCPCR was &lt;0.2 nmol/mmol, allowing genetic testing to be excluded on the basis of a simple urine test. If UCPCR is positive (≥0.2 nmol/mmol) the probability of a patient having HNF1A/4A MODY is 14%. Other nongenetic tests, such as those for diabetes autoantibodies, and clinical features, such as family history, also may be useful to further modify this probability.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s18">
                <title>UCPCR compared with other criteria to screen for MODY versus type 1 diabetes</title>
                <p>Little work has been done on biomarkers to discriminate MODY from type 1 diabetes. The monosaccharide 1,5-anhydroglucitol was unable to discriminate HNF1A MODY from type 1 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). An important biomarker would be pancreatic autoantibodies, and this is likely to be a better test than C-peptide close to diagnosis. Although 70–96% of patients with type 1 diabetes have autoantibodies, if multiple antibodies are tested at diagnosis, this positive rate falls off in the years after diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). No studies have been done to systematically determine the autoantibody prevalence in MODY, but it is likely that autoantibody measurements will be better closer to diagnosis but less sensitive and specific 5 years after diagnosis than UCPCR measurement.</p>
                <p>Although parental history has relatively good sensitivity (91%) in identifying MODY, it falls down on the specificity (77%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which would increase the number of patients who are falsely identified as having MODY. In contrast, three or more generations have good specificity (91%) but only modest sensitivity (83%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which would miss cases of MODY. Using parental history or multigenerational family history in isolation is likely to miss cases attributed to the selection bias for screening patients using traditional MODY criteria. The advantage of using UCPCR is that it has both strong sensitivity (97%) and specificity (96%) for discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 1 diabetes.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s19">
                <title>UCPCR in discriminating type 2 diabetes from HNF1A/4A MODY</title>
                <p>UCPCR was less robust at discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes, compared with type 1 diabetes. A UCPCR value ≤3.1 nmol/mmol was 81% sensitive and 44% specific for HNF1A/4A MODY compared with type 2 diabetes. This will reflect that in MODY the predominant defect is insulin secretion rather than the combined defect seen in type 2 diabetes of insulin secretion and insulin resistance, resulting in higher C-peptide whether measured in serum or urine. This level of discrimination, although significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.07), is hard to use in clinical practice in contrast to the discrimination against type 1 diabetes.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s20">
                <title>UCPCR compared with other biomarkers to screen for MODY versus type 2 diabetes</title>
                <p>1.5-AG and the proteins apolipoprotein M, C5, C8, and TTR all have been identified as potential biomarkers for discriminating HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), but the utility of these in clinical practice is unclear. Although they could discriminate between HNF1A MODY and type 2 diabetes, the sensitivity and specificity were not sufficiently powered to be clinically useful (sensitivity/specificity [%]: TTR 80/2, C5 90/11, and C8 60/5). The sensitivity (81%) and specificity (44%) of UCPCR to identify HNF1A/4A MODY from type 2 diabetes is higher than seen for these other biomarkers but probably not useful as a diagnostic tool. UCPCR may, however, have a role in identifying type 2 diabetes in patients with high UCPCR levels, and in those who are insulin treated, but further investigation will be required to assess this in a clinical setting.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s21">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>This study includes patients with long-duration diabetes ≥5 years to ensure patients are outside the honeymoon period of type 1 diabetes. Additional studies are needed with a shorter duration to assess the role of UCPCR in patients closer to diagnosis. However, the value of a negative test within 5 years of diagnosis may be of use and is likely to be as strong if not stronger than outside the honeymoon period.</p>
                <p>Our study is cross-sectional, and a prospective study with serial measurement would let the evolution of changes in UCPCR be assessed in all of the different subtypes of diabetes.</p>
                <p>Our patients only were included if they had normal renal function because C-peptide metabolism largely occurs in the kidney (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). The utility of UCPCR in renal impairment remains to be established. These caveats prove that our results should not be extrapolated to patients within 5 years of diagnosis or with renal impairment until other studies are performed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s22">
                <title>Persistent C-peptide in type 1 patients</title>
                <p>It is important to appreciate that C-peptide may persist in type 1 diabetes. In our cohort, 3 of 69 (4%) type 1 diabetic patients had detectable C-peptide ≥5 years after diagnosis. They probably represent unusual type 1 diabetes or an unidentified subtype, because autoantibodies were detected in two of three patients. The DCCT found that in 5 years after diagnosis, 3–7% type 1 diabetic patients had stimulated C-peptide &gt;200 pmol/L (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p>
                <p>In conclusion, UCPCR is a useful, simple, noninvasive biomarker for discriminating HNF1A and HNF4A MODY from long-duration type 1 diabetes.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn1">
                <p>This article contains Supplementary Data online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1">http://care.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/dc10-1293/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>This work was supported by Diabetes UK. Diabetes UK provided funding through a clinical training fellowship to R.E.J.B. Other funding was received from the Peninsula National Institute for Health Research Clinical Research facility, the European Union (FP7 Integrated Project No. CEED3 [HEALTH-F2-2008-223211]), and the Madam Curie initial funding network BOLD).</p>
              <p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p>
              <p>R.E.J.B. designed the study, recruited patients, performed analysis, and wrote the manuscript. M.H.S. recruited patients and reviewed and edited the manuscript. T.J.M. analyzed samples, contributed to the analysis, and reviewed and edited the manuscript. B.M.S. performed analysis and reviewed and edited the manuscript. B.A.K. contributed to the study design and researched, reviewed, and edited the manuscript. S.E. performed genetic testing of MODY case subjects and reviewed and edited the manuscript. A.T.H. had the original idea, designed the study, performed analysis, and reviewed and edited the manuscript.</p>
              <p>Parts of this study were presented in poster form at the 70th Scientific Sessions of the American Diabetes Association, Orlando, Florida, 25–29 June 2010.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tattersall</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mild familial diabetes with dominant inheritance</article-title>. <source>Q J Med</source><year>1974</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4212169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fajans</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms and clinical pathophysiology of maturity-onset diabetes of the young</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>345</volume>:<fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11575290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Colclough</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturity-onset diabetes of the young (MODY): how many cases are we missing?</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>2504</fpage>–<lpage>2508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20499044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Møller</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalgaard</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pociot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nerup</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the hepatocyte nuclear factor-1alpha gene in Caucasian families originally classified as having type I diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1528</fpage>–<lpage>1531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9867222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruhova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castleden</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumb</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wierzbicki</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetics and phenotypic characteristics of MODY caused by hepatocyte nuclear factor 4alpha mutations in a large European collection</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15830177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio-Cabezas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genetic diagnosis of HNF1A diabetes alters treatment and improves glycaemic control in the majority of insulin-treated patients</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19388975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaxillaire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Møller</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urhammer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Almind</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Echwald</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel MODY3 mutations in the hepatocyte nuclear factor-1α gene: evidence for a hyperexcitability of pancreatic β-cells to intravenous secretagogues in a glucose-tolerant carrier of a P447L mutation</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>726</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9075819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Starkey</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribble</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic cause of hyperglycaemia and response to treatment in diabetes</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<fpage>1275</fpage>–<lpage>1281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14575972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cervin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Axler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmkvist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Almgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rantala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Groop</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlbäck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation of serum concentration of apoM as a potential MODY3 marker using a novel ELISA</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>267</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19754856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Selwood</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrow</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klyne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grew</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gloyn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of serum 1,5 anhydroglucitol levels as a clinical test to differentiate subtypes of diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19933992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfrum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajans</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of apolipoprotein M gene expression by MODY3 gene hepatocyte nuclear factor-1α: haploinsufficiency is associated with reduced serum apolipoprotein M levels</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>2989</fpage>–<lpage>2995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14633861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Groop</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can complement factors 5 and 8 and transthyretin be used as biomarkers for MODY 1 (HNF4A-MODY) and MODY 3 (HNF1A-MODY)?</article-title><source>Diabet Med</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18513302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skupien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorczynska-Kosiorz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klupa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanic</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Button</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieradzki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Malecki</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical application of 1,5-anhydroglucitol measurements in patients with hepatocyte nuclear factor-1α maturity-onset diabetes of the young</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1496</fpage>–<lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansa</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzilli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Skyler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffes</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-peptide is the appropriate outcome measure for type 1 diabetes clinical trials to preserve β-cell function: report of an ADA workshop, 21-22 October 2001</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14693724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajans</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoltz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname> Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Halter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered insulin secretory responses to glucose in subjects with a mutation in the MODY1 gene on chromosome 20</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7789636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajans</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dronsfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Velho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Froguel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Polonsky</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered insulin secretory responses to glucose in diabetic and nondiabetic subjects with mutations in the diabetes susceptibility gene MODY3 on chromosome 12</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1503</fpage>–<lpage>1510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8866553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruining</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Njolstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaghue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><collab>International Society for Pediatric and Adolescent Diabetes</collab></person-group><article-title>ISPAD clinical practice consensus guidelines 2006-2007: the diagnosis and management of monogenic diabetes in children</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Diabetes</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17212604</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assays for insulin, proinsulin(s) and C-peptide</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Biochem</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10505204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandrup-Poulsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Battelino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haastert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludvigsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzilli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><collab>the Type 1 Diabetes Trial Net Research Group, the</collab><collab>European C-Peptide Trial Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Mixed-meal tolerance test versus glucagon stimulation test for the assessment of β-cell function in therapeutic trials in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1966</fpage>–<lpage>1971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18628574</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitation of human pancreatic β-cell function by immunoassay of C-peptide in urine</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1977</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">318625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability and reproducibility of a single-sample urinary C-peptide/creatinine ratio and its correlation with 24-h urinary C-peptide</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2035</fpage>–<lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19713273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The DCCT Research Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Effects of age, duration and treatment of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus on residual beta-cell function: observations during eligibility testing for the Diabetes Control and Complications Trial (DCCT)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1987</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2884229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallen</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying hepatic nuclear factor 1α mutations in children and young adults with a clinical diagnosis of type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547858</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schober</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapellen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinehr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holl</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><collab>the DPV-Wiss Initiative of the German Working Group for Paediatric Diabetology</collab></person-group><article-title>Phenotypical aspects of maturity-onset diabetes of the young (MODY diabetes) in comparison with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in children and adolescents: experience from a large multicentre database</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19646184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabbah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Savola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebeling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulmala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vähäsalo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmela</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Knip</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic, autoimmune, and clinical characteristics of childhood- and adult-onset type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1326</fpage>–<lpage>1332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10977027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
