<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:21:26Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8691398" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8691398</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>abm</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Behav Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Behav Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abm</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Annals of Behavioral Medicine: A Publication of the Society of Behavioral Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0883-6612</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1532-4796</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8691398</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8691398</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8691398</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33821937</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33821937</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/abm/kaab019</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">kaab019</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Regular Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00010</subject>
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI02170</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Mechanisms of Action in a Behavioral Weight-Management Program: Latent Growth Curve Analysis</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6358-0060</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bates</surname>
                    <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BSc, MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="AF0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <!--sebates1@sheffield.ac.uk-->
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5892-0470</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Norman</surname>
                    <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BSc, PhD, CPsychol</degrees>
                  <xref rid="AF0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Breeze</surname>
                    <given-names>Penny</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BA, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="AF0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brennan</surname>
                    <given-names>Alan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BSc, MSc, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="AF0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ahern</surname>
                    <given-names>Amy L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>BSc, MSc, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="AF0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label><institution>School of Health and Related Research, University of Sheffield</institution>, <addr-line>Sheffield</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Sheffield</institution>, <addr-line>Sheffield</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label><institution>MRC Epidemiology Unit, University of Cambridge</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1">Sarah Bates <email>sebates1@sheffield.ac.uk</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-04-03">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>56</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>64</fpage>
              <lpage>77</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society of Behavioral Medicine.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="kaab019.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="s0100">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>A greater understanding of the mechanisms of action of weight-management interventions is needed to inform the design of effective interventions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0101">
                  <title>Purpose</title>
                  <p>To investigate whether dietary restraint, habit strength, or diet self-regulation mediated the impact of a behavioral weight-management intervention on weight loss and weight loss maintenance.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0102">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Latent growth curve analysis (LGCA) was conducted on trial data in which adults (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1,267) with a body mass index (BMI) ≥28 kg/m<sup>2</sup> were randomized to either a brief intervention (booklet on losing weight), a 12 week weight-management program or the same program for 52 weeks. LGCA estimated the trajectory of the variables over four time points (baseline and 3, 12 and 24 months) to assess whether potential mechanisms of action mediated the impact of the weight-management program on BMI.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0103">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Participants randomized to the 12 and 52 week programs had a significantly greater decrease in BMI than the brief intervention. This direct effect became nonsignificant when dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation were controlled for. The total indirect effect was significant for both the 12 (estimate = −1.33, standard error [<italic toggle="yes">SE</italic>] = 0.41, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) and 52 week (estimate = −2.13, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.52, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) program. Only the individual indirect effect for dietary restraint was significant for the 12 week intervention, whereas all three indirect effects were significant for the 52 week intervention.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0104">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Behavior change techniques that target dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation should be considered when designing weight loss and weight loss maintenance interventions. Longer interventions may need to target both deliberative and automatic control processes to support successful weight management.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <p>The effect of a behavioural weight-management intervention on weight loss was explained by changes in dietary restraint, habit strength and autonomous motivation</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
                <title>Graphical Abstract</title>
                <p>
                  <fig position="float" id="ga1">
                    <graphic xlink:href="kaab019f0004" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Weight management</kwd>
                <kwd>Mediation</kwd>
                <kwd>Restraint</kwd>
                <kwd>Habit</kwd>
                <kwd>Self-regulation</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Wellcome Trust Doctoral Training Centre in Public Health Economics and Decision Science</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>108903/Z/19/Z</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>University of Sheffield</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000858</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>National Prevention Research Initiative</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>MR/J000493/1</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Medical Research Council</institution>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>MC_UU_00006/6</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="14"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Approximately two thirds of adults in the UK and USA are classed as being overweight or obese based on their body mass index (BMI) and there is little evidence that the prevalence is decreasing [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Behavioral weight-management programs are the first-line treatment for people classed as overweight or obese [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and, although there is evidence that these are effective [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the results are heterogeneous between and within studies [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In a systematic review, the average weight loss across randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of nonsurgical weight loss interventions varied from −4.03 to −21.3 kg [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. There is also variability in evidence for the duration of the intervention effect. A systematic review of trials with a follow-up of at least 16 weeks found evidence for significant intervention effects ranging from 18 months to 5 years from baseline [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p>
              <p>The heterogeneity in the size and duration of treatment effect may be due to differences in the behavior change techniques (BCTs) used in an intervention and the mechanisms of actions targeted. For example, in a previous trial, an intervention that used BCTs, such as developing implementation intentions to target habit formation, resulted in greater weight loss than an intervention that used BCTs, such as education about misinformation to target unhealthy relationships with food [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Given the similarities in the duration and mode of delivery, the findings indicate that the different BCTs used, and mechanisms of action targeted, resulted in differences in weight change. Identifying relevant mechanisms of action associated with the desired outcome will enable the evidence-based selection of BCTs to include in an intervention [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This is particularly important for weight loss maintenance as weight regained postintervention is commonly reported (e.g., [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]). Thus, a greater understanding of the mechanisms of action associated with short- and longer-term weight loss is needed to inform the design of effective interventions, through the selection of appropriate BCTs, that result in both weight loss and weight loss maintenance.</p>
              <p>There are many potential mechanisms of action for weight-management interventions. A common focus of these interventions is to create healthy eating behaviors by restricting the amount and types of food and drinks consumed [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Efforts to restrict food intake, such as using strategies to prevent overeating (e.g., portion control or avoiding unhealthy foods), adjusting eating behavior after over consuming, and being conscious of food choices in order to control weight are often referred to as dietary restraint [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A recent review of studies that measured dietary restraint found that restraint was associated with weight loss [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; specifically, higher dietary restraint was associated with a lower weight in populations with obesity, and increases in dietary restraint were associated with greater weight loss. In studies that have examined weight loss maintenance, increases in dietary restraint during weight loss have also been found to predict weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and decreases in dietary restraint have been found to be associated with greater weight regain over 18 months [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] to 10 years [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Although there is evidence from observational and RCTs that changes in dietary restraint are associated with weight control [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], there has been less research on dietary restraint as a mechanism of action (i.e., mediator) of weight-management interventions. In a review, only one study had conducted formal mediation analysis [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], reporting that dietary restraint mediated the impact of a weight-management intervention on weight loss over 24 months [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In a more recent study, dietary restraint was not found to mediate the effect of a weight-management intervention; however, the intervention included meal plans and prepackaged food, which may have limited the opportunity for participants to practice restrained eating [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p>
              <p>Continued dietary restraint may lead to healthy dietary behaviors becoming habitual, which, in turn, may aid the maintenance of weight loss. Habits can be defined as learned stimulus–response associations such that when a stimulus is encountered, an individual responds automatically with a certain behavior or set of behaviors [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Habits are formed when a behavior, such as monitoring diet, eating fruit and vegetables, or taking part in physical activity, is repeated frequently in the same context such that a cognitive association is made between the situation and behavior [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Habit strength has been associated with eating behaviors in observational studies [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and decreases in BMI during a weight loss intervention [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In addition, in a weight loss maintenance intervention, increases in healthy eating habits were associated with decreases in BMI over 1 year [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Although there has been some research on the benefits of habit-based interventions [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], there is little research on whether habit strength is a mechanism of action of effective interventions. In one study, the effect of a brief habit-based weight loss intervention was mediated by automaticity [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, this analysis was conducted over a short time period (3 months) and only one item was used to assess automaticity.</p>
              <p>The motivation that drives behavior change is also a key factor in weight loss and weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Autonomous regulation occurs when engaging in a behavior is autonomously motivated; that is, the behavior is perceived as valued, important to the individual, consistent with intrinsic goals or outcomes, and part of the individual’s identity [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It is predicted that those with higher autonomous self-regulation are more likely to adhere to the behavior change desired [<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and this is supported by findings that increased autonomous self-regulation is associated with adherence to self-monitoring behavior [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], weight loss [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In contrast, controlled regulation is driven by external pressures, such as a reward or avoidance of negative consequences. Although there is evidence that controlled regulation results in success in the short term [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], it is predicted that without autonomous regulation, positive changes in behaviors and weight loss will not be maintained [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In a systematic review of mediators of weight loss [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], only one study examined the mediating role of autonomous self-regulation [<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]; an intervention aimed at promoting autonomous regulation resulted in greater weight loss than a general health education program and intervention effects on 3 year weight change were partially mediated by autonomous self-regulation at 2 years [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], supporting the proposition that autonomous diet self-regulation contributes to weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
              <p>Overall, although there is evidence that dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous self-regulation are associated with weight control, there have been few formal mediation analyses examining whether change in these factors mediate the impact of effective interventions. In addition, of those mediation analyses that have been conducted, traditional regression methods have been used, which only examine two time points. This results in the loss of information or requires several analyses between each set of time points. Using only two time points, especially the start and end of a study means that the model does not represent the trajectory of weight throughout the intervention and follow-up [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Latent growth curve analysis (LGCA) enables the analysis of the full trajectory of a variable over time. This is particularly important when individual changes follow a nonlinear trajectory, which is likely in a weight-management intervention in which a greater change during the active intervention than during follow-up is often expected [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. LGCA also enables variables to be both outcomes and predictors so that the trajectory of a potential mediator can be conditional on demographics factors while also being a predictor of an outcome. This method allows a greater understanding of the complex associations between treatment, mechanisms of action, and outcomes over time [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p>
              <sec id="s2">
                <title>The Present Study</title>
                <p>Secondary mediation analysis was conducted on data from the Weight loss Referrals for Adults in Primary care trial (the weight loss referrals for adults in primary care [WRAP] trial), which examined the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a 52 week referral to an open-group behavioral weight-management program (WW, formerly Weight Watchers) compared to a 12 week referral to the same program and a brief intervention (written materials on how to lose weight) [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Participants assigned to the 12 and 52week weight-management programs lost significantly more weight than the control group at 3 and 12 months and those assigned to the 52 week program lost significantly more weight than the 12 week program and the brief intervention at 12 and 24 months. The full results are reported in Ahern et al. [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The aim of the present study was to investigate whether the trajectories of dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous, controlled, and amotivation self-regulation of diet mediated the effect of the weight-management program on BMI trajectory over 24 months using LGCA, a method that incorporates the full trajectory of the mediators and BMI.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials" id="s3">
              <title>Method</title>
              <sec id="s4">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>Eligible participants were aged 18 years or older with a BMI of 28 kg/m<sup>2</sup> or above and were recruited through general practice records in England. Eligible individuals were identified by their primary care providers. Patients who were pregnant or were planning pregnancy within 2 years, had past or planned bariatric surgery, were already participating in a structured monitored weight-management program, were taking part in other research that would impact on the study outcomes, had a diagnosed eating disorder, or were unable to understand study information were excluded. Practices also excluded patients considered ineligible for other reasons not stated above, such as terminal illness or a mental health diagnosis. Eligible participants were then invited to take part in the study by letter and asked to contact a study coordinator for a telephone screening if interested in participating. Eligible and willing participants were given an appointment where weight and height were measured to confirm eligibility. All participants gave written informed consent [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s5">
                <title>Interventions</title>
                <p>Participants were randomly assigned to either a brief intervention, a 12 week referral to an open-group behavioral weight-management program (WW, formerly Weight Watchers) or a 52 week referral to the same program in a 2:5:5 allocation stratified by center and gender using a randomization sequence generated by the trial statistician.</p>
                <p>The brief intervention included the recognition of the problem by the GP in the form of a letter and written information on self-help weight loss strategies (British Heart Foundation Booklet: So you want to lose weight…for good). At the baseline visit, participants were read a scripted introduction that drew attention to each section of this booklet. The 12 and 52 week behavioral weight-management programs were group based and led by an individual who had personal experience of successful weight management. It included one-to-one discussions with participants at their first session and during the part of the session when participants were weighed [<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Sessions were held once a week at community-based venues and were an hour long. The core program material consisted of a food points-based system (calculated based on the participant’s age, gender, height, weight, and activity) and strategies to tackle hunger, increase physical activity, manage eating out, and keeping motivated. Sessions also included information about recipes, health and nutrition, and physical activity. Weight loss goals were between 0.5 and 1 kg per week based on a deficit of 500 kcal per day. Participants were encouraged to be physically active and work toward a goal of 10,000 steps per day. The intervention used food and activity diaries, goal setting, evaluation of progression and the provision of rewards for reaching weight loss targets. Using the taxonomy described by Michie et al. [<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], the intervention content has retrospectively been categorized into the following BCTs: provide general information on behavior-health link, prompt intention formation, prompt review of behavioral goals, prompt self-monitoring of behavior, provide feedback on performance, provide contingent rewards, set graded tasks, provide opportunities for social comparison, instruction on how to perform a behavior, information from a credible source (i.e., someone with experience of successful weight management), social support, relapse prevention, and restructuring the food environment [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>
                <p>Participants assigned to the behavioral weight-management programs were given vouchers to attend weekly sessions and use online tools for the duration of their intervention. Those allocated to the 12 week referral received vouchers to attend 12 group sessions and access to internet resources for 16 weeks and those allocated to the 52 week referral received vouchers for 52 sessions and access to internet resources for 12 months [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The vouchers covered the full cost of the sessions and access to online resources.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Measures</title>
                <p>BMI and potential mediators were collected at baseline and 3, 12 and 24 months.</p>
                <sec id="s7">
                  <title>Body mass index</title>
                  <p>Height was measured at baseline to the nearest 0.1 cm using a stadiometer, and weight was measured to the nearest 0.1 kg using a four-point segmental body composition analyzer at all time points. This was used to calculate BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s8">
                  <title>Dietary restraint</title>
                  <p>A 14-item subscale of the Three-Factor Eating Questionnaire [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] was used to assess two types of restraint: rigid control, which refers to an all-or-nothing perception of weight control, and flexible control, which refers to more adaptability in eating behaviors to control weight. In the current study, the two types of restraint were highly correlated (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = .89), so the total subscale score was used (alpha = .86). This reflects findings from other studies in which dieting behavior and weight loss are associated with similar increases in both rigid and flexible dietary restraint [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The measure includes items such as “I deliberately take small helpings as a measure of weight control.” Eight items have a true/false response option and the remaining six items are presented with a four-point Likert scale. Higher scores on this measure represent greater control over dietary behaviors [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s9">
                  <title>Self-report habit index</title>
                  <p>The self-report habit index [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] was used to measure habit strength. The measure includes items assessing behavioral frequency, automaticity, and identity (alpha = .89). The statement “Watching what I eat is something” was followed by 12 items, such as “I do frequently” or “would require effort not to do it.” The items were accompanied by seven-point Likert scales from agree to disagree. Higher scores indicate that the behavior is more habitual.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s10">
                  <title>Diet self-regulation</title>
                  <p>The measure of diet self-regulation was adapted from the treatment self-regulation questionnaire [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] to assess self-regulation of eating a healthy diet. The measure “The reason I would eat a healthy diet is” is followed by 15 items split into three subscales. The autonomous self-regulation subscale (alpha = 0.81) includes six items such as “Because it is consistent with my life goals.” The controlled self-regulation subscale (alpha = 0.88) includes six items such as “Because I want others to approve of me.” The amotivation self-regulation subscale (alpha = 0.79), a measure of the absence of motivation, included three items such as “I do not really think about it.” All items were presented with a seven-point Likert scale from not at all true to very true.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s11">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>To examine the longitudinal associations between the potential mediators and BMI, LGCA was conducted. This type of analysis, in which a curve is fitted to the variable at each of the four time points, allows examination of the trajectory of variables over the 2 years. More detail about this analysis method can be found in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>. All analyses were conducted using Mplus8, Version 1.6 [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Maximum likelihood estimation was used for all models. The analysis was conducted in three stages.</p>
                <sec id="s12">
                  <title>Step 1. Fit a latent growth curve to each variable</title>
                  <p>Scores at baseline and 3, 12, and 24 months were used to fit a curve to BMI, dietary restraint, habit strength, and the three subscales of diet self-regulation: autonomous, controlled, and amotivation. The intercept factor represented the values at baseline and the slope and quadratic factors represented the change in variables between baseline and 24 months. The means of each variable over the four time points were examined to determine the likely shape of the curve (i.e., linear or quadratic). First, a simple model was fitted in which there was a single growth factor with a variance of zero. Then, as recommended [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], increasingly complex models were fitted and compared. At each stage, if the simpler model had a better or equal fit to the more complex model, it was chosen for analysis. An example of the path diagram for the unconditional model is in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>. Once the best fitting unconditional model was chosen, variables were added to form the conditional model [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Age, gender, and treatment group were included as control variables for each latent growth factor. For the BMI curve, income and education were also controlled based on evidence that these demographic factors are associated with BMI [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These additional factors were not included in the curve for the potential mediators due to the lack of evidence supporting an association. Path diagrams for the conditional models are in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figs. 4 and 5</xref>. A piecewise analysis was also fitted, splitting the trajectories of BMI and potential mediators into two latent growth curves based on the initial change (baseline to either 3 or 12 months depending on the trajectory of the variable; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) and the subsequent return toward baseline values. This analysis was conducted to determine whether piecewise models resulted in a better fit to the variables and to explore the relationships between BMI and potential mediators at different time points in the trial.</p>
                  <fig position="float" id="F1">
                    <label>Fig. 1.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Mean change in BMI in each treatment group over 24 months.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="kaab019f0001" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                  <fig position="float" id="F2">
                    <label>Fig. 2.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Mean change in habit strength, dietary restraint, and diet self-regulation subscales in each treatment group over 24 months.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="kaab019f0002" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s13">
                  <title>Step 2. Examine associations between change in potential mediator variables and change in BMI</title>
                  <p>Parallel processes models were developed for each of the potential mediator variables and BMI. These models allow the examination of the correlation between the growth curves fitted in step one. Specifically, the curve fitted to the potential mediators in the previous step was (individually) combined with the curve fitted to the BMI trajectory to determine the correlations between the latent growth factors of the two variables.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s14">
                  <title>Step 3. Mediation models</title>
                  <p>If the trajectory of a potential mediator was associated with group allocation (identified in Step 1) and with the BMI trajectory (Step 2), then it was included in the full mediation model. The curves fitted to the potential mediators and BMI in Step 1 were combined in a single model in which the trajectory of BMI was conditional on the trajectory of potential mediators. The significance of the individual indirect effects of each mediator, total indirect effect, and the direct effect between the intervention and the BMI was examined to determine whether the intervention effect was mediated.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s15">
                  <title>Model fit</title>
                  <p>Model fit was checked at each stage. The criteria used to make a judgment on model fit were a comparative fit index (CFI) above or equal to 0.95, root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA), and standardized root mean-square residual (SRMR) below or equal to 0.08 [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A nonsignificant value of the chi-square (χ <sup>2</sup>) statistic is often used to judge model fit; however, due to the large sample size, which often results in a significant value even with a good model fit [<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], this criterion was not used in this study. The fit of each model was assessed using all criteria.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s16">
                <title>Missing Data</title>
                <p>The percentage of participants who completed the assessments at 3, 12, and 24 months was 79%, 65%, and 68%, respectively. The percentage of missing data for each treatment group and specifically for BMI and the measures are reported in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 3 and 4</xref>. The pattern of missing data was assessed and was treated as missing not at random. There was an increasing number of missing values at later time points and it is probable that dropout was linked to treatment effectiveness [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Multiple imputation was conducted using R. For each variable, the missing values were predicted; the variables selected for prediction were based on the strategy outlined by van Buuren et al. [<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. A prediction matrix (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>) shows the variables that were used to predict missing values for each variable. Full details of the method used are in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>. Convergence plots confirmed that convergence had been achieved and strip plots showed that the imputed values did not go out of the range of the actual values and that they followed the same distribution.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s17">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s18">
                <title>Baseline Characteristics</title>
                <p>Between 18 October 2012 and 10 February 2014, 1954 participants were screened and 1,267 were eligible and were randomly allocated to a condition [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The baseline characteristics of the participants (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1,267) including psychological variables are in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Additional participant characteristics can be found in the original reporting of the study [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The change in both BMI and the psychological/behavioral variables are shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. There were no significant differences between the treatment groups at baseline on BMI or the potential mediators determined by one-way analysis of variance tests. BMI and the mediator variables showed change between baseline and 3 or 12 months before a stabilization or return toward baseline between 12 and 24 months. Autonomous diet self-regulation decreased over the 24 months for all intervention groups.</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                  <label>Table 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Baseline characteristics of participants in the weight loss referrals for adults in primary care (WRAP) trial (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1,267)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="6" rowspan="1">Treatment group</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Brief intervention</th>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">12 week intervention</th>
                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">52 week intervention</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">358</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  None</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GCSE/A-level/equivalent</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> University degree or higher/equivalent</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Under £20,000</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> £20–£49,999</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> £50,000+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prefer not to say or missing</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.91</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.07</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.60</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.27</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.98</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.43</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.68</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.45</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary restraint</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habit strength</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet self-regulation</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Amotivation</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Autonomous</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.93</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.04</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Controlled</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="fn-0100">
                      <p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index; <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> standard deviation; GCSE general certificate of secondary education.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s19">
                <title>Latent Growth Curve Analysis</title>
                <sec id="s20">
                  <title>Step 1. Fit a latent growth curve to each variable</title>
                  <p>A latent growth curve was fitted to the four time points (baseline and 3, 12, and 24 months) for BMI, dietary restraint, habit strength, and the three subscales of diet self-regulation (autonomous, controlled, and amotivation). A quadratic growth curve was the best fitting model for all variables other than the amotivation subscale of diet self-regulation for which an intercept-only model was the best fit. For the other four potential mediators (dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous and controlled diet self-regulation), the model was able to converge and fitted best when the variance of the quadratic factor was set to 0. The model for BMI fitted well without this restriction. The results from the increasingly complex unconditional models are reported in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 5–10</xref>. Once the best fitting unconditional model was established, the conditional factors were added. The values for each of the latent growth factors along with fit statistics of the conditional model are shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The model fit for all variables was good for all the criteria other than the model for BMI, which did not meet the cutoff criteria for CFI and RMSEA. However, the values were close to the criteria, indicating that the model provided a reasonable description of the data.</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                    <label>Table 2.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Model fits to trajectory of BMI and psychological/behavioral variables</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFI </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSEA</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRMR</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.16 (1.02)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.95)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.32)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary restraint</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82 (0.37)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68 (0.59)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.87 (0.19)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habit strength</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (0.19)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.27)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.21 (0.11)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSR autonomous</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75 (0.13)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.16 (0.33)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 (0.13)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSR controlled</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 (0.17)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08 (0.30)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.13)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSR amotivation</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 (0.12)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="fn-0101">
                        <p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index; <italic toggle="yes">CFI</italic> comparative fit index; <italic toggle="yes">DSR</italic> diet self-regulation; <italic toggle="yes">RMSEA</italic> root mean square error of approximation; <italic toggle="yes">SRMR</italic> standardized root mean square residual.</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn id="fn-0102">
                        <p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .00. </p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <p><xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the full details of the associations between the latent growth factors of each variable and age, gender, and treatment group in the conditional models. There were significant effects of both the 12 and 52 week program on the slope and quadratic of the BMI trajectory, controlling for age, gender, income, and education. There were significant effects of both the 12 and 52 week program on the slope and quadratic factors of dietary restraint and habit strength but only the 52 week intervention significantly impacted autonomous diet self-regulation. Age and gender were controlled for in all models. Gender was associated with the slope and quadratic of dietary restraint and controlled diet self-regulation, and age was associated with the slope and quadratic of autonomous diet self-regulation.</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                    <label>Table 3.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Coefficients of age, gender, and group allocation on trajectories of BMI and potential mediators</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (reference group male)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th>
                          <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment group (reference brief intervention)</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 week group</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 week group</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.31)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04 (0.01)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.52 (0.27)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 (0.01) **</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.91 (0.38)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.82 (0.39)***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quadratic</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.10)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.003)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 (0.13)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.13) ***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary restraint</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 (0.18)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.01)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.86 (0.24)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.01)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.29)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 (0.31)***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quadratic</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (0.08)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003 (0.003)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30 (0.10)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.47 (0.10)***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habit</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 (0.09)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.003)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.11)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004 (0.004)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 (0.14)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.14)***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quadratic</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 (0.04)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002 (0.002)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16 (0.06)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.23 (0.06)***</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet self-regulation autonomous</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.06)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.002)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.24 (0.13)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.01)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 (0.16) </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.17)*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quadratic</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.05)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01 (0.002)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06 (0.07)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.15 (0.07)*</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet self-regulation controlled</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.08)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003 (0.003)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.38 (0.13)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.01)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (0.13) </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.17)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quadratic</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (0.05)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.002)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05 (0.06)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12 (0.07)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet self-regulation amotivation</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07 (0.03)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.04)*</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="fn-0103">
                        <p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index.</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn id="fn-0104">
                        <p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001. </p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <p>There were significant associations between the BMI intercept and slope (estimate = −2.31, standard error [<italic toggle="yes">SE</italic>] = 0.77, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .002), intercept and quadratic (estimate = 0.72, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.30, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .02), and slope and quadratic growth factors (estimate = −2.81, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.30, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), indicating that a higher BMI at baseline was associated with a steeper decline in BMI and a steeper return toward the baseline BMI. There were also significant correlations between the intercepts and slopes of dietary restraint (estimate = 0.40, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.12, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001) and controlled diet self-regulation (estimate = −0.05, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .02), indicating that higher baseline values resulted in a lower slope (lesser increase) for controlled diet self-regulation and a higher slope (greater increase) for dietary restraint. The correlations between the intercept and slope of autonomous diet regulation (estimate = 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .10) and habit strength (estimate = -.04, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.41) were nonsignificant. Piecewise latent growth curves were fitted to the trajectories of BMI and the potential mediators; however, this resulted in a poorer fit than the quadratic model. Full results are in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 11–14</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s21">
                  <title>Step 2. Examine associations between change in potential mediator variables and change in BMI</title>
                  <p>The associations between each of the latent growth factors of the potential mediator variables and the latent growth factors of BMI along with the model fit statistics are in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. There were negative associations between the slopes of BMI and three potential mediator variables; dietary restraint (estimate = −0.60, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003), habit strength (estimate = −0.36, <italic toggle="yes">SE =</italic> 0.08, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001), and autonomous diet self-regulation (estimate = −0.87, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). Increases in these potential mediators were associated with decreases in BMI. At baseline, a higher controlled diet self-regulation score was associated with a higher BMI (estimate = 0.71, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) but the association between the slopes was nonsignificant (estimate = −0.02, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> = 0.06, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .74). The amotivation subscale of diet self-regulation was specified as an intercept-only model, so the correlation of the change over time in this variable with change in BMI could not be examined. Although the curve of the potential mediator variables were quadratic, the quadratic growth factors were fixed to 0 and, therefore, the correlation between this and the BMI growth factors could not be calculated. Although three models fell slightly below the criteria recommended for the CFI, all were close and met other measures of fit.</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                    <label>Table 4.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Correlations between the latent growth factors of BMI and potential mediators</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
                          <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">BMI growth factors</th>
                          <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Fit statistics</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFI</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSEA</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRMR</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietary restraint</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.57 (0.36)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.28 (0.36)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.12)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.22)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.60 (0.20)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.07) </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habit strength</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.35 (0.19)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.17)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01 (0.06)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (0.10)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36 (0.08)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 (0.03)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autonomous diet self-regulation </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.14)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.11)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 (0.04)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.45 (0.31)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.87 (0.25)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.09)**</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controlled diet self-regulation </td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.19)***</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03 (0.15)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.05)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Slope</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12 (0.08)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02 (0.06)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.02)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="fn-0105">
                        <p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index; <italic toggle="yes">CFI</italic> comparative fit index; <italic toggle="yes">RMSEA</italic> root mean square error of approximation; <italic toggle="yes">SRMR</italic> standardized root mean square residual.</p>
                      </fn>
                      <fn id="fn-0106">
                        <p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001. </p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <p>In the piecewise analyses, associations between the slopes of the mediators in the intervention (0–12 months) and maintenance phases (12–24 months) were examined. In the intervention phase, the BMI slope was associated with the slopes of dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation. The BMI slope in the maintenance phase was associated with the slope of autonomous diet self-regulation in the intervention phase and the slope of habit in the maintenance phase. However, the fit of the piecewise models was poor based on model fit statistics (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 15</xref>). Therefore, these results should be interpreted with caution and a full mediation model was not examined.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s22">
                  <title>Step 3. Mediation models</title>
                  <p>In Step 1, it was determined that there were treatment effects of both the 12 and 52 week intervention on BMI trajectory compared to the control group. Of the potential mediators, dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation were associated with both treatment group (Step 1) and BMI trajectory (Step 2). The amotivation and controlled subscales of diet self-regulation did not fit these criteria and, therefore, were not included.</p>
                  <p>Mediation models were tested to determine whether the impact of the intervention on BMI slope was mediated by the slope of dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation (the variance of the quadratic variables was restricted to 0 and, therefore, could not be included as a mediator). The results of the separate models for each of the potential mediators are in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 16</xref> and indicate that dietary restraint and habit strength were significant mediators of the 12 week intervention and that all three variables were significant mediators of the 52 week intervention. A full mediation model with all three mechanisms of action was then tested. When fitted, the total effects of both interventions on BMI slope were significant and the direct effects became nonsignificant (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The total indirect effect via the three mediator variables was significant; for the 12 week intervention effect, only the individual indirect effect of dietary restraint was statistically significant, whereas for the 52 week intervention, the individual indirect of all three variables were significant. Effect sizes were larger for the 52 week program than the 12 week program on all mediators but only significantly larger for dietary restraint and habit strength. Model fit statistics indicate an adequate fit on RMSEA (0.06) and SRMR (0.06) measures and was close to the fit criteria for CFI (0.94). The results of this are shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> and a simplified model is included in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> (full model tested is presented in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" id="T5">
                    <label>Table 5.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Total, direct, and indirect effects via mediating variables of the 12 and 52 week intervention on BMI</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="vsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effects</th>
                          <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">12 week intervention</th>
                          <th colspan="3" rowspan="1">52 week intervention</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total impact of intervention on BMI</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.69</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.72</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct effect of intervention on BMI when mediators included</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.51</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total indirect effect of mediating variables</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.33</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.13</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indirect effect of mediators</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dietary restraint</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.61</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.98</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> .008</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Habit strength</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.56</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.88</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> .018</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Autonomous diet self-regulation</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.27</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> .048</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <fn id="fn-0107">
                        <p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index; <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> standard error.</p>
                      </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                  <fig position="float" id="F3">
                    <label>Fig. 3.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Mediation path diagram.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="kaab019f0003" position="float"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s23">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation mediated the effect of a weight-management program on BMI change. The 12 and 52 week programs were both associated with increases in dietary restraint and habit strength and the 52 week program was also associated with a lower reduction in autonomous diet self-regulation. These changes were associated with decreases in BMI over the 2 years. When controlling for change in habit strength, dietary restraint, and autonomous diet self-regulation, the impact of both the 12 and 52 week programs on the slope of BMI became nonsignificant. Although the combined indirect effect was significant for both the 12 and 52 week interventions, for the shorter intervention, only the individual direct effect of dietary restraint was significant, whereas the indirect direct effect of all three variables were significant for the 52 week intervention.</p>
              <p>This intervention included several BCTs and so it is not possible to establish which specific BCTs or combination of BCTs resulted in the increases in dietary restraint and habit strength observed during the 12 and 52 week weight-management programs. However, the intervention included several BCTs that have been linked with behavioral regulation, including self-monitoring of behavior and outcomes, through food and activity diaries and regular weight measurement, goal setting, and action planning [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Behavioral regulation is defined as behavioral, cognitive, and/or emotional skills for managing or changing behavior [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Given that dietary restraint can be considered as behavioral and cognitive control of eating behavior, these BCTs may have contributed to the observed increase in dietary restraint.</p>
              <p>The BCTs that may have contributed to the increase in habit strength are social support, restricting the food environment and general information on behavior-health link. These have all been linked to behavioral cueing, a construct that promotes the formation of habits [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. However, the finding that habit strength was a significant independent mediator for the 52 week intervention but not the 12 week intervention indicates that the intervention length might be an influential moderating factor. This may be linked to a higher “dose” of the BCTs in the 52 week intervention compared to the 12 week intervention due to the longer duration, which may help the formation of stronger habits to support weight maintenance. This formation of stronger habits may be particularly important as piecewise analysis indicated that a reduction in habit strength following the intervention was associated with an increase in BMI. Given that the content of the weight-management programs were the same other than their length, the 52 week intervention provided participants with continued social support from the group leader and other attendees, as well as more opportunity to perform behaviors frequently in a stable context compared to the 12 week intervention; this may have enabled the transition of diet monitoring behavior from deliberative to automatic control [<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], which, in turn, supported weight loss maintenance. Such an interpretation is in line with dual-process theories. These theories outline deliberative (or reflective) processes that involve conscious and rational decision-making and automatic (or impulsive) processes that involve nonconscious, learned reactions [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55–57</xref>]. This is particularly important in health behaviors when individuals aiming to perform healthy behaviors often have to overcome unhealthy habitual behaviors and make conscious and reasoned healthier decisions [<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. These findings support the use of long-term interventions that may facilitate the transition from deliberative attempts to control eating (dietary restraint) to more automatic and less effortful self-regulation of eating behavior (habit strength).</p>
              <p>Although autonomous self-regulation was identified as an independent significant mediator for the 52 week intervention, all groups actually experienced a decrease in autonomous motivation throughout the trial and follow-up. This indicates that, although the lesser reduction experienced by the individuals in the 52 week intervention compared to the other two groups was beneficial (for weight loss), all interventions (including the brief intervention) had a negative effect on autonomous self-regulation. It is possible that this, and other, weight-management interventions may have a negative impact on autonomous self-regulation through implicitly promoting the message that participants need to be told what to do by people with expertise in order to manage their weight [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This is supported by qualitative findings from the WRAP trial that suggested that participants felt a sense of obligation to the leader of the group sessions [<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The weight loss and weight loss maintenance achieved in both the 12 and 52 week intervention may have been greater if autonomous self-regulation had been maintained or increased during the intervention.</p>
              <p>The findings have implications for the content of future interventions. Given that dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation mediated the effect of the weight-management program on weight loss and maintenance over 2 years, researchers should consider including BCTs that are hypothesized to target these mechanisms of action in future interventions. Recent research that has sought to link specific BCTs and mechanisms of action could be used to identify further BCTs to increase dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. For example, expert consensus exercises have indicated that the BCTs of introducing prompts and cues for a desired behavior and avoiding or reducing exposure to cues for an unhealthy behavior may be linked to behavioral cueing [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], a mechanism of action that is likely to support the formation of new habits. Similarly, self-monitoring and goal setting have been linked to behavioral regulation [<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and could be used as strategies to support dietary restraint. Although a range of BCTs have been linked with motivation as a mechanism of action, including the use of rewards and the consideration of pros and cons [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], particular attention needs to be given to how to specifically target autonomous motivation. For example, interventions implementing an autonomy-supportive environment, in which individuals are encouraged to engage in health-related behaviors for their own reasons, are supported in overcoming barriers to change, and are made to feel accepted and respected, have been found to be associated with higher autonomous self-regulation, a healthier diet, and greater weight loss in a meta-analysis [<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In contrast, techniques such as the use of rewards may foster more extrinsic or controlled forms of motivation, which, although may promote initial behavior change, may not be sufficient to support the maintenance of behavior change [<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In addition, given that the longer duration of intervention was associated with larger changes in dietary restraint and habit strength, researchers should consider interventions that provide support over an extended period of time to promote sustained changes in those mechanisms of action that contribute to weight loss maintenance.</p>
              <p>A key strength of this study compared to previous studies was the use of LGCA to disentangle the complex system of interactions between behavioral weight-management interventions, mechanisms of action, and the trajectory of weight change. This method enabled a mediation analysis that accounted for changes at every time point rather than just two time points that are often considered in traditional regression methods. This is particularly important as changes in the mediators and BMI were nonlinear and an analysis assuming a linear trajectory may not have captured the full impact of the mediating variables. This method also enabled growth factors to be both outcomes and predictors. For example, the model tested enabled the slope of the habit strength to be an outcome conditional on treatment group, age, and gender and a predictor of the BMI trajectory simultaneously. These results largely support previous research, which indicates that dietary restraint, habit strength, and self-regulation are potential mediators for the effect of a behavior weight-management program on weight loss and weight loss maintenance [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In particular, the findings add to the small number of formal mediation analyses on these factors [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and, using a complex method examining the mediating action of the three variables simultaneously, provide evidence that these are relevant mechanisms of action for weight management.</p>
              <p>There were some study limitations that needed to be taken into consideration when interpreting the findings. First, it was not possible to include the associations between the quadratic growth factors of the mediators and the trajectory of BMI due to nonconvergence of the individual latent growth curves (conducted in Step 1 of the analysis) when allowing the variance of the quadratic factors to vary between individuals. Thus, the rate of acceleration/deceleration of change in BMI was not conditional on the acceleration/deceleration of change (quadratic) of the mediating variables. Including this would have resulted in a greater understanding of the associations between the mediators and BMI. However, even without this, the model fit was adequate. Second, the attrition rate was over 30% at 12 and 24 months, which could have introduced some bias; however, multiple imputation was used, which is a valid general method for managing missing data in RCTs [<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Finally, although participants were referred to the commercial weight loss program and the cost of sessions was covered for a set period of time (either 12 or 52 weeks), attendance at weekly sessions was not recorded consistently throughout the trial. Due to the large proportion of missing data on attendance (40%), it was not included as a covariate in the analysis. Therefore, the potential impact of attendance on both the mediators and BMI was not controlled for.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, dietary restraint, habit strength, and autonomous diet self-regulation were all identified as mechanisms of action for the effective 52 week weight-management program. The finding that habit strength was only a significant mediator of the 52 week program suggests that longer interventions may provide the consistency of support required for behaviors to move from deliberative to habitual control. BCTs that target dietary restraint and habit strength and maintain or increase autonomous diet self-regulation should be considered when designing weight loss and weight loss maintenance interventions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>kaab019_suppl_Supplementary_Material</label>
                <media xlink:href="kaab019_suppl_supplementary_material.docx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="a1">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>We thank the WRAP trial investigators Paul Aveyard, Emma Boyland, Simon Cohn, Jason Halford, Susan Jebb, Adrian Mander, and Marc Suhrcke for allowing us to use the WRAP trial data for our analysis. </p>
            </ack>
            <sec id="s0105">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>S.B. is supported by the Wellcome Trust Doctoral Training Centre in Public Health Economics and Decision Science (108903/Z/19/Z) and the University of Sheffield. The original trial (WRAP trial), on which this analysis was conducted, was funded by the National Prevention Research Initiative (MR/J000493/1). A.L.A. is supported by the Medical Research Council (MC_UU_00006/6).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0106">
              <title>Compliance With Ethical Standards</title>
              <p><bold>Authors’ Statement of Conflict of Interest and Adherence to Ethical Standards</bold> The WRAP trial was publicly funded but the intervention for the trial was delivered by WW (formerly Weight Watchers) at no cost.</p>
              <p><bold>Authors’ Contributions</bold> ALA was the chief investigator of the WRAP trial and provided the data that was analyzed. SB planned and conducted the analysis with input from ALA, PN, PB and AB. All authors contributed to the interpretation of results. SB wrote the first draft of the manuscript. All authors contributed to the writing and critical revisions of the manuscript.</p>
              <p><bold>Ethical Approval</bold> This study was secondary data analysis of a randomized controlled trial. Ethical approval for the original trial was received from NRES Committee East of England Cambridge East and local approvals from NRES Committee North West Liverpool Central and NRES Committee South Central Oxford. The current article does not contain any additional studies with human participants or animals and only includes analysis of data collected in the previous randomized controlled trial. </p>
              <p><bold>Informed Consent</bold> Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the randomised controlled trial [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] on which the analysis in this paper was based.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list id="r1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CIT0001">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</collab>. <comment>Overweight &amp; obesity statistics</comment>. Available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-statistics/overweight-obesity" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-statistics/overweight-obesity</ext-link>. Accessibility verified <comment>February 15, 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0002">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS Digital</collab>. <comment>Statistics on obesity, physical activity and diet</comment>. Available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/publications/statistical/statistics-on-obesity-physical-activity-and-diet" ext-link-type="uri">https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/publications/statistical/statistics-on-obesity-physical-activity-and-diet</ext-link>. Accessibility verified <comment>Febraury 15, 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0003">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stegenga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Guideline Development Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Identification, assessment, and management of overweight and obesity: Summary of updated NICE guidance</article-title>. <source>BMJ.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>349</volume>:<fpage>g6608</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25430558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0004">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patnode</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redmond</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rushkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral and pharmacotherapy weight loss interventions to prevent obesity-related morbidity and mortality in adults: Updated evidence report and systematic review for the US Preventive Services Task Force</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>320</volume>:<fpage>1172</fpage>–<lpage>1191</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30326501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0005">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Loveman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The clinical effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of long-term weight management schemes for adults: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Health Technol Assess.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0006">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knittle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avenell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Araújo-Soares</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sniehotta</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long term maintenance of weight loss with non-surgical interventions in obese adults: Systematic review and meta-analyses of randomised controlled trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>g2646</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25134100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0007">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dansinger</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tatsioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balk</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis: The effect of dietary counseling for weight loss</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17606960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0008">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Carels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koball</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A randomized trial comparing two approaches to weight loss: Differences in weight loss maintenance</article-title>. <source>J Health Psychol.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0009">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>From theory-inspired to theory-based interventions: A protocol for developing and testing a methodology for linking behaviour change techniques to theoretical mechanisms of action</article-title>. <source>Ann Behav Med.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27401001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0010">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Butryn</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wadden</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral treatment of obesity</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Clin North Am.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0011">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Westenhoefer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stunkard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pudel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of the flexible and rigid control dimensions of dietary restraint</article-title>. <source>Int J Eat Disord.</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10349584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0012">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary restraint and self-regulation in eating behavior</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond).</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0013">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papandonatos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Maintaining large weight losses: The role of behavioral and psychological factors</article-title>. <source>J Consult Clin Psychol.</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1015</fpage>–<lpage>1021</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19045969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0014">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vogels</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diepvens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westerterp-Plantenga</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of long-term weight maintenance</article-title>. <source>Obes Res.</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2162</fpage>–<lpage>2168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421351</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0015">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Weight-loss maintenance for 10 years in the National Weight Control Registry</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0016">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carraça</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Successful behavior change in obesity interventions in adults: A systematic review of self-regulation mediators</article-title>. <source>BMC Med.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25907778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0017">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Mediators of weight loss and weight loss maintenance in middle‐aged women</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19696752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0018">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>JaKa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Mediation of weight loss and weight loss maintenance through dietary disinhibition and restraint</article-title>. <source>J Obes Weight Loss Ther</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148471</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0019">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Orbell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verplanken</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The strength of habit</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol Rev.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25559285</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0020">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The habitual consumer</article-title>. <source>J Consum Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0021">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Orbell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verplanken</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The automatic component of habit in health behavior: Habit as cue-contingent automaticity</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20658824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0022">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding college students’ fruit consumption. Integrating habit strength in the theory of planned behaviour</article-title>. <source>Appetite.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0023">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adriaanse</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The power of habits: Unhealthy snacking behaviour is primarily predicted by habit strength</article-title>. <source>Br J Health Psychol.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22385098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0024">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lally</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chipperfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Healthy habits: Efficacy of simple advice on weight control based on a habit-formation model</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond).</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>700</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18071344</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0025">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A feasibility randomised controlled trial of a motivational interviewing-based intervention for weight loss maintenance in adults</article-title>. <source>Health Technol Assess.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0026">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beeken</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leurent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickerstaff</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A brief intervention for weight control based on habit-formation theory delivered through primary care: Results from a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond).</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0027">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kliemann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickerstaff</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nazareth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beeken</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of self-regulatory skills and automaticity on the effectiveness of a brief weight loss habit-based intervention: Secondary analysis of the 10 top tips randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0028">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmeira</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivation, self-determination, and long-term weight control</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22385818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0029">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hardcastle</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Autonomous and controlled motivational regulations for multiple health-related behaviors: Between- and within-participants analyses</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol Behav Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25750803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0030">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stiff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The strength model of self-regulation failure and health-related behaviour</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0031">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowling</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivation and its relationship to adherence to self-monitoring and weight loss in a 16-week Internet behavioral weight loss intervention</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Educ Behav.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0032">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Going</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houtkooper</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Exercise motivation, eating, and body image variables as predictors of weight control</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc.</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16394972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0033">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carraça</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Exercise autonomous motivation predicts 3-yr weight loss in women</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0034">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houfek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pullen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivational factors predict weight loss in rural adults</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nurs.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26105202</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0035">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Using self-determination theory to promote physical activity and weight control: A randomized controlled trial in women</article-title>. <source>J Behav Med.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20012179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0036">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wickrama</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Neal</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>FO.</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Higher-Order Growth Curves and Mixture Modeling With Mplus: A Practical Guide</source>. <publisher-name>Oxfordshire, UK: Routledge</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0037">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aveyard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Extended and standard duration weight-loss programme referrals for adults in primary care (WRAP): A randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>:<fpage>2214</fpage>–<lpage>2225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28478041</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0038">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adab</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A randomised controlled trial to compare a range of commercial or primary care led weight reduction programmes with a minimal intervention control for weight loss in obesity: The lighten up trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20663185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0039">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ashford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sniehotta</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>French</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A refined taxonomy of behaviour change techniques to help people change their physical activity and healthy eating behaviours: The CALO-RE taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21678185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0040">
                <label>40.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hartmann‐Boyce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jebb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Behavioural weight management programmes for adults assessed by trials conducted in everyday contexts: Systematic review and meta‐analysis</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>920</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25112559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0041">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Public Health England</collab>. <comment>Uptake and retention in group-based weight-management services: Literature review and behavioural analysis</comment>. Available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uptake-and-retention-in-group-based-weight-management-services" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/uptake-and-retention-in-group-based-weight-management-services</ext-link>. Accessibility verified <comment>February 13, 2020</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0042">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aveyard</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Weight loss referrals for adults in primary care (WRAP): Protocol for a multi-centre randomised controlled trial comparing the clinical and cost-effectiveness of primary care referral to a commercial weight loss provider for 12 weeks, referral for 52 weeks, and a brief self-help intervention [ISRCTN82857232]</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>620</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24943673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0043">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stunkard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Messick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The three-factor eating questionnaire to measure dietary restraint, disinhibition and hunger</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res.</source><year>1985</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3981480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0044">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>York-Crowe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Measurement of dietary restraint: Validity tests of four questionnaires</article-title>. <source>Appetite.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17101191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0045">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>French</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between restraint and weight and weight-related behaviors among individuals in a community weight gain prevention trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord.</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>574</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11319664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0046">
                <label>46.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Verplanken</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orbell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reflections on past behavior: A self‐report index of habit strength</article-title>. <source>J Appl Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1313</fpage>–<lpage>1330</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0047">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bodenhamer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validating the theoretical structure of the Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire (TSRQ) across three different health behaviors</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Res.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0048">
                <label>48.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wichman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>NE.</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Latent Growth Curve Modeling</source>. <publisher-name>Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0049">
                <label>49.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tyrrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Height, body mass index, and socioeconomic status: Mendelian randomisation study in UK Biobank</article-title>. <source>BMJ.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>352</volume>:<fpage>i582</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26956984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0050">
                <label>50.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moroshko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of dropout in weight loss interventions: A systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>912</fpage>–<lpage>934</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21815990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0051">
                <label>51.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Buuren</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groothuis-Oudshoorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>mice: Multivariate imputation by chained equations in R</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0052">
                <label>52.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Links between behavior change techniques and mechanisms of action: An expert consensus study</article-title>. <source>Ann Behav Med.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>708</fpage>–<lpage>720</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0053">
                <label>53.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Behavior change techniques and their mechanisms of action: A synthesis of links described in published intervention literature</article-title>. <source>Ann Behav Med.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30304386</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0054">
                <label>54.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Habit and intention in everyday life: The multiple processes by which past behavior predicts future behavior</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull.</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0055">
                <label>55.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henshaw</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heffernan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Applying theories of health behaviour and change to hearing health research: Time for a new approach</article-title>. <source>Int J Audiol.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>S99</fpage>–<lpage>S104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27138716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0056">
                <label>56.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-conscious processes and dual-process theories in health psychology</article-title>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0057">
                <label>57.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Thinking, Fast and Slow</source>. <publisher-name>New York City, NY: Macmillan</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0058">
                <label>58.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boyland</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jebb</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Participants’ explanatory model of being overweight and their experiences of 2 weight loss interventions</article-title>. <source>Ann Fam Med.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23690325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0059">
                <label>59.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ntoumanis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thøgersen-Ntoumani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Self-determination theory applied to health cntexts: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Perspect Psychol Sci.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26168470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0060">
                <label>60.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kwasnicka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sniehotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Theoretical explanations for maintenance of behaviour change: A systematic review of behaviour theories</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol Rev.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0061">
                <label>61.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname><given-names>NLD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-determination theory.</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>Predicting Health Behaviour</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Education</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>;<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CIT0062">
                <label>62.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gluud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wetterslev</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>When and how should multiple imputation be used for handling missing data in randomised clinical trials—A practical guide with flowcharts</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Res Methodol.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29207961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
