<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:09:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10359587" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10359587</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-07-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmjgroup</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Thorax</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Thorax</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">thoraxjnl</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">thorax</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Thorax</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0040-6376</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1468-3296</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10359587</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10359587</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10359587</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36198573</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36198573</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">thoraxjnl-2022-218874</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thorax-2022-218874</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Critical Care</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>1506</subject>
                  <subject>2313</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <series-title>Original research</series-title>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Acute hypoxaemic respiratory failure after treatment with lower tidal volume ventilation facilitated by extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal: long-term outcomes from the REST randomised trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-64249165" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6201-805X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Boyle</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrew J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-49997076" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McDowell</surname>
                    <given-names>Clíona</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-49978981" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Agus</surname>
                    <given-names>Ashley</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-95965027" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Logan</surname>
                    <given-names>Danielle</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-95965028" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                    <given-names>Jonathan D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-49997118" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jackson</surname>
                    <given-names>Colette</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-95965031" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mills</surname>
                    <given-names>Jeanette</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-95965032" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McNamee</surname>
                    <given-names>James J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-21527349" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>McAuley</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniel F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Wellcome-Wolfson Institute for Experimental Medicine</institution>, <institution>Queen's University Belfast</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Belfast</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Regional Intensive Care Unit</institution>, <institution>Royal Victoria Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Belfast</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Northern Ireland Clinical Trials Unit</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Belfast</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Andrew J Boyle, Wellcome-Wolfson Institute for Experimental Medicine, Queen's University Belfast, Belfast, UK; <email>aboyle26@qub.ac.uk</email>
</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>78</volume>
              <issue>8</issue>
              <fpage>767</fpage>
              <lpage>774</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>23</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <ali:free_to_read/>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense" start_date="2022-10-05">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported (CC BY 4.0) license, which permits others to copy, redistribute, remix, transform and build upon this work for any purpose, provided the original work is properly cited, a link to the licence is given, and indication of whether changes were made. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="thorax-2022-218874.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>Lower tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by veno-venous extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal (vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R), does not improve 90-day mortality in patients with acute hypoxaemic respiratory failure (AHRF). The aim of this analysis was to evaluate the effect of this therapeutic strategy on long-term outcomes.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>This was a prespecified analysis of the REST trial, a UK-wide multicentre randomised clinical trial that compared lower tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R (intervention), with standard care in the treatment of patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF. Mortality to 2 years was assessed, while respiratory function, post-traumatic stress disorder, cognitive function and health-related quality of life were evaluated in survivors at 1 year using standardised questionnaires.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Of 412 patients enrolled into the REST trial, 391 (95%) had 2-year mortality outcome data available. There was no difference in the time to death between intervention and standard care (HR 1.08 (0.81, 1.44); log-rank test p=0.61). 161 patients alive at 1 year provided at least one questionnaire response. There was no difference in respiratory function, post-traumatic stress disorder, cognitive dysfunction or health-related quality of life between patients allocated to intervention or standard care.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Lower-tidal volume ventilation facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R does not affect 1-year mortality in patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF. Of the patients who provided questionnaire responses, there was no treatment effect on long-term respiratory function, post-traumatic stress disorder, cognitive dysfunction or health-related quality of life.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration number</title>
                  <p>ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: <ext-link xlink:href="NCT02654327" ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov">NCT02654327</ext-link>.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>ARDS</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group id="funding-1">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000664</institution-id>
                      <institution>Health Technology Assessment Programme</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>13/143/02</award-id>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="funding-2">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Health Research Board of Ireland</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>CTN 2014-012</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>special-feature</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>unlocked</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float">
              <sec>
                <title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Patients admitted to the intensive care unit with acute hypoxaemic respiratory failure (AHRF) have significant long-term morbidity and mortality. The use of veno-venous extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal (vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R) to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation does not improve 90-day mortality, but the effects on long-term mortality and functional outcomes are unclear.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>In this prespecified analysis of the REST trial, lower-tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R, does not affect long-term mortality, or other long-term outcomes in patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF who completed follow-up.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>These findings reinforce that a lower tidal volume ventilation strategy, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R as delivered in the REST trial, should not be used in the management of patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF, and that vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R should not be used routinely outside the setting of clinical trials.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
            </boxed-text>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Acute hypoxaemic respiratory failure (AHRF) is one of the most frequent indications for admission to the intensive care unit (ICU), and is associated with hospital inpatient mortality rates of approximately 40%.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In addition to this high short-term mortality, patients with AHRF are also at increased risk of death in the 2-year period following hospital admission.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
</p>
              <p>Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is a common cause of AHRF, and survivors of ARDS have a significant and persistent functional limitation up to 5 years after discharge from the ICU, with over 50% of patients not returning to work.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref> For survivors of critical care admission, the prevalence of psychiatric symptoms, including PTSD and anxiety, may be greater than 60%, while cognitive impairment affects up to 60% of patients with ARDS who survive to 1 year.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8</xref> Mechanical ventilation can induce hippocampal neuronal cell apoptosis,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and preclinical models suggest that this may be exacerbated by higher tidal volume ventilation.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> It is therefore feasible that strategies aimed at reducing the tidal volume delivered as part of mechanical ventilation for patients with AHRF may reduce the long-term psychological and cognitive impact in patients with AHRF who survive hospital admission.</p>
              <p>The short-term and long-term outcomes from AHRF emphasise the importance of continuing to identify novel therapies that may improve these. The protective ventilation with veno-venous lung assist in respiratory failure (REST) trial evaluated the use of veno-venous extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal (vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R) (using a device with maximal blood flow rate of up to 550 mL/min and CO<sub>2</sub> removal capacity of approximately 80–90 mL/min<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation in patients with AHRF.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The REST trial aimed to achieve mechanical ventilation with a tidal volume of ≤3 mL/kg predicted body weight (PBW), while the comparator group received standard care. The REST trial was discontinued by the data monitoring and ethics committee prior to recruitment of the planned sample size, and the results of the trial did not demonstrate any short-term benefit of lower tidal volume ventilation facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R. Given that AHRF is associated with increased risk of death for up to 2 years,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and adherence to a lung-protective ventilation strategy is associated with improved long-term outcomes in ARDS,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> it is feasible that analysis of the long-term outcomes of patients recruited to the REST trial may identify benefit from the intervention strategy. Furthermore, it is uncertain whether lower tidal volume ventilation, below current standards of care,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 15</xref> is associated with long-term improvements in functional status of survivors of AHRF. The aim of this analysis was to assess whether lower tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R, was associated with a reduction in long-term mortality, and whether it improved long-term respiratory, psychological and cognitive function, or health-related quality of life, in survivors of AHRF.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="s2-1">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This was a planned secondary analysis of the REST trial.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The REST trial was a multicentre, randomised, allocation concealed, open, pragmatic clinical trial, conducted across 51 ICUs in the UK, evaluating lower tidal volume ventilation facilitated by ECCO<sub>2</sub>R with standard care. Between May 2016 and December 2019, 412 participants were enrolled. Patients were eligible for the REST trial if they were within 48 hours of onset of an acute and potentially reversible cause of hypoxaemic respiratory failure (defined as a ratio of the partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood to the fractional inspired concentration of oxygen (PF) ratio&lt;150 mm Hg) while receiving invasive mechanical ventilation with a positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) of at least 5 cm H<sub>2</sub>O.</p>
                <p>In patients randomised to receive intervention, vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R was commenced via a percutaneous catheter inserted into a central vein. Intravenous heparin was commenced as systemic anticoagulation to prevent circuit thrombosis, and sweep gas flow of 10 L/min was commenced to maximise carbon dioxide removal. Tidal volume reduction was performed in increments, aiming for a tidal volume≤3 mL/kg predicted body weight. The intervention was intended to be continued for at least 48 hours, and for a maximum of 7 days. Patients who were randomised to standard care were recommended to receive mechanical ventilation with a tidal volume 6 mL/kg predicted body weight, with PEEP titrated according to the ARDSNet protocol.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> There was no statistically significant difference between treatment arms in 90-day mortality, and the full results of the REST trial have previously been reported.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-2">
                <title>St George’s Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ)</title>
                <p>To assess for an effect on long-term respiratory function, patients enrolled into the REST trial who consented to long-term follow-up were contacted to complete the SGRQ. The SGRQ is a 50-item questionnaire that has 76 weighted responses and is separated into three domains (symptoms, activity and impacts), with a lower score indicating fewer symptoms within that domain.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> For responders to the SGRQ, results are subdivided into the three domains. Data was included for individual domains regardless of whether the full questionnaire was completed. The SGRQ was sent by post to patients, and non-responders had follow-up contact by telephone.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-3">
                <title>Post-traumatic stress disorder</title>
                <p>Neuropsychiatric symptoms were evaluated using the post-traumatic stress symptoms (PTSS)-14 questionnaire. PTSS-14 is a telephone questionnaire comprised of 14 symptoms of post-traumatic stress that has been validated for use in patients who survive ICU in the UK.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The PTSS-14 questionnaire was completed at 1 year after randomisation by trained study staff.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-4">
                <title>Cognitive function</title>
                <p>Cognitive function was assessed using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)-Blind scoring system. If the participant was unable to complete the MoCA-Blind questionnaire, the AD8 Score was completed by a proxy to inform the level of cognition.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The MoCA-Blind questionnaire is an adapted version of the MoCA assessment tool,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21 22</xref> which is used to assess for cognitive dysfunction using domains that assess attention and concentration, memory, language, conceptual thinking, calculations and orientation. It is recommended as a tool to assess cognition in patients who survive ICU admission with AHRF.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> These questionnaires were completed by telephone at 1 year post randomisation by trained study staff.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-5">
                <title>Health-related quality of life</title>
                <p>Health-related quality of life was assessed in survivors at 1 year post randomisation using the EuroQol Five Dimension 5 Level (EQ-5D-5L) Questionnaire, which provides a description of health using five dimensions each with 5 levels of severity and a visual analogue scale (VAS).<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Responses on the descriptive system were converted into utility scores using the Crosswalk Value Set for the UK population.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> This tariff maps the EQ-5D-5L responses on to the EQ-5D-3L and is currently the approach recommended by the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> To complete the EQ-5D-5L, patients were sent the questionnaires by post. Telephone completion was also used for non-responders.</p>
                <p>If participants returned questionnaires, or answered telephone questionnaires, with concerning mental health symptoms or expressed suicidal ideation, the patient’s response was discussed with the study chief investigator, or the patient’s general practitioner if prior permission was granted for this.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-6">
                <title>Outcomes</title>
                <p>All outcomes reported in this manuscript were prespecified in the REST trial protocol.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Mortality status was confirmed by contacting the patient’s general practitioner at 6 months, 1 year and 2 years post randomisation, prior to contacting participants for their questionnaire data. Responses to the SGRQ, PTSS-14, MoCA-Blind and EQ-5D-5L were obtained at 1 year post randomisation.</p>
                <p>The REST trial evaluated a complex intervention that was intended to facilitate lower tidal volume mechanical ventilation. To evaluate whether there was a treatment effect based on tidal volume reduction, an exploratory analysis of patients who had a reduction in tidal volume (defined as a change from baseline to day 3 of at least 2 mL/kg PBW), compared with patients in standard care who had no reduction (defined as a change in tidal volume from baseline to day 3 no greater than 2 mL/kg PBW) was performed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-7">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Patients were analysed according to their randomisation group. For 6 months, 1 year and 2 years mortality risk ratios and mean difference with 95% CIs were calculated, and p values reported, from χ<sup>2</sup> tests. Mortality was also analysed by survival methods with p values reported from the log-rank test and Cox proportional hazards used to estimate the HR and 95% CI. The proportionality assumption was tested using the Schoenfeld test and the assumption was satisfied. For all other outcomes and for the exploratory tidal volume analysis, the mean difference and 95% CIs were calculated and p values reported from independent samples t-tests. For the baseline characteristics median and IQR are presented and n (%) for categorical data. For all other analyses, data are presented as mean (SD) unless otherwise stated. Questionnaire responses are presented as n (%), and the denominator represents the number of patients alive at 1 year who had not withdrawn from questionnaire follow-up. In order to be able to combine the MoCA-Blind and AD8 scores, the analysis was based on level of cognitive impairment (severe, moderate, mild, normal). The MoCA-Blind was converted to a score out of 30 and then categorised as follows; &lt;10 severe, 10–17 moderate, 18–25 mild and &gt;25 normal cognition.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21 27</xref> An AD8 Score of 0–1 is considered normal cognition.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In the event of missing data for the MoCA-Blind questionnaire, the total recall score was calculated based on the items answered. Level of cognition was analysed using a χ<sup>2</sup> test. Additional post-hoc analyses were performed. First, to assess whether hypoxaemia and treatment allocation had an influence on the cognitive outcomes, the MoCA-Blind Score was adjusted for the lowest recorded daily PaO<sub>2</sub> in the first 7 days from randomisation, and the data were analysed using analysis of covariance. Second, to assess whether there was a relationship between daily PaCO<sub>2</sub> or neuromuscular blockade and health-related quality of life, correlation between these variables and EQ-5D-5L VAS Score was calculated using Pearson’s correlation coefficient. There was no imputation for missing data. Analysis was conducted using Stata/SE, V.15.1 (StataCorp). Statistical significance was defined using a two-sided test with α=0.05.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Of the 412 patients enrolled into the REST trial, 1-year mortality status was available for 401 patients (198 (49.4%) randomised to receive intervention and 203 (50.6%) randomised to receive standard care), and 2-year mortality status was available for 391 patients (194 intervention, 197 standard care). Of patients alive at 1 year, 161 provided at least one questionnaire response (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). The baseline characteristics of these patients are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. The baseline characteristics were similar to those of patients who did not complete any of the 1-year questionnaires (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table S1</xref>).</p>
              <supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thorax-2022-218874.supp1</object-id>
                <label>Supplementary data</label>
                <p>
                  <inline-supplementary-material id="SS1" xlink:href="thorax-2022-218874supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
                </p>
              </supplementary-material>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Baseline characteristics of all patients who responded to at least one questionnaire 1 year following randomisation</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention (n=81)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard care (n=80)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5 (49.2, 67.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1 (49.4, 67.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female—N (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (38%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (40%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">Dependency prior to hospital admission—N (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Able to live without assistance</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (86%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (91%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Minor assistance</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (13%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (7%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Major assistance</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total assistance</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted body weight (kg)*</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.0 (56.9, 74.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.0 (57.0, 72.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">ICU admission diagnostic category—N (%)†</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Respiratory</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (84%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (84%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sepsis</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (38%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (44%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cardiovascular</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (21%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (21%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Kidney</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (18%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (19%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gastrointestinal</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (16%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (18%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Central nervous system</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (9%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Toxicology</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Haematology</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Orthopaedic</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARDS present at enrolment<sup>†</sup>
</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/79 (53%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/80 (55%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">Aetiology of ARDS—N (%)‡</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pneumonia</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (76%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (73%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sepsis</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (45%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (41%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gastric content aspiration</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pancreatitis</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thoracic trauma</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoke/toxin inhalation</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APACHE II Score at ICU admission§</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (14, 22)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16, 22)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOFA Score¶</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (8, 11) n=78</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8, 12) n=76</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">Mode of ventilation—N (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mandatory</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (84%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (83%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mandatory and spontaneous breaths</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Spontaneous</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">Adjunctive ventilatory therapies—N (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Neuromuscular blocking drugs</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (52%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (46%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prone positioning</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (7%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inhaled nitric oxide</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nebulised epoprostenol</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tidal volume (mL/kg PBW)**</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (5.7, 7.1)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (5.8, 7.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory rate (breaths/min)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (20, 26)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (20, 28)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEEP (cm H<sub>2</sub>O)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9, 12) n=80</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8, 14) n=80</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plateau pressure (cm H<sub>2</sub>O)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (22, 27) n=61</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (24, 30) n=60</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driving pressure (cm H<sub>2</sub>O)††</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (11, 17) n=60</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (12, 18) n=60</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio (mm Hg)‡‡</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.5 (96.8, 136.5) n=79</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.8 (92.3, 130.5) n=79</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaCO<sub>2</sub> (mm Hg)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.8 (47.3, 62.3) n=79</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.9 (47.2, 60.5) n=78</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33 (7.27, 7.39) n=79</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31 (7.25, 7.38) n=78</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T1_FN1">
                    <p>Baseline clinical data were collected in the 24 hours prior to randomisation unless stated otherwise. If more than one value was available for this 24-hour period, the value closest but prior to the time of randomisation was recorded.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN2">
                    <p>Data presented as median (IQR) unless otherwise stated. Where median (IQR) presented, p value is from a Wilcoxon rank sum. Where, N (%) presented, p value is from a χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN3">
                    <p>*The predicted body weight of male patients was calculated as equal to 50+0.91 (centimetres of height—152.4); that of female patients was calculated as equal to 45.5+0.91 (centimetres of height—152.4).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN4">
                    <p>†Patients may have had more than one admission diagnostic category or cause of ARDS identified.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN5">
                    <p>‡The presence of ARDS was assessed by the treating physician.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN6">
                    <p>§Scores on the Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation (APACHE) II range from 0 to 71, with higher scores indicating greater severity of illness.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN7">
                    <p>¶Scores on the Sequential Organ Failure Assessment (SOFA) scale range from 0 to 24, with higher scores indicating greater severity of disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN8">
                    <p>**Tidal volume represents the pre-randomisation value.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN9">
                    <p>††Driving Pressure = Plateau Pressure − PEEP.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN10">
                    <p>‡‡Second qualifying PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN11">
                    <p>APACHE, Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation; ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; FiO<sub>2</sub>, fraction of inspired oxygen; ICU, intensive care unit; PaCO<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure of arterial carbon dioxide; PaO<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure of arterial oxygen; PBW, Predicted Body Weight; PEEP, positive end-expiratory pressure; SOFA, Sequential Organ Failure Assessment.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig position="float" id="F1">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Flow of patients in the REST trial. <sup>a</sup>The primary analysis, including the reasons for exclusion, has previously been reported.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R, veno-venous extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="thorax-2022-218874f01" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>After randomisation, patients allocated to intervention had a lower daily tidal volume (to day 7), and a lower PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio but a higher PaCO<sub>2</sub> on days 2–6. Daily postrandomisation ventilatory parameters are provided in the <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table S2</xref>. There was no difference in the duration of mechanical ventilation between patients allocated to intervention (17.5 (10.8) days) or standard care (21.0 (40.2); p=0.46).</p>
              <sec id="s3-1">
                <title>Mortality</title>
                <p>The time to death up to 2 years following randomisation was similar between patients allocated to intervention and standard care (HR 1.08 (0.81, 1.44); log-rank test p=0.61) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>). Overall mortality at 6 months, 1 year and 2 years was 42.4%, 43.4% and 46.9%, respectively. There was no statistically significant difference between patients allocated to intervention or standard care in mortality at any of these timepoints (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Mortality results at 6 months, 1 year and 2 years following randomisation</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention, N (%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard care, N (%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% point difference (95% CI)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio (95% CI)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-month mortality</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (42.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (41.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1% (−8.6% to 10.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.8 to 1.3)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-year mortality</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (43.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (42.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1% (−8.6% to 10.8%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.8 to 1.3)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-year mortality</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (47.2%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (47.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7% (−9.2% to 10.6%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.8 to 1.3)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T2_FN1">
                      <p>Randomisation represents the start of each time period. p value derived from χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig position="float" id="F2">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Kaplan-Meier curve of the time to death dichotomised by treatment group in patients recruited to the REST trial. There was no difference in the time to death between patients allocated to intervention or standard care (HR 1.1 (0.8, 1.4); log-rank p=0.61).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="thorax-2022-218874f02" position="float"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-2">
                <title>St George’s Respiratory Questionnaire</title>
                <p>The SGRQ was completed in its entirety by 116 (53%) patients alive at 1 year who had not withdrawn from paper questionnaire follow-up. The most frequently completed domain was the SGRQ symptom score (n=129). There was no significant difference in SGRQ total score between patients allocated to intervention (40.9 (27.1)) or standard care (40.9 (26.4); p=1.00). Similarly, there was no significant difference between treatment allocation in either the symptoms (intervention 41.7 (29.8) vs standard care 45.1 (31.8)); p=0.52), activity (intervention 58.9 (31.2) vs standard care 58.2 (32.4); p=0.91) or impacts (intervention 29.7 (28.1) vs standard care 28.6 (26.2); p=0.83) component scores of the SGRQ (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Questionnaires at 1 year following randomisation</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard care</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference (95% CI)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGRQ total score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 (27.1) n=53</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 (26.4) n=63</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02 (−9.9 to 9.9)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Symptoms score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 (29.8) n=62</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1 (31.8) n=67</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (−7.4 to 14.2)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Activity score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9 (31.2) n=57</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.2 (32.4) n=66</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7 (−12.1 to 10.7)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Impacts score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7 (28.1) n=58</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 (26.2) n=64</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.1 (−10.8 to 8.7)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSS-14 Score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3 (19.8) n=60</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8 (22.2) n=56</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (−3.2 to 12.2)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA-Blind Score*</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1 (3.9) n=59</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 (3.1) n=56</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (−0.5 to 2.1)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal cognition†</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (50.0%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (48.2%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.41</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild cognitive impairment†</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33.3%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (41.1%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate cognitive impairment†</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (16.7%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.9%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe cognitive impairment†</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8%)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EQ-5D-5L utility score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 (0.36) n=63</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 (0.34) n=67</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004 (−0.13 to 0.12)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EQ-5D-5L VAS</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.4 (23.6) n=66</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8 (22.1) n=67</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (−1.4 to 14.2)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T3_FN1">
                      <p>Data presented as mean (SD) and analysed using independent samples t-test.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="T3_FN2">
                      <p>*Maximum score of 22.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="T3_FN3">
                      <p>†MoCA-Blind and AD8 scores were converted to level of cognition and analysed using χ<sup>2</sup>.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="T3_FN4">
                      <p>EQ-5D-5L, EuroQol Five Dimension five level; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; PTSS, Post-traumatic stress symptoms; SGRQ, St George’s Respiratory Questionnaire; VAS, visual analogue scale.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-3">
                <title>Post-traumatic stress disorder</title>
                <p>Overall, 116 (56%) patients alive at 1 year who had not withdrawn from telephone questionnaire follow-up completed the PTSS-14 questionnaire, and there was a similar score between treatment groups (intervention (34.3 (19.8)) vs standard care 38.8 (22.2); p=0.25) indicating that the prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder was similar between treatment groups (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-4">
                <title>Cognitive function</title>
                <p>The MoCA-Blind Questionnaire was completed by 115 (56%) patients alive at 1 year who had not withdrawn from telephone questionnaire follow-up, while for 1 patient, cognitive function was assessed via proxy using the AD-8 Questionnaire, and the results from both questionnaires were combined. At 1 year, there was no significant difference in the proportion of patients between intervention and standard care who had mild (intervention 33.3% vs standard care 41.1%), moderate (16.7% vs 8.9%) or severe (0% vs 1.8%) cognitive impairment (p=0.41) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p>
                <p>Likewise, rates of cognitive impairment, as measured by the MoCA-Blind questionnaire score, were similar between treatment groups (intervention 17.1 (3.9) vs standard care 17.9 (3.1); p=0.23) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Adjustment for the lowest recorded PaO<sub>2</sub> did not affect these results (mean difference 0.8 (−0.2, 2.2)).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-5">
                <title>Health-related quality of life</title>
                <p>Health-related quality of life, assessed by both the EQ-5D-5L utility score and VAS score, was the most frequently returned questionnaire, 133 (61%) of participants alive at 1 year who had not withdrawn from paper questionnaire follow-up. Both the EQ-5D-5L utility and VAS scores were similar between patients allocated to either intervention or standard care who survived to 1 year (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p>
                <p>There was no statistically significant correlation between daily PaCO<sub>2</sub> (within the first 7 days after randomisation) and EQ-5D-5L VAS Score (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figures e1-7</xref>), nor between the number of days of neuromuscular blockade within the first 7 days after randomisation and EQ-5D-5L VAS Score (correlation coefficient −0.08; p=0.39).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-6">
                <title>Effect of tidal volume reduction on long-term outcomes</title>
                <p>Overall, 45 patients allocated to intervention, who completed at least one questionnaire, had a reduction in tidal volume of at least 2 mL/kg PBW between baseline and day 3. These patients were compared with 68 patients allocated to standard care who did not have at least a 2 mL/kg PBW reduction in tidal volume over the same time. As expected, at day 3, the tidal volume was lower in the intervention subgroup than the standard care subgroup (3.6 (0.7) vs 6.9 (2.0) mL/kg PBW; p&lt;0.001).</p>
                <p>In patients who had a reduction in tidal volume, there was no significant effect on respiratory function, cognitive dysfunction or health-related quality of life at 12 months. Although patients allocated to intervention who had a meaningful tidal volume reduction had a numerically lower PTSS-14 Score than those standard care patients with no change in tidal volume, the difference in PTSS-14 Score did not reach statistical significance (p=0.06) (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="T4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Exploratory analysis evaluating the effect of tidal volume reduction</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention<break/>(tidal volume reduction≥2 mL/kg PBW)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard care<break/>(tidal volume reduction&lt;2 mL/kg PBW)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference<break/>(95% CI)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGRQ total score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9 (27.2) n=33</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6 (26.5) n=54</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (−8.0 to 15.5)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Symptoms score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0 (30.8) n=39</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 (31.0) n=58</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (−7.2 to 18.2)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Activity score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5 (31.6) n=34</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.9 (32.5) n=57</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (−10.5 to 17.2)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Impacts score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.9 (28.5) n=37</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2 (26.8) n=55</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (−9.4 to 13.8)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSS-14 Score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 (19.6) n=32</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 (22.3) n=48</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4 (−0.2 to 19.1)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA-Blind total score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 (3.6) n=32</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 (3.1) n=48</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (−1.1 to 1.9)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EQ-5D-5L utility score</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.35) n=39</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.34) n=58</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05 (−0.19 to 0.10)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EQ-5D-5L VAS</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4 (25.1) n=40</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.5 (21.6) n=58</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (−7.4 to 11.5)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T4_FN1">
                      <p>Data presented as mean (SD) and analysed using independent samples t-test.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="T4_FN2">
                      <p>EQ-5D-5L, EuroQol Five Dimension 5 Level; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; PBW, Predicted Body Weight; PTSS, Post-traumatic stress symptoms; SGRQ, St George’s Respiratory Questionnaire; VAS, visual analogue scale.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Understanding the effect of an intervention on long-term mortality and the long-term physical, neurological and psychological impact on patients is an important component to interpreting the results of a randomised controlled trial. In the REST trial, although the intervention of vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation did not reduce 90-day mortality,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> it was feasible that there could have been benefits to patients who were only identified at a later time period. However, in this prespecified analysis,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> it has been demonstrated that the intervention studied in the REST trial did not reduce mortality at either 6 months or 1 year from randomisation. Furthermore, in the patients who provided questionnaire responses, lower tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R, did not significantly reduce the long-term physical or neuropsychological symptom burden, nor improve their health-related quality of life. These data do not support the use of vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation in patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF.</p>
              <p>In the REST trial, patients allocated to intervention had a 90-day mortality rate of 41.5%, while in patients allocated to standard care 90-day mortality was 39.5%. There was a small increase in mortality between 90 days and 1 year in these patients (2.4% increase in patients allocated to intervention, 3.4% increase in patients allocated to standard care), and the time to death was similar between groups. The small increase in mortality over time was lower than has been previously reported. Most studies of patients with ARDS demonstrate an increase in mortality over the first year of between 8% and 17%.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref> Furthermore, pneumonia and sepsis were the most common reasons for ICU admission in this study, and a previous study of patients with sepsis demonstrated a 6%–8% increase in the annual mortality rate in patients who survived critical care admission.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> The REST trial recruited patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF and it is possible that the small increase in late mortality over the first year in this study is related to a higher 90-day mortality in a population with greater disease severity at inclusion.</p>
              <p>In an effort to better understand the role that tidal volume reduction had on long-term outcomes, patients allocated to intervention who had a tidal volume reduction of at least 2 mL/kg PBW were compared with those patients in standard care who did not have this change in tidal volume. The results from this subgroup analysis did not demonstrate a statistically significant difference in self-reported respiratory function, neuropsychological symptom burden or health-related quality of life. However, patients allocated to intervention who had a tidal volume reduction of at least 2 mL/kg PBW had a numerically lower PTSS-14 than patients allocated to standard care who had no change in tidal volume. Although this difference did not reach statistical significance, it remains a potentially important difference between these groups that may warrant further study. Previously, it has been demonstrated that lower tidal volume ventilation is associated with less hippocampal apoptosis in a preclinical model.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, in this subgroup analysis, there was no difference in cognitive dysfunction (as assessed using the MoCA-Blind questionnaire) at 1 year between treatment groups, suggesting that this mechanism of injury may not be clinically significant in this patient cohort.</p>
              <p>In comparison to previously described cohorts of patients with ARDS, the SGRQ scores were numerically higher (indicating a higher symptom burden) in survivors at 1 year in the REST trial when compared with previously described cohorts of patients with ARDS.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref> Interestingly, the recorded values in the REST trial are also higher than those described for patients with COPD and asthma.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Further evaluation of the long-term physical consequences of AHRF is warranted to improve understanding and identify therapies that can modulate long-term outcomes in these patients.</p>
              <p>This planned analysis of the REST trial has several strengths. The extended evaluation of mortality to 1 year provides important data that excludes a later treatment effect, which may have been missed had follow-up ceased at 90 days. Patients with AHRF are recognised as having an increased risk of mortality beyond their hospital discharge,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and therefore longer-term follow-up of these patients allows investigators to identify a late trend in outcomes which may influence the overall interpretation of the clinical trial results. In addition, the 1-year mortality rate in the REST trial is comparable to that observed in patients with ARDS,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 29 36</xref> suggesting that the long-term outcomes presented in this manuscript are in keeping with that of a broader population of patients. The 1-year symptom and functional assessments were conducted using validated questionnaires many of which are recommended in the core outcome set for this population.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Evaluating this broad set of outcomes supports the mortality results and provides an opportunity to identify differences in morbidity and quality of life that may affect survivors and therefore influence the interpretation of results from a clinical trial. Finally, because the REST trial evaluated a complex intervention that was intended to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation, there were patients who were allocated to intervention but did not have the intended reduction in tidal volume. In performing a subgroup analysis which evaluated patients with a reduction in tidal volume of at least 2 mL/kg PBW, we sought to establish whether intervention fidelity was associated with outcomes. The absence of an observed benefit in this cohort strengthens the overall findings of this study, highlighting that the absence of an effect was unlikely to be a consequence of low intervention fidelity.</p>
              <p>Despite these aspects there are some limitations to consider. First, only 40% of eligible patients provided responses to the questionnaires, while the most frequently completed questionnaire was informed by 33% of the eligible population. The incomplete response rate to questionnaires is likely to be multifactorial and is consistent with previous studies of ICU survivors.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28 37</xref> This is a significant limitation that means the results are subject to response bias, and therefore they may not fully reflect the health status of all survivors to 1 year. Second, although validated for their use, the questionnaires were self-reported, and are therefore subject to bias, including that the postal questionnaires were completed by a proxy rather than the patient themselves. To overcome this, an objective assessment of physical function, such as the 6 min walk test, could have been considered. Although the core outcome set for studies evaluating survivors of acute respiratory failure was published after the REST trial had commenced,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> it remains a weakness that there are some domains from this recommendation that were not covered in this long-term analysis. In addition, data regarding a patient’s capacity to return to work would have been useful; however, these data were not available. This highlights the need to collect multidimensional long-term outcomes in future trials. Finally, the intervention was designed to use vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R to facilitate lower tidal volume ventilation, with the aim of reducing ventilator-induced lung injury. The ECCO<sub>2</sub>R device used in the trial has a centrifugal pump.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> It remains uncertain whether devices using differing technology with higher flow rates and with higher CO<sub>2</sub> removal capacity which could facilitate further reductions in injurious ventilation than achieved in the REST trial, would be associated with clinical benefit. In the absence of a biological difference between the groups, it is implausible that there will be a difference in clinical outcomes. Identification of whether there was a difference in the biological response between patients allocated to intervention and standard care is a potentially important step to understanding why there was no difference in short-term and long-term outcomes between intervention and standard care.</p>
              <p>In summary, these data demonstrate that lower tidal volume ventilation, facilitated by vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R as delivered in the REST trial, does not reduce long-term mortality in patients with moderate-to-severe AHRF, when compared with standard care. These data reinforce that vv-ECCO<sub>2</sub>R with lower tidal volume ventilation strategy should not be used routinely in this patient cohort. Further clinical trials are required to determine if devices with higher CO<sub>2</sub> removal capacity to facilitate further reductions in injurious ventilation are associated with clinical benefit.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Correction notice:</bold> This article has been corrected since it was published Online First. Table 1 footnotes were not all cited correctly in the table. These have been updated accordingly.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> All authors contributed to the conception, design and conduct of the study. CM and DL performed statistical analysis. AJB, CM, DL, AA, JDS and DFM drafted the first version of the manuscript, and all authors contributed edits. AJB compiled edits, and all authors read and approved the final manuscript. DFM acts as the guarantor.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> This project was funded by the National Institute for Health Research Health Technology Assessment Programme (13/143/02) with additional support from the Irish Critical Care Clinical Trials Network at the University College Dublin, which is funded by the Health Research Board of Ireland (CTN 2014-012). The trial was also supported by the UK Intensive Care Society, the United Kingdom Critical Care Research Group and the International ECMO Network.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> AJB received grants from the Northern Ireland Health and Social Care Research and Development Agency to undertake a clinical trial of extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal, grants from the NIHR HTA Programme for a clinical trial of extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal (13/143/02). CM, AA, DL, CJ and JM reported the Northern Ireland Clinical Trials Unit receiving funds from the NIHR HTA Programme for its involvement during the conduct of the study. JJM reported receiving grants from the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Health Technology Assessment (HTA) Programme during the conduct of the study and speaking fees from Baxter outside the submitted work. DFM reported receiving grants from the NIHR HTA Programme during the conduct of the study, and DFM has received funding to his institution for studies outside of this submitted work from the NIHR, Wellcome Trust, Innovate UK, Northern Ireland Health and Social Care Research and Development Office and Randox. DFM has a patent application issued to his institution. Outside of the submitted work DFM has received fees for consultancy from Bayer, GSK, Boehringer Ingelheim, Eli Lilly and Novartis and SOBI and for being a member of the data monitoring and ethics committee for Vir Biotechnology and Faron studies and as an educational seminar speaker for GSK.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability statement</title>
              <p>Data are available upon reasonable request.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="ethics-statement">
              <title>Ethics statements</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Patient consent for publication</title>
                <p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not applicable.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Ethics approval</title>
                <p content-type="ethics-approval">This study involves human participants. The clinical trial protocol was approved by research ethics committees in England, Wales, Northern Ireland (16/SC/089) and Scotland (16/SS/048). Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bellani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laffey</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology, patterns of care, and mortality for patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome in intensive care units in 50 countries</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>315</volume>:<fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2016.0291</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26903337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sjoding</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langa</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Late mortality after acute hypoxic respiratory failure</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2017-210109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Herridge</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>One-Year outcomes in survivors of the acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa022450</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12594312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12594312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Two-Year outcomes, health care use, and costs of survivors of acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200505-693OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16763220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Herridge</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matté</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Functional disability 5 years after acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>364</volume>:<fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1011802</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21470008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21470008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kamdar</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Return to work and lost earnings after acute respiratory distress syndrome: a 5-year prospective, longitudinal study of long-term survivors</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2017-210217</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28918401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28918401</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanken</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The adult respiratory distress syndrome cognitive outcomes study</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>1307</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201111-2025OC</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492988</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colantuoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinglas</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Rosuvastatin versus placebo for delirium in intensive care and subsequent cognitive impairment in patients with sepsis-associated acute respiratory distress syndrome: an ancillary study to a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00005-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26832963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26832963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>González-López</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>López-Alonso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical ventilation triggers hippocampal apoptosis by vagal and dopaminergic pathways</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>702</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201304-0691OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23962032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23962032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covarrubias</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Il-6 inhibition reduces neuronal injury in a murine model of ventilator-induced lung injury</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2021-0072OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/34014798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34014798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sklar</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNamee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal for lowering the risk of mechanical ventilation: research questions and clinical potential for the future</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(18)30326-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30484429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30484429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McNamee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of lower tidal volume ventilation facilitated by extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal vs standard care ventilation on 90-day mortality in patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure: the rest randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>326</volume>:<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.13374</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/34463700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34463700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colantuoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendez-Tellez</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Lung protective mechanical ventilation and two year survival in patients with acute lung injury: prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>344</volume>:<elocation-id>e2124</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e2124</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22491953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22491953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del Sorbo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goligher</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An official American thoracic Society/European Society of intensive care Medicine/Society of critical care medicine clinical practice guideline: mechanical ventilation in adult patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201703-0548ST</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28459336?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28459336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>MJD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines on the management of acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>e000420</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2019-000420</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/31258917?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McNamee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>pRotective vEntilation with veno-venouS lung assisT in respiratory failure: a protocol for a multicentre randomised controlled trial of extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal in patients with acute hypoxaemic respiratory failure</article-title>. <source>J Intensive Care Soc</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1751143716681035</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28979565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Network</collab>, <string-name><surname>Brower</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthay</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Ventilation with lower tidal volumes as compared with traditional tidal volumes for acute lung injury and the acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>1301</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200005043421801</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10793162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10793162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baveystock</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A self-complete measure of health status for chronic airflow limitation. The St. George's respiratory questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source><year>1992</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm/145.6.1321</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1595997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1595997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Twigg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humphris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Use of a screening questionnaire for post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) on a sample of UK ICU patients</article-title>. <source>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2007.01531.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18005373?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powlishta</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The AD8: a brief informant interview to detect dementia</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000172958.95282.2a</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16116116?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16116116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bédirian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The Montreal cognitive assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15817019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wittich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of the Montreal cognitive assessment modified for individuals who are visually impaired</article-title>. <source>J Vis Impair Blind</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0145482X1010400606</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinglas</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Core outcome measures for clinical research in acute respiratory failure survivors. An international modified Delphi consensus study</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201702-0372OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28537429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28537429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Herdman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gudex</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Development and preliminary testing of the new five-level version of EQ-5D (EQ-5D-5L)</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1727</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21479777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21479777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>van Hout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Interim scoring for the EQ-5D-5L: mapping the EQ-5D-5L to EQ-5D-3L value sets</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>708</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2012.02.008</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22867780?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22867780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NICE</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Position statement on use of the EQ-5D-5L value set for England</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/about/what-we-do/our-programmes/nice-guidance/technology-appraisal-guidance/eq-5d-5l">https://www.nice.org.uk/about/what-we-do/our-programmes/nice-guidance/technology-appraisal-guidance/eq-5d-5l</uri> [Accessed <comment>29 Nov 2021</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>MoCA – Cogn. Assess</collab></person-group>. <article-title>FAQ | MoCA - Cognitive Assessment</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://mocatest.org/faq/">https://mocatest.org/faq/</uri> [Accessed <comment>18 Dec 2021</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Agus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hulme</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verghis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Simvastatin for patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome: long-term outcomes and cost-effectiveness from a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Crit Care</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>108</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-017-1695-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28511660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28511660</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dinglas</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>One-Year outcomes of rosuvastatin versus placebo in sepsis-associated acute respiratory distress syndrome: prospective follow-up of sails randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-208017</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26936876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26936876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calfee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>One-Year mortality and predictors of death among hospital survivors of acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-013-3186-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24435201?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24435201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shankar-Hari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrando-Vivas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors at index hospitalization associated with longer-term mortality in adult sepsis survivors</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>e194900</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.4900</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/31150081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Reduced quality of life in survivors of acute respiratory distress syndrome compared with critically ill control patients</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.281.4.354</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9929089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9929089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heyland</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanism of injury influences quality of life in survivors of acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1895</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-006-0344-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16983550?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chiumello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taccone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berto</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term outcomes in survivors of acute respiratory distress syndrome ventilated in supine or prone position</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-011-2445-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22187085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villasante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Interpretation of quality of life scores from the St George's respiratory questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.02.00213202</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11936515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11936515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musthafa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Quality-Adjusted survival in the first year after the acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>1389</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.163.6.2005123</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11371406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sganzerla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The burden of mental illness among survivors of critical Care-Risk factors and impact on quality of life: a multicenter prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Chest</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2021.02.034</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/33640377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33640377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cove</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacLaren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Federspiel</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Bench to bedside review: extracorporeal carbon dioxide removal, past present and future</article-title>. <source>Crit Care</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<elocation-id>232</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc11356</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23014710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23014710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
