<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:44:28Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7537140" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7537140</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-10-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmjresp</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open Respir Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open Respir Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjresp</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopenrespres</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMJ Open Respiratory Research</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2052-4439</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7537140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7537140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7537140</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020113</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjresp-2020-000694</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2020-000694</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Cystic Fibrosis</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>1506</subject>
                  <subject>2218</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Investigating outcome measures for assessing airway clearance techniques in adults with cystic fibrosis: protocol of a single-centre randomised controlled crossover trial</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-52104773" contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6967-6883</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Stanford</surname>
                    <given-names>Gemma</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-33505790" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davies</surname>
                    <given-names>Jane C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-75937060" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Usmani</surname>
                    <given-names>Omar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-67023950" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Banya</surname>
                    <given-names>Winston</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-79780107" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Charman</surname>
                    <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-33507281" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>Mandy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-79780150" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Simmonds</surname>
                    <given-names>Nicholas J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-33503938" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bilton</surname>
                    <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Adult Cystic Fibrosis</institution>, <institution>Royal Brompton Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">National Heart and Lung Institute</institution>, <institution>Imperial College London</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Paediatric Respiratory Medicine</institution>, <institution>Royal Brompton Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Research and Development</institution>, <institution>Royal Brompton Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Cystic Fibrosis Trust</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Health Sciences, College of Health, Medicine and Life Scientists</institution>, <institution>Brunel University London</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Respiratory Medicine</institution>, <institution>Royal Brompton Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Nicholas J Simmonds; <email>n.simmonds@imperial.ac.uk</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>7</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <elocation-id>e000694</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>26</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>09</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2020. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <ali:license_ref start_date="2020-10-05">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Introduction</title>
                  <p>Airway clearance techniques (ACTs) are a gold standard of cystic fibrosis management; however, the majority of research evidence for their efficacy is of low standard; often attributed to the lack of sensitivity from outcome measures (OMs) used historically. This randomised controlled trial (RCT) investigates these standard OMs (sputum weight, forced expiratory volume in 1 s) and new OMs (electrical impedance tomography (EIT), multiple breath washout (MBW) and impulse oscillometry (IOS)) to determine the most useful measures of ACT.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods and analysis</title>
                  <p>This is a single-centre RCT with crossover design. Participants perform MBW, IOS and spirometry, and then are randomised to either rest or supervised ACT lasting 30–60 min. MBW, IOS and spirometry are repeated immediately afterwards. EIT and sputum are collected during rest/ACT. On a separate day, the OMs are performed with the other intervention. Primary endpoint is difference in change in OMs before and after ACT/rest. Sample size was calculated with 80% power and significance of 5% for each OM (target n=64).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
                  <p>Ethics approval was gained from the London–Chelsea Research Ethics Committee (reference 16/LO/0995, project ID 154635). Dissemination will involve scientific conference presentation and publication in a peer-reviewed journal.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Trial registration numbers</title>
                  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ISRCTN11220163">ISRCTN11220163</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="NCT02721498">NCT02721498</ext-link>.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>cystic fibrosis</kwd>
                <kwd>respiratory measurement</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="funding-1">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000659</institution-id>
                      <institution>Research Trainees Coordinating Centre</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>CDRF-2014-05-055</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>special-feature</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>unlocked</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Over 10 500 people in the UK have cystic fibrosis (CF),<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> a genetic disorder of ion transport across cell membranes causing organ damage with a median predicted survival of 47.3 years. Impaired mucociliary clearance in the CF lung due to airway dehydration and viscous secretions causes airway obstruction, mucus plugging and infections.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Removal of airway secretions is critical to minimise recurrent infections and inflammation, which lead to lung damage, respiratory failure and death.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 4</xref> Traditionally, combinations of mucoactive agents and airway clearance techniques (ACTs) are prescribed on an individual basis by specialised physiotherapists.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p>
              <p>There are many ACTs including breathing methods such as the active cycle of breathing techniques (ACBTs) or autogenic drainage and adjuncts such as positive expiratory pressure, high frequency chest wall oscillation or oscillatory devices, for example, the Acapella. Previous research comparing several ACTs showed no significant difference in clinical effectiveness between techniques over 1 year,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and the Association of Chartered Physiotherapists in Cystic Fibrosis standards of care does not advocate one technique over the others based on the available evidence.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> However, the currently available research regarding ACTs is mainly of low quality on the GRADE (Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development and Evaluations) system used in systematic reviews,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> often due to methodological or outcome measurement issues.</p>
              <p>A long-standing debate exists within respiratory physiotherapy and the wider medical community about which are the best outcome measures (OMs) for research into ACTs in CF.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Established measures of forced expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV<sub>1</sub>) and expectorated sputum wet weight have been recognised by the international CF community as the gold standard for ACT research, although their limitations are well recognised.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6–12</xref></p>
              <p>Spirometry, yielding the FEV<sub>1</sub> is effort dependent, and is criticised as having high variability due to patient participation in the manoeuvre.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The nature of completing a forced expiratory manoeuvre, such as FEV<sub>1</sub>, may create an airway reaction or mobilise sputum, which on its own, may influence ACT study results. FEV<sub>1</sub> also mainly reflects obstruction of large airways, and can remain ‘normal’ when significant small airway damage is present.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> As the small airways are affected early in CF lung disease, OMs need to effectively monitor this area.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In addition, studies using FEV<sub>1</sub> may not detect differences as it may not be sensitive enough to pick up small, but possibly clinically significant changes.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6–8 12</xref></p>
              <p>Weight of sputum expectorated is often used as a simple OM to reflect the amount of mucus mobilised during ACT.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 15</xref> However, sputum expectorated may not be the most relevant or valid OM: it is not specific to airway clearance or alveolar recruitment; it is not sensitive to small changes or suitable in early disease; and it has limited repeatability, being dependent on the will/ability of a subject to fully expectorate. Sputum could be swallowed, cleared after ACT, or contaminated by saliva, all which can result in inaccurate estimations of ACT effect.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8 16</xref></p>
              <p>Recent technological advances have supported the development of new OMs. These may provide more detailed information on ACT effect in relation to small airways function, ventilation distribution and changes in airway obstruction and include multiple breath washout (MBW), electrical impedance tomography (EIT) and impulse oscillometry (IOS).</p>
              <p>The lung clearance index (LCI<sub>2.5</sub>) is calculated from an MBW, which measures the number of lung volume turnovers required to clear an inert tracer gas during relaxed tidal breathing. When the level of the tracer gas has fallen to 1/40th of the starting concentration, the washout is considered complete. Functional residual capacity (FRC) and the cumulative expired volume (CEV) can be derived from MBW measurements, and are used to calculate LCI<sub>2.5</sub> (CEV divided by FRC).<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> LCI<sub>2.5</sub> reflects ventilation inhomogeneity, increasing with airway obstruction typical in more severe disease.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> LCI<sub>2.5</sub> detects small changes in CF lungs, in particular in peripheral airways, and so is considered a sensitive measure of lung disease severity.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18–20</xref> Despite research into reliability, validity and responsiveness of LCI<sub>2.5</sub> as a longer term OM, and support of LCI for clinical trial use by the European CF Society Clinical Trial Network Standardisation Committee,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> it is not clear whether LCI<sub>2.5</sub> is useful in determining differences over a short time, for example, single-ACT sessions.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 21 22</xref> In particular, as LCI<sub>2.5</sub> is altered by airway obstruction, the movement of secretions which occurs during ACT, alongside altered ventilation of lung segments, could result either in increased or decreased LCI<sub>2.5</sub>; both directions of change have been reported in previous small studies measuring ACT effect.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22 23</xref></p>
              <p>IOS provides information about the mechanical properties of airways by using alternating frequency pressure oscillations, in the form of sound waves, superimposed over normal breathing. Airflow and sound wave response are used to calculate resistance (R) and reactance (X) to tidal breathing.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Changes in IOS, demonstrating changes in resistance to airflow indicate obstructions to the airways, for example, mucus plugging or altered airway reactivity such as in asthmatic airways.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Low frequency oscillations, such as those at 5 Hz (R5), travel through the airways to the peripheries and are reflected back, while higher frequencies such as those at 20 Hz (R20) are reflected back from central airways.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Calculation of the difference between R5 and R20 (R5−R20) indicates extent of small airway obstruction. Reactance (X) indicates the elastic recoil of the airways. Most literature is in other patient populations, such as asthma; however, there are some studies emerging using IOS as an endpoint for CF intervention evaluation.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27 28</xref></p>
              <p>EIT creates a real-time image of ventilation by measuring the impedance to a low voltage electrical current as it travels through the lungs. Electrodes are attached to the thorax via a belt, and small alternating currents (of a magnitude undetectable to the subject) are applied. The resulting electrical potentials are measured, and a reconstruction algorithm is used to obtain the electrical impedance distribution within the thorax.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Analysis of the data obtained calculates end expiratory lung impedance, which is affected by changes in lung volumes and ventilation, and so has been proposed as a measure to detect changes resulting from sputum mobilisation and ACT.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6 30</xref> Most current literature in EIT is from the intensive care environment,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29 31</xref> with few studies investigating EIT in CF.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref> Wettstein <italic>et al</italic><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> demonstrated that EIT detected differences in ventilation distribution following ACT in a small cohort of nine CF adults, but reported high variability. These findings support further investigation of a larger sample of patients during ACT with a wide range of lung disease severity to assess whether the high intersubject variability observed is due to differences within the individual participants (eg, airway obstruction), or due to the inherent variability of EIT itself.</p>
              <p>The importance of patient preference and patient reported OMs (PROMs) is acknowledged within CF ACT research.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8 9 12</xref> The most sensitive OM scientifically, may be the least useful clinically if patients do not wish to perform it. The present study, therefore, includes a PROM in the form of a questionnaire asking opinions on the OMs performed. Good patient feedback of an OM is the key to its future within CF research and clinical care.</p>
              <p>Several Cochrane reviews suggest further work is required to identify the most appropriate OMs for ACT assessment.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8 15 35–40</xref> The European CF Society Allied Health and Nursing Professions Working Group reported the need for evaluation and identification of appropriate and robust OMs for allied health professional research as one of their four key objectives.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
              <p>This study seeks to identify a robust OM in ACT research that will benefit patients, facilitating their choice of ACT. Additionally, identifying the best OM will benefit the physiotherapy community in designing future trials of ACTs. Furthermore, industry can use this research in the assessment of new devices and mucoactive agents.</p>
              <p>Our hypothesis is that the use of a new OM tool box will allow more sensitive assessment of ACTs in stable adult patients with CF than the current gold standard measures. It was developed following extensive literature review and discussions with CF experts and patients. These experts acknowledge that physiotherapy practice guidelines are largely based on low-grade evidence because of underpowered studies with poor OMs.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 42</xref> This study seeks to improve this situation by evaluating new OMs thoroughly, providing robust evidence, which could then be used in future studies.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>Methods and analysis</title>
              <sec id="s2-1">
                <title>Trial registration</title>
                <p>This trial is registered on the public database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.clinicaltrials.gov.uk">www.clinicaltrials.gov.uk</ext-link> and is part of the International Standard Randomised Controlled Trial Number (ISRCTN) database.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-2">
                <title>Patient involvement</title>
                <p>Patients were involved in the conceptualisation, design and conduct of this research. During planning patients’ opinions on the trial design, research question and recruitment methods were gathered via discussions with adults with CF, and the Patient Representatives Group (RPG) of the Respiratory Clinical Research Facility (RCRF) based at the Royal Brompton Hospital (RBH), London. The study assessment questionnaires (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1 SP2">online supplemental appendices 1 and 2</xref>) have been designed and developed in conjunction with the CF patient advocate at RBH and the RPG. A patient representative is an independent member of the trial steering committee.</p>
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP1">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2020-000694.supp1</object-id>
                  <label>Supplementary data</label>
                  <p>
                    <inline-supplementary-material id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694supp001.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" content-type="local-data"/>
                  </p>
                </supplementary-material>
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP2">
                  <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2020-000694.supp2</object-id>
                  <label>Supplementary data</label>
                  <p>
                    <inline-supplementary-material id="SS2" xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694supp002.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" content-type="local-data"/>
                  </p>
                </supplementary-material>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-3">
                <title>Study design</title>
                <p>This is an open label, single-centre, single-blind, randomised controlled crossover trial investigating OMs for ACT in stable adults with CF. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the study design.</p>
                <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Schematic of trial design. Diagram illustrating the research journey for a trial participant, from their recruitment and giving of informed consent to completing study day one: baseline outcome measures (OMs) followed by randomisation to intervention (rest or airway clearance therapy (ACT)) and postintervention OMs. The time gap in-between visits should be no longer than 3 months. On study day 2, the participant completes the same OMs before and after the other intervention. Participation in the study is then complete.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694f01"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-4">
                <title>Recruitment</title>
                <p>Adults (16+ years) with CF registered as RBH patients are eligible for inclusion. Patients are approached during routine clinic visits for a project introduction and are given a patient information sheet (PIS) (first recruitment contact). They are given at least 48 hours to consider the PIS before a follow-up communication is completed to discuss any questions regarding study involvement and to arrange their first study visit if applicable.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-5">
                <title>Inclusion/exclusion criteria</title>
                <p>The study’s inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. In addition, before the start of any planned study visit (visit 1 or 2), participants are screened through discussion with the research team to see if they are unwell or if they have had any treatment changes to their CF or CF-related conditions within 4 weeks of the visit date. If treatment changes have occurred or the person is unwell, the visit is postponed.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion criteria</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exclusion criteria</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis of cystic fibrosis as confirmed by standard criteria<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence of pulmonary exacerbation within 3 weeks prior to screening</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sixteen years of age or older</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any change in a chronic treatment/prophylaxis for CF or CF-related condition within 4 weeks of visit</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current haemoptysis</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependency on positive pressure support with airway clearance technique</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of spontaneous rib fracture</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inability to give consent for treatment or measurement</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrolment in another interventional study</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent on non-invasive ventilation or oxygen therapy at rest</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-6">
                <title>Informed consent</title>
                <p>Every potential participant is provided with a PIS, verbal study explanation and the opportunity to ask questions regarding participation at the first recruitment contact. Following this, each participant is given a full explanation of what the study entails at the start of visit 1, and has the opportunity to ask questions before the consent form is provided. Written informed consent for participation is gained at start of visit 1, and verbally confirmed at visit 2.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-7">
                <title>Study visits</title>
                <p>Study visits are booked in advance with the participant’s agreement and consist of two separate visits to the RBH RCRF, ideally occurring within 3 months of each other. Participants complete their usual morning routines before visit attendance, which may include nebulisers and ACT, and are specifically asked to ensure they complete exactly the same routine before the second research visit.</p>
                <p>Prior to starting study assessments, subjects are questioned to ensure they are in a stable state of their disease and continue to satisfy the inclusion and exclusion criteria. To ensure stability in disease state in between the 2 assessment days, spirometric measurements of FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC are required to be within 5% absolute percentage points of the recorded prevalues at visit 1 when taken at visit 2.</p>
                <p>The format of a trial visit is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>. Subjects perform MBW, IOS and spirometry, then a 2 min EIT recording is performed. The EIT belt stays in situ throughout the intervention period (ACT or rest) that is supervised by a specialist CF physiotherapist. Coughs, expectoration frequency and oxygen saturations are recorded during the intervention period and a 2 min EIT recording is completed. At the end of the intervention period, the participant completes a Likert scale questionnaire asking how the intervention completed has affected their breathing and sputum clearance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>). At the end of the intervention period, a further 2 min EIT recording is completed before removing the EIT belt. MBW, IOS and spirometry are repeated immediately after the intervention period. Patient views on the OMs in terms of comfort, ease to perform and preference are gathered via a second questionnaire at the end of each study visit (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP2">online supplemental appendix 2</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Flow diagram of a study visit. CF, cystic fibrosis, EIT, electrical impedance tomography; ISO, impulse oscillometry; MBW, multiple breath washout.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694f02"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-8">
                <title>Interventions</title>
                <sec id="s2-8-1">
                  <title>Intervention 1: airway clearance</title>
                  <p>The ACBTs have been selected as the ACT within this study as it was the most common non-equipment-reliant ACT performed in the UK at the time of trial set-up,<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> and is easy to learn. All participants complete ACBT as the ACT intervention to prevent complications of analysis from possible differing effects of different ACTs. ACBT includes three elements—breathing control, thoracic expansion exercises and the forced expiration technique (also known as a ‘Huff’) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref>).<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Teaching or revision of ACBT from a specialist CF physiotherapist is provided at the start of both trial visits to ensure correct technique. The participant completes ACBT cycles in a supported sitting position. Supervision from a specialist CF physiotherapist is provided during the intervention session to encourage good ACBT and patient motivation.</p>
                  <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Figure 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>The active cycle of breathing techniques (adapted from the International Physiotherapy Group-Cystic Fibrosis (IPG/CF) Blue Booklet, 2019<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="bmjresp-2020-000694f03"/>
                  </fig>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2-8-2">
                  <title>Intervention 2: rest</title>
                  <p>In the second intervention period, the participant rests in a seated position (the same position as ACT is completed in). This intervention acts as the control arm for the study. Supervision is provided to ensure the participant does rest.</p>
                  <p>Participants are their own controls and are randomly assigned to the order that they perform the study sessions by a computerised randomisation programme. The randomisation code is held by the principle investigator who is not involved with study visits. One visit involves a period of rest for 30 min in-between assessments; the other visit involves a session of ACT using ACBT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>). The length of the ACT and rest intervention periods are the same, and are predetermined prior to the first visit based on the length of the participant’s usual ACT routine. Sessions last for a minimum of 30 min, up to 60 min maximum.</p>
                  <p>To minimise bias, all OMs are completed by the same investigator as far as possible; they are blinded to the order of the study visits and are not present during the intervention period. Both the intervention periods are supervised by the specialist CF physiotherapist. The specialist CF physiotherapist and the participant are instructed to not divulge which intervention has been completed to the investigator or to any other party. The questionnaire asking how the participant feels after the intervention (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>) is given by the specialist physiotherapist and is returned to the investigator in a sealed envelope to be opened at the end of the data collection period for all subjects.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-9">
                <title>Study OMs</title>
                <p>A summary of OM procedures is stated in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Details of outcome measures</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome measure test</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equipment used<break/>(manufacturer)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guideline or protocol followed</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spirometry</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MicroLab hand held spirometer (Carefusion UK, Basingstoke, UK)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joint European Respiratory Society/American Thoracic Society guidelines<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impulse oscillometry (IOS)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaeger IOS (Jaeger, Wurzburg, Germany)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Royal Brompton and Harefield NHS Foundation Trust standard operating procedure described by Paredi <italic>et al</italic><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple breath nitrogen washout</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecomedics Exhalyzer D machine (Eco Medics AG, Duernten, Switzerland)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecomedics Exhalyzer D standard operating procedure.<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electronic impedance tomography</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Draeger Pulmovista 500 (Draeger Medical U.K. Limited, Hemel Hempstead, UK)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmovista 500 operator guidance (Draeger Medical, Germany)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-10">
                <title>Multiple breath washout</title>
                <p>The MBW test is completed following the standard operating procedure for the Exhalyzer D machine (EcoMedics AG, Switzerland).<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Calibration for environmental conditions, flow and volume is completed prior to test completion. Disposable antibacterial filters and sterile mouthpieces are used. Distraction is provided during the test via a television programme. The MBW test is completed when three acceptable measurements are obtained. Once the tests are completed, the data are downloaded and analysed using Spiroware V.3.1 (EcoMedics AG, Switzerland).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-11">
                <title>Impulse oscillometry</title>
                <p>Calibration for ambient conditions, volume and impedance reference is performed before each use. The IOS tests are completed in an upright seated position, following a standard RBH hospital protocol which was described by Paredi <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Disposable antibacterial filters and sterile mouthpieces are used. The patient is asked to place their hands over their cheeks to prevent wobble and a nose clip is worn. The patient is instructed to breathe normally on the mouthpiece and at least 30 s of ‘normal breathing’ is completed before the test is commenced. Once started, the patient continues to breathe normally for a further 30 s, which is recorded. Each test is reviewed after completion and abnormal breaths (eg, coughs or swallows) excluded from the final analysis. The test is repeated when three acceptable measurements have been completed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-12">
                <title>Spirometry</title>
                <p>Spirometry is completed using a MicroLab spirometer (Carefusion, UK) and following the European Respiratory Society/American Thoracic Society guidelines.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Disposable antibacterial filter mouthpieces are used for each patient. Each test is repeated three times and the best value was recorded. Percentage predicted values are obtained using the Global Lung Initiative 2012 equations.<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Calibration of the equipment is performed before each use.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-13">
                <title>Electrical impedance tomography</title>
                <p>EIT recordings are made via electrodes connected to a thoracic belt, which is then connected via a trunk cable to the Pulmovista 500 machine (Draeger Medical UK, UK). Belt size is determined using a guide measure (Draeger Medical UK, UK). The belt is placed around the chest as per the manufacturer’s guidance (instructions for use—Pulmovista 500, Draeger, UK) at the height of the 4th–6th intercostal space with the belt moistened using water for enhanced contact. A reference electrode is attached to the seated patient using a disposable adhesive ECG electrode (Leonhard Lang GmbH, Austria). System checks and signal quality are checked prior to the first recording as per the manufacturer’s guidelines. Recordings are completed, before and after the intervention period and one in the middle of the intervention period; each recording is 2 min in duration. Recordings are uploaded to the EIT Data Analysis Tool (Draeger Medical UK, UK). Further analysis is then completed using Excel.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-14">
                <title>Oxygen saturations</title>
                <p>Oxygen saturations are monitored continuously throughout the intervention periods using a Pulsox-300i oximeter and finger probe (Stowood Medical, UK). Recordings are analysed using Visi-Download software (Stowood Scientific Instruments, UK).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-15">
                <title>Sputum collection</title>
                <p>Patients are given a sputum pot with lid (Unisurge, UK) to expectorate into throughout the intervention period. The pot is weighed pre and post use using portable scales (Kenex, UK).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-16">
                <title>End of trial and follow-up</title>
                <p>There are no follow-up contacts for participants after completion of visit 2. The trial will end once 64 participants have been recruited, and have completed both study visits.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-17">
                <title>Primary and secondary outcomes</title>
                <p>As this study assesses the five OMs with equal weight, the main measurement derived from each of the OM tests are all considered to be primary outcomes (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>), and were all considered in the calculations to derive the optimal sample size. Other measurements that can be derived from each of the OMs will be investigated as secondary outcomes.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Primary and secondary outcome measures</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary outcome measures</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary outcome measures</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Forced expiratory volume in 1 s</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Sputum wet weight expectorated during treatment</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>End expiratory lung impedance derived from EIT</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>LCI<sub>2.5</sub> derived from MBW</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>R5–R20 derived from IOS</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <list list-type="bullet">
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Forced vital capacity (FVC), forced expiratory flow at 25% of FVC, forced expiratory flow at 50% of FVC, forced expiratory flow at 75% of FVC, slow vital capacity derived from spirometry</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Oxygen saturation measurements during treatment</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Patient feedback questionnaire</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Regions of interest % derived from EIT</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>Functional residual capacity, LCI<sub>5</sub>, Scond, Sacin, washout time, number of washout breaths, M1M0, M2M0 derived from MBW</p>
                            </list-item>
                            <list-item>
                              <p>R5, R20, X, Fres derived from IOS</p>
                            </list-item>
                          </list>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T3_FN1">
                      <p>EIT, electrical impedance tomography; IOS, impulse oscillometry; LCI 2.5, Lung Clearance Index; MBW, multiple breath washout.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-18">
                <title>Sample size calculations</title>
                <p>In this study, we are assessing changes in OMs before and after ACT. To do this, for each individual participant we are calculating the change in the OM before and after ACT and comparing this with the change in the same OM after a period of rest. Due to the lack of agreement and definition as to what a minimal clinical important difference is for most of these OMs within the CF population,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47 48</xref> we conducted sample size calculations based on detecting minimum clinically relevant differences (MCRDs) from expert opinion and previous research findings.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30 34</xref> Sample size calculations were based on detecting MRCDs with 80% power and a significance level of 5% for all five OMs and on the premise of using a two-sample paired means test. All sample size calculations were conducted in STATA V.13.</p>
                <p>From the calculations, FEV<sub>1</sub> required the largest sample size of 32 participants. Initially we planned to study patients based on three severities of lung disease by FEV<sub>1</sub> (mild (&gt;70% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted), moderate (40%–70% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted) and severe (&lt;40% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted)); therefore, we aimed to recruit 32 patients in each group. Allowing for drop outs, we aimed to recruit a total of 106 participants. However, due to difficulties recruiting participants with low lung function, the protocol was changed (with Research Ethics Committee (REC) approval in March 2020) to study two groups (FEV<sub>1</sub> over 60% and FEV<sub>1</sub> 60% or below), requiring 70 participants.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2-19">
                <title>Data analysis plan</title>
                <p>Demographic and outcome numerical data will be summarised as mean (SD) or median (IQR) depending on the distribution of the data and categorical data will be presented with frequencies (percentage).</p>
                <p>Between visit differences in the change in OM’s will be compared using the paired t test or the Wilcoxon sign-ranked test as appropriate. All tests will be two-sided and significance will be set at p&lt;0.05.</p>
                <p>The clinimetric properties of the OMs will be assessed and minimally important changes (MICs) to participants will be calculated.<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Construct validity as a measure of responsiveness will be assessed using a construct approach. Reliability will be assessed by calculating intraclass correlation coefficients and limits of agreement using Bland and Altman plots, taking measurement error between study days into account.</p>
                <p>MICs differ from MCRDs, because MICs are calculated from patient feedback, and so represent what needs to change in an OM for a patient to feel a difference,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> as opposed to an MCRD, which is defined by clinical experts.<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> MICs will be calculated using an anchor-based method<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49–51</xref> derived from the results of the intervention effect questionnaire (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>).</p>
                <p>The clinimetric properties of the secondary OMS will be explored using the same approach. Exploratory analysis of associations between the OMS and change in OMs will be completed.</p>
                <p>To ensure blinding of investigators, no interim analysis is planned. Data analysis will be completed once full recruitment is accomplished and data gathered.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>Ethics and dissemination</title>
              <p>Ethics approval was gained for this trial from the London–Chelsea REC on 5 August 2016, with Health Research Authority (HRA) approval granted on 31 August 2016 (reference 16/LO/0995) and local research and development approval on 7 September 2016.</p>
              <sec id="s3-1">
                <title>Safety reporting</title>
                <p>Data on serious adverse events (SAE: as described by good clinical practice guidelines) and adverse events (AEs) will be collected during the trial visits and during time gaps in-between visits. All SAEs will be reported to the sponsor within 48 hours of notification, and will be followed until resolution. SAEs in this study include participant hospitalisation, including elective admissions, for any condition including pre-existing conditions. There are no expected AEs for this trial, except for possible fatigue from completion of interventions, and so all AEs are treated as unexpected, discussed with the trial management team, then reported to the sponsor in the annual progress report.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-2">
                <title>Changes to trial after commencement</title>
                <p>The study details reported here are described within the trial protocol V.4.2 (date: 20 January 2020). There have been two protocol amendments, the first of which added the intervention effect questionnaire into the trial visits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>). The first amendment was granted ethical approval by the London–Chelsea REC on 16 March 2017 and HRA approval on 27 March 2017. The second protocol amendment changed from studying three groups of participants by level of FEV<sub>1</sub> (FEV<sub>1</sub> mild (over 70% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted), moderate (40%–70% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted) and severe (under 40% FEV<sub>1</sub> predicted)), to studying two groups (FEV<sub>1</sub> over 60% and FEV<sub>1</sub> 60% or below) due to recruitment difficulties in the severe lung function group. The second amendment also included the addition of slow vital capacity into the protocol as a secondary OM. The second trial amendment was granted ethical approval by the London–Chelsea REC and the HRA in March 2020.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-3">
                <title>Publication and dissemination</title>
                <p>All participants will receive a lay summary of results on study completion. Trial results will be presented at national and international conferences, and local scientific meetings of Imperial College, London, and RBH. A report on results will be submitted to the trial funder (National Institute for Health Research). Publication will be pursued in a relevant peer-reviewed scientific journal.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>Thanks to Penny Agent; the Royal Brompton Hospital (RBH) adult cystic fibrosis physiotherapy team including Fiona Cathcart, Zelda Beverley, Tom Tobin and Paul Wilson; the Lung Clearance Index (LCI) Core Facility based at RBH especially Christopher Short and Claire Saunders; Martyn Biddiscombe; Sally Meah and the RBH research office for supporting this study.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> GS, NJS, DB, OU, WB, JD and MJ were involved in the original protocol writing, review and amendments. GS and NJS wrote this protocol version for publication, with final review and comments from all authors. SC was involved in the writing and review of the statistical analysis plan.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work is funded by a Health Education England and National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) clinical doctoral research fellowship for Gemma Stanford (reference number CDRF-2014-05-055). The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> JD reports other from Algipharma AS; Bayer AG; Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG; Galapagos NV; ImevaX GmbH; Nivalis Therapeutics; ProQR Therapeutics III B.V.; Proteostasis Therapeutics; Raptor Pharmaceuticals; Vertex Pharmaceuticals (Europe) Limited; Enterprise; Novartis; Pulmocide; Flatley; Teva and grants from CF Trust outside the submitted work. NJS reports personal fees from Vertex; Chiesi; Teva; Roche; Pulmocide and Zambon outside the submitted work.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to the Methods section for further details.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CF Trust</collab></person-group><source>Uk cystic fibrosis registry annual data report 2018</source>, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zach</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung disease in cystic fibrosis--an updated concept</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>1990</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.1950080311</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2190148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2190148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cystic fibrosis lung inflammation: early, sustained, and severe</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>939</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.151.4.7697269</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7697269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7697269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current understanding of the inflammatory process in cystic fibrosis: onset and etiology</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1099-0496(199708)24:2&lt;137::AID-PPUL13&gt;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9292910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9292910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ACPCF</collab></person-group><source>CF Trust Factsheet - Physiotherapy treatment in cystic fibrosis: airway clearance techniques</source>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Beyond postural drainage and percussion: airway clearance in people with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcf.2010.01.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20153269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20153269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ACPCF</collab></person-group><source>Standards of care and good clinical practice for the physiotherapy management of cystic fibrosis</source>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elborn</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for physical therapies (airway clearance and physical training) in cystic fibrosis: an overview of five Cochrane systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2005.11.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16412951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16412951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the best airway clearance technique in cystic fibrosis?</article-title><source>Paediatr Respir Rev</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>14 Suppl 1</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prrv.2013.01.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23541002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23541002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McIlwaine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chilvers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Long-Term comparative trial of two different physiotherapy techniques; postural drainage with percussion and autogenic drainage, in the treatment of cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1064</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.21247</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20836133?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hankinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brusasco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Standardisation of spirometry</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.05.00034805</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16055882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quittner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Lessons learned from a randomized trial of airway secretion clearance techniques in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.21179</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20146387?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146387</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Usmani</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Techniques of assessing small airways dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Eur Clin Respir J</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ecrj.v1.25898</pub-id>. [Epub ahead of print: 17 Oct 2014].<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26557240?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reix</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Lung clearance index: evidence for use in clinical trials in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcf.2013.09.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24315208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24315208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mckoy</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Active cycle of breathing technique for cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>CD007862</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007862.pub4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27378490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27378490</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding evidence to support airway clearance techniques in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09638289809166734</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9637932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9637932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horsley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung clearance index in the assessment of airways disease</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2009.01.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19246184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19246184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alton</surname><given-names>EWFW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Lung clearance index in CF: a sensitive marker of lung disease severity</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2007.082768</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18234652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiddens</surname><given-names>HAWM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Multiple-breath inert gas washout and spirometry versus structural lung disease in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2007.077784</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17675316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17675316</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayfield</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Developments in multiple breath washout testing in children with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Res Opin</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03007995.2016.1268999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27931123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27931123</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toussaint</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edlhaimb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Short-Term effect of physiotherapy on variability of the lung clearance index in children with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.21180</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20146388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfleger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwantzer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Short-Term effects of physiotherapy on ventilation inhomogeneity in cystic fibrosis patients with a wide range of lung disease severity</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcf.2014.12.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25612899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25612899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosse-Onnebrink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellies</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Chest physiotherapy can affect the lung clearance index in cystic fibrosis patients</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.23670</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28125158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28125158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paredi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alamen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Comparison of inspiratory and expiratory resistance and reactance in patients with asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2009.120790</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20335298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zajda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipworth</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are we overlooking persistent small airways dysfunction in community-managed asthma?</article-title><source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<elocation-id>e182</elocation-id>:<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anai.2012.06.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22920073?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komarow</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myles</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzzaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Impulse oscillometry in the evaluation of diseases of the airways in children</article-title>. <source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anai.2010.11.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21354020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21354020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coutier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vrielynck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>An impulse oscillometry system is less efficient than spirometry in tracking lung function improvements after intravenous antibiotic therapy in pediatric patients with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1073</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.23301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26340567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26340567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatziagorou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pappa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>132 multiple breath washout and forced oscillation technique to assess lung disease in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>S84</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1569-1993(16)30370-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>ELV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Bedside estimation of recruitable alveolar collapse and hyperdistension by electrical impedance tomography</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1132</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-009-1447-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19255741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roughton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Short-Term comparative study of high frequency chest wall oscillation and European airway clearance techniques in patients with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2008.111492</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19703826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teschner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imhoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Electrical impedance tomography: the realization of regional lung monitoring</source>. <publisher-name>Dräger Medical GmbH EIT booklet</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buonpensiero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregorio</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pasqua</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>WS15.6 short term effects of positive expiratory pressure mask breathing on distribution of lung ventilation in cystic fibrosis patients: a preliminary report with electrical impedance tomography</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>S25</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1569-1993(16)30150-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swingwood</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>302 comparison of airway clearance techniques (act) in the cystic fibrosis (CF) population: a single case study report</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>S125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1569-1993(14)60437-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wettstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radlinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of different breathing AIDS on ventilation distribution in adults with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>e106591</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106591</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25222606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25222606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conventional chest physiotherapy compared to other airway clearance techniques for cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>CD002011</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002011.pub2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15674888?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McIlwaine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Button</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dwan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Positive expiratory pressure physiotherapy for airway clearance in people with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD003147.pub4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <collab>Cochrane Cystic Fibrosis and Genetic Disorders Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Oscillating devices for airway clearance in people with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<elocation-id>CD006842-CD006842</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD006842.pub4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Airway clearance techniques for cystic fibrosis: an overview of Cochrane systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>CD011231</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011231.pub2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30676656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30676656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warnock</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <collab>Cochrane Cystic Fibrosis and Genetic Disorders Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Chest physiotherapy compared to NO chest physiotherapy for cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001401.pub3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burnham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autogenic drainage for airway clearance in cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>CD009595-CD009595</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD009595.pub2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28984368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28984368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Cystic fibrosis research in allied health and nursing professions</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcf.2012.03.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22516511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Guidelines for the physiotherapy management of the adult, medical, spontaneously breathing patient</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>64 Suppl 1</volume>:<fpage>i1</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2008.110726</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19406863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19406863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <label>43</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CFTrust</collab></person-group><source>UK Cystic Fibrosis Registry - Annual data report 2012</source>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <label>44</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPG/CF</collab></person-group><source>Physiotherapy for people with cystic fibrosis: from infant to adult (blue Booklet)</source>, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <label>45</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><source>Standard operating procedure: multiple breath nitrogen washout EXHALYZER® D, Eco MEDICS Ag. version one</source>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <label>46</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quanjer</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanojevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Multi-Ethnic reference values for spirometry for the 3-95-yr age range: the global lung function 2012 equations</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1324</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00080312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22743675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanojevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratjen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiologic endpoints for clinical studies for cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Cyst Fibros</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcf.2016.05.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27316663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27316663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rayment</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratjen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lung clearance index as a monitoring tool in cystic fibrosis: ready for the clinic?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0000000000000515</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30095491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30095491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <label>49</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Knol HCWDVCBTLBMDL</collab></person-group><source>Measurement in medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <label>50</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolotkin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining clinically meaningful change in health-related quality of life</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0895-4356(03)00044-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12812812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12812812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R51">
                <label>51</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lydick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpretation of quality of life changes</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00435226</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8401458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8401458</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R52">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Boeck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilschanski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castellani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Cystic fibrosis: terminology and diagnostic algorithms</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2005.043539</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16384879?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16384879</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
