<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:27:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8140200" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8140200</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-25</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bjsopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJS Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJS Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjsopen</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BJS Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2474-9842</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8140200</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8140200</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8140200</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34021326</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34021326</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsopen/zrab003</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zrab003</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Randomized Clinical Trial</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>Bjs/1</subject>
                  <subject>Bjs/2</subject>
                  <subject>Bjs/4</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00010</subject>
                  <subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00910</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>Bjs/2</subject>
                  <subject>Bjs/18</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Surgical cognitive simulation improves real-world surgical performance: randomized study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cragg</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Vascular Surgery, Russells Hall Hospital</institution>, Dudley, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                  <xref rid="zrab003-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <!--jcragg1@nhs.net-->
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mushtaq</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>School of Psychology, University of Leeds</institution>, Leeds, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lal</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of General Surgery, Queen Elizabeth Hospital</institution>, Birmingham, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Garnham</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Vascular Surgery, New Cross Hospital</institution>, Wolverhampton, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hallissey</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of General Surgery, Queen Elizabeth Hospital</institution>, Birmingham, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Postgraduate School of Surgery, West Midlands Deanery</institution>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shiralkar</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Worcestershire Health and Care NHS trust</institution>, Worcestershire, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="zrab003-cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Department of Vascular Surgery, Russells Hall Hospital, Pensett Road, Dudley DY1 2HQ, UK (e-mail: <email>jcragg1@nhs.net</email>)</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-05-22">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>5</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <elocation-id>zrab003</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>03</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of BJS Society Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="zrab003.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="s1">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>Despite the acknowledgement of human factors, application of psychological methods by surgeons to improve surgical performance is sparse. This may reflect the paucity of evidence that would help surgeons to use psychological techniques effectively. There is a need for novel approaches to see how cognitive training might be used to address these challenges.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Surgical trainees were divided into intervention and control groups. The intervention group received training in surgical cognitive simulation (SCS) and was asked to apply the techniques while working in operating theatres. Both groups underwent procedure-based assessment based on the UK and Ireland Intercollegiate Surgical Curriculum Programme (ISCP) before the training and 4 months afterwards. Subjective evaluations of SCS application were obtained from the intervention group participants.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Among 21 participants in the study, there was a statistically significant improvement in 11 of 16 procedure-based assessment domains (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.050) as well as a statistically significant mean reduction in time to complete the procedure in the intervention group (–15.98 <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> –1.14 min; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024). Subjectively, the intervention group experienced various benefits with SCS, especially in preoperative preparedness, intraoperative focus, and overall performance.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s4">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>SCS training has a statistically significant impact in improving surgical performance. Subjective feedback suggests that surgeons are able to apply it in practice. SCS may prove a vital adjunct for skill acquisition in surgical training.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <p>The aim was to address previous methodological flaws by objectively and subjectively assessing the effect of surgical cognitive simulation on both simulated and real-world surgical practice. Surgical trainees were randomized to receive training, and their simulated performance was assessed objectively using validated methods before and afterwards; the subjective effect this had on their real-world practice was also assessed. There were significant improvements in technical scores and speed following surgical cognitive simulation training, and real-world transferability over a prolonged period of time was demonstrated.</p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Health Education England (West Midlands)</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Alan Turing Institute and an MRC Confidence in Concept Award</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>MC/PC/17165</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="6"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>A key component of surgical training is the acquisition and development of technical skills. In recent years, changes in patterns of work, the expanding range of procedures, and technical demands have altered pathways of learning. The reduction in workplace experience has been identified as a training risk, and the role of simulation has been investigated as a method of preparing individuals before patient contact and developing skills<xref rid="zrab003-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. Although simulation has been shown to be useful in aiding skill development<xref rid="zrab003-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>, there are considerable limitations in its application to surgery<xref rid="zrab003-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The qualitative experience of non-virtual reality simulators frequently falls short of expectations. Virtual reality simulators are expensive and resource-intensive, and there are doubts about transferability of the skills acquired to the operating theatre<xref rid="zrab003-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The role of human factors in surgery has led to interest in the application of psychological techniques to surgical performance, reflected by more than 1000 publications on this topic in surgical journals, mostly in the past decade<xref rid="zrab003-B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. Many studies have shown benefits of mental practice<xref rid="zrab003-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>, with a meta-analysis<xref rid="zrab003-B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> of RCTs demonstrating enhancement in surgical skills. Although earlier studies focused on mental practice or rehearsal for improving psychomotor skills, recent studies have applied wider cognitive skills such as mental readiness and anticipatory planning. These have shown much broader benefits in surgical performance, including better stress management and situational awareness<xref rid="zrab003-B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12–17</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>In spite of favourable outcomes, the application of psychological methods in surgery remains far from commonplace, in contrast with other groups such as the military<xref rid="zrab003-B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>, police<xref rid="zrab003-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> or athletes<xref rid="zrab003-B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>, who also perform under stressful conditions and have benefited demonstrably from psychological interventions. This infrequent use of psychological methods by surgeons may reflect variable methodologies in studies, and the dearth of practical relevance in the evidence concerning training, processes, and outcomes. Most studies have failed to assess the impact of psychological methods on surgical performance in real operating theatres. Skills assessed have been relatively simple or a single surgical procedure on a simulator. In some studies<xref rid="zrab003-B22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22–24</sup></xref>, subjects were not surgeons or were assessed for short-term changes.</p>
              <p>This pragmatic study set out to address these methodological issues by linking subjective operating theatre assessment with objective assessment in the skills laboratory. A training programme, surgical cognitive simulation (SCS), was designed for application in operating theatres. SCS comprised evidence-based performance-enhancing strategies, including preperformance routines, goal setting, thought management and focused, mental practice. A previous study<xref rid="zrab003-B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> had examined the feasibility of providing SCS training for surgical trainees, and the aim of the present work was to assess the real-life efficacy of SCS.</p>
              <p>A prospective RCT was therefore designed to see whether SCS training delivered to surgical trainees led to the application of these skills in clinical situations. A further objective was to determine whether such application of SCS improved surgical skills in the laboratory and overall surgical performance in the operating theatre.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>This RCT examined the effect of SCS on a simulated operative procedure and subjective experiences while performing in the operating theatre. The School of Psychology Research Ethics Committee at the University of Leeds granted ethical approval (reference <xref rid="zrab003-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-0166).</p>
              <p>General surgical trainees in years 3–5 from the West Midlands Deanery were recruited and consented to participate. Baseline details for each candidate were collected via questionnaires to assess level of surgical experience. Participation was voluntary and candidates could withdraw at any point. Participants were randomized by means of a random number generator to either an intervention group that received SCS training or a control group that received no SCS training.</p>
              <p>Frozen and thawed porcine specimens that provided acceptable tissue handling with dissection were used. A baseline video recording was made of all participants performing laparoscopic cholecystectomy on an <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> model. Instrument availability was kept constant, as was the seniority of the surgical assistant. Videos were graded objectively by assessing surgeons in a blinded fashion according to the Intercollegiate Surgical Curriculum Programme problem-based assessment (PBA) criteria for laparoscopic cholecystectomy, a validated objective assessment tool used for all UK surgical trainees in relation to operative training. Multiple assessors were used to minimize inter-rater variation.</p>
              <p>SCS training (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref></italic>) was provided for the intervention group by a surgical performance coach along with reading material on SCS for self-study. The participants were advised to perform cognitive simulation for approximately 20 min on the day before undertaking procedures.</p>
              <p>At 4 months after the initial assessment, all candidates underwent another video assessment of laparoscopic cholecystectomy performed on porcine specimens. Those in the intervention group provided subjective information about their experience of practising and applying cognitive simulation in their work (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref></italic>).</p>
              <p>Sixteen domains from the PBA for laparoscopic cholecystectomy were considered relevant to a simulated operation, in addition to time taken to complete the procedure and a global performance score, for which the principles of the PBA terms were used; results were converted to a numerical score ranging from 1 (poor) to 10 (excellent). The mean rating for each dependent variable was taken, and these were used to compare performance across the two groups. For each group, a difference score was obtained by subtracting the performance score (mean score provided by assessors) at baseline from that at the end of training.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Previous studies suggested that nine participants per group would be required to show statistical significance at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.050 with 80 per cent power<xref rid="zrab003-B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref>, so 21 trainees were used, 10 assigned to the intervention and 11 to the control group. Video assessors were blinded to which group the candidate was assigned, but not to whether the video showed a baseline or follow-up attempt.</p>
                <p>Objective scores from each assessor were assessed for κ correlation. Before undertaking the inferential analysis, the Shapiro–Wilk test was used to check for normality in the distribution of the data for each dependent variable. Of the 18 (16 from ISCP) domains, three had statistically significant scores indicating that they violated the assumptions of normality. For these measures, the non-parametric Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used to compare differences between the two groups, and an independent two-sample Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was employed for the remaining 15 variables. A false discovery rate correction was used to control for the increase in type I errors in null hypothesis testing that arise when conducting multiple comparisons; this was done by ranking all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values in ascending order and applying the formula (i/m)Q, where i is the rank of the individual <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value, m is the total number of tests, and Q the false discovery rate. The false discovery rate was fixed at 0.050 for this study, setting the expectation that 5 per cent of reported results would be false-positives. This correction was implemented using the p.adjust function from the stats package in R version 3.1.2 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria)<xref rid="zrab003-B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Of 21 trainees recruited to the study, all performed the procedures, but recordings from seven trainees were not available for assessment for technical reasons. Complete objective data were available for seven trainees in the intervention group and seven controls (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref></italic>). Two expert surgeons with 15 years of experience rated the video recordings. The assessors had a statistically significant moderate level of agreement (κ  =  0.434; z = 3.55; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zrab003-F1">
                <label>Fig. 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Study flow diagram</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zrab003f1" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>There was no significant difference at baseline in terms of logbook experience of laparoscopic cholecystectomy, with a mean total of 101 procedures for trainees in the control group control and 108 in the intervention group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.425) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></italic>). There was no significant difference between the perceived adequacy of the specimens or video between the groups (6.357 (control) <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 7.142 (intervention); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.111).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zrab003-T1">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Participant characteristics</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Age (years)*</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Sex ratio (M : F)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 : 2</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 : 1</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Postgraduate years*</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>No. of laparoscopic cholecystectomies*</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Assisted</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Trainer scrubbed</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Trainer unscrubbed</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Performed</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Values are mean.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>A greater improvement was observed in the intervention group in terms of procedure times (<bold>–</bold>15.98 min in intervention group <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> –1.14 min in control group; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref></italic>), global performance scores (+1.742 <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> +0.357; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref></italic> and <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></italic>), and in 11 of 16 individual scoring domains (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref></italic>). Subjectively, SCS was well received and there was perceived value in its application to real-world situations. Trainees reported a greater sense of preoperative preparedness and intraoperative focus in addition to feeling an overall improvement in their quality of performance (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zrab003-T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></italic>). Many (88 per cent) expressed a view that SCS should be incorporated into the training programme.</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zrab003-F2">
                <label>Fig. 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Mean change in time taken to complete the procedure in intervention and control groups</p>
                  <p>Median (bold line), mean (dot), interquartile range (box), and range (error bars) are shown. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.024 (independent T- test).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zrab003f2" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <fig position="float" id="zrab003-F3">
                <label>Fig. 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>Mean change in global performance score in intervention and control groups</bold> Median (bold line), mean (dot), interquartile range (box), and range (error bars) are shown. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.011 (independent T-test).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zrab003f3" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <fig position="float" id="zrab003-F4">
                <label>Fig. 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Significance of differences in mean change in probem-based assessment scores between intervention and control groups</p>
                  <p>CVS, critical view of safety. Dotted line represents cut-off for significance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.050, Wilcoxon rank sum).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zrab003f4" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zrab003-T2">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Effect size of surgical cognitive simulation on each domain</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohen’s d</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (min)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.071 (3.819) (–6.779, 8.921)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1060</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative strategy score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321 (0.480) (–0.665, 1.308)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2531</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equipment choice score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.330) (–0.679, 0.679)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adequate exposure achieved score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750 (0.554) (–0.389, 1.889)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5116</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key structures seen score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.143 (0.625) –0.141, 2.427)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6914</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Logical sequence score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107 (0.417) (–0.749, 0.964)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0972</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Handles tissue well score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607 (0.643) (–0.714, 1.929)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3569</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of stapler score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643 (0.370) (–0.118, 1.404)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6561</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrument safety score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179 (0.447) (–0.741, 1.098)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1508</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pace score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214 (0.617) (–1.055, 1.484)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1312</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Economy of movement score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250 (0.630) (–1.046, 1.546)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1499</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Responds to anatomical variation score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321 (0.422) (–0.546, 1.189)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2877</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deals calmly with unexpected events score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.393 (0.284) (–0.191, 0.976)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5232</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uses assistant effectively score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.393 (0.441) (–0.514, 1.300)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3365</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Critical view of safety achieved score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607 (0.767) (–0.970, 2.184)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2992</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duct and artery ligated score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.857 (0.481) (–0.131, 1.845)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6741</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallbladder mobilization score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.571 (0.670) (–0.806, 1.949)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3223</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357 (0.637) (–0.952, 1.667)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2119</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn2">
                    <p>Values are mean(s.e.m.) (95 per cent c.i.).</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zrab003-T3">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Subjective feedback</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted score</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improved sense of preparedness</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improved confidence</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in time taken to perform procedure</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in quality of focus while operating</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in ability to learn while assisting</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in decision-making while performing a procedure</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in team working skills during operative procedure</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in performing new technique or approach</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in overall quality of surgical performance</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in dealing with unexpected situations in routine procedure</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in operating on emergencies</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in stress of performing operations</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement in feeling of fatigue after operating list</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you see any role of cognitive simulation in surgical training? (yes/no)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88% yes</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn3">
                    <p>Weighted mean scores of subjective improvement experienced in specific domains in the intervention group are shown. Score range 0–10, with 10 representing most and 0 least perceived improvement.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>This study has demonstrated successful application of psychological techniques by surgeons in a clinical environment and its effect on performance in real life. The results indicate that SCS training helped trainees to practise independently and apply it in operating theatres. Application of SCS showed objective improvement in surgical skills on a simulated procedure, and subjective improvement in various performance domains in the operating theatre.</p>
              <p>Aside from physical operative experience, evidence suggests that non-operative skills can independently improve performance and outcomes in surgery<xref rid="zrab003-B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref>. At the same time, fatigue, memory failures, and lapses in concentration are common reasons for patients coming to harm. Lack of cognitive skills has been identified as a common contributor to this<xref rid="zrab003-B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>. The present study mirrors other findings that psychological methods improve surgical skills along with surgeons’ mental well-being<xref rid="zrab003-B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>. This is an important aspect when considering the growing recognition of stress and burnout among surgeons<xref rid="zrab003-B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The present study has overcome some of the methodological limitations in other studies of skill improvement<xref rid="zrab003-B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref>, including the use of surgical trainees as subjects instead of medical students<xref rid="zrab003-B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref>, applicability to more than one procedure<xref rid="zrab003-B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref>, evaluation of both simulated and real procedures<xref rid="zrab003-B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref>, as well as assessing long-term effects in the operating theatre<xref rid="zrab003-B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref>. It has demonstrated durability of this approach with delayed testing after unsupervised practice, representing a more realistic approach for implementation of psychological methods into training<xref rid="zrab003-B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zrab003-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The term SCS merits explanation. In a recently published review, the authors concluded that establishing a taxonomy for mental skills in surgery would help in the development of robust mental skills training programmes to promote optimal surgeon wellness and performance. The lack of use of psychological methods in surgical practice is thought to be due to wide variation in study methodologies, lack of clarity about processes, and use of imprecise terminology such as ‘mental practice’, ‘mental rehearsal’ or ‘mental imagery’. Terms such as mental imagery and visualization are not only imprecise, but also counterproductive, as they limit application of the cognitive process to visual information. Unless multiple sensory modalities are applied, the performer is unlikely to experience the benefit of cognitive simulation. Mental practice usually covers very limited psychomotor functions, but surgical skill acquisition also requires situational awareness, anticipation, and other cognitive functions that are addressed in SCS. Thus, SCS is not just a different label for an established term such as mental practice, but a reflection of a distinct cognitive process with a new perspective.</p>
              <p>An earlier study<xref rid="zrab003-B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> had shown that SCS training was well received by trainees, although follow-up after the initial training revealed that application of SCS dropped significantly after 4 weeks. In the present study, participants were asked every month to provide details about their application of SCS in the previous 4 weeks. From the feedback, it was possible to grade the quality of cognitive simulation of each participant. A correlation has been shown between quality of imagery and performance improvement<xref rid="zrab003-B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref>. The present results agree with other studies showing that surgical performance improved proportionately with the quality of mental imagery scores<xref rid="zrab003-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>There are some limitations to this study. The sample size was very small and data were lost for seven subjects. Considering the outcomes, however, it seems unlikely that additional data from three intervention and four control subjects would have substantially altered the results. Inclusion of a subjective evaluation can be seen as another limitation. However, the objective was to conduct a pragmatic study with practical relevance. This would not be the case if the study had omitted evaluations during routine working in the operating theatre. Simulated assessments have been shown to offer a reasonably good reflection of performance in the real world<xref rid="zrab003-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref>. In addition, as SCS is a subjective process, subjective assessment needed to be considered. A Hawthorne effect—the temporary alteration of behaviour by the subjects of a study owing to their awareness of being observed—cannot be discounted<xref rid="zrab003-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>The results of this study have implications for the manner in which surgeons acquire and improve surgical skills. Although both the Chief Medical Officer in the UK<xref rid="zrab003-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> and the American College of Surgeons<xref rid="zrab003-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> have suggested simulation technology as a training strategy, the present results suggest that SCS may be an effective adjunct to technical simulation. SCS is designed to help surgeons to focus on their sensory capabilities and simulate the procedure before undertaking it. The fundamentals of SCS are underpinned by existing psychological and neuroscience theories<xref rid="zrab003-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref>. By mentally practising the procedure, surgeons may need to spend less time in the skills laboratory, shortening their learning curve by using the ‘simulation centre in the brain’. It is free, available to all, and much less resource-intensive than other approaches to training. After initial training with a facilitator, trainees can perform it anywhere and in their own time. Those responsible for surgical training need to acknowledge the benefit of such training and incorporate it as an essential part of surgical training.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The project team received funding from Health Education England (West Midlands). F.M. was supported by a Fellowship from the Alan Turing Institute and an MRC Confidence in Concept Award (MC/PC/17165).</p>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Disclosure.</italic> The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary material</title>
              <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">BJS Open</italic> online.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>zrab003_Supplementary_Data</label>
                <media xlink:href="zrab003_supplementary_data.zip">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="ref1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zrab003-B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kneebone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>ApSimpson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Surgical skills training: simulation and multimedia combined</article-title>. <source>Med Educ</source>  <year>2001</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>909</fpage>–<lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11555230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nagendran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gurusamy</surname><given-names>KS.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Laparoscopic surgical box model training for surgical trainees with no prior laparoscopic experience</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>  <year>2014</year>;(<volume>1</volume>)<fpage>CD010479</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Badash</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burtt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solorzano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JN.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Innovations in surgery simulation: a review of past current and future techniques</article-title>. <source>Ann Transl Med</source>  <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28090509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Korndorffer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefanidis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Touchard</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Simulator training for laparoscopic suturing using performance goals translates to the operating room</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>  <year>2005</year>;<volume>201</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stefanidis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korndorffer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Closing the gap in operative performance between novices and experts: does harder mean better for laparoscopic simulator training?</article-title>  <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>  <year>2007</year>;<volume>205</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ström</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kjellin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wredmark</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Felländer-Tsai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Training in tasks with different visual–spatial components does not improve virtual arthroscopy performance</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>  <year>2004</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–1<lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yurko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Increased stress levels may explain the incomplete transfer of simulator-acquired skill to the operating room</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>640</fpage>–<lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20403516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabbott</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Critical analysis of evidence about the impacts on surgical teams of ‘mental practice’ in systematic reviews: a systematic rapid evidence assessment (SREA)</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source>  <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32664909</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sirimanna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Mental practice enhances surgical technical skills: a randomized controlled study</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>  <year>2011</year>;<volume>253</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tait</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alijani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of the role of mental training in the acquisition of technical skills in surgery</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source>  <year>2015</year>;<volume>210</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage><lpage>e53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Mental practice enhances technical skills and teamwork in crisis simulations—a double blind, randomised controlled study</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>  <year>2011</year>;<volume>213</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kreutzer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cannon-Bowers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Team resilience as a second-order emergent state: a theoretical model and research directions</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1360</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28861013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cannon-Bowers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Converse</surname><given-names>SA.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <part-title>Shared mental models in expert team decision making</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Castellan</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name></person-group> (ed.). <source>Individual and Group Decision-Making: Current Issues</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>, <fpage>201</fpage>–20<lpage>3</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>KT.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Getting them on the same page: strategies for enhancing coordination and communication in sports teams</article-title>. <source>J Sport Psychol Action</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maran</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Identifying and training non-technical skills for teams in acute medicine</article-title>. <source>Qual Saf Health Care</source>  <year>2004</year>:<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aoun</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batjer</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rezai</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Can neurosurgical skills be enhanced with mental rehearsal?</article-title>  <source>World Neurosurg</source>  <year>2011</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21986407</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cobley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>The effect of psychological skills training on self-regulation behavior, self-efficacy, and psychological skill use in military pilot-trainees</article-title>. <source>Mil Psych</source>  <year>2013</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>136e47</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Selder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nideffer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Psychological factors associated with the successful completion of basic underwater demolition SEAL training</article-title>. <source>US Navy Tech Rep</source>  <year>1989</year>;<fpage>66</fpage><lpage>e76</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Scanff</surname><given-names>Le</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taugis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>J. Stress management for police special forces</article-title>. <source>J App Sport Psych</source>  <year>2002</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>330e43</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guenthner</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammermeister</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Smoke and mirrors or wave of the future? Evaluating a mental skills training program for elite crosscountry skiers</article-title>. <source>J Sport Behav</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>3e24</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raison</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Mental training in surgical education: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>ANZ J Surg</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28851014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raison</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghumman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Cognitive training: how can it be adapted for surgical education</article-title>. <source>Surgeon</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27658665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammonds</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefanidis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Application of mental skills training in surgery: a review of its effectiveness and proposed next steps</article-title>. <source>J Laparoendosc Adv Surg Tech A</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28225325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sinclaire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beamish</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shiralkar</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Results of a cognitive simulation course pilot</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source>  <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>S106</fpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Louridas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonrath</surname><given-names>E M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>D A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dedy</surname><given-names>N J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grantcharov</surname><given-names>T P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Randomized clinical trial to evaluate mental practice in enhancing advanced laparoscopic surgical performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Surgery</italic></source>  <year>2014</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.9657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25332065</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J R Statist Soc Series B</source>  <year>1995</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Catchpole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panesar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <italic toggle="yes">Surgical Safety Can Be Improved Through Better Understanding of Incidents Reported to a National Database</italic>. Oxford, UK: National Patient Safety Agency, <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mushtaq</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Driscoll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>AR.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Contributary factors in surgical incidents as delineated by a confidential reporting system</article-title>. <source>Ann R Coll Surg Engl</source>  <year>2018</year>; <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29543056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Mental practice: effective stress management training for novice surgeons</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>  <year>2011</year>;<volume>212</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21276534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Stress, burnout and maladaptive coping: strategies for surgeon well-being</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Coll Surg</source>  <year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Mental skills training and resident surgical outcomes: a systematic review. J Surg Educ 2020;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1377</fpage>–<lpage>1391</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadoski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Walsum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bramson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiprud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fossum</surname><given-names>TW.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Learning basic surgical skills with mental imagery: using the simulation centre in the mind</article-title>. <source>Med Educ</source>  <year>2008</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18435713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bathalon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorion</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darveau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Cognitive skills analysis, kinesiology, and mental imagery in the acquisition of surgical skills</article-title>. <source>J Otolaryngol</source>  <year>2005</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16181595</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mulla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moghul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Learning basic laparoscopic skills: a randomized controlled study comparing box trainer, virtual reality simulator, and mental training</article-title>. <source>J Surg Educ</source>  <year>2012</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22365864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Louridas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonrath</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>Randomized clinical trial to evaluate mental practice in enhancing advanced laparoscopic surgical performance</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>  <year>2015</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25332065</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Geoffrion</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal>  <article-title>The mind’s scalpel in surgical education: a randomised controlled trial of mental imagery</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>  <year>2012</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Deshauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mutabdzic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>CAE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mental skills in surgery: Lessons learned from virtuosos, olympians, and navy seals</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>  <year>2019</year>. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000003573</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B38">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ruffino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papaxanthis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lebon</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>The influence of imagery capacity in motor performance improvement</article-title>. <source>Exp Brain Res</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>235</volume>:<fpage>3049</fpage>–<lpage>3057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B39">
                <label>39</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Demetriou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Hing CB. <article-title>Hawthorne effect on surgical studies</article-title>. <source>ANZ J Surg</source>  <year>2019</year>;<volume>89</volume>:1567–1576</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B40">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Department of Health. Annual Report of the Chief Medical Officer; On the State of Public Health. London: Department of Health,</collab>  <year>2008</year></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B41">
                <label>41</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunnington</surname><given-names>GL.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>The new ACS/APDS Skills Curriculum: moving the learning curve out of the operating room</article-title>. <source>J Gastrointest Surg</source>  <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17926105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zrab003-B42">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shiralkar</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Psychological insight for surgeons</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>  <year>2013</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1675</fpage>–<lpage>1676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227351</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
