<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2024-05-03T10:07:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10153590" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:10153590</identifier>
        <datestamp>2023-05-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>tvst</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Vis Sci Technol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Vis Sci Technol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TVST</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Translational Vision Science &amp; Technology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2164-2591</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC10153590</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10153590</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">10153590</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37126336</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37126336</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/tvst.12.5.1</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">TVST-22-4571</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Neuro-Ophthalmology</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category">
                  <subject>Neuro-Ophthalmology</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Visual Field Pointwise Analysis of the Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension Weight Trial (IIH:WT)</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="runhead">Visual Field Pointwise Analysis for the IIH: WT</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6314-4437</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mollan</surname>
                    <given-names>Susan P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bodoza</surname>
                    <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1920-3513</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ní Mhéalóid</surname>
                    <given-names>Áine</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                    <given-names>James L.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                    <given-names>Neil R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9148-2804</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Montesano</surname>
                    <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8754-3902</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Crabb</surname>
                    <given-names>David P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wall</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3921-0166</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brock</surname>
                    <given-names>Kristian</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>7</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2777-5132</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                    <given-names>Alexandra J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>8</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Birmingham Neuro-Ophthalmology, Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham, University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Informatics, Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham, University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Optometry and Visual Sciences, School of Health Sciences, City University of London, London, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Wilmer Eye Institute, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>NIHR Biomedical Research Centre, Moorfields Eye Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, UCL Institute of Ophthalmology, London, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Neurology, Queen Elizabeth Hospital, University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust, Birmingham, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Cancer Research Clinical Trials Unit, College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Institute of Metabolism and Systems Research, College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Alexandra J. Sinclair, Institute of Metabolism and Systems Research, College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK. e-mail: <email>a.b.sinclair@bham.ac.uk</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>01</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2023</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>12</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <elocation-id>1</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>06</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2023</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>07</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2022</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="tvst-12-5-1.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Purpose</title>
                  <p>This study was designed to determine if point analysis of the Humphrey visual field (HVF) is an effective outcome measure for people with idiopathic intracranial hypertension (IIH) compared with mean deviation (MD).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Using the IIH Weight Trial data, we performed a pointwise analysis of the numerical retinal sensitivity. We then defined a medically treated cohort as having MDs between −2 dB and −7 dB and calculated the number of points that would have the ability to change by 7 dB.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>The HVF 24-2 mean ± SD MD in the worse eye was −3.5 ± 1.1 dB (range, −2.0 to −6.4 dB). Total deviation demonstrated a preference for the peripheral and blind spot locations to be affected. Points between 0 dB and −10 dB demonstrated negligible ability to improve, compared with those between −10 dB and −25 dB. For the evaluation of the feasibility for a potential medical intervention trial, only 346 points were available for analysis between −10 dB and −25 dB bilaterally, compared with 4123 points in baseline sensitivities of 0 to −10 dB.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Patients with IIH have mildly affected baseline sensitivities in the visual field based on HVF analyzer findings, and the majority of points do not show substantial change over 24 months in the setting of a randomized clinical trial. Most patients with IIH who are eligible for a medical treatment trial generally have the mildest affected baseline sensitivities. In such patients, pointwise analysis offers no advantage over MD in detection of visual field change.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>visual field</kwd>
                <kwd>point sensitivity</kwd>
                <kwd>idiopathic intracranial hypertension</kwd>
                <kwd>pseudotumor cerebri</kwd>
                <kwd>perimetric mean deviation</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="11"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Idiopathic intracranial hypertension (IIH) is characterized by raised intracranial pressure (ICP) associated, in most cases, with papilledema, visual field defects, and, in some cases, permanent visual loss.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Most people with IIH have moderate to severe headaches, systemic metabolic dysfunction, and central obesity.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> The incidence of IIH is increasing around the world, commensurate with the increase in worldwide obesity.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Depending on the severity of IIH, patients can be treated with weight loss alone, ICP-lowering medications such as acetazolamide, ICP-lowering surgery, or a combination of these. The IIH Weight Trial (IIH:WT) showed that weight loss achieved by bariatric surgery resulted in long-term remission of ICP compared with a lifestyle weight-management intervention.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></p>
              <p>The Humphrey visual field (HVF) mean deviation (MD) has been used as an endpoint in IIH clinical trials.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> However, although the IIH:WT met its primary endpoint (change in ICP measured by lumbar puncture opening pressure at 12 months), there was no significant improvement seen in the MD in either arm. We thus wondered if a different method—pointwise analysis—might be a more sensitive indicator of a change in the visual field in IIH patients participating in a treatment trial.</p>
              <p>There are a number of different ways to evaluate visual field damage.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> The MD determined by the HVF Analyzer (Carl Zeiss Meditec, Dublin, CA) is measured in decibels (dB) using a logarithmic scale and determines the average difference in visual field sensitivity compared with the mean sensitivity of a normal person of the same age. Weighting is inversely proportional to the expected variance at each location in a normal population, effectively giving more weight to the central locations.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>–</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> A key regulator, the US Food and Drug Administration, considers a change of 7 dB in MD to be acceptable as being clinically meaningful.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> In IIH, the expected MD change is smaller compared with other optic neuropathies such as glaucoma. For most patients in an IIH medical intervention trial, a 7-dB change would be unachievable, as the MD inclusion criteria would likely be between −2 dB and −7 dB, which would represent a floor effect.</p>
              <p>Another functional endpoint that has been recommended for an optic neuropathy treatment trial is a change of 7 dB in five or more predefined reproducible visual locations.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Restricting an analysis to a particular subset of points in the visual field has not been previously prospectively investigated in IIH; however, the IIH Treatment Trial (IIHTT) investigators performed a post hoc pointwise analysis of the HVF. For each of the 52 points, a linear regression analysis was performed with the decibel measurement as the outcome variable and time as the independent variable. The IIHTT investigators demonstrated that peripheral points were more affected than central points. Although the magnitude of change in points was modest, there was significantly more improvement in the acetazolamide treatment arm.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Given the lack of correlation in the IIH:WT outcome measures and MD, we hypothesized that a pointwise analysis of the IIH:WT visual field data could potentially reveal localized improvements not demonstrated by the MD. The number of participants required and the number of points that could be predicted to change in an IIH trial population could be determined. The purpose of this study was to assess if point analysis of the HVF would be feasible in a cohort of people with active IIH in the setting of a randomized clinical trial.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <p>IIH:WT was a prospective, multi-center, open-label, parallel-group, controlled trial in which participants with IIH were randomized in a 1:1 ratio to a bariatric surgery pathway or the Weight Watchers program, a community weight management intervention (CWI). The study was approved by the Ethics Review Board of the National Research Ethics Committee West Midlands, and the Black Country approved IIH:WT (14/WM/0011). In accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, all subjects gave written informed consent to participate in the study, and the detailed clinical trial methodology has been published.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Anonymized individual participant data will be made available along with the trial protocol and statistical analysis plan. Proposals should be made to the corresponding author and will be reviewed by the Birmingham Clinical Trials Unit Data Sharing Committee in discussion with the chief investigator. A formal data sharing agreement may be required after release of the data has been approved and before the data can be released.</p>
              <sec id="sec2-1">
                <title>Subjects</title>
                <p>Women (18–55 years old) with a body mass index (BMI) &gt; 35 kg/m2 were eligible if they had a clinical diagnosis of active IIH according to criteria outlined by Friedman et al.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> All participants were recruited between March 2014 and October 2017. Evaluations were performed at baseline, 12 months, and 24 months.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The primary outcome was ICP as measured by lumbar puncture; secondary outcomes have been reported elsewhere.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> At each visit, HVF with a 24-2 Swedish interactive threshold algorithm standard test pattern using a size III white stimulus was performed. HVFs were included for analysis if they were considered reliable as defined by less than 15% false-positive rates and 30% fixation losses and false-negative rates according to previous criteria.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Acquisition of Data From the Visual Fields</title>
                <p>In this analysis, the raw values of the patient's retinal sensitivity at each of the HVF 24-2 predetermined points were extracted from pdf scans of the HVFs using a custom data extraction tool based on the Python<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> package “hvf extraction script.”<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> This script used Google's tesseract optical character recognition<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> to distinguish text inside a digital image and return the relevant text in a useable format. Although the “hvf extraction script” was not originally intended for use on scanned documents, cleaning the images before processing gave values for the majority of the visual field locations. A manual validation of the total cohort point retinal sensitivity eliminated missing data and discrepancies between the original values and the data extraction tool.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>HVF Analysis</title>
                <p>To detect pointwise change over the course of the study, the points were categorized by individual pointwise retinal sensitivity at baseline. The mean change in sensitivity was plotted at each point from baseline to 12 and 24 months. Subsequently, the cohort was restricted to a population defined by a baseline MD between −2 dB and −7 dB to simulate a medically managed population. Finally, the number of points in the visual field in the whole cohort and in the restricted simulated medically treated cohort that would be expected to change per sensitivity category were calculated.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>Analysis of clinical data was based on the full dataset according to the statistical analysis plan.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> In this evaluation, analyses were based on a per-protocol analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using R 3.6.3 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). Data were reported with mean and SD for normally distributed variables and median and range for data that were not normally distributed. Missing clinical data, due to any absence or choice, were excluded from the analysis.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Characteristics of the study population are summarized in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Retinal sensitivity values for the whole cohort at baseline showed that the central points were less affected than the peripheral points (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). The whole cohort was then categorized according to the extent of their reduced visual function at baseline as per MD category (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref>B–<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). As the visual function declined, the distribution of the average deviation points became increasing prominent in the periphery and around the blind spot.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" content-type="2col" id="tbl1" specific-use="style-1col">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>IIH:WT Baseline Characteristics</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col align="char" char="plusmn" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 66)</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at baseline (y), mean ± SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 ± 7.8</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of IIH diagnosis (y), median (IQR)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.5–2.6)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number on acetazolamide (%)</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (29)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opening lumbar puncture pressure (cm CSF), mean ± SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5 ± 7.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg), mean ± SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.5 ± 21.1</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, mean ± SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9 ± 7.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perimetric MD worse eye (dB),</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.6 ± 3.7</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> mean ± SD</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 65)<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frisén grade, worse eye, mean ± SD</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.0</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tb1fn1">
                    <p>IQR, interquartile range; CSF, cerebrospinal fluid; BMI, body mass index.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="tb1fn2">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Missing data are indicated in parentheses.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <fig position="float" id="fig1">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p><bold>(A)</bold> The retinal sensitivity at baseline for each location of the HVF for the whole cohort, within eye. All patients were used. <bold>(B)</bold> The retinal sensitivity at baseline for each location of the visual field for those with MDs of −2 dB or better. <bold>(C)</bold> The retinal sensitivity at baseline for each location of the visual field for those with MDs between −2 dB and −7 dB. <bold>(D)</bold> The retinal sensitivity at baseline for each location of the visual field for those with MDs worse than −7 dB.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="tvst-12-5-1-f001" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <sec id="sec3-1">
                <title>Pointwise Location Sensitivity for Whole Cohort at 12 and 24 Months</title>
                <p>Points with baseline sensitivities between 0 dB and −10 dB showed small changes over time points (0–5 dB, mean 0.02 ± 3.1; −5 to −10 dB, mean 2.4 ± 4.7 at 12 months) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Points with sensitivities worse than −10 dB demonstrated a larger improvement over time; for example, at 12 months, between −10 dB and −15 dB, the mean ± SD was 5.78 ± 6.10 dB, and from −15 to −20 dB, the mean was 11.10 ± 5.02 dB (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). For points with baseline sensitivities of −35 to −30 dB, there was a large SD (mean, 16.51 ± 13.75 dB) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) at 12 months. When points with baseline sensitivity between −10 dB and −25 dB were analyzed for the whole cohort, the mean change at 12 months was 8.53 ± 6.75 dB, increasing further to 9.61 ± 6.99 dB by 24 months (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p>
                <fig position="float" id="fig2">
                  <label>Figure 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p><bold>(A)</bold> The mean change in deviation from baseline (and 95% confidence intervals) to 12 months and 24 months in subsets of points classified by baseline deviation. All patient eyes were used. Categories with at least 10 observations at each time point are shown. The sizes of the groups are naturally different, and this is reflected in the widths of the confidence intervals. <bold>(B)</bold> The mean change in deviation from baseline (and 95% confidence intervals) to 12 months and 24 months in the population defined by MDs between −2 dB and −7 dB at baseline (simulation of a medically treated population).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="tvst-12-5-1-f002" position="float"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap position="float" content-type="6col" id="tbl2">
                  <label>Table 2.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Number of Points and Mean Change in Point Sensitivity in Visual Field Test Locations Categorized by the Baseline Point Sensitivity Subgroup at 12 and 24 Months</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="center" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="7pc" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="7pc" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="7pc" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="3pc" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (mo)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline Point Sensitivity Subgroup (dB)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Points</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean at Baseline (dB)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Change From Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−35, −30)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−32.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−30, −25)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−25, −20)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−20, −15)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−15, −10)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−10, −5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">711</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−5, 0)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3412</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0, 5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">661</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5, 10)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−35, −30)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−32.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−30, −25)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−25, −20)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−20, −15)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−15, −10)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−10, −5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">652</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−5, 0)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2784</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0, 5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5, 10)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" content-type="5col" id="tbl3">
                  <label>Table 3.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Number of Points and Mean Change in Point Sensitivity Over Time in Test Locations With a Baseline Point Sensitivity Between −10 dB and −25 dB, Categorized by Trial Arm and Use of Acetazolamide</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (mo)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Points Between −10 dB and −25 dB</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cohort</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI with acetazolamide</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI with no acetazolamide</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bariatric surgery</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cohort</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI with acetazolamide</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CWI with no acetazolamide</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bariatric surgery</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <sec id="sec3-1-1">
                  <title>Analysis of Pointwise Sensitivities in the Simulated Medically Managed Cohort</title>
                  <p>Those with a MD between −2 dB and −7 dB at baseline had a similar distribution of changes in the point-sensitive deviation at baseline (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B). Overall, the vast majority of data points that were included were in the 0 to −10 dB category (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4123), compared with points between −10 dB and −25 dB (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 346) and those between −25 dB and −5 dB (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 487) (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" content-type="5col" id="tbl4">
                    <label>Table 4.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Subanalysis (Defined by MD Between −2 dB and −7 dB at Baseline) to Simulate a Medically Treated Cohort Where the Number of Point Sensitivities Are Categorized by the Location Point Sensitivity</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." width="3pc" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." width="4pc" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." width="3pc" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." width="3pc" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline Point Sensitivity Subgroup (dB)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Point (mo)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Points That Could Be Analyzed</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (dB)</th>
                          <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 to −10</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4123</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 to −10</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3436</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10 to −25</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10 to −25</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25 to −35</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">487</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25 to −35</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec3-1-2">
                  <title>Analysis of Pointwise Sensitivities in the Whole Cohort</title>
                  <p>The utility of baseline points between −0 dB and −10 dB was examined to establish how point-sensitivity analysis performed in IIH:WT. As expected, these demonstrated very little change at 12 and 24 months (at 12 months, the mean change was 0.4 ± 3.5 dB; at 24 months, the mean change was 0.48 ± 4.11 dB). Baseline sensitivities between −10 dB and −25 dB have the ability to change over time (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). It was only when using the whole cohort that the largest mean changes were found: 8.53 ± 6.75 dB at 12 months and 9.60 ± 6.99 dB at 24 months (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). However, there were fewer points available for analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 346 at 12 months and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 329 at 24 months) compared with cases where the baseline pointwise sensitivity ranged from 0 to −10 dB (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4123 at 12 months and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1844 at 24 months) (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Furthermore, there was little difference observed between trial arms when analyzing the points that were between −10 dB and −25 dB at baseline, as the bariatric surgery arm was 8.75 ± 6.51 dB at 12 months and the CWI group was 8.16 ± 7.15 dB at 12 months. This was despite a significant difference between baseline and 12 months in the ICP of −6.0 cm cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) between the trial arms. Among those in the CWI arm who were not on acetazolamide, the point sensitivity mean change between baseline and 12 months was 8.03 ± 7.26 dB. Despite the significant reduction in ICP found between the bariatric surgery group and the CWI group, there was little discrimination analyzing point sensitivities among bariatric surgery, CWI, CWI with no acetazolamide treatment, and CWI with concurrent use of acetazolamide (<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p>
                  <table-wrap position="float" content-type="11col" id="tbl5" specific-use="style-1col">
                    <label>Table 5.</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Longitudinal Mean Pointwise Location Sensitivity Changes in Those With Point Sensitivities Between −10 dB and −25 dB, Categorized by Treatment at 12 and 24 Months</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total Cohort</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bariatric Surgery</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">All CWI</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CWI and No Concurrent Acetazolamide Treatment</th>
                          <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CWI and Concurrent Use of Acetazolamide</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 mo</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.53 ± 6.8 (346)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.75 ± 6.5 (219)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.16 ± 7.2 (127)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.77 ± 4.3 (22)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03 ± 7.6 (105)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 mo</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60 ± 6.99 (329)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.55 ± 6.7 (211)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 ± 7.1 (118)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.16 ± 7.2 (103)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00 ± 4.52 (15)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3-2">
                <title>Categorizing the Population by Baseline MD</title>
                <p>To understand how representative a baseline point sensitivity beyond −10 dB in one or more points was in an active IIH population, we calculated the number of points ≥ −10 dB in each individual (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). In the whole cohort, the median number of points on the baseline visual field worse than −10 dB was 5 (interquartile range, 2–13), with 57% of the cohort having at least two points worse than −10 dB at baseline (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). In the subgroup with a MD between −2 dB and −7 dB at baseline, 42% had more than five points that were worse than −10 dB. As the number of points required for analysis decreased, more participants were available for inclusion; for example, 73% had at least two or more points, and 85% had one point worse than −10 dB (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Also, 31% of patients at 12 months and 38% at 24 months would have achieved five or more points that improved by 7 dB (<xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap position="float" content-type="8col" id="tbl6">
                  <label>Table 6.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Number of Participants Who Had One or More Baseline Points in Either Eye With a Sensitivity Worse Than −10 dB in the Entire Cohort With and Without Perimetric MD Criteria</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char=")" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Number of Points ≤ −10 dB in Either Eye at Baseline (%)</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median Points (IQR)<xref rid="tb6fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cohort</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (0.67)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (0.57)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (0.45)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (0.35)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (0.35)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2–13.5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MD ≥ −2 dB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (0.87)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (0.76)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (0.58)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (0.50)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (0.50)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2–15)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MD between 2 dB and 7 dB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (0.85)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (0.73)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (0.52)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (0.42)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (0.42)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2–10)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MD ≤ −7 dB</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.00)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.00)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.00)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.00)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.00)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5 (32.75–71.25)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="tb6fn1">
                      <label>a</label>
                      <p>The median number of points ≤ −10 dB in either eye at baseline (and IQR) in only those patients who had at least one qualifying point.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap position="float" content-type="3col" id="tbl7" specific-use="style-1col">
                  <label>Table 7.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Percentage and Number of Participants Who Had Pointwise Improvement of 7 dB or More From Baseline at 12 and 24 Months</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="7pc" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." width="7pc" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patients Who Had a Pointwise Improvement of 7 dB or More From Baseline at</th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Available Points on the HVF 24-2 at Baseline</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 mo (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 53), % (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 mo (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 44), % (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (14)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (8)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (4)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (16)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (17)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this study, we characterized the pointwise pattern of visual field change in a cohort of people with active IIH recruited to the IIH:WT. Those with baseline point sensitivities between 0 dB and −10 dB showed small changes over time and, as expected, were unlikely to demonstrate clinically meaningful change over both 12 and 24 months. Points in the −10 to −25 dB category demonstrated change that could be considered clinically meaningful (mean of 8.5 dB in at least one point in the whole visual field); however, using data between −10 dB and −25 dB resulted in fewer data points and larger SDs for analysis. Although the median number of points worse than −10 dB was five, 43% of all of the IIH:WT participants had fewer than two points worse than −10 dB at baseline, emphasizing that data points worse than −10 dB were not representative of the majority of IIH patients.</p>
              <p>It should be emphasized that eligibility for the IIH:WT was not determined by MD criteria. Therefore, to simulate the HVF data to reflect a typically medically managed cohort, we chose a baseline HVF in which the MD was between −2 dB and −7 dB (the criterion range used in the IIHTT<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>). Among this group, 42% had five or more points worse than −10 dB at baseline (<xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). If only two points were required for analysis, 73% had two or more points worse than −10 dB in either eye at baseline (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Thus, we found that it would be challenging to use point analysis as an outcome for an interventional medical trial in IIH, as the pool of point-sensitivity data available for meaningful analysis would be extremely small. Additionally, the participants overall would be less representative of the whole disease spectrum, which could affect the applicability of the results being directly translatable to clinical practice. Finally, test locations with 8 to 18 dB of loss at baseline had a 95% prediction interval that nearly covered the full measurement range of the instrument (0–40 dB)<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>; thus, the test–retest variability of these locations was so poor that there was little signal above the variability-related noise.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref></p>
              <p>There is no universally adopted, minimally clinically important change in HVF measures in IIH as there are in glaucoma.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> In glaucoma, visual field progression equal to or faster than −0.5 dB per year for at least five abnormal test locations at baseline has been found to be clinically significant,<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> as have changes from baseline beyond the 5% probability levels for the Glaucoma Change Probability analysis in five or more reproducible visual field locations.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Although pointwise analysis in patients with IIH has revealed changes around the blind spot and in the nasal area, likely reflecting the reduction in optic head nerve swelling as the papilledema resolves,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> visual fields with global diffuse damage, such as occur in patients with IIH, tend to be more variable than fields with focal damage such in glaucoma.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> The fundamental differences between these diseases confound the applicability of glaucoma outcome measures to IIH trials. IIH is a rare condition compared with glaucoma which immediately affects the trial design and recruitment potential, particularly as other tools that assess visual function, such as visual acuity (Snellen or logMAR), color vision, and contrast sensitivity, have not been found to be discriminatory in medically managed IIH.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></p>
              <p>A limitation of this study is that it included only patients with well-established IIH. Thus, the results may not be applicable to patients with recently diagnosed IIH or to severely affected patients who may require urgent surgery.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> In addition, because our cohort was small, it was subject to regression to the mean with respect to the mean deviation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Regression to the mean is a common statistical phenomenon that occurs when repeated measurements are made on the same subject. Subjects would not be expected to have the same measurements at two different times due to measurement error and random fluctuation. Regression to the mean needs to be considered to distinguish a real change from the expected change due to the natural variation in test readings. To minimize regression to the mean, participants should be randomized to study arms, with a control arm being fundamental to the design of the trial. Variability can be further reduced by selecting participants using two or more baseline measurements, resulting in better estimates of the mean and the within-subject variation.</p>
              <p>In this study and in studies reported by others,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> the visual field deficit in IIH typically occurs across the full VF and increases with eccentricity.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Unfortunately, these are the very points that show the largest variability in visual field testing.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Visual field tests also have been found to be unreliable when visual field locations have sensitivity below 15 to 19 dB because of a reduction in the asymptotic maximum response probability.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> In addition to test limitations, there are demonstrable changes in cognition in the domains of attention and executive function that have been found in patients with IIH and that directly affect the performance indicators in HVF testing.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></p>
              <p>Our data indicate that point analysis of the HVF has no advantage over global MD analysis, at least in the population we studied from the IIH:WT. As expected, baseline points that were better than −10 dB had little room to improve over time and, thus, offered little utility for analysis. If the generic threshold for a clinically meaningful change of 7 dB is recommended for IIH treatment trials, baseline points in the range of −10 to −25 dB would be needed for analysis. The US Food and Drug Administration has stated that visual field loss has likely occurred if ≥5 visual field locations have significant change beyond the 5% probability level or if there is at least a 7-dB between-group mean difference for the entire field.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> A pointwise approach for people with IIH is not feasible as demonstrated here because there are too few data points available for analysis. Additionally, the points that could be used are known to be more variable. In our study, even when a limited threshold was set to determine a clinically meaningful change, point analysis did not offer an advantage over global MD. Consequently, point sensitivity analysis in medically treated IIH is likely to be prohibitive in clinical trials and not representative of the IIH disease spectrum. In addition, if the requirement of regulators for a meaningful change in MD is a 7-dB difference between trial arms, as recommended for glaucoma treatment trials,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> then using MD as a primary outcome would not be achievable in medical IIH trials, as these typically recruit participants with MDs between −2 dB and −7 dB. Future studies may consider investigating the use of a larger stimulus size that has been demonstrated to retain the ability to detect defects, lower retest variability, and improve the useful dynamic range of the instrument.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>Supported by a National Institute for Health Research clinician scientist fellowship (NIHR-CS-011-028 to AJS); by the Medical Research Council, UK (MR/K015184/1 to AJS); and by a Sir Jules Thorn Award for Biomedical Science (to AJS). The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the UK National Health Service, the NIHR, or the UK Department of Health and Social Care.</p>
              <p content-type="COI-statement">Disclosure: <bold>S.P. Mollan</bold>, Allergan, Chugai Pharmaceutical, GenSight Biologics, Heidelberg Engineering, Invex Therapeutics, Janssen, Neurodiem, Roche, Santen, Velux Foundation; <bold>S. Bodoza</bold>, None; <bold>Á.Ni Mhéalóid</bold>, None; <bold>J.L. Mitchell</bold>, None; <bold>N.R. Miller</bold>, None; <bold>G. Montesano</bold>, None; <bold>D.P. Crabb</bold>, None; <bold>M. Wall</bold>, None; <bold>K</bold><bold>.</bold>
<bold>Brock</bold>, AstraZeneca, Eli Lilly, GlaxoSmithKline, Invex Therapeutics, Merck; <bold>A</bold><bold>.</bold><bold>J. Sinclair</bold>, Allergan, Amgen, Cheisi, Invex (F), Novartis</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grech</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alimajstorovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wakerley</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>New horizons for idiopathic intracranial hypertension: Advances and challenges</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br Med Bull</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>; <volume>136</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33200788</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Westgate</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botfield</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alimajstorovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Systemic and adipocyte transcriptional and metabolic dysregulation in idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JCI Insight</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>e145346</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33848268</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westgate</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hornby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>A unique androgen excess signature in idiopathic intracranial hypertension is linked to cerebrospinal fluid dynamics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JCI Insight</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>e125348</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30753168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tahrani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The potentially modifiable risk factor in idiopathic intracranial hypertension: Body weight</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e504</fpage>–<lpage>e507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34484948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Adderley</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Association between idiopathic intracranial hypertension and risk of cardiovascular diseases in women in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>76</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1098</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31282950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mytton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsermoulas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic intracranial hypertension: Evaluation of admissions and emergency readmissions through the Hospital Episode Statistics dataset between 2002-2020</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34063037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ottridge</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of bariatric surgery vs community weight management intervention for the treatment of idiopathic intracranial hypertension: A randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>78</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>686</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33900360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes measures in idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Neurother</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34047224</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>NORDIC Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension Study Group Writing Committee</collab>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Effect of acetazolamide on visual function in patients with idiopathic intracranial hypertension and mild visual loss: The idiopathic intracranial hypertension treatment trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>311</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>1641</fpage>–<lpage>1651</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24756514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cello</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Visual field outcomes for the Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension Treatment Trial (IIHTT)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26934136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A package for the statistical analysis of visual fields</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Doc Ophthalmol Proc Ser</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fitzke</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hitchings</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poinoosawmy</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNaught</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crabb</surname><given-names>DP.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of visual field progression in glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8664231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Threshold static automated perimetry of the full visual field in idiopathic intracranial hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>60</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1898</fpage>–<lpage>1905</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31042797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Normal variability of static perimetric threshold values across the central visual field</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1544</fpage>–<lpage>1549</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3675288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A clinical study of perimetric probability maps</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2644927</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zamba</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The repeatability of mean defect with size III and size V standard automated perimetry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>54</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>1351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23341012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Weinreb</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>PL.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The glaucoma research community and FDA look to the future: A report from the NEI/FDA CDER Glaucoma clinical trial design and endpoints symposium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1497</fpage>–<lpage>1505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ottridge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botfield</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Randomised controlled trial of bariatric surgery versus a community weight loss programme for the sustained treatment of idiopathic intracranial hypertension: The Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension Weight Trial (IIH:WT) protocol</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>e017426</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Digre</surname><given-names>KB.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Revised diagnostic criteria for the pseudotumor cerebri syndrome in adults and children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>81</volume>(<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>1165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23966248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yohannan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Evidence-based criteria for assessment of visual field reliability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ophthalmology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>124</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>1620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28676280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van Rossum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>FL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Python Reference Manual</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centrum Wiskunde &amp; Informatica</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Saifee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Development and validation of automated visual field report extraction platform using computer vision tools</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Med (Lausanne)</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>625487</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33996848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Tesseract Open Source OCR Engine</collab>. <article-title>tesseract</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/tesseract-ocr/tesseract" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tesseract-ocr/tesseract</ext-link>. Accessed October 6, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Test-retest variability in glaucomatous visual fields</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>108</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2757094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zamba</surname><given-names>KD.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The effective dynamic ranges for glaucomatous visual field progression with standard automated perimetry and stimulus sizes III and V</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29356822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Csaky</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>FL</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Report from the NEI/FDA ophthalmic clinical trial design and endpoints symposium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Heijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leske</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <collab>Early Manifest Glaucoma Trial Group</collab>. <article-title>Measuring visual field progression in the early manifest glaucoma trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Ophthalmol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>81</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12780410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liebmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>LA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Detection and measurement of clinically meaningful visual field progression in clinical trials for glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Retin Eye Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27773767</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crabb</surname><given-names>DP.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Examination of different pointwise linear regression methods for determining visual field progression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source><italic toggle="yes">.</italic><year>2002</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1400</fpage>–<lpage>1407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11980853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burdon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nightingale</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Low energy diet and intracranial pressure in women with idiopathic intracranial hypertension: Prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>341</volume>: <fpage>c2701</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mollan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Idiopathic intracranial hypertension: Consensus guidelines on management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>89</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29903905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keltner</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quigg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cello</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Confirmation of visual field abnormalities in the Ocular Hypertension Treatment Study. Ocular Hypertension Treatment Study Group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>118</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>1194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10980763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kardon</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Total deviation probability plots for stimulus size V perimetry: A comparison with size III stimuli</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18413515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mansberger</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Demirel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the reliability of standard automated perimetry in regions of glaucomatous damage</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ophthalmology</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>121</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1359</fpage>–<lpage>1369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Grech</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group><article-title>Cognitive performance in idiopathic intracranial hypertension and relevance of intracranial pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Commun</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>; <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>fcab202</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34704028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zamba</surname><given-names>KD.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The effective dynamic ranges for glaucomatous visual field progression with standard automated perimetry and stimulus sizes III and V</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29356822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>SK.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the relation between perimetric sensitivity and variability between locations across the visual field</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>3667</fpage>–<lpage>3674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30029253</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
